Okay, our next topic is Desktop Icons.
And what we will introduce here is called
Bubble
Clusters.
So the topic we discuss here, is a
management of desktop icons.
So, suppose you have a desktop and the one
possible
way, the organized desktop is viewed
special aggregation or special clusters.
So, you put system icons here and
shortcuts here
and some documents here and documents on
other topic here.
So, this way people can manage, various
information in limited space.
However, a program is at this kind of
visual cluster.
Is not comprehensible from a computer.
So they're just icons for a computer's
point of view.
So, whenever you have, you walk on this
kind of
a layout, you have to explicitly select
group of objects.
So, that's one problem.
Another problem is that you have to, if
you put too
many icons in a same location, it can
cause a cluster.
And if you want to grab one icon hidden,
behind these icons, you have to move other
icons away.
So that's a problem we want to address.
Let me describe the program.
So here, you be, clearly see four groups
here.
However, system does not understand these
kind of clusters.
So, you have to manually select and move
around and then you should get a new
group.
Then you again, you have to manually
select.
Though, this can be very tedious.
Also, if you have, a big cluster, like
this
and there you have to pick up, icon hidden
it.
Hidden behind it.
You have to manually move out and then
pick one object.
So, this is
very tedious.
So, what we propose is, Bubble Clusters.
So, Bubble Clusters is automatic grouping
of nearby icons.
And then visualization of them as in a
bubble.
And also, additionally, we introduce
automatic spreading
of cluster to pick up on hidden icon.
So let me go back to the demonstration.
So here, you have three grids, and if you
enable
Bubble Clusters, you will see the three
bubbles, and then
if you grab a bubble, you can drag them
around
by, just by grabbing a bubble, without
manually selecting a group.
[SOUND] And bubble, is automatically
computed,
as soon as you place these two icons
nearby.
And there's a little bit very small
details but interesting details.
Here, these two and these two, are in the
same distance,
however you know, if these two icons are
previously separated.
They will resist to be merged fast.
But as soon as they are merged, then they
start to resist to be splitted.
So, this is, kind of history resist and it
is very useful.
And then you can, you know, move around
and pick up many icons.
And then, if you have a hidden icon, like
this.
Then you can double click here, and then
you would temporarily spread icons
and then you grab icon and the system go
back to the original state.
So, this is a bubble causal technique.
And a bubble clusters technique, and then
same idea
can be applicable to this kind of digital
ink.
So, if we were walking on digital ink
system.
You know, you probably do not want to
manipulate individual strokes.
Rather than that, each cluster has a
meaning grouping.
And then, whenever you draw strokes,
the system automatically groups nearby
strokes together.
And you can move around these strokes, by
grabbing blue area.
And if you connect together, it'll be one
object, and
then you can draw line and you will split
them,
so this is very useful for a discussion or
a
discussion on whiteboard or digital inks
because that's a demonstration.
Let me briefly describe the essence of
implementation.
So, we, I will first describe clustering
algorithm.
So, we use very, very simple pair-wise
distance threshold.
So, for all objects on the screen, first
we assign each object to one cluster.
So, cluster of object is like this.
And then, for all object pairs, oi on the
oj.
If the distance is smaller than threshold.
Then they will merge to object.
Here's a view.
So for each paper, each pair, we check the
distance, against the one threshold.
And if it is smaller, we merge them.
And interesting part is here, the
threshold.
So, if the, if previously, in the previous
frame, if the
object in the different cluster, then the
threshold becomes very small.
So, difficult to merge together.
And then, if the two objects are from the
same cluster, in the
previous step, then it becomes larger,
which means very easier to merge together.
And after having a cluster, we regenerate
a visualization of the bubble.
And here, what technology we use here, is
2D Implicit Surface.
So, Implicit Surface, is, to compute
potential field.
Field around each element, and then place
iso-surface over the field.
So, suppose you have one, two, three,
four, five object and then
we generate this kind of potential field
around it, kind of height field.
And then we aggregate them together and
then compute iso-surface.
And here is a visualization.
[SOUND] So, if you have this kind of
icons.
And then this will, this one showings
potential field.
As you see, if you aggregate more and more
object it becomes brighter which means
high potential field.
And after that, we just trace.
lines, with the same
height, heights.
And, however, it's very time-consuming, to
process individual pixels.
So, we compute potential field values at
grid cells, like this.
And after computing potential fields at
the grid cells, then we, out
of, we, extract iso-surface by a technique
called Marching Cubes.
So, here's a summary of this video.
So, the program we discuss here, is
a management of spatially organized
mini-icons on desktop.
And then solution here.
What we propose here, is automatic
clustering of nearby icons as a bubble.
And here's a pointers for further
learning.
So, original paper was published as a
Bubble Cluster,
Clusters: An Interface for Manipulating
Spacial Aggregation of Graphical Objects.
And the technique we use here, is called
Implicit Surfaces.
And Implicit Surfaces are very popular
technique in
computer graphics, to represent liquids
and [INAUDIBLE] object.
And the first publication was at SIGGRAPH
82 by Jim Blinn.
And then also, iso-surface extraction
technique,
called Marching Cubes was published at
1987.
And this is a very basic literature, and I
recommend that, to take a look at them.
Thank you.