Okay.
So, next topic is pointing.
And so, what we introduce here is called
the Ninja Cursors.
A problem we address here, is that it's
very, very
difficult to point to a long-distance
object very far away.
So, today, the screen resolution is gets
higher and higher.
And then the screen gets bigger and bigger
and you can even have multiple monitors.
So in, in such a situation it's very hard
to
get a point, a very distant target with
the mouse you
have to you know, move the mouse many
times to get
the target, so this is the problem we're
going to address.
And then we propose a message to address
this problem.
Let me show you what we do.
So, yeah, from here we discuss pointing
with the mouse cursor.
But this can be very tedious if some,
target is far away like this way.
So you have to clutch marks many times.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So in the [UNKNOWN] program, we propose to
use multiple cursors covering the screen.
So here, we have so, four cursors.
And we, if we have multiple cursors on the
screen,
you can just use a mouse cursor near the
target object.
So this can save time for pointing a
distance
target, that's the technique we propose in
this paper.
But the problem is that, ambiguity, so if
you
have multiple cursors and multiple objects
in the screen.
Then it's possible that, multiple pointers
point to different targets at a time.
So this is very problematic.
[SOUND] So to address this problem we
allow
only one cursor to point some object at a
time.
So when a mouse cursor is in some other.
Some object.
Then another, other cursor needs to wait
until the cursor moves out from the
target.
So here, the user moves the mouse pointer
to the right continuously.
And then, this one goes out.
And, this one goes in.
And the next one becomes in waiting state.
So as you see pointing.
[INAUDIBLE] pointers in a queue.
When tries to, when trying to point to
object.
So, yeah let me describe again.
So the basic idea of Ninja Cursors is to
cover
the screen with multiple syncronizedly
moving cursors, like this way.
And the user just use the nearest cursor
to the target object.
And this one effectively reduce the
distance of the target.
So it reduces average distance from the
nearest cursor.
It comes from D.
To D divided by square n.
So n means the number of cursors.
And this one, this help you to point a
distant, distant target.
By the way, this is a little bit of
background knowledge about pointing.
So pointing is a very popular topic in HCA
field.
And then pointing performer this models by
this
kind of equation, and its called Fitt's
law.
So suppose you have mouse cursor here, and
then you try to point a target
with distance D, and suppose that the
target size is W.
And then, here we consider only one
dimensional motion.
And in this situation target acquisition,
or pointing time is model like this.
Time equals a plus b log b and then inside
the log is 1 plus D divided by W.
So which means, if the distance is longer,
longer,
then time gets longer and longer with the
logarithmic function.
And however, the we, width is, is, get
bigger then time will be reduced.
So that's equation.
And Ninja Cursors, our technique
effectively reduces this D.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And as we have already discussed in the
video there is a ambiguity problem.
If multiple cursors point to multiple
objects at a time, this can be a problem.
So to address this problem we allow only
one cursor point to a target.
And others are blocked and in the waiting
queue.
So here green cursor points to this object
and then this
red one in the waiting queue, and then our
user continuously
moves a mouse cursor to the down, and then
green one
goes out, and then the red one goes into
the object.
And we provide a visual feedback
Normal cursor, Pointing cursor and Blocked
cursor.
And also, we also provide visual feedback
about the waiting
time.
So, yeah, that's it and here's the
summary.
So we discussed the problem of pointing a
distant target on a very large high
resolution displays.
And then our solution is to show multiple
cursors and use the nearest one.
And we also describe how to address
ambiguity problems.
So original paper was published as Ninja
Cursors, Using
Multiple Cursors to Assist Target
Acquisition on Large Screens.
And pointing is a very, very popular topic
in your field.
In many publications.
And here is a couple of interesting recent
papers.
One is bubbled cursors.
And this mean, this bubble cursor
technique changes
the mouse size, depending with the target
density.
So if the target is dense, the mouse
cursor gets smaller.
But the target is vast, the mouse cursor
gets larger.
So it's a very interesting technique.
Another is called drag and pop, pop and
drag and pick.
So as you see here, as you start to locate
an object, then related
icons jumps to near the cursor position to
help you point.
To help you do drag and drop efficiently.
So that's it.
Thank you.