Hello, our topic here is voice
interaction, and
the work we introduce here is voice and
sound.
So
here the background motivation, we see
there are two aspects in our voice.
So one is verbal information.
And the other is non-verbal information.
And typical speech interactions use verbal
information such as they
convert your speech into recognizable
command and then do something.
But however, on the other hand, our voice
also contains
non verbal information such as pitch,
volume, speed, and so on.
So these are non-verbal information has
been ignored in traditional speech
recognition.
But here, what we want to do is
leverage, leverage these non-verbal
information in your voice.
And here is a kind of concept.
So, interaction turn-around is very long
in traditional voice or speech
recognition.
So you say something, and then computer
tries to understand it,
and then you say something, and the system
tries to do something.
And this is, this is very, very, very
time-consuming.
And it's very discontinuous.
On the other hand.
For example if you are working on a,
mouse, if you grab an
object, you continuously move your mouse
cursor
and then the system continuously provides
feedback.
So this kind of direct manipulation
experience is
what we want to achieve, as in computer.
So we, in our technique, the user
continuously produce makes your
voice, and then system continuously
provides feedback to your vocal input.
So let me show you a video.
So, here, we introduce three techniques.
The first one is more simple.
On/off button.
So here, your voice works as on/off
button.
So if you say nothing, it's off.
So if you say something continuously it
means you press button.
Here's an example.
So here, typical approach is voice
recognition.
So if you want to move this node, say,
maybe you say 30 degree, and you get
result here.
And so, 90 degree, you get result here.
But again if you use voice recognition,
interaction can be very discontinuous.
Here your voice is a switch, so if you
make voice this one
starts moving, as you, as soon as you stop
speeching, speaking it will stop.
So you can continuously see the visual
feedback [SOUND].
So as you see, you can continuously get
feedback, so if you get a satisfact
result, satisfactory result, you just stop
speech and you get a result.
And if the voice is very annoying or
difficult to produce
you can make any noise, so you can use a
breath.
To control a system.
>> Down.
>> And if you combine this with
traditional
speed recognition, you can do something
like this.
[SOUND] Again, traditional approach
is to say, like, 100 meter.
Away, or one kilometer away, and so on.
But it's kind of difficult to understand
what's going on.
But here, you just speech, and then stop
speaking.
And this especially useful for zooming.
You know, zooming 1.2 is very difficult to
imagine.
But here, you just see it.
>> Bike.
Zoom out.
Out.
Up.
>> Okay so that was a fast technique and
here is the second one.
Second one is addition to on and off, you
control, control a parameter
using a voice, using a pitch of your
voice, so you let me see.
[NOISE] So you control a slider with the
pitch of your voice.
[NOISE] It's very, very st, stable, that's
a most important part [NOISE].
>> Up.
Down.
>> So, here, in addition to controlling
the distance,
you can also control a speed of the
scrolling.
>> Up.
Right.
Up.
>> [NOISE] Again, higher the
voice, the faster you move.
So, so far, I showed very continuous
control parameters, but
here, the last one is discontinuous
Discrete Control by Tonguing.
So suppose you want to change TV channel,
or something like that.
>> [SOUND] down.
[UNKNOWN] Left.
[UNKNOWN] up.
[UNKNOWN] right.
[UNKNOWN] down [UNKNOWN].
>> So here we use very, very basic signal
processing, so you can
do any noise, so you can also clap your
hands to control it.
>> Down.
[SOUND] Right.
Right.
[SOUND].
[BLANK_AUDIO].
So those three techniques we introduced.
And then next we, I will show
you a couple entertainment applications of
these techniques.
The first, okay,
the first one is jumping game using your
voice.
Up, up, up, up, up, up, up, down.
>> So next
one is
using pitch control to control the
vertical position of this fish.
[INAUDIBLE]
So last one is, like punching game using
your voice.
[UNKNOWN].
[SOUND] So that, that's it and let me go
back to the slide.
So let me briefly describe the
implementation of this kind of system.
First, where we use a signal processing
techniques.
And we use existing.
A fourier transform library.
So it transforms input voice signal data
into frequency domain.
And then application is control's
implemented in Java.
And the first technique, on and off
control is very, very nice.
Implement this and we use.
It just checks total volume, total power.
Or was the input signal.
And if it's, we check whether the total
volume is larger than the threshold or
not.
One implementation detail is that we
ignore
low frequency part to subtract, separate
background noise.
An important part is pitch detection, so.
We con, we use voice pitch to control
parameter up
and down but this needs to be very, very
stable.
A naive approach is to use identify
absolute pitch for each voice.
So here's an input signal and then try to
identify the dominant pitch.
However this is very very difficult.
It's very ambiguous, noisy, and unstable.
Please imagine that at this kind of
frequency signal, is changing all
the time and then it is very difficult to
identify a peak.
So some t, at some point this is the
highest.
But at nex,next moment this one gets
highest, so it's very unstable.
So this naive approach is not works very
well.
So our approach is to just all checks
slightly up or slightly down of each
frame.
So in this way the result is very stable.
So we only check whether the pitch is
getting high or lower, a little bit.
So here's a detailed algorithm.
Suppose you have this kind of spectrum of
time t0.
So the vertical, horizontal axis is
frequency, low frequency
to high frequency, and for each frequency
you get amplitude.
And then you get another thing now of t0
plus dt.
And then your task is to detect whether
this frequency signal is shifting
downwards or upwards.
So in order to do it, we get this
we aggregate this signal into a vector,
and then in the next time.
For the next fray, we get a vector for the
shifted upwards and also shifted
downwards, so you have three vectors.
And then we just compute dot products
between them.
So this one is dot product between v and v
minus.
And then you compute also v and v plus.
So if v minus is higher, then v minus is
more
closer to v, so which means that the pitch
is shifted over.
And then if this thought product of v plus
is higher than v minus, which means
that v plus is closer to v, which means
the spectrum is, gets higher.
So this very, very simple implementation.
Returns a very, very stable result.
So here's a summary.
So we discussed problem of controlling
object
continuously, using your voice, using
non-verbal features.
And then our approach is to use a
non-verbal aspect of your voice.
And the original paper was published as
Voice
as Sound, Non-verbal Voice Input for
Interactive Control.
And multi-modal interface using gesture
and voice is also a very popular topic in
your field, and very original paper was
called Put, Put That
There so you say, put and then say that,
showing some object.
And then again say there.
And they're showing another object using
your gesture.
And then you get the task.
And the video is available on the YouTube.
So I recommend you to take a look at it.
And also there are a couple of interesting
voice based interaction techniques.
And one recommendation for you is speech
completion.
And this one tries to complete.
Your speech in the middle.
And also video is available, so I
recommend you too take a look at it.
Thank you.
So this is the end of week one.
Some topic we discuss in this week was
graphical user interfaces.
And then we discuss scrolling interfaces,
the manageable desktop icons.
Pointing techniques on the large screen.
And management of digital ink.
And then finally, we discuss voice
interaction.
Thank you.