Our next topic is style-by-demonstration.
So, the what we do this here is
called style by demonstration,
teaching interactive movement,
movement style to robots.
So the goal here is to teach
interactive behavior to robots.
The robot observes user behavior.
And the user do something and
the robot do something.
So we try to teach this
kind of interactive motion.
And you will have to do this,
you know traditional programming
is require, you know?
User have to how to call, how to do it.
However, traditional text
based programming like C or
Java is too difficult for designers.
So, our goal is to, do this, make it
possible for artists to design behavior.
And then, we take proble,
programming by demonstration approach.
So the intertwining phase, user interacts
with the robot, operated by an operator.
So, the designer actually operates
this robot, interacting with the user.
And then, from this demonstration
result training data, is a run time,
systems automatically
synthesizes robot motion,
responding to the user input in the real
time and defaulting to the training data.
So that's the basic idea.
Let me show you a video.
So here this is a user and
this is a designer operator, and
then here's a robot.
So, and this is a training phase.
In the training phase,
operator is operating the robot
to responding to the user.
After that, he leaves.
He disappears.
So I think he's teaching
following behavior.
So, in this case, the designer
is teaching attacking behavior.
So, tries to push this user away from
the lesion, so that's a behavior.
Oh, by the way, everything in tracked
using a motion capture system, so
if the users positions, and robot
position is continuously tracked, and
recorded, as a training data.
After the learning in the lab time,
robot replays interactive motion
adapting to the current situation.
So here is a robot who is reprising
a burglar attacking behavior.
So, I think it's very tedious to teach
this kind of motion using standard program
language, taking user and robot position
as input, and then compute many geometric.
How to code motor motion
is hard very difficult.
We also tested this kind of tabletop
configuration for teaching.
So the user is manipulating,
controlling the robot in this way
following the character
following the user.
I think here the user is
teaching stalking behavior.
You know, following a person
from the behind, hiding away.
So, this is the result.
So the system is learning automatic
auto-resume based on the training data.
So this why he's following the person,
like a stalking, with a certain distance.
So this is not just a replay, or
pre-programmed, predefined motion.
It is adaptive to the current,
current configuration.
Okay.
So, that's, that's video.
So let me briefly describe the algorithm.
How to do it.
So, here's situation.
So, we have training data.
User motion data, position data,
robot position data, and
these are time sensitive data.
So, in the training data you have lots
of time series paired, traditional data,
motion data.
And also, we have a runtime situation.
So use is suppose to show he's
continuously interact and
the robot motion is continuously interact.
So, now, this is the current time.
In the current time frame you have the
history of user position, robot motion,
and also user's current position.
And the task is how to compute
the robot's next next desired position.
So that's a.
Tasks, so input is this old data,
and the output is position.
Desire to position was lowered.
In order to do it, in order to send
similar motion to the training data,
first task is searches for
the similar situation.
So, you compute the current configuration,
we send you suppositions.
Recent user motions and
recent robot motions, and it searches for
the similar situation in the data set.
You can make it faster by
indexing it beforehand, but
anyway what you do is search for
the similar situation.
And after identifying
the most similar situation.
And the system basically just copies and
pastes, takes the motion in
the training data to the current data.
Of course, this is a very,
very simplified view, but
this describes the basic idea behind it.
And this kind of two-pair and
two-pair synthesis is inspired by this
technique so called image analogies.
This is the technique designed,
developed for image filtering.
So what we, what they do is here,
so A, A dash, and B is an input.
And the B dash is a result.
So, here the user tries
to teach image filtering.
So this is a, A is an input image.
And A dash is output image of this one.
So this one is kind of water painting
filter, so system takes image and
then converts it to a kind of a water
painted painting from the input.
So here the user provides
an example as A and
A dash, and
it also provides B as a source image.
After the system learns
filtering from A and
A dash, and applies to B,
and you get B as an output.
What happens internally is similar
to the method we had just described.
For each pixel in B dash we searches for
the similar situation in A,
A dash, and B, and then applies
the result in A dash to B dash.
So that's what they do.
Okay.
So, in this short video we describe how to
teach interactive behavior
to a robot by demonstration.
So the, the designer operates a robot in
training time, and then know what behaves.
The based on the training data.
And internally what they do is
what the lower do is searches for
the similar data in the demonstration or
training data, and then copies
the previous motion to the current motion.
And then the algorithm is
inspired by the image and
the logistic developed
the image filtering.
To allow more art, original paper was
published as Style by Demonstration,
teaching interactive
movement style to robots.
And image analogies is at SIGGRAPH 2001.
And the general concept of
programming by demonstration, or
programming by example,
has been extensively studied in field.
And one represented reading is,
recommended reading is
titled book is Watch What I do:
Programming by Demonstration.
So this book introduce many
interesting techniques and
examples of program,
programming by demonstration.
Thank you.