Next topic we discuss is control
of robotic lighting system.
The work we introduce here is titled
Lighty, A Painting Interface for
Room Illumination by Robotic Light Array.
So as a program, we want to address
here is that it is difficult to
control many light, especially
when they can change orientations.
So here an example destination, so suppose
we have many lights in the ceiling,
and the individual lights
can change its orientation.
And this is a very huge
control parameter space, and
it's very hard to control
appropriate parameters.
And typical user
interfaces look like this.
You have many sliders to change
brightness and orientation, and so on.
And this is not very useful for
people to quickly sketch
desired lighting configuration.
So our approach is to
use painting interface.
So configuration looks like this.
We have an environment, and
we have many robotic lights, and they
can change brightness and orientation.
And we have a camera here
to capture our environment.
And then in this kind of view,
there's a paint, desired lighting this up.
So this part should be bright,
this should be, this part should be dark.
We just paint desired configuration.
And then the system learns
inverse relation, and
then obtain desired parameter setting.
So that's the idea.
Let me show you a video.
So again, this is a system work view.
So you have actuated the light on
the ceiling and the UI in the environment.
And then you would attempt to control
the light you pick up a tablet and
they use these environment and
they paint on it.
So this is a prototype
hardware we developed.
We the, we built a miniature
room with miniature lights and
miniature furniture and
this is a array of robotic lights.
So, they can change
orientation individually, and
also can change brightness.
So, each light has three
degrees of freedom.
So if we have 12 light,
which means 36 yeah, degrees of freedom.
So, here's a painting user interface.
So, given this screen,
you're going to pick up a color and paint.
Yeah.
Okay.
So here lots of things happening here.
So this view is always a real-time
capture of the camera view.
So you see camera view.
And as I use a paint,
user's paint is actually feedback
is given as these quanta lines.
So this area bright,
this area is a little bit dark.
And then given this control on user
request, system continuously learns
optimization to get desired parameters,
and it's a real-time.
The environment con
moves around the light.
And then up, and you see the result
in real-time in this camera view.
So, there's a lots of
happening behind the scene.
Yeah, so user paint system searches for
the, the parameter setting interactively.
And then you see the layout
result immediately.
So, you always see the camera view.
Yeah.
So, depending what the user input,
system automatically computes
the parameters said and
then derives the robotic system.
So, this is more rapid example.
So, if you touch down, and move around,
it will actually paint uncommitted.
But, if you hover, you paint it on
top of the surface, you can still see
the preview of the painting without
actually committing the paint.
So this is a mimic of oh,
simulation of traditional approach.
So you have 12 lights and
then you individually control
brightness and orientation.
So, and this a typical interface, and
it's very tedious control one by one,
to get the desired result.
So we compare this interface
with our painting interface, and
if you want to bright somewhere,
if you want to illuminate somewhere,
it's relatively easy.
You just turn on, you edit right,
and then delete it.
However, if you want to
make some part dark,
it suddenly turns out to be very difficult
using traditional interface because it
involves control of many lights.
You know, you move like sideways,
moving away, looking away and turn off.
But there's lots of interruptions behind,
between multiple lights, so
that's a difficulty.
Okay, so that's the video I think.
So all the benefit of our
system is that in addition,
make specific regions bright,
you can also make specific regions dark.
This is kind of negative light.
So you ask a specific region to
get darker, and the system do it,
and looks like a negative light, and
if you, figure it out from our user study,
in the painting if the user asked to
make up a upper left corner dark,
just paint a region darker and
you get this result.
However, if you use traditional
direct controller, it takes time and
it's very difficult to
get this kind of result.
And let me briefly describe the algorithm,
behind the scene.
So, this is what's happening.
So, this is the light parameters,
so you have many parameters.
Light orientations, brightness and so on.
And then if you derive the light, and
if you get this out, then you know,
physics will happen and
then you will get this camera view.
And then, after that I use a paint,
desired painting result.
So, system compares these two, and
then optimize the parameter setting and
then we'll get it.
And in order to run optimization, you need
to do this iteratively many times, so
instead of using actually driving
physical lights, we run simulation.
You know, what happens if this
parameter setting is given,
and the system simulates the illumination
result and then compare the result compare
it to the user input, and then again last
simulation and so, so that's the idea.
So the physical process
again is the process,
physical process is too complicate
to obtain analytic model.
So in order to do this simulation,
we use a data-driven prediction method.
So we, so we capture many,
many illumination results.
So you have many parameters,
like lighting parameters.
So this light and brightness,
the second right query orientation.
So you have many parameters and then this,
you get many, many camera views.
So you capture many images.
And then based on this data, you predict
the resulting elimination results for
a new given parameter set.
And in order to do this,
we basically individually control
the lighting parameter for individual
light, and then we add them together.
However, important point is
naive summation of image data
where pixel values does not work.
So suppose you have pixel A illumination
rays out here, no, suppose you have
a illumination result over A here and then
illumination result over light B here.
But id you are tired of,
to doing pixel values, it does not
correspond to the result, eliminated
by light A and B simultaneously.
That is because of the non-linear
radiation set between radiance.
So, physical physical value of
the brightness is not directly linear.
Relate, linearly related to the pixel
value, because there's a non-linearity.
So in order to handle this,
you, we first need to convert pixel
values into a radiance value.
So re-award brightness value.
After converting pixel
value to radiance value you
can accurately predict the summation
of two light illumination.
Then after that we can again convert it
to the pixel body to get the prediction.
So that's what you need to do
to get this kind of system.
So in summary, we, I just shows Robotic
lighting system with painting interface.
And I briefly discussed what you need
to do, to implement this kind of thing.
So, you need to compute
a simulation in the radiance space,
instead of pixel space,
pixel brightness value space.
So the reason a paper was
published as design and
the enhancement of painting interface for
room lights.
And if you want to know more
about Radiance Computation, one,
one good starting point is this paper,
recovering high dynamic range,
dynamic radiance maps from photographs.
So this paper discuss, hot to compute
original radiance values from
multiple photographs, over the same scene.
And also our lighting control with
painting interfaces, there are a couple
experiments in 3D graphics, and one
example is this one, lighting with paint.
So user paints desired lighting result,
and
the system computes, appropriate
lighting for the computer graphics.
So what do we do is a real
world version of this one.
So that's it for this week