[MUSIC]
Hi, welcome back.
Previously, we introduced
cryptography as a tool for
security solutions in
cyber physical systems.
We also presented how symmetry key ciphers
are used for securing wireless networks.
In this video lecture, we will learn
how public key cryptography works,
we will have a close look at
the well-known RSA algorithm.
Public key cryptography
comprises a set of algorithms
that are designed based on
some mathematical problems.
As we discussed earlier,
unlike in symmetric cryptography,
in public key cryptography the decryption
key is not the same as the encryption key.
And for this reason it is also
known as asymmetric cryptography.
A pair of key is called a public key and
a private key are used in such a system.
The public key,
as it is clear from its name,
is publicly known by everybody and
is used for
encryption, while the private key is
kept secret and used for decryption.
So anybody can encrypt the message
with the recipient's public key,
but only the recipient can decrypt
it using his or her own private key.
This eliminates the need for
a secure channel to exchange
the key between two parties.
In a public key cryptography, the key
pairs are mathematically related, but it
is computationally infeasible to get the
decryption key from the encryption key.
Let's have a brief look
at some important and
popular public key encryption algorithms.
The Rivest-Shamir-Adlerman or
RSA algorithm is one of
the most practical and
secure public key algorithms,
which is widely used for
secure communication.
RSA, which is named after its three
inventors was published in 1977.
It provides three main functionalities,
key generation, encryption,
and decryption.
Diffie-Hellman, or DH protocol,
provides an efficient and secure way
of exchanging an encryption key often
symmetric cipher through a public channel
without any need for a secure channel.
Diffie-Hellman is one of
the earliest applications
of public key encryption,
published in 1976.
This protocol is still
used in many applications.
Elliptic Curve Cryptography or
ECC provides an alternative mechanism for
public key encryption.
It was introduced in 1985.
ECC is based on algebraic elliptic
curves over finite fields.
And offer smaller keys with
a reasonable level of security
compared to other public
key encryption algorithms.
It is therefore known as
a lightweight encryption method.
ECC is widely use in embedded
resource constraint devices and
provides many applications of
public encryption such as,
encryption and decryption, digital
signatures, and digital certificates.
To demonstrate how a public key
system mathematically works,
we will first have a bit closer look
into the popular RSA algorithm.
In another lecture, we will also have
a look at the Diffie-Hellman algorithm.
We use these classic algorithms as
examples, because they are well known and
relatively easy to present
in a short lecture.
If you are interested in details of ECC,
I encourage you to search for
related online documentation.
There is a lot of information on
ECC in a reader friendly forum.
The complex mathematics behind ECC
is out of the scope of this course.
So, let's look at RSA.
We start with generation of the public and
private keys.
The first step is to choose two
relatively large prime numbers p and q.
Typically, 1,024 bits or more in length.
The next step is to calculate
product of n of p and q,
and product phi(n) of (p-1) and (q-1).
N later becomes the modulus
of the public and
private keys, which we will see shortly.
Now, the encryption key e is chosen in
such a way that it needs two properties.
First, e has to be
relatively prime to phi(n).
Second, e has to be greater than 1 and
less than phi(n).
Two integers are relatively prime if
they share no common positive factors or
divisors except 1.
In other words, the greatest common
divisor of e and phi(n) must be 1.
We use a tuple notation for the greatest
common divisor as shown on the screen.
Now our public key is the pair of e and n.
Let's see how the private
key is calculated.
If e and phi n are prime,
then there is some integer d for
decryption, such that e times
d equals one modular phi(n).
Our private key is then defined
as the pair of d and n.
Notice that without knowing p and q it is
practically impossible to determine d.
Security of RSA relies
on this observation.
Now that we have generated the keys,
we can encrypt and decrypt a message.
In RSA, a full message is
presented as a sequence of
positive integers between 0 and n-1.
Each taking a fix number of bits
depending on the value of the modulus n.
The same applies to
the produced cipher text.
For simplicity,
let's consider a message m,
which is composed of a single
integer between 0 and n- 1.
For encryption, we take the message m and
compute the ciphertext c as m
to the power of e modular n.
For decryption we take
the cypher text c and
compute the message m as c
to the power of d modulo n.
Now let's try an example.
Suppose our two primes, p and
q, are 5 and 11 respectively.
Then n is equal to 55,
and phi(n) is equal to 40.
Now we should select
the encryption exponent, e.
Divisors of phi(n) are 1,
2, 4, 5, 8, 10, 20, and 40.
So, it could be any number less than 40,
which has no common divisor with 40.
Of the candidates, well, let's pick seven.
We should now select
the decryption exponent d,
such that d times e equals 1 mod 40.
Let's pick 23,
which satisfies the given condition,
because 23 times 7 equals 161,
which equals 4 times 40 plus 1.
Determining d is computationally
a non-trivial task.
The best way is to use
the extended Euclidean algorithm.
We don't study this algorithm here though.
So, here it is,
our public key is the pair 7,
55, and
our private key is the pair 23, 55.
Now, let's check how encryption and
decryption work.
First, our message m could be
any integer between 0 and 54.
Let's randomly pick the number 8.
For encryption to get the ciphertext c,
we calculate 8
to the power of 7 modulo 55,
which equals 2.
So our ciphertext c is 2.
Let's then decrypt the cypher text and
see if we get our original message or
plain text in or not.
We calculate 2 to the power of 23,
modulo 55,
which, amazingly, equals 8.
So it worked, we managed to
retrieve the original message m.
In this lesson, we learned about
basics of public key cryptography.
Moreover, we saw how we can
protect confidentiality
of data by RSA public key encryption.
In the next video lecture,
we will learn how public key
encryption is used for establishing
a shared secret between two parties
that don't know each other previously.
[SOUND]