Okay now we were looking at
an old nominal big omega.zero.
The wheel's not accelerating.
We don't launch that way.
We launch with everything locked down and
then we release it.
And in fact, the craft will have
some spin after it gets kicked off.
And then we engaged its wheel and
momentum happens and
how does it settle in the end
as you're spinning up?
There are some classic
answers we can go through.
So To begin with, what's commonly
done with these dual spinners,
they're released where it's spinning about
an axis that's not aligned with the wheel.
Wheel was aligned with b1, so
the spacecraft, let's assume it's spinning
about b2 or b3 or some combination
thereof, something orthogonal to b1.
So we want it to be doing this in the end,
spinning skinny, but
right now it's just doing
this kind of a tumble.
And then the reaction wheel is spun up.
If this is spinning, and
it has inertia of one, and
a spin rate of one, then inertia times
spin rate gives momentum of one.
Just non dimensional units.
I'm going to spin up my wheel until
its momentum magnitude matches that
of the space craft after launch
which is one in this case, right?
Now, in this kind of a dynamical system is
Is the angular momentum vector conserved?
Tony.
>> No, because there's a torque
being applied to spin up.
>> Right.
There's a torque.
But the torque is applied
between which two bodies?
>> The wheel and the spacecraft.
>> Okay so for the system I'm talking
about wheel and spacecraft system.
>> Okay.
>> Is that an internal torque or
an external torque?
>> It would be an internal.
>> Exactly.
So there is still no external torque.
So for the combined hub and wheel system,
the total momentum vector which
is what we [LAUGH] used to derive the
equations of motion like h dot equal to L.
That h still has to be fixed
as seen by inertial observer.
So we can use that.
So then we want to really study what
happens to the attitude as we do this
spin up, right?
And we're going to go through this.
So the initial spin rate, we said,
we're tumbling here, right?
About b2, just without loss of generality,
I'm tumbling at a rate 1,
inertia 1, gives me momentum 1,
that's what I have here.
And spinning up the momentum of
the wheel relative to the body,
that was the wheel
inertia times big omega.
Big omega was omega of
wheel relative to b, right?
I'm simply having omega dots, that tells
me how little h is changing with time.
And we're just going to
constantly increase it right now.
We're not doing any input shaping or
something like that,
just going to ramp it up linearly
until you hit the desired speed.
And the desired speed will make little h
be equal to big H, that's what we said.
So the momentum of the wheel relative to
the craft is same as the total momentum
of the system.
So the manuever time
you can figure it out.
Well at the end I have to have this much.
That's my constant rate.
You can quickly compute.
This is going to take a hundred seconds,
a thousand seconds depending on
how quickly you're ramping
up your wheel speed.
Right?
This is how long it will take to
reach this total amount of momentum.
So we can compute that.
Nominally we had launching like this,
we're spinning right and
then this wheel is going to be spinning
up until its momentum magnitude matches
this spacecraft momentum at the time T0,
and this is going to line up.
Or is it?
We argued total H vector
has to be constant, right?
We cannot change the total
momentum of this two body system
with internal torques as Tony was saying.
So h is always the same,
it's always pointing up in this drawing.
If the wheel momentum is the same as
the spacecraft initial momentum, and
the wheel is spinning about this axis.
Since the total momentum is
the momentum of the spacecraft plus
the momentum of the wheel, doesn't
that mean the spacecraft is despun,
like what Nathan was talking about?
And it must be lined up this way.
Now, the way I'm asking that question,
obviously the answer is no, right?
The trick is why?
Why?
What are the other attitudes that allow
you to have little h be equal to big H,
but I'm not lining up perfectly.
Onzo, what do you think?
>> I can't think of anything
off the top of my head.
>> Any ideas?
Think of this.
Right now we've been
talking about magnitudes.
What we have to add up really is vectors,
the ang momentum vector of the body plus
the ang momentum vector of the wheels.
Yes?
>> Depending on the direction that you.
>> Well no, we are spinning up
>> Okay, so you are assuming
>> It's locked in, and we're there, right.
But it is dependent on
the direction of these vectors.
Just because little h is equal to
the magnitude of the initial big H
doesn't mean the two directions
have to be the same.
And that's essentially, this is our
initial h that we have, this system.
This is how we launched, wheels were
locked down, then we're speeding it up.
And, at the ends the wheel has a vector
magnitude that is the same as
the initial magnitude of the system.
Little h was equal to big H,
those are the scalars.
But you could have two vectors
that have the same magnitude but
not be in the same direction.
And then this is actually what
the spacecraft body must be doing.
So this momentum vector plus this one
add up to be the same as the original.
We argue we cannot
change initial momentum.
So, by doing this maneuver,
we're not guaranteed, we, typically,
when spacecraft launched this way,
they want it to line up like this.
We talked about the Boeing 501s.
They have geostats that always point
at the earth, skinny ones like this.
You want them to be nice and even.
They're not doing this big wobble.
They call this coning motion.
This is your coning angle
that you can see right here.
So we'd like it to be zero, but
it's not typically zero when it happens.
And there's different ways to explain what
is happening, but basically this momentum
matching guarantee doesn't enforce that
those two things actually line up.
Now the analysis of this
gets rather complicated.
Typically we have to,
now I will show you some numerical
results to kind of talk about this.
We don't have nice analytic answers
to guarantee these behaviors, but
we can study this stuff.
I mean there's lots of theories
behind this but I'm giving it a spin.
Initially with Tom Blake you're not omega
2 but omega 3 for 30 degrees per second.
Have wheel inertia, spacecraft stuff,
everything's locked down.
This gives me an initial big H, momentum.
And now I'm going to go ahead and start
spinning up that wheel at a constant rate.
So I just took the equations of motion
you saw earlier, last class, and
I'm integrating them with these initial
conditions and also tracking the attitude.
I'm not just tracking omega but I used
Euler angles and, I forget what I used,
something, maybe MRPs.
And at two hundred seconds,
I have finished that maneuver.
And you saw then at two hundred seconds,
we were close to being lined up like this.
But there was still a little bit of
a wobble left, that happens there.
And so
that amount of wobble, that's what's
happening with these amplitudes here.
We can predict that now and
see what's happening.
So we get close but not quite there.
Here I'm taking a thousand seconds,
because I'm taking a lot more time.
So it'll take about a minute to run and
you can see all these simulations running
and it keeps wobbling and spinning.
But it's a much more gradual process.
So what's going to happen now
in this process is It'll take,
obviously takes more time to roll up,
but if you look at the final omega two's
before it was like plus minus seven
degrees and even these axis were bigger,
we will have less of a coning
angle at the end of this maneuver.
So when It gets close there we'll
want to take a look at that.
And that's the general trends
we have in these systems.
With a dual spinner we're just spinning
it up, we don't want to be too aggressive
because you end up with this huge
momentum vector off to the side.
You really have,
then you have to do other stuff.
You want to have a coning
angle as small as possible so
a little patience goes a long way.
Take a little bit longer
to spin this thing up and
at that point,
you have a smaller coning angle.
So it will get there.
We're about halfway there.
The way we get rid of this coning angle,
you could use thrusters,
in the end if you want
to change the attitude.
You could apply h dot equal to l, apply
some thrusters, in the right control.
And change that momentum vector of
the body, and puff it back into place.
But now we're using fuel,
we hate using fuel in space.
There's an elegant method that people have
devised which called the mutation damper.
Anybody heard of a mutation damper before?
No?
What it does is you put basically
a ball in a tube of slush,
oil, something highly viscous.
So it creates friction.
So we're losing energy.
All right?
And what we want to have is spin
about omega one in the end and so
you make that damper, you line up that
tube of slush along either b2 or 3.
So if you're still wobbling
with the conic motion,
you're always actually exciting that
slosh, and you're losing energy.
And then people have shown this stuff,
at the end it would actually get rid
of the coning motion completely.
And that goes there.
We've used this as a 50 turn project in
the past where people have to integrate
this and study the spin up and
go through that.
It's a fun project actually.
So take away notes is spin up,
just because you match momentum magnitudes
doesn't mean you've matched the vectors.
Teaching those vectors and
patience goes a long way.
To get rid of the coning angle, you want
to put a mutation damper orthogonal.
That'll get rid of the energies of
these modes here over time, and
it'll settle in place.
And there's all kinds of,
you can look up mutation dampers.
But here's the results.
So with two hundred seconds
you see where you are.
A thousand seconds,
you know, five times longer,
we've improved it by a factor of two.
There's really, it's an asintotic thing.
So if you want to get even closer,
you might take a long time.
That's where,
how patient are you, you know.
A little bit of mutation
damping can go a long way, and
get rid of the coning motion.
Other things are, we've seen plots.
I'm just going to go through this,
reasonably high-level.
But just to show you, plots have also been
applied not just for rigid bodies, but
also systems of rigid bodies like
these wheels and dual spinners.
The energy here, this is really
the energy of the spacecraft only,
here, not the real energy
relative to the spacecraft.
So not the part with i w over two,
big omega squared.
So that's called E star.
The total momentum energy of the system
is as before, the momentum sphere just
has to be constant, even with internal
torques acting because they're internal.
They're not changing the total
momentum of the system.
Which is kind of nice,
that's a constraint.
So we can rewrite the energy
ellipsoid of the spacecraft
in terms of these coordinates.
And with a little math this is how you,
this is what you come up with.
So because the energy that you have,
the momentum about the one axis is due to
the wheel and due to the spacecraft, so
you have to pull out the wheel momentum.
And then divide by the right stuff
to come up with the energy terms
of the spacecraft about the one axis.
The two and three axis look like before.
But this is a sphere, this is still an
ellipsoid, but it's a shifted ellipsoid.
If your h one two threes are essentially
your X, Y, Z, independent coordinates.
If you go look up the classic
ellipsoidal equation.
If you didn't have minus h this would be
a centered ellipsoid that's there, and
with the minus h, it actually shifts
that ellipsoid along the one access.
So as we spin up the wheel that
energy ellipsoid is going to move.
And that's what you see here.
Initially we launched
the spacecraft spin is here.
We were spinning purely about b3 in
that numerical problem I showed you.
Then as we spin up the wheel
you can see these are the momentum
coordinates that we have to satisfy.
That's the total momentum
coordinates of the spacecraft.
It intersects energy in here.
And the energy ellipsoid starts to shrink
inside and of the spacecraft cause as
we spin up the wheel the spacecraft tends
to de-spin and change it's orientation.
Although momentum we'd like
it to go into the wheels.
So there's different critical points.
At one point this ellypsoid intercepts
in this nice figure eight motion.
This kind of a separate trick stuff
that we've seen with rigid bodies.
And then when the momentum magnitude
matches, this is what you end up with.
Just because you match momentum magnitudes
doesn't guarantee that you've despun
the primary body completely.
And this is where a mutation damper would
help get rid of that remaining energy and
make that actually attractive and
collapse onto a point.
And that's what would be happening there.
So I'm just kind of showing
this more as a pictorial thing.
So you've seen this.
It's not something that'll be on the exam.
But these plots, these graphical
visualizations of momentum and
energy are quite powerful.
And if you read a lot of
classical attitude control,
you will see these kind of tools
being used in different areas.