So here's a example we
want to run through.
Here, I have some principle inertias
that are 350, 300, and 400.
Now, just by the numbers, a little
bit unfortunate, the intermediate one
if 50 beneath the max and is 50 above
the min, so it's plus and minus 50.
This is why when we look at these wheels,
the critical wheel speeds,
where things go stable unstable,
it happens to be symmetric.
But, generally these inertias
aren't split evenly like that.
So generally those critical wheel speeds
are not necessarily symmetric, all right.
This example will have them symmetric.
The wheel inertia is ten kilograms,
just to make a lot of math easy.
Spacecraft is to spin about 60 rpm, about
b1, so that's our Omega e1 that you have.
And so now, we're trying to figure out
how fast do we have to spin this wheel
at least to guarantee linear
stability of the system.
So you want both bracketed terms
to be either positive or negative.
Now, those two bracketed terms could
be positive, that's the Set 1.
That's where we have I1 must be greater
than these other two terms here.
In that case, the left bracket and
the right bracket are both positive, and
then we have a stable system.
Set 2, actually just simply reverses this,
greater than becomes a less than.
This is the condition that makes the first
and second bracket go negative and
that is also a stable configuration,
all right.
So now, we want to look at what
is the range of spin rates.
So the way I like to think of this
is just look at the spin axis.
We have zero.
And then, I can go positive spin rate and
negative spin rate.
And we're going to put in inequality
condition to start to go it has to be
at least to the right of this mark.
And it has to be at least to the left
of this mark, so what's left?
The union or
intersections of these different areas,
that's how I solve this stuff at least.
So if we're looking at this,
in this problem
if the wheel speed is zero,
is this system going to be stable?
Brian.
>> They'd take a look at
the inequalities again.
>> No, no.
If the wheel speed is zero,
there's no longer a dual spin,
there's simply a single rigid body.
And we're spinning about b1.
About which inertia axis
are we spinning then?
>> It's not going to be stable.
>> All right, because now we have 350.
So b1 is an axis of intermediate inertia
in this particular example, right.
So we know up front, zero cannot
be included in my solution space.
I have to, if this is going to work,
I have to have something positive or
negative.
And we'll see how that drops out.
So if we do this,
here's the two inequality conditions.
The second one, for
example here, this is one set.
You can say okay, I2 minus,
you can bring this term over,
that gives you I2 minus I1,
divide by this.
Iw, I2 minus I1,
gives you minus 350 divided by 10.
No, it gets you minus 50 divided by ten,
gives you minus five.
So by bringing this over, omega hat
has to be bigger than minus five.
If I'm just going to draw that here,
so let's say,
here's the minus five part,
that means, what did I say, less than?
All right,
thinking too many steps ahead, okay.
No, it's greater than.
Okay, so that means we would have to be
somewhere greater than minus five.
But that's only one condition.
Now the other condition,
here I'm just going through the math
a little bit more steps, right.
I'm bringing this condition and bringing
this part over to the left hand side.
I1 back over to the right hand side.
I divide by IW2, here it's I3 minus I1.
You plug in the numbers, which you do
something similar in the homework, so
I'm just not going to.
You know how to do this algebra.
Then omega hat as to be
greater than plus five.
So if we look at this now and say, okay,
there's also a plus five,
and here's the other point.
This is the domain that makes
the second bracket go to B positive.
What is the actual solution space then for
stability?
[INAUDIBLE] Great.
So that union between both, right?
because we need both of
them to be positive.
That's going to be here, all right?
Outs greater than.
Is that the only domain, though?
Carlo, what do you think?
>> Will be less than minus five.
>> Less than minus five, now talk me
through why that it's also domain correct.
>> Because the second set of equations
doesn't give us that answer.
>> Yep, the first set always
has greater than, greater than.
You've identified two points where
each bracketed term flips signs.
Once you've found those, you've really
found, instead of greater than,
it's all less than.
So instead of always
being to the right of,
it's always going to
be all to the left of.
And, again, the same unions.
So if you did that to make both brackets
negative, If I pick a different color,
let me make blue for negative right.
Then you would have to be here or here and
the union of that is
just going to be here.
So you can see as expected the origin
is not included in the solution space.
Because as Brian was pointing out,
this is a single rigid body spinning
about axis remediated inertia.
We know it's not stable, but
if the wheel spins up enough
then at some point,
you'll notice with this wheel spinning,
you're spinning oars is an oblate body,
you're spinning by axis of max inertia.
That wheel by itself,
the way it's defined.
It's always going to be stable, right?
So if that wheel spins fast enough,
one way to think of this is the stability
of that wheel is going to overcome
the instability of the spacecraft spin and
that's how we stabilize it.
But you have to get to some minimum
amount where it's just equal and
then you have to be greater than that,
hopefully, quite a bit greater that
it will increase your stiffness and
your response time as well, right.
So either you can go positive or you can
go negative and that will get you there.
Now, so good.
So in this case, I have, this is one of
the wheel's speed, the critical speeds,
you could use or
it has to be bigger than that really,
that's what you have to write.
Not equal, but probably bigger than that.
Or it could also be less
than minus 300 in this case.
There's two sets, both brackets positive,
both brackets negative.
So if I'm giving you some
problem like this though,
here I am saying,
we are spinning about major axis.
So in this case, b1 is axis of maximum
inertia and without a rotor spin, so
the origin, we would have to be stable,
which is what I am showing.
If we are spinning up more about
the spacecraft by definition,
already has a positive spin, about b1.
That is how we derived to all this stuff.
That's how picked b1.
And now,
the wheel is also spinning about that.
If the spacecraft is max inertia stable,
the wheel is max inertia stable and
they're both spinning about positive b1,
it's always just going to be stable.
More and more stable.
If you start to spin it
the opposite direction though,
even though the space craft by itself
without that wheel will stable,
it has the speed momentum
that helps stabilize it.
What happens with the wheel,
if it's in the opposite direction,
it's going to start to pull out the total
momentum gets reduced, actually.
If this is spinning at 10 RPM positive and
the wheel is 100 RPM negative,
you're pulling out momentum.
And in fact, the momentum perspective,
at some point it acts like the separatrix,
it acts like the unstable
intermediate axis motion and
you will drive a system unstable.
But the good news is no matter what axis,
principle axis,
you want to spin nominally, we can always
find a wheel speed that will stabilize it.
[LAUGH] The bad news is no matter how
stable the spacecraft was before you
touched it, once you touch it, you have
the capability to drive it unstable.
So make sure you have the right
real speeds otherwise
your sponsor will not be happy.
At some point again,
if you go fast enough,
then the wheel momentum will dominate and
it's very, very stable.
Whatever the spacecraft's
doing is almost noise.
So with all duo spinners to extremes
infinity real speeds always stable.
But in between, there is a region,
a finite zone, that is unstable.
So for an intermediate axis speed,
which we looked at.
And in our problem, we had plus and
minus five, that was just because of the
inertias, it doesn't have to be symmetric.
If you see something like this
that excludes the origin,
right away I could say,
this must be spinning about an axis of
intermediate inertia with a dual-spinner.
Just from the solution space.
And, if you have an axis
of a least inertia,
you're spinning about this region that you
shouldn't be spinning about is actually in
the positive spin direction and just
all comes out of the mathematics then.
Jordan.
>> Sorry,
I missed how can it be stable if you're
spinning it less than negative five.
>> Both bracketed terms.
because the two brackets have
to either be positive, and
that was the argument for
the black hash lines.
But we found the two critical points.
If we also less than
those critical points,
then both brackets both become negative.
>> Okay.
>> And that's why this is also a possible
answer, out of the mathematics.
>> Thanks.
>> Yeah, good.
So anyway, but
this gives you now a quick solution space.
You can do these easy homework with
this yourself, to come up with it.
But just remember the extremums
are always included.
The origin is only included for
a max and min inertia case and
then you kind of look at the pattern.
If I see the pattern, I know right
away what type of spin we're doing.