We're doing a review of
what we covered last time.
We had dual spinners.
So with a dual spinner,
I had some spacecraft,
didn't necessarily have to be symmetric.
But this spacecraft has b1, b2,
b3 and
you'd have some panel attached to it.
So now, Nathan.
What do we do with the dual spinner?
What's the set up that we do here?
>> Well you have one section spinning
to maintain your angular momentum.
Or, so it's spinning about its axis of
minimum energy, so maximum inertia.
>> Okay.
>> And then the other section is
not spinning essentially.
>> Is that required?
Do we have to spin about an axis
of a minimum of inertia?
Does the second section have to be despun?
>> I guess not.
>> No, in fact that's what I'm going
to show today through an example.
We can stabilize which is
the beauty of dual spinners.
I can make any of the axis stable.
Now if you have energy loss the minimum
inertia one you have to kind of be
a little bit more careful there's
some power equations you can find
on this stuff.
But conceptually, we know without
energy loss this is a stable spin and
this is a stable spin.
But a spin about the access of
intermediate act inertia tends to
flip around and be unstable, all right?
So, with a dual spinner in this
mathematics, we have a fly wheel.
How do we line up, Brett, how do we line
up this fly wheel in our dual spinner?
>> One of the body axis?
>> Yeah, one of the principal ones.
So, if we wanted to have a nominal spin
here, Omega1, that's my equilibrium spin.
I am going to add a wheel, which has
a spin axis, going to call it gs-hat,
that's my wheel spin axis,
which is the same thing as b1.
Those are lined up.
Good, then we went through,
how do we find equations of motion?
We still use H equal to L.
But H is now due to two rigid bodies.
And there's different ways to derive it.
We went through that last time.
There's angular momentum of the space
craft and the wheel that was I,
that was a summed I times omega plus the
wheel momentum routed to the spacecraft.
Or you can treat them as two separate
ones, I showed you that as well and
you can combine again.
That's a great problem that I've
used before in the final so
make sure you go through that.
It's a good simple exercise.
Later in class, you can do spacecraft
within variable speed CMGs.
It's the same process but
about 12 pages more algebra.
So this is where you want
to practice the process so
you don't get silly sign errors.
Then the rest of it just
kind of becomes mechanical.
I'm going to do this,
I'm going to do this, and
you can use computer
tools as well to do that.
So practice this.
So we went through this.
Now I labeled this as an equilibrium
spin omega 1E, all right.
What does it mean Mandar
to be in equilibrium spin?
What does that mean?
[COUGH]
>> All Omega dots go to 0.
>> Exactly, any dynamical system, any
flow process or whatever you have, if you
have x dot equal to f, a nonlinear thing,
for [INAUDIBLE] xe is x dot equal to 0.
And the planar pendulum has one
equilibrium here, one equilibrium here.
Does this have anything to do with
stability, finding equilibrius?
No, which just it's a convenient point
about which we tend to discuss stability.
But stability is a separate concept
from finding equilibrius, all right.
So we found the equilibrius and
in particularly for
the single rigid body there were three
equilibrium spins we discussed earlier.
Spinning about axis of least inertia,
maximum inertia, but
also intermediate inertia.
Those are equilibrium spins.
If you put it perfectly on
there it would tumble that way.
But if you bump it, if you perturb it,
that little delta that we were talking
about earlier, do you stay close?
What happens to my spin rates?
Right, do I wobble just a little bit and
stay there, which is true for
this kind of a thing?
But if I throw it this way you can see
it did several gyrations right away,
that's an unstable motion, all right?
That's what we're after now.
And so good, so
we identified while the single rigid
body could have equilibrium
spins about all three axis.
For the duel spinner
the equilibrium spins we end
up using is primarily
the one about the GS axis.
I say primarily,
let's look at that equation again.
[SOUND]
Here,
we argue that if I have a non-0
Omega 1 and Omega 2's and 3's are 0,
I always have all my dots.
Omega dots are going to be 0
like Mandar was saying earlier.
Perfect, but
you can also have Omega E1 be non-0.
Omega E2 is 0.
Which makes this 0 and this 0.
You could pick particular inertias, a
particular E1 at a particular wheel speed,
such that this combination with a non-0
omega E3 actually goes to 0 as well.
That's also an equilibrium, but
it's not one we typically fly,
because now all of a sudden you
have a very particular solution.
You have to have exactly this wheel speed.
If you're a little bit fast,
or little bit lower,
you're out of that equilibrium part.
Whereas this other spin we had if this
wheel speed is supposed to be 10 rpm and
I put in 11 rpm it's still
an equilibrium actually and
still going to hold the stair.
And so, we did that, here we just added
what is the equilibrium plus delta and
then dropped tie over terms, right?
And you end up with these
differential equations.
That it's stable,
if you can see here, again.
If instead of putting in that 10 rpm but
I gave it something slightly faster and
perturbed, this can hold that speed
because my angular acceleration about
the one axis,
the spin axis of the wheel, is just 0.
So you just stay there.
The other two, tends to couple and
we have two first order differential
equations that are coupled and
the way we solve these was,
we differentiate again, substitute in.
So we replaced two coupled differential
equations with one second order decoupled
differential equation, and in the end,
it's all about these two bracketed terms.
This is your effective stiffness.
X doubled up plus K X,
K has to be positive right?
And either we make this positive or
this positive or
we make both bracketed terms negative.
Different ways we can write it?
We'll have in that example today,
you will see omega hat that's
a non-dimensionalized.
We take our wheel speed, 100 RPM,
divide by the spacecraft speed, 2 RPM, so
megahat would be 50 in this case.
It's a 50 multiplier factor between
the spacecraft spin and the wheel spin.
And then it just breaks down to
these inertias that you need.
And you have to pick spin speeds such
that both terms are positive, or
both terms are negative.
If you put in 0 spin speed we recover
the case of having a single rigid body.
And that's how we quickly found that this
stiffness is only going to be positive if
my inertia is either the maximum inertia,
that means we're doing the flat spin we
discussed earlier with the pole hose.
Or b1 is access of least inertia
which at least linearly without
energy loss is also stable.
So you see in here also mathematical
linearized proof of the stability
of the min and max inertia case.
The intermediate one gets positive and
negative, definitely not stable.
And the non-0 one in
the non-dimensionalized terms.
These are the conditions we need.