[MUSIC]
Hello, I am glad to see you back for
this lesson.
In previous modules, we explored different
types of embedded IoT operating systems.
Now we will look into
the details of Contiki and
discover certain detailed behaviors.
At the end of the lesson,
you will be able to understand
some of the challenges in developing
IoT applications for Contiki.
First of all, let's elaborate
the title of today's lesson, Contiki,
a hybrid operating system.
Remember our discussion in previous module
on operating system kernel designs?
We discussed contiki as an example
of a modular kernel design,
combining features from monolithic and
microkernel.
This allows it to inherit some
advantages of both systems.
Contiki implements a hybrid model
through an event driven kernel.
In Contiki, preemptive multi-threading is
implemented as an application library.
This is optionally
linked with the program,
if the program requires
multi-threading features.
There are two key benefits when
building a system like this.
First, concurrency can be provided
without the need of per-thread stacks or
locking mechanisms.
This benefit is evident by looking at why
per-thread stacks are not suitable for
embedded devices.
Per-thread stack approach
allocates a stack for each thread.
It is hard to specify how
much a thread requires.
In addition,
when a thread is created the memory for
stack must be assign or allocated.
This creates a problem,
because memory assigned for
specific task cannot be use
by other concurrent test.
The second benefit is that event driven
model with the state driven programming
are difficult for programmers to manage.
In addition, not all programs can
be expressed as state machines.
Let's take an example of a purely
event driven operating system.
In such a system, a task could
consume the full CPU time completely.
When the task is complex and
require a long CPU time, the system cannot
respond to external events sometime.
A preemptive multi-threaded system
overcomes the problem in such situation.
Hence, a hybrid system can be
considered as the most suitable for
such kind of problems.
As I mentioned earlier,
Contiki inheritance advantages
from microperable design, and hence
separates from the kernel from processors.
This helps to reduce the kernel
size as small as possible and
consequently the probability of
bulks can be dramatically reduce.
Similar to microkernel design,
Contiki also uses messaging mechanism for
communication between services and
the kernel.
However, instead of using the peer
messages discussed in micro kernel lesson,
Contiki uses posting events.
The only difference between pure messages
and event posting is formatting.
There is no hardware abstraction layer or
HAL in Contiki.
Therefore, the bias drivers and
applications communicate
directly with the hardware.
In order to give you a better
understanding of the pros and
cons of removing hardware
obstruction layer in Contiki,
I will first discuss about
the hardware obstruction layer.
The hardware abstraction layer is a layer
between application, component code,
and hardware.
In other words, HAL allows operating
systems to interact with devices
at an abstract level rather
than a detailed hardware level.
The main purposes of halt is to help
the OS access hardware simply and
portably via abstract API's regardless
of the type of underlying hardware.
Therefore, HAL has many advantages.
For example,
first it enables switching hardware.
It is possible to switch
to another hardware,
such as a different microcontroller
during development.
As a result, there is less of a risk
due to choosing suitable tools.
Second, it allows cross development.
It is not possible to develop application
and components more conveniently.
As a result,
the development speed can be fast.
In addition, a large-scale
simulation environment can be built.
Third, it results in less effort and
less bugs.
This enables a significant reduction in
lines of code, which leads to less bugs.
The final benefit is for
automated unit testing.
It is possible to run embedded
software on a computer platform,
extending the concept of continuous
integration with automated unit tests.
Although HAL has many advantages,
it also has several drawbacks.
Let's look at some of them.
First, HAL cannot completely cover
all available features of a particular
hardware, such as a microcontroller.
As a result, it limits some
functionalities of the hardware.
Possible conflict with other frameworks,
libraries and
components is the second drawback of HAL.
The third problem is that it is hard or
even possible to maintain the hold,
especially in cleaning HALs mess.
Finally, a number of lines of
code increase dramatically
when integrated into the OS.
Currently, HAL is deprecated in
different Linux distributions.
Since Contiki is built for
wireless sensor networks and
embedded IoT devices,
it is better off without HAL.
Because of this, device drivers and
applications communicate
directly with the hardware.
Based on a modular kernel approach,
Contiki has the ability to load and
unload models at run time.
This allows Contiki to load
only the necessary services,
consequently allowing it to
have a reduced kernel size.
Almost all abstractions are implemented
as libraries and services, except for
CPU multiplexing, which is the only
obstruction provided by the core system.
The implementation is almost similar
to a scheduler of microkernel.
Looking at this implementation,
Contiki is developed in C language, and
it's applications are also written in C.
Therefore, its is easy to develop
application, reprogram, and
replace services.
Last but not least,
Contiki is easily portable.
This implies that it possible to run it
on various microcontroller architectures
such as the CC2538, CC2650, SensorTek,
AdmilABR, and the MSP430, and so on.
It is easy to add support for
new microcontrollers using the built-in
libraries and existing Contiki platform.
For example, a programmer can easily
port Contiki to their own board
by creating configuration files for
the specific microcontroller and
edit existing general
configuration files of Contiki.
However, it is rare for
a programmer to add a new
microcontroller to the Contiki platform.
As Contiki supports all popular micro
controllers and embedded devices.
This is all for the lesson about Contiki,
a hybrid system.
I hope that you got the important features
of Contiki's kernel, and the hybrid model.
We also discussed unique characteristics
of Contiki, and its kernel.
I hope to see you in the next video,
which will further explain many
advanced features of Contiki.