[MUSIC]
Welcome.
It is good to see you back for
this lesson.
Previously, we explored
Contiki as a hybrid system.
Now we will look into more
details of the operating system
to discover other
characteristics in depth.
At the end of this lesson, you will be
able to understand what benefits and
challenges Contiki presents when
developing iOT applications.
First of all, let's discuss
the main components of Contiki.
A Contiki system includes the kernel,
libraries and applications or
services, of which applications and
services are implemented as modules.
They are only loaded when
an application requires them.
As discussed before, this is one of the
main positive characteristics of Contiki.
If you do not remember details about this,
I recommend you go back to other videos,
we let it to modular kernel design and
Contiki.
In Contiki, it is possible to dynamically
replace all processes at run-time,
thus helping to save resources.
Processes in this case can be either
services or application programs.
So far in our discussion,
we haven't addressed what applications and
services are and their differences.
From the point of view of Contiki,
they are all modules which
are loaded when needed.
However, from the point of view of
a programmer, a service is implemented to
provide a functionality which is used work
for one or more application processes.
All communication between processes
are done through the kernel.
We mentioned in the previous lesson that
there is no hardware
obstruction layer in Contiki.
As a result of this, device drivers and
applications communicate
directly with the hardware.
If you don't know or
remember why Contiki does not provide
a hardware abstraction layer,
I suggest you to go back to the previews
lesson titled Contiki, a hybrid system.
All processes share the same address and
space and
all run in the same protection domain.
This enables Contiki to run in
memory constrained devices.
In order to give you a deeper
understanding of this idea,
we will have a lesson threads and
multi-threading.
In that lesson, you will get an idea
of why and how Contiki achieves it.
But let's now examine how a process
is created and treated in Contiki.
A process is a piece of program code
which is executed by Contiki's system.
A process is started in two ways.
The first is when Contiki starts, and
the second when the module loaded.
A process runs when an event
related to the process occurs,
such as a timer event or an external one.
For example,
consider an application that prints hello
world to the terminal every second.
This application process runs whenever a
timer event is triggered at every second.
It means that a counter of the timer
will count down every second, and
when it reaches zero,
the event is triggered.
Countdown frequency is based on
the particular type of timer event used.
In order to have a closer
view of a timer event,
I recommend that you stay with me for
the upcoming videos.
In those videos,
different types of time or events, and
other types of events
will be deeply discussed.
There are two types of
execution modes in Contiki.
These are cooperative and
preemptive modes.
Cooperative process code runs
sequentially in a queue.
This means that the first process
has the right to use the CPU,
while other processors wait for
their right to access the CPU.
After the process which
occupied the CPU is finished,
then the next waiting process in
the queue gets the right to use the CPU.
In contrast, preemptive mode
handles process differently.
In the preemptive context, a running
process can be stopped by an interrupt,
and the higher priority test immediately
takes over the right to use the CPU.
After finishing its job,
it returns the right to access
the CPU to the interrupted process.
A process is defined by
an event handler function and
an optional poll handler function.
In order to give you a better view of
a process, and how it is defining Contiki,
we're going to look at the internal
structure of a Contiki process.
The Contiki process is a combination
of two different parts.
These are process control block and
the process threat.
In this lesson, we only focus on
Contiki System and Contiki Processes.
Therefore a process thread will
be discussed in following videos.
The process control blog is composed of
information about each process such as
the state of the process, the pointer to
the next process, name of the process,
a pointer to a process thread, the state
of the proto thread and internal flags.
The slide shows a structure
of a process in Contiki.
The structure is written
in a standard C language.
The process, Control Block,
is only used by the kernel.
Therefore, users do not have any right
to access the Control Block directly.
This helps the system
protect the process and
avoid unexpected mistakes or
bugs caused by programmers.
Actually, the kernel only keeps
a pointer to the process of state
which is health in
the process' private memory.
This means that every process
has its own state, and
the state cannot be accessed
by other processes.
As you can see in this slide, the Process
Control Block's structure is quite simple,
and it does not contain
complex information.
Therefore, it is lightweight, and
it just occupies a few bytes of memory.
In Contiki, a Process Control Block
cannot be declared or defined directly.
The block is defined
via the process macro.
In order to give you
a better view of this macro,
I am going to take an example
of hello world processing.
As you can see,
the process macro has two parameters,
the name of the Process Control Block and
the textural description.
The variable name of the Process Control
Block is used for accessing the process,
while the description text of the process
is used by programmers for debugging.
As mentioned in previous videos,
Contiki uses posting events for
interprocess communication.
This mechanism is also similar
to the messaging mechanism in
Microkernel described before.
Contiki's system is
partitioned in two parts.
The first part is the core, and
the second is the loaded program section.
The partitioning is made at compiled time,
and
it's specific to the deployment
in which Contiki is used.
Typically, the core consists of
Contiki kernel, the program loader,
most commonly used parts of the language
run-time, support libraries, and
a communication stack with device
drivers for the communication hardware.
The core is compiled into
a single binary image
that is stored in the deploy devices.
It is generally not
modified after deployment.
Although it is possible to overwrite or
patch the core by a special boot loader.
Programs are loaded into
the system by the program loader.
Which gets the program binaries by
using directly attached storage, or
using the communications tech.
Typically, programs to be
loaded into the system
are first stored in the EEPROM before
they are moved into the code memory.
This is all for this lesson on
Contiki System and Contiki processes.
I hope that you have now a better
understanding of Contiki System's
structure and how it works.
I hope to see you in the next videos,
which will explain many other advanced
features of Contiki, such as Contiki's
kernel architecture and threats.
[SOUND]