[MUSIC]
We have learned how to differentiate just
a ton of functions.
If we can differentiate two functions, we
can differentiate their sum.
We can differentiate their difference.
We can differentiate any polynomial.
If we can differentiate two functions, we
learned about the product and
the quotient rule, so we can differentiate
their product and their quotient.
We've also seen how to differentiate e to
the
x, and we know how to differentiate
natural log.
But there are still some functions that we
can't differentiate.
We can't differentiate trig functions yet.
We don't yet know how to differentiate
sine or cosine, and that is now our task.
What is the derivative of sine?
What is the derivative of cosine?
Once we know those derivatives, we will be
able to calculate, very complicated
expressions involving trig functions.
Because we've already learned the change
rule,
which lets us differentiate the
composition of functions.
So if we can just figure out what the
derivative of sine of x is, and what the
derivative of cosine of x is, then we're
going to
be able to differentiate all kinds of very
complicated expressions.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]