[MUSIC]
Welcome to the lesson on
Transport Layer Protocol.
Previously, we have looked at
Application Layer Protocols or
protocols designed to help programs and
services understand each other.
In this lesson,
we will look at transport layer protocols
which take date from
application layer services and
make sure they reach the service or
process the destination end.
One thing that most of us
are familiar with is an IP address.
An IP address is associated
with a machine or host and
it's a way to make your data
reach that specific host.
They can be multiple processes running
on that machine, such as Outlook mail,
Firefox browser, FTP server,
Secure Shell, and Remote Desktop.
Now, the host got the data but
how do you make sure that
each process receives the data
that was intended for it?
This is where transport
layer protocols come in.
They receive information
from lower layers and
pass it up to the right user
application or service.
In this way, you can have multiple
services and applications running on your
machine, although you have only one
IP address and network interface.
Transport layer protocols do
a lot more than just that.
They establish and manage these
connections between processes,
they divide the data from user
applications into chunks so
that they are easier to transport.
Transport layer protocols can
also offer congestion control,
they analyze the network and
adjust the throughput.
Moreover, they can offer error
correction to detect and
correct errors that occurred
during data transmission.
Some can also offer other
services like reliability.
Making sure that all
the data is transferred and
received in the order
it was initially sent.
Transport layer protocols do not dictate
how a packet is sent over the network.
They simply hand off data to
the lower Internet layer, and
pick up data from the Internet layer.
In essence, they operate on the end nodes,
not on the network itself.
And are therefore also
called end to end protocols.
So a short round up of these services that
a transport layer protocol can provide.
They can establish, manage,
and terminate the connections.
Handle the flow of data in case
the receiving end is slower or
has smaller buffers.
Make sure all the packets are sent and
are arrow free and
avoid too much traffic on the network.
We will now look into two of
the main transport layer protocols,
mainly TCP and UDP.
Transmission Control Protocol is
a connection oriented transport
layer protocol.
In the Internet protocol suite TCP/IP,
this is where the acronym
TCP comes from,
it's a fairly complex protocol.
Especially compared to
its counterpart UDP,
simply because of the multiple
services it provides.
Some of the distinctive
features of TCP are,
TCP offers the ability to receive
exactly the same numbers of
packets as will send and
in the same order.
All TCP packets are therefore
numbered making it easier for
the end system to re-group them in order.
For reliability TCP uses acknowledgements,
each transmission is
acknowledged by the receiver.
If the packet is not acknowledged in
a certain time frame, it is retransmitted.
The receiver can also inform the sender of
the specific packets it has not received.
TCP delays can sometimes be very high for
the upper layer application.
As TCP waits for
all the data to be received,
puts the data in order and
then forwards it to the upper layer.
Reliability is the reason why some
application layer protocols do not offer
their own reliable communication
structures but rely on TCP instead.
TCP offers bidirectional communication,
both parties can send and
receive packets and
they can do it simultaneously.
TCP offers flow control,
if the receiver buffers are small,
TCP can reduce the rate of transmission in
order to avoid overflowing the end system.
If the receiver buffers are full,
the receiver will start dropping packets,
meaning the sender will not
get any acknowledgements.
This lack of acknowledgments
acts as an indicator for
the sender to either slow down or stop.
Network congestion is the reduction
of throughput because of
too much traffic on the network.
TCP offers a mechanism called slow start,
it starts transmitting
lower number of packets and gradually
increases until congestion occurs.
An indication of congestion is
the lack of acknowledgements.
That means either the sender
has reached the network's
transmit capacity or
the receiver can't handle anymore packets.
In both cases it scales back,
this is a method to prevent the host
from causing immediate congestion.
Finally, it's up to TCP how it
organizes and sends the data.
TCP sends data in streams of bytes.
It takes data from the application layer,
let's say 1000 bytes,
chops it into pieces.
For example, ten pieces of 100 bytes, and
sends the pieces down to the network or
Internet layer for transmission.
On the other hand it can take data in
multiple bytes from the application layer.
For example, ten pieces,
each of 20 bytes, and
send them as 100, 200 bytes packet.
TCP is slow due to its
reliability controls.
Another reason for TCP being slow
is the three-way handshake it uses,
the initiator sends a synchronized packet.
The receiver,
upon reception of the synchronized packet,
sends a synchronized acknowledge packet.
And lastly, the connection initiator
sends an acknowledge packet.
This is why we call TCP
a connection oriented protocol,
it first establishes a proper connection.
When we want to close a connection,
then there is even more
comprehensive four way handshake.
Transport Layer Security, or
TLS, is another transport layer
protocol that secures
communication between two parties.
It's not a part of TCP but
it relies on TCP,
which is why we are mentioning it here.
This protocol will be discussed later on.
TCP is a reliable means of
communication and therefore,
it can be used in any situation
where a sure delivery is required.
This assured delivery
comes at the cost of time.
TCP is slow and delays can be very long as
it will wait to reorder all the packets.
That's why it might not be the best option
for very time dependent applications.
HTTP doesn't offer any built-in
reliability mechanisms but,
as it runs on top of TCP,
TCP handles that for it.
The file transfer protocol, FTP, and
the chatting protocol, XMPP, also use TCP.
XMPP is a chat protocol, so
if you send a good night message or
message with some expression
of love to someone via XMPP.
You don't want your message to get
lost and never reach its destination.
TCP ensures that the receiver
gets your emotions,
well maybe a little late,
but she or he will get it.
TCP can handle that networks or
congestions.
In unreliable network situations
its better to use TCP.
Netflix uses TCP to send
a movie to your device.
But you might say that
movies are real time and
TCP is slow, I don't want stuttering.
Well, avoiding that stuttering
is the reason Netflix uses TCP.
First TCP's congestion
control mechanisms will probe
the network and use all the available
bandwidth between you and Netflix.
Secondly, TCP uses buffers to
temporarily store the received data.
And therefore, the local application
can prefetch data from Netflix servers.
Well, this was TCP,
now we will look at UDP.
User Datagram Protocol or
UDP is another transport layer protocol.
Unlike TCP,
it doesn't offer congestion control,
it's not reliable and
it doesn't send data in packet streams.
It also doesn't assure in-order delivery
or care if you receive duplicates.
Also, there is no three
way handshake which is so
far the only good thing
we have said about UDP.
So why does it exist and
why would anyone use it?
First of all, because of all the things
it doesn't do, it's very simple.
This makes it light and
as it doesn't care about connections or
handshakes, it's fast.
It is stateless, meaning it doesn't
maintain session or connection state.
Each request is treated as
a separate unique entity.
This also makes it suitable for
simple request response queries.
TCP sends numbered packet streams and
then reassembles them at the other end.
UDP treats each packet as
an individual complete message.
It sends one complete message and
receives one complete message
with every sent receive request.
To show you the difference
between the TCP and
UDP formats, this is a 20-byte TCP header.
And this is an 8-byte UDP header.
This shows the relative size differences
between the two and the simplicity of UDP.
UDP has its own use cases,
it is used for real time streaming,
where timing is more important
than in order delivery.
And where reliability is not
that important because one or
two lost frames do not affect
the end user experience.
Therefore, UDP is suitable for
time sensitive applications
such as Voice Over IP and
multiplayer online games.
The smaller header size of UDP compared to
TCP makes UDP suitable for
bandwidth constraint environments.
Also, it has a lower processing
overhead which is beneficial for
very small low power devices.
Being connectionless, UDP's good for
broadcasting as well,
especially IPTV or streaming.
The server doesn't have to
maintain a separate state, and
session information for each connection.
As it treats each message as
an independent entity, UDP is generally
good for
simple request response style operations.
Some protocols that employ and benefit
from UDP are Domain Name Service, DNS.
Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol,
DHCP, and Network Time Protocol, NTP.
In each of these, you send a query and
receive a response.
One message is sent,
one message is received.
And there is DTLS or
Datagram Transport Layer Security.
It is not part of UDP but
it's used in conjunction with UDP.
This security of protocol
will be discussed later on.
In this lesson, we discussed the basic
functionalities of the transport layer.
We also looked at the transport
layers protocols, TCP and UDP.
In another lesson,
we will look into the Internet layer and
see how data is moved from
the host over the network.
So far, we have been dealing with data
that is still on the local machine.
[SOUND]