[SOUND] [MUSIC] Hi, and welcome to week
four, of Creative Programming for Digital
Media and Mobile Applications.
I'm Mick, and this is Marco and Matt.
Today we're going to be looking at making
a basic game.
But we're going to focus on a certain
type of game.
A physics-based game that you can run on
a mobile device.
These are really, really popular casual
games, and they're, I think for two
reasons.
Firstly because it's nice to be able to
run something which uses physics on your
phone.
But in addition to that, it's something
which has got us a dynamic game play.
So, when you use physics in a game, you
can never be quite sure what's going to
happen and it, very, very small changes
in the way that you use the game can have
a big effect on your game world.
so this is the first time we've done a
game, and it's going to, I think, take a
step up in the intensity.
In the, complexity of some of the
programming that we're doing.
Mark has got a big chunk of stuff to tell
you about physics.
He's built his own physics engine, which,
integrates Java and Javascript in a
really neat way, and works entirely in
processing.
And then, Matt's going to use that to do
some interesting stuff triggering sound
effects and actually generating and
triggering that sound effects entirely
based on collisions that happen in the
game world.
So there is a lot of interesting stuff
this week, there is also a little demo of
an app that we have built for you called,
Angry Droids, which I can tell you has
absolutely nothing to do with any other
2D physics based games that you might of
played.
fine so without further ado, I think
we're going to start with Marco.
[MUSIC]