[SOUND].
This week I'm going to talk about Physics
Engines.
Now, physics engines have a really
powerful tool to get animation into
action in in, in interactive programs.
The great things about physics engines is
that they use mathematics, physics, to
simulate the movement of objects.
So you can get objects that move just
like they do in the real world.
And really if you've got a physic sense
you don't have to write much of the code
at all for that animation, because the
physics engine will handle a lot of it
for you.
They're very hard code to write yourself,
but once you've got all that mass
encapsulated.
You can just create objects and they will
behave much as they would in the real
world.
You're going to work with a physics
engine called Box2D, which does
everything in two dimensions.
So, it's just slightly simpler than a
three dimensional physics engine.
And it suits our, our needs very well
because it's, we're all writing 2D 2D
programs, in this course.
It's been used very extensively.
Probably most famously in the game Angry
Birds which, you've probably heard of.
Considering it's one of the most
successful video games of all time, by
now, I expect.
so, what is a physics engine?
A physics engine works with objects, and
it moves objects around.
So here we have a circle and rectangle,
and these objects are moved by forces.
So as in the physical world, forces are
types of objects and that causes them to
move around.
We'll talk in detail about both of these
things in this lecture.
But first I need to sort of talk a bit
about how the whole world is represented.
Now, you actually need to have an
explicit representation of the physics
world as well as the objects in it.
And I'll come back to how you create it.
But before I say that there's something a
little different about how the physics
world is represented than what we've done
up until now.
Up to now we've upcentered everything in
terms of pixels on the screen, and that's
fine.
That's, we're dealing with the screen.
We can work all our distances can be our
pixels.
But this is the real world isn't broken
up into squares.
And if you really want to simulate the
real world properly.
You have to seem like there's a
continuous world, things don't change
that much.
You just get rid of the grid.
But you're still using x and y position.
these are no longer whole numbers., they
can be fractional.
but the x and y are still our fundamental
representation of positions and
directions to the work.
But I'll talk a little bit about how to
discuss x and y but deeper
mathematically.
Because that will help a little bit when
discussing physics engines.
I won't get heavily mathematical, I'll
just prepare you with a few things.
X and y aren't really separate things.
They, they were just a way of
representing a position of an object on
the screen.
And we can combine them together into a
single thing we call a vector represented
by this line in this diagram.
So here we have a vector.
Well it's showing now like v.
We can think of it as an x and a y,
that's our position.
And we can also think of it has having
direction and a length.
It looks like an arrow, it has it's
pointing in a certain direction and it
looks align, it has a certain length.
We called the length align filled with
two hallow bars, across it, we might need
that notation for much.
And once we've got vectors, they're not
just the representations the x and y's.
Mathematically vectors also include a
bunch mathematical operations we can do
with them, some of which are quite
powerful.
So, for example if we negate a vector, do
minus v, which is just minus x minus y,
it points in the opposite direction.
If we multiple the vector by a number,
say the vector multipled by 1.5 is 1.5
times x, 1.5 times y.
We change the length of the vector gets
longer in this case and then we can go
further now.
If we've got a vector representing a
position, we've got another vector.
And we put that vector at starting at the
end points of the end point of the
original one p, except v starts at the
end point of p.
We can take it, it can take us to a new
position.
And that position is actually the
resulting of taking p, taking v and
adding them together.
So we can add a vector v to vector p and
get a new vector p2, and if we do that,
we can do the opposite and subtract it
off.
So if P is px, py, p2 is p2x, p2y And we
know from what we just done that p2 is
equal to p plus v.
Well that means that v is equal to p2
minus v.
And so we can subtract off p, p for p2
again, by subtracting p2, p2 from P2x.
And that, if you look at the diagram
here, V is the vector that goes from
point p to point p2.
So by subtracting one, the vector of one
point from the vector of another point we
get the vector that goes between those
two.
And I use that in a couple of slides to
do a calculation.
So back to our physics engine, [COUGH],
as I said, we've got objects.
We've got forces applied to them, and
they exist in world.
Let's look first at the objects.
So we've got a physics object and this is
a simplified representation of an object.
It has a shape, a simple shape.
Or say that we mostly deal with circles
and rectangle and occasionally we'll deal
with some more complex objects.
But I think for the example I think just
in circles and rectangles.
It's got a position, it's got an angle,
it's going to take [UNKNOWN].
And it's got a mass, which is a physical
quantity which is how much it resists
forces.
So you need for, if it's got a high mass,
you'll need more force to push it.
So these are the things that define
physics objects.
Physics object exist within a world.
So, this is how you create a world.
Create a new physics world by, it's an
object, you have available physics equals
new physics.
And you give it the size of the world,
which is the width and height of the, of
the, the window normally.
And we use this, which, basically this is
a representation of your program.
So by passing, putting, passing this into
your physics world, you're linking it to
your program.
Then, the, the next thing we do to the
physics world is set the density.
That's quite important because it's used
to set the mass of objects, so.
You don't need to set the mass of an
object explicitly.
It will just calculate from how big the
object is based on the density, so the
bigger an object, the more mass it's
going to be.
But the density is going to control how
how massive each of your objects is.
So if you increase the density, then
objects are going to resist movement
more, you're going to need bigger forces,
they're going to move a bit less.
The exception to that is if you set
density to zero.
If you set density to zero, then you're
obviously not going to get affected by
any forces.
so they'r not going to move, they're
going to be static and in the physics
implementation.
You automatically it creates for you
static objects at the sides of the
screen, so things bounce off the sides of
the screen.
So now we've seen created that physics
world, we can start creating objects.
And that's a little bit like drawing
objects in, in processing.
We've got a function of physics
.createRect, so it's the physics object
that's creating the rectangle.
We're creating a rectangular object.
And just as in processing, to create a
rectangle we need four numbers, but it's
a little bit different, like in placing
the first two numbers at the top left.
But the next two numbers are the bottom
right of the rectangle, not the height
and width, so that' something to
remember.
Is that it's the top left and bottom
right rather than the top left weidth and
height.
We can also create circule objects.
Again a different function creates
circle.
That's three parameters, x and y
positioned at the center of the circle.
And the radius of the circle, how big the
circle is.
And the great thing is, once we've
created these physics objects, they will
just be part of the simulation.
The physics world will just carry on
simulating and you don't really need to
do much at all.
And you'll already get some quiet
compelling interaction.
The only problem is, it's just the
physics world, there's nothing graphical
on screen.
So, for, for your physics objects you
also need to create a graphical object.
Now a graphics objects is much what we,
is what we're used to.
They've complex shapes, they've got
colors.
They could be images, so this is exactly
what we're drawing.
Now, we're not necessarily going to have
a representation of an object in there.
but we're just going to use all the same
drawing trechniques that we've been using
up to now.
And I'll show you an example of how to do
that.
The most important thing you need to do
is link your physics to your graphics.
So you need to get the precision and
rotation of your of your physics bodies.
And then apply that to whatever graphics
you're going to do.
So, first we get the object's position,
body.getWorldCenter.
So that's the center of the object in
world's coordinates.
So if you remember I went back we've got
the pixel coordinates that we use on
screen.
And we've got a set of vector coordinates
that we're using behind the scenes in the
physics engine.
And sometimes you want those to be
different.
In fact, most of the time you're likely
to want it you're having one unit per
pixel is a bit small.
roughly the physics world works in meter.
So one unit is a meter in terms of
physical simulation.
So having one meter per pixel seems
really small, so you might want 10 or
even 100.
So, to get those coordinates back into
pixels, you call physics.worldToScreen,
so world coordinates to screen
coordinates, screen coordinates to
pixels.
The result of that is a vector, of the
Vec2 type, so it's a variable of Vec2,
which is a vector, and it has a position.
You can also get the angle of the object,
physics.getAngle, and you pass in the
object itself.
And then you can use these for translate
and rotate, just as we saw last week.
so, you need to get out the x and y
positions of the vector, plus .x, plus
.y, and put them in the translate, and
then you rotate by the angle.
I've converted that in to radiance, again
as we saw last week.
So we don't, as the original angles and
degrees, and I've putting in a minus sign
because the directions.
In the physics world, it's different from
directions in the, in the screen worlds.
but just put that in, and then we can do
whatever we like to do.
In this case, I'm drawing an image.
And you must remember to put pressure pot
matrix around those to make sure that
your objects move independently.
[MUSIC].