[NOISE]
So, we've talked about objects.
The, the things that affect objects may
move other forces.
I'm going to talk about a couple forces
that we'll work with.
The first force is the pervasive gravity.
Basically we're always going to have
force downwards that pulls objects down.
Doesn't have to be downwards you can
actually set gravity to move to the left
or even 0 if you want a space world.
But most of the time you're going to have
a force pulling things downwards.
And that's automatically built into the
worlds.
So, you don't have to do anything to get
gravity.
You can use the Set Gravity commands to
change the gravity force.
It's a vector.
So you can have, at the moment, gravity
is something like 0, minus 10.
0x minus 10y so it's, vertical, but you
can have horizontal gravity if you give
it a, an x value.
Another kind of force is an impulse.
That's basically a force that's applied
at a particular moment in time.
So, sometimes you just want to push an
object in a certain direction to get it
moving and applying impulses is a good
way of doing it.
It's just applied for one moment, just
like kicking an object.
This is how you do it.
An impulse is a vector.
You create a new vector with whatever
values you want so that you'd call new
Vec2.
That's a vector type.
And you pass in the x and y coordinates
of that vector.
It's actually a direction.
Say 2, 4 where we mostly vertical, we
mostly downwards with a bit across.
And then you call the Apply impulse
command on the box.
So you do box.applyimpluse and that
applies impluse to that box.
You pass in you have to say where the
impulse is acting on.
So you can apply an impulse to different
bits of the box.
Often you just want to apply to the
center of the box so it's not going to
spin around.
But if you apply it to the edge of the
box, you, bo-, box won't just move, it
will also spin around.
And then you obviously have to apply past
the impulse into that function.
I'm going to show a bit more of a complex
example that Mick will be following up
later and in, in, in the code he's going
to show you.
[COUGH] Of how to implement a catapult.
So we've got a ball that's on a piece of
elastic and when we pull that ball, the
further back we pull it, when we release
it, it will fly in the direction that
we've been pulling back.
So the two things we need to know will
fly in the direction of the elastic.
But, the more we pull the elastic back
the further it will fly.
So, it depends on both the distance and
the direction from the catapult to the
ball and what it produces is an impulse
that's applied to the ball.
So that impulse, if you remember what I
was saying about vectors earlier.
Is based on the vector that goes from the
ball to the catapult.
It's in that direction, then the more
that the growth of distance is, the
bigger the force is going to be.
That's fine, because that vector includes
that.
So the vector from the ball to the
catapult is simply catapult minus ball.
The catapult is the vector position of
the catapult.
Ball is the vector position of the ball
and we multiply that by constant c.
just so, you know, just so we've got a
bit more control about how big that
impulse is.
So we can vary that to make it a bigger
force or, or a lesser force and just
tweak it again.
When you, when you're working with
physics again there's a lot of tweaking
to do to make sure that all the densities
and the, the, these constants are right.
Just get the right feel that it's moving
at the right dynamically enough without
things going all over the place.
So, if we look here how we do the
calculation we create first an impulse
vector.
That's a vector.
We set its value to be equal to the
position of the catapult.
Then we subtract off the position of the
ball.
And finally, we multiply by a constant,
in this case, 200, quite a big number to
get a quite a dynamic move.
And we'll see that later in the example
that Mick's going to show you.
The final kind of force, and maybe the
most important one for physics engine is
collisions.
A lot of what a physics engine does is
handle when objects collide at each other
and bounce off.
And gets that, those collisions
absolutely physically correct.
And, you see in example, we've got
objects bouncing off crates, and then
objects bouncing off the sides of the
screen, stuff bouncing everywhere and
that's all handled by the physics engine.
Um, [COUGH] in a, in a sense, you don't
really need to do anything.
to handle collisions the physics engine
will do everything for you.
But sometimes you want to know when a
collision's happening.
so, for example, you might want to,
increase your score whenever a collision
happens.
And as, as Matthew would show you, you
may want to you may want to play a sound
whenever you have a collision.
So you need to know when there's a
collision.
In the first extension we're using, we do
this in a very simple way.
You just create a function in your
program called collision.
That has to look exactly like this.
It has to have collision.
Takes three parameters.
body 1 body 2 and the impulse.
So the body 1 and body 2 are the 2
objects that are colliding with each
other.
And the impulse parameter is how big the
force or the impulse of the collision
was.
So that's really useful.
You can find out which objects are
colliding.
So, depending on which objects there are,
you can make different sounds.
And you can make use of how big the
collision was.
So maybe if the collision was very small,
you don't make a sound.
Maybe with a bigger collision, you make a
bigger sound.
So,
With those three parameters you can
really control exactly what happens in
your program when different collisions
happen.
And the next, Matthew will talk about how
to create a sound engine which can
produce different results, based on
different objects and with, varying
parameters of the sound, which is exactly
what we need to change the sound whenever
an impulse is played.
Once he's done that, Mick will show you
full example that has physics objects
colliding all over the place and audio
being triggered by those physics objects.
[MUSIC]