[SOUND].
[MUSIC].
Hello!
Today in this lesson, I'm going to show
you how to create some simple sound
effects for, for a collision-based game
that we're going to develop later in the
lessons this week.
And I'm then going to show you how to
import those into your, your project
quickly which, which is revision, you've
already seen how to do that, but will
just do it do the workflow again, just to
show you that.
I now want you to get really creative
with these sound effects.
You know collisions are great fun to
make.
I am just going to demonstrate some quick
examples of how to do that but I want you
to go for make your own sounds and once
we got those collision sound effects into
the application, what we going to do is
figure out how to trigger them.
But not just play them as they are, we
want to play them with a bit more a bit
of dynamic range on them.
So what we'll do is, is parameterize the
playback, so that depending on the number
that comes in they might be played back
in a different way.
So let's make some sound effects.
So I've already loaded up audacity which
is a simple open-source.
Audio editor and I'm just going to record
straight into this, and my laptop mic.
Of course you could record with much
higher quality microphones if you like,
and you'll get a better sound, but this
will do just for demonstration purposes.
So, I hit record, and then I'm going to
make my sound effects.
[MUSIC] Okay so I've now recorded a few
sound effects lets just listen to those
they're not quite healthy on the wave
form display.
[SOUND] Okay there fine.
I quite like that.
That's a good one.
That's a quite nice one.
And.
[SOUND] There's one.
So I'm going to take these uh, [SOUND]
these three sounds and use these.
Okay, so, first of all, I'll do, I'll
convert to mono.
So, it's track, stereo track to mono.
Okay and then I will trim them down.
So, it's good if you want to, if you want
to, cause they're sound effects, you want
them to trigger very accurately.
So, it's best if you trim them right
down.
Okay, so, let's get the whole thing.
That'll do.
Copy that, paste it into a new one, then
export and I'm going to put it into, I'm
going to create a folder sound effects.
And this one's going to be ping one dot
wav.
Okay.
[SOUND] Close that.
Then I've got the next ping.
Zoom in.
Make sure we've got a nice trim on it so
that it's right up against the start the
sound.
And you can even duck into the sound a
bit because they're sound effects,
they're a little bit of a click.
It's not too much of a problem.
So, Edit, I can actually export directly
from my selection.
ping2.wav.
[SOUND] Then I'm going to get
[INAUDIBLE].
What have I got here?
I'm just going to use this rumble sound
here [NOISE].
Okay and export that file, export
selection and rumble.
Don't laugh.
Okay.
Get rid of that.
Now I'm going to import these into my
sketch.
So my s-, I need to find the data folder
for my sketch and it's called Android
sound effects.
There's the data folder.
I've put all these into this folder
called fx, so I'll copy those.
Paste them into there.
So I've got ping1, ping2 and rumble.
you m-, yeah, remember that all the files
that you put in the data folder will be
included in your sketch.
So you might want to just trim it down to
just the ones that you need.
so let's just get rid of The ones we
don't need.
Alright so we just got ping1, ping2 and
rumble.
So we've got all our files they're all
ready to go just need to import, need to
load them up so I'm going to have three
players.
play 1, you might because they're sound
effects you might want to call them call
the players something more sensible like,
that relates to the sound they might
make.
So I've got ping one ping two and rumble,
okay?
That, that will make it easier to read
the codes, know which one you're
triggering.
Okay?
Now, so then I load them in.
Ping one.
Ping 2, then rumble.
I wouldn't [UNKNOWN] here these sounds
playing on my phone.
That's why I'm talking so fast.
So rumble, ping 1 Ping 2.
So what I'll do quickly is I'll just test
them So I'll do.
let's just do a quick test to, to listen
to the sounds.
So, if the mouse, when the mouse is
pressed.
If mouseX [SOUND] is greater than uh,
[SOUND] well, let's just trigger them,
actually, one by one.
So ping [SOUND] ping1.play, [SOUND]
ping2.play, [SOUND] and rumble.play, just
to make sure there's no problems there.
Okay.
So we've got all, we've loaded up the
sounds, and we are playing like that.
Now, because they're sound effects, I
don't want them to loop.
So I'm just going to tell them not to
loop.
Ping one set looping, so that's false.
Okay.
Now do that to the other two as well.
Ping two set looping false.
Rumble.
Right.
That's saved.
Now I'm ready to run it on the device, so
let's just tap the screen to wake it up
and we hit play.
If I don't have any syntax errors they'll
build that app and push it onto the phone
and hopefully when I tap the mouse button
I should hear all three sounds playing at
the same time.
[SOUND] There they are.
That's my sounds.
Now.
Now, as I said earlier, I'm going to
parametrize these sounds.
So I don't want them to be the same sound
every time I play them.
So I won't at, to, to set up, a perimeter
I see.
So I'll create a new function, could play
sound.
and, so, the, it's going to take an
integer which is what sound I want to
play and, it's going to take another
integer, which is That's where I float,
which is going to be the speed.
When in fact I can just randomly generate
the speed.
so if sound equals 1, ping 1 dot play.
Then I'll do a random number.
Random between 0.1 and 2.
So that will play sorry.
Speed and then ping 1 dot play.
Okay, so it sets the speed to a random
number between 0.1 and 2.
And it triggers play.
And so I'm just going to copy that block
and, and Activated for the other sound.
So if they, if they pass it at number 2,
then we play ping two.
If we pass a number 3, we play rumble.
Rumble.
All right.
So now, I'm going to just say h, if the
mouse is pressed, play sound.
And I pass in,
Again I'm going to do it random, choose
at random which sound I want to play.
So, it's going to be in the range, one,
two, three.
Okay.
And I'm going to.
Cast that to an integer, because random
normally gives you values which have
floating points.
Right, so, what have I done?
I've got my three sounds.
They're not, they're not looping.
And when I, that's what we call one shot,
as well as loop, or one shot is when it
plays once.
call play sound when they press the mouse
and choose a random sound.
And then actually I'm going to put that
up to four, so that it can potentially go
up to three, because it will round it
down.
And then finally I'm going to trigger the
sound and depending which id comes in
I'll choose which sound.
To play.
And I'm setting the speed on the sound up
to random.
So every time I tap it should show a
different sound rather than parameters.
OK.
So now, I'm now ready to run my code on
the phone.
Now notice I had a little error there
which I put an l instead of an i.
So I'll just change that.
So hopefully it should be ready to go.
Okay, so again, we get the same error,
run again.
That's pushing onto the phone now.
[SOUND] There's 1 more thing I might add
to that, which is I'm going to cue the
sound so that they go back to the start
before playing.
So, cue it back to 0, that rewind it.
That's ready to play ping2.cue.
[SOUND] To note and ping3.cue to p, sorry
it's not called ping3, it's called
rumble.
Rumble cue to note.
So that rewind the sound before I trigger
it.
So let's just run that on, on the phone
and that's our last step.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND]
[MUSIC].
Okay, so that's a little bit of musique
concrete for you at the end there.
Have fun playing with this.
You can obviously make all, all kinds of
interesting sounds yourself.
And you might think of other ways of
maybe hooking, hooking interactivity into
that function.
So you might add another variable which
controls the pitch so maybe it could be
pitched in different ways depending on
where the mouse is or the accelerometer
data.
And you can really make a fun little
instrument which, you know, depending on
what you're doing with the phone it can
trigger all different samples with
different Dynamics.
So do play around with that one and we
need to make a music [INAUDIBLE]
instrument with that.
What we're going to do based on that is,
is develop a, set of dynamic sound effect
for a game.
[MUSIC]