[SOUND].
Hello.
So you just heard about how you can use a
physics engine to control the movement
and collisions of a variety of objects on
the screen.
What we're going to do now is, is look
into a real example where we develop that
into a game with, with nice graphics and
sound.
And I'm going to begin that inspection by
figuring out how we can connect sound
events up to this collision events that
we've seen before.
Let's look into the code of the, the, the
example here.
[BLANK_AUDIO] So we're modeling this as a
little droid character that can be
bounced around the screen, and it smashes
into crates.
So, we got [SOUND] an array of crate uh,
[INAUDIBLE] crates, which is an array of
physics engine body objects.
So these represent all the crates that
move around the screen.
We've also got another entity which is a
physics engine circle called Droid which
represents a little character that's
going to bounce around the screen.
Finally, we've got these walls which the
Droid might bounce into and also the
crates.
So what we're going to try and do is hook
up the audio engine so that every time a
collision happens, it triggers an
appropriate sounds.
First of all, in here, you can see we
create maxim as usual.
and then, we've got two audio players, so
let's just look at the variables up at
the top there.
So these are all the audio variables.
It's all we need.
[SOUND] We've got no maxim, we've got two
single audio players, and then we have an
array of audio players.
As I said earlier, we had this array of
crate and body objects.
so for each of those crates, I'm going to
have an individual audio player, so that
will allow me to simultaneously play
sounds for all of the creates.
So you can hear all of those creates
hitting each other at the same time.
then we need a single sound for the, for
the droid, because there's only one of
those in the screen, and then a sound for
the walls.
Okay.
[BLANK_AUDIO] Here, we basically load,
load a file, which I prepared earlier.
And then, another files.
I've got droid sound and a wall sound.
The droid sound is kind of funny vocal
sound that I made and the, the wall sound
is a clanging metallic sound.
You'll hear them shortly.
And then I tell them both not to loop
[SOUND] because their one shot sample,
the [INAUDIBLE], the 20 play all the way
through once and then stop when, when,
when a collision happens.
Next, I create the array of crate sounds.
So, they're, they're again, they're just
all audio players, but they're stored
into an array, so it's more convenient to
work with them.
And we use the same method and we load a
[UNKNOWN] file into each one.
Now, it's worth noting here that, that
we're actually going to store that copies
about [INAUDIBLE] file data but we need
to do that, so that we can playback
easily and with several the same time.
So we load that file up and got all those
[INAUDIBLE].
We tell them up to mute either.
The next thing is we hook up the
collision function, which Marco mentioned
earlier, which cool every time a
collision happens between two of the, two
of the objects in the physics world.
So collision is called.
It tells us that two objects have
collided and it tells us how hard they
hit each other if you like.
So let's just have a look at that
function down here.
So here.
[SOUND] we've got the, the [INAUDIBLE]
two bodies coming in, which are the two
colliding bodies, and then we've got the
strength of that collision.
And we've got some logic here, which
basically decides whether there should be
a score or not.
And Mick's going to talk a little bit
more about that later.
But then, here's the logic that decides
when to play sounds.
[SOUND] So, first of all, the first trick
is that we know that the walls have a
zero mass.
The walls are set up having a zero mass.
So in order [INAUDIBLE] to figure out
whether one of the bodies that's been hit
is a wall, we just test the two bodies.
So we say b1.getMass, that will tell us
the mass.
And we test if it's equal to zero.
So if b1 is equal to 0 mass, that means
it, it's wall, because the walls are the
only things with zero mass.
And then if b4, we got this double bar
side here, which means all, so if b1 or
b2 have zero mass, it means at least one
of those things that's just collided is a
wall.
And that means we're going to trigger the
wall sound.
So you can see we cue the sound up and
rewind it to the beginning.
And then, we set the speed on the sound.
So we're actually going to make the sound
more dynamic by assigning a speed based
on how hard that, that thing hit the
wall.
So if it hits the wall really hard, it
will play the sound faster.
So it will be a high pitch sound.
If it hits it slower it's, it's, it's a
low pitched sound, which kind of makes
sense because it, it's this idea that the
sound plays more slowly with a slower
collision.
And, finally, we play.
Notice I'm scaling the, the impulse into
a range of zero to one there.
because that, the impulse comes in, can
be quite high value.
So it's, I, I, I did a lot of tests and
they come in the range of 100,000.
So I'm just scaling it down with that.
So again we, we, we've got this thing
where you've got different types of data
coming into your, your code and you need
to know what kind of range that data is
in, and then you can scale it into a
range that's appropriate for parametizing
audio and parametezing graphics.
So lot of the tricks and how to make
things work properly is all about knowing
what range or numbers you're dealing so
with the accleratometer what range of
numbers do it generate.
With the physics engine what range of
number does that generate and being able
to correctly scale the numbers to map to
other things okay so the next bit of
logic.
there's a quick test to see if either the
things are the actual drawing object, so
if we've [UNKNOWN] the droid that means
we've triggered the droid sound.
So we queue it up and again set the speed
in the same way and then hit play.
And then find with that logic is which of
the crate sounds need to be played.
Okay.
So, this loop here is the same four loop
we've seen a few times now.
which loops through the array of crates.
And tests each of the, the bodies that
have come in.
So the, b1 and b2 are the two bodies that
have collided.
We want to check if either of those is
one of this, is one of those crates.
If it is, then we cue it up, and trigger
it.
And I've done a bit of fine tuning here.
I've got 10,000 here instead of 100,000
because I found that the crates in this
game tended to collide more slowly than
other things.
So I've kind of scaled down the, the, the
number there a bit to reflect that.
So again, it's a bit of tweaking.
It's not always super precise.
It's about playing around with it and
tweaking it so it works how you want.
Okay, so the speed is set like that.
So a slightly different way of setting
the speed.
Finally I'll play it, okay, so now what
we're going to do is just run this on the
Android device.
And, you'll be able to see and hear it.
That's just building now.
So I just lift it up so everybody takes
the screen, because this one works in
Okay, so there's my boyd.
Mick is going to talk to you more about
the graphics and how to make those really
good.
but at the moment, I'm just, just worried
about the sound.
So, if he, if he hits the walls, [SOUND]
[INAUDIBLE] that's the crates colliding.
So that metallic sound is, is, is the,
the wall sound.
And then the tappy sound is the crates
colliding.
So you can see if he hits the wall really
fast, if I fling him against the wall,
[SOUND]
[INAUDIBLE]
[SOUND].
Okay.
One more into the wall, just to
demonstrate that.
[SOUND]
[SOUND].
>> Sounds pretty good.
[MUSIC]