[SOUND].
so that was week four.
And you've seen how to use a physics
engine to make a basic game.
And how the use of physics can really
bring richness to the game play and
strong interactivity.
And there's a mass of games out there on
mobile platforms.
Maybe you want to talk a little bit
about.
>> Well.
>> The potential.
>> Well there is a lot of potential
because you can use those kind of
techniques to easily make a casual game.
And casual gaming is the it's one of the
big up and coming genres in markets.
So you can here, it's the sort of game
which you can play when you're on the bus
or you're on the train.
And it's really engaging.
Because really, really small changes in
the way that you use and massive impact.
And you know you, you cant, it's quite
difficult to get exactly the same thing
each time although it's always
deterministic.
So it's always the same if you get the
same thing.
So yeah it's a really useful thing for
making games.
But also we did a little bit of some
sound [INAUDIBLE], and collision didn't
we?
>> Yeah so, so as usual we try to get
creative with the sounds as well as the
graphics, so, so, so we were, we were
looking at how.
This way we're sort of working from the
opposite direction to how we did last
week.
So we were kind of parameterizing the
audio from what was going on in the
graphics.
So we were kind of sending back impacts
velocities from, from the physics engine
and using that to control the playback.
>> Yeah, that worked really well.
So there's a lot more you could do.
As always, its just a thing to get you
started.
It's a jumping off point.
>> I mean, I think you can, there's,
you can look at the game you already play
and see all the games on the the android
and iPhone markets.
And loads of them use physics and you
could probably start figuring out how
they're built and trying to build your
own versions.
>> [INAUDIBLE] Yeah.
>> Or coming out with your own games.
>> that's right.
>> [INAUDIBLE] It's not as if it's
going to go away.
It's a genre which is going to be around
for a long time.
And it's something which is easy enough
for you to build in 2D with any source of
engaging.
So yeah you don't have to make big 3D
monstrosities to be making, to be big in
the games market.
Next week we're going to be doing
something which is a bit more
complicated.
We're going a bit deeper.
It's Facebook integration and also using
stuff like the camera from your mobile
device.
So that's going to be an interesting
week.
There's a lot of new stuff there.
A lot of people are interested in social
media and integration and that.
We're really kind of covering that all
over then.
So and remember to check the forums, and
to talk to our students who are there who
are able to, you know.
Who are going to respond to you and any
questions that you have.
And we'll see you next week.
>> [MUSIC]