[MUSIC]
Oh, I think the reason to be
passionate about data sharing and
replication is because of
the impact it can have.
So it's really terrific that we each
individually get to work on scholarship,
and invent new things, and come up with
discoveries that no one's ever known
before in the history of the world,
no matter how small they are.
It feels really great.
However, if you can actually
change the infrastructure, and
change the norms, then you can have
an impact on many, many more people.
And collectively, we can do way better
than any one of us can individually.
>> One purpose is a sort of sanity check,
a basic can we reproduce this,
can we see what you did.
Transparency and replication
around that particular experiment.
Another is, more generally, for science to
move forward you need all of the evidence.
>> Data sharing always produces
better quality data for my projects.
Just the process of
having to be rigorous and
sufficiently well documented in
creating an archive data set.
That means I've got better data sets,
better documentation.
Might all be the same data, but
it's better for this project now.
Second thing is,
I hope it'll help productivity.
[LAUGH] I hope by handing off this data
set to Dr. Einstein's lab that this graph
they will draw will actually get into
the public use, be published as a paper.
Maybe we'll get another prize.
But, fundamentally,
these data will see the light of day, and
we'll hence have better
productivity from this study.
And then the third thing
is kind of a more general
hope that by archiving
the data that in the future,
there will be some,
not just for this project, but
some larger purpose served
by having open access.
And sometimes that might be tangible,
such as the public,
who fund our research and
participate in our studies,
might have greater faith in research and
the process of research.
They might be less suspicious about what
the government is doing with its research
money, or what professors do
in laboratories, and so forth.
>> When people talk about open
access to data, they often still
are talking about the article about
the research that points to the data.
But I think that we're also
getting a sense that the nature of
the research practice itself is changing.
And that there's an expectation
to share the data,
not only,
here's my article about what I did.
So, I think it's part of that whole trend.
>> We are moving from things like phone
surveys, where we call people up and
ask them how much they like
Hillary Clinton, getting fewer and
fewer responses on the phones,
to looking at things that people
say through blogs,
through tweets, through Facebook,
and analyzing their sentiments,
their behavior.
And it seems to me that we
have a tremendous potential to
use this information to understand humans,
human behavior, and human institutions.
But we also have a tremendous
responsibility to make sure
that that evidence base is available,
not just to people who are working at
Facebook, not just to people who are like,
we're friends with the vice
presidents of Twitter.
But to the research community, and
to the public at large, so that they
understand how, what we're learning,
how it applies to their political
institutions, their social institutions.
And that that evidence will be
available long into the future,
because we're just developing
ways of understanding it now.
So there's a lot more.
>> Most researchers have to make
some form of impact in their field,
otherwise nobody recognizes
the worth of their research.
So they can make an impact by either
having their data become the basis for
future research, so
somebody else's research will
depend upon your observations.
For that to happen, you have to share
your observations or publish them, so
other people can then do
the next generation of research.
>> What science is is the community
of people acting in cooperation and
competition, in pursuit of the same goals.
When you have a community
of people doing that,
then we can learn things that any
one of us couldn't possibly learn.
So that's really what science is.
That is what accounts for
most of the progress in society over
the last several hundred years.
And that's what we want to contribute to.
>> So in that sense, It is like a village,
it is like a community.
And belonging to a community means
that you need to give your share
to that particular community.
And data is the coin of the realm, and
if you can share that with other people,
other people will share the data with you,
and everybody will be better for that.
[MUSIC]