[MUSIC]
Data could be repurposed in different
ways, so it could be reused for
entirely different things.
And we're finding things
like YouTube videos can be
used to determine whether
somebody has Parkinson's.
So that was not looking at
speech patterns in video,
was not envisioned at collection,
you can find that out.
Now, that can be a two edge sword.
So one of the problems with data
sharing especially when you're sharing
data about people, is that you might
violate privacy and confidentiality.
It can be very difficult to allow
serendipitous discovery of stuff,
especially with rich sources like video or
social networks, and also guarantee
that no one will ever learn anything about
an individual from that data source.
Besides confidentiality,
another issue that somebody could
prove that you did something wrong.
Or stupid.
And that's an individual disincentive.
I think in general that's a social
incentive for data sharing.
In that it helps with error correction.
But it makes, from an individual point of
view, if the norm is not to share, that
may disincent you from sharing, because
you could be proved to make a mistake.
And a third is that, it's like
everything else, it takes time, effort.
For a lot of data, especially
things in the social sciences, traditional
surveys and stuff, the amount of bits,
the size of the bits is so small that
storage costs are not really the issue.
But for some new forms of data, videos,
social networks,
storage costs can be high.
And for anything, what you have
to do to document instrument etc.
So that not only you and
your research group understands it,
but everybody else who's in
a particular domain can understand it
without talking to you,
is going to be more.
That's capturing that tacit knowledge and
documenting it.
Now peculiarly that's also maybe a good
thing from a scientific practice point of
view, but it's an additional cost.
>> The drawbacks of sharing data, I guess
I would think of them more as
considerations in sharing data.
Because I think that, really,
we should be sharing data.
We may have to delay.
And there could be valid reasons for
delays.
That could be that reasonably
the researchers who spend a whole lot of
their time and effort in creativity and
getting the data
have the window of opportunity to publish
about it, and I think that's valid.
One of the things we did at ICPSI
was have a delayed release,
so you deposit it right away,
there is a three year window in which the
researchers can do what they need to do.
And at that point its agreed upon,
and then it will be shared.
If you wait until the research project
gets to that point, very often the data
preservation can be less easy.
More costly.
>> Well I don't know if there
are drawbacks to sharing data, but
there are certainly
challenges to sharing data.
Particularly in the social sciences.
Much of our data is about people and
those people have rights to privacy and
rights to have their own being
protected by us as researchers.
Often subjects exchange
their data with the assurance that
they will be protected in some way.
And so we have an obligation to do
no harm as we're doing our research.
There are some challenges
I think particularly for
young scholars that spend a lot of
time and energy collecting their data.
They want to have an opportunity to
do their research, publish out of
their data before they have to expose it
to the rest of the research community.
So there are challenges like that
in the process of sharing data,
but I don't think those
are reasons not to share data.
I think those are just issues that
have to be managed as we try to
be more open about the science
that we're conducting.
[MUSIC]