[MUSIC]
Hello, welcome back.
In earlier video lectures,
we have discussed the key properties
of the application layer M2M
communication protocols.
In this lessons, we will look at set
of popular communication protocols
with the goal to give some guidelines to
select the right protocol for your system.
One thing that always
needs to be considered
is that selection between any
protocols is a matter of compromise.
It's rare to find a situation
where a protocol fits perfectly.
Checking all the check marks.
In the light of this is always
a good idea to divide your criteria
at least into two categories.
The absolutely necessary
must have features and
the optional of good to have features.
Absolutely, necessary
will be the features that
are critical to the project or
the operations performed.
Good to have features would be those
that facilitate the operations further.
In this video lecture,
we will describe and
provide some of these criteria and
use cases for the considered protocols.
These criteria are Deployment Scenario.
The Deployment Scenario is one of
the most important factors to look into.
In what kind of scenario
will a protocol be deployed?
Would be a real-time system,
telemetry, security, messaging?
What kind of connection will be provided?
Is it a low power lossy network or
a high throughput always on setup?
All of these cases require different
features from the communication protocol.
Security.
You need to determine what
kind of security you need and
then look into whether it is provided or
not by your candidate protocols.
With the current emergence of malware and
data breaches,
it's very important to not only project
data at rest, but also data in motion and
this means the data that would
be carried by the protocol.
Communication Paradigm.
If your link layer connectivity
product goal is mesh-based.
Meaning, there is no primary gateway or
broker.
It make sense to use an application layer,
communication protocol
that has the same feature.
A protocol which offers direct
client to client communication
without a central server.
On the contrary, if you need to
aggregate data from multiple sensors,
it's better to use a protocol that
has a broker or central server.
In this case, there is by default,
only one data point,
the broker from which all the information
can be collected and processed.
Payload Format.
The cyber-physical system
rarely works on its own.
Generally, it is part of a larger system,
such as a control or monitoring system.
In this case, design time and
complexity can be reduced by
using a protocol that supports the payload
format of the rest of the system.
Web connected system should
utilize communication
protocols that support web
related formats, such as HDML,
XML, even JSON or
JavaScript object notation.
Strictly, machine to machine
systems should utilize protocols
that provide support for JSON.
Compatibility with Existing Installation.
It is important to know what kind of
protocols and systems are in use at
the moment in the environment in
which your system will be installed.
This should be the primary guideline for
your decision unless there are severe
limitations in the current systems that
are going to be fixed with the new one.
Quality of Service.
Critical systems require
strong quality of service.
Some protocols offer built-in
quality of service features.
Some protocols do not, but rely on
low layer protocols to provide them.
Communication Performance.
Speed, throughput, cashing, complexity and
quality of service are all
factors of performance.
How fast are the connections established?
How much throughput can
the protocol provide?
Does it for a cashing and resending?
What is the communication complexity and
how is quality of service handled?
All of these provide a measure of the
communication performance of the protocol.
The first protocol to address is HTTP.
HTTP offers non-optimal performance,
as it was designed for
always on always reliable
connectivity platforms.
However, it offers the highest level of
flexibility and ease of integration into
current and future cloud systems
without any gateways or translations.
It also offers the most comprehensive
support for different payload formats.
And moreover, the newer standard
HTTPS offers solid security features.
The downside of HTTP are low performance
and high energy consumption.
Also, it is a connection list protocol.
So new connections have to be established,
frequently.
Consider CoAP,
Constrained Application Protocol to be
a cyber-physical systems and
Internet of Things version of HTTP.
It offers what HTTP does
plus it is lightweight,
has basic quality of service features and
higher performance in terms of
processing power and memory consumption.
CoAP was designed in such
a way that it is easy
to build a gateway between HTTP and CoAP.
And therefore, CoAP can be used,
rather seamlessly in web-based scenarios.
MQTT or Message Queuing Telemetry
Transport Protocol is good for telemetry
applications, of course, because it was
originally designed for this purpose.
The main issue with MQTT is security.
It by itself doesn't provide any security
features although it can used with
lower-level security solutions,
such as TLS, transport layer security.
MQTT is very lightweight.
It doesn't offer any specific
payload format support.
It just transmits everything has bias.
This makes its integration with
current systems, rather difficult.
Because of its quality
of service features,
it can handle unreliable connections
very well and should be considered for
applications where remote operations or
messaging plays the key role.
XMPP or Extensible Messaging and
Presence Protocol is all about messaging,
and security.
If your devices or notes require
messaging between each other and
this messaging should be done securely,
XMPP used the protocol of choice.
XMPP supports both one to one and
group oriented messaging.
Security alarm systems can use XMPP
to alert users on their smartphones.
As most of the modern operating
systems have some form of
XMPP implementation already built-in.
Cities can use XMPP to alert users
about traffic changes due to
construction work or
natural disasters, for example.
XMPP suitable to mashing
to mashing messaging and
then relaying that information
to humans or controllers.
On the downside, it is heavy and
not very real-time.
DDS or Data Distribution Service protocol
is about reliability and performance.
It has a comprehensive support for
quality of service.
Each message will get delivered to
its recipient even if the broker,
which the recipient is
connected to goes offline.
This reliability feature
is one of the key reasons
why DDS is preferred in
military applications.
It also has a strong focus on security.
It's very scalable and can easily
accommodate growing number of nodes.
In this module and the previous one, we
have discussed different communication and
connectivity protocols and the underlying
architecture of the web and its protocols.
In the next module,
we will move onto building web
connectivity into embedded systems.
[MUSIC]