[MUSIC]
Hello and welcome to the first
lecture of the course.
This course if called embedded
hardware and operating systems.
This course is a practice oriented guide
on how to build an embedded system.
Nowadays, computers
are literally everywhere.
They run engines, they encode voice, and
construct radio signals to use them for
mobile communication.
They even control your microwave.
This non-visible computers that make it
all possible are called embedded systems.
Although embedded system have received
much attention from researcher
in the past,
the community has just recently recognized
that new approaches are needed
to develop and analyze them.
Mainly because they are one
of the most rapidly growing
fields in the computer industry.
Considering the transient technology,
we can say that such kind of systems will
soon be integrated into more things.
Computer will be everywhere information
will be available anytime, any where.
As an example of embedded systems,
we can think of airplanes.
An airplane is full of
embedded computers in it.
Seats have entertainment systems with
video, audio and gaming capabilities.
There is an air conditioning system
adjusting the temperature and
pressure of the cabin.
On the other hand,
the flight management system is heavily
equipped with embedded systems.
There are plenty of different sensors
reporting the situation to the pilot.
Location, weather, altitude,
speed, orientation,
all these values are constantly monitored.
The autopilot system significantly
reduces the pilot workload.
Wings, jet engines,
landing gear, brakes, and so
on are controlled electronically
from the cockpit.
So as we see,
an airplane is full of computers
embedded in different locations
with different functionalities and
purposes and
with different requirements too.
What are the main characteristics and
constraints of an embedded
system used in airplanes?
Well first and the most important one,
they have to be reliable.
Sensors should report
correct values all the time.
The control system should not make any
mistake under any circumstances and
must react according to deadlines.
Wings, brakes, landing gear, and so
on should follow exactly
what the pilot demands.
If any of these reliability
requirements are not fulfilled,
then a catastrophe can easily happen.
What do we mean by reliability,
and how to measure it?
Anyway, we will discuss
it in future lessons.
On the other hand,
embedded systems should be secure.
No one must be able to break
in to the control system or
the airplane and
override the sensors and command data.
What else can we think of?
Well another important concern is the real
time behavior of the airplane's systems
both in the passenger cabins and
in the cockpit.
Passenger expects to watch smooth
movies with no interruption or jitter.
The pilots commands should take
effect at the right time, and
the autopilot system must
not make late decisions.
Another good example that reflects
the idea that computing will be everywhere
is the Internet of Things.
Indeed, the aim is to spread
nodes around the world.
A node, it's the small embedded system
connected to sensors and activators.
Nodes will collect data of any kind.
It may be temperature measurements or
acceleration.
The data then will be pre-processed in
the fog layer an sent to the Cloud.
There are many problems
to tackle in this field.
Nodes may be located in remote areas, and
it is desirable to make the nodes work for
longer.
So energy efficiency is one of the issues
that the Internet of Things pulls out.
Another issue is making
the gathered data meaningful.
In other words, it is about getting
information out from the messy data.
Here machine learning is
coming into the picture.
So Internet of Things will provide people
with a lot of data, which can be used, for
example, to optimize processes.
There are many other examples of
embedded systems that are applied
in different fields of industry,
from home appliances to aerospace.
Now that you probably have a basic
idea of what an embedded system is,
let's talk about how we
can describe such system.
Well an embedded system
is typically reactive.
This means that such system is constantly
interacting with its environment and
executes with that environment say so.
Reactive systems being in some
state is waiting for an input,
performs computations, produces an output,
and transits to a new state.
Thus such systems can
be modeled as Automata.
In other words, it is a set of states,
inputs, and outputs.
So the abstract model of an embedded
system consists of inputs,
outputs, a unit to perform computations,
and
communication interfaces to exchange
data with other embedded systems.
Inputs provide the computation
unit with data.
Sensors can play the role of inputs.
Sensors can convert physical
quantities into numbers.
Actuators for example,
electrical moderators can be outputs.
In between inputs and outputs there
is a unit called processing element
that makes computations on the input and
produces output.
A persisting element
is the digital device.
During the course, we will talk about
two types of processing elements and
better processors and FPGA's.
In the course, we will talk about
what a processing element is, and
how to pick an appropriate one for
certain applications.
We will discuss how embedded
processors and FPGA's are built, and
how to deal with them.
We also will cover most popular embedded
platforms, this will be of great interest
for those who want to get hands on
experience on building an embedded system.
We will also talk about sensors and
actuators, and how to interface with them.
Embedded hardware works
guided by software.
That's why embedded operating systems
will also be covered in the course.
Indeed, the right choice of embedded
operating system may not only
simplify the development, but also
affect crucial parameters of the system,
such as energy consumption,
or computational performance.
This course is intended for
those who want to obtain knowledge
on how to build an embedded system.
This is,
selecting the appropriate components,
based on the requirements you have for
your application.
To ease the process of selection,
it maybe important
to know how those components work and
what their main characteristics are.
After selecting those components,
they are assembled together,
program may have needed and used.
All these steps from selection to assembly
are going to be covered during the course.
So if you want to design
your own embedded system,
this course is a good starting point for
that.
[MUSIC]