hello, this is week 5 of
interactive computer graphics.
A topic we discuss here is fabrication.
So, so far, we have been working on,
introduced, discussed computer graphics.
So display imagery on the screen.
Everything was on the computer
screen inside of a computer.
So this week, we discussed trying to
going out of the computer screen and then
try to work on the physical object we can
touch and manipulate in the real world.
And the background motivation is here,
so you know there are so
many possible publication machines
getting available, getting cheaper.
So if you have a 3D model inside
a computer, you can easily directly print.
3D models are the physical objects.
For example, if you have a 3D printer,
you can get a 3D model.
Similarly, milling machines
automatically mills, material and
then you get the 3D model.
And so you have, 3D dimensional patterns.
You can easily send it to the laser
cutter, our cutting machine and
you will get nice three,
two dimensional shapes out of the box.
So, here's the list of
topics we discussed here.
We discussed design with plush toys and
design with beadworks and chairs and
also discussed soft folding or
crossing materials, and
also interactive packing, packing method.
So first one is a plush toy design.
So this one is called Plushie.
So the program is address is that it
is very difficult for non experts, for
us to design 2D pattern who
are stuck [INAUDIBLE] appropriately.
You know?
You want to get a three-dimensional
stuffed animal,
you need to design
two-dimensional clothes patterns.
For experts, it may be easy to
understand the relationship, but
for novice users or no-experience people,
it's very difficult to go back on course
between 2D to 3D and then 3D to 2D.
So, for the sketch-based 3D modeling and
automatic close pattern generation.
So this is extension of
teddy system we introduced.
So you just sketch desired shape, and
the system generates a three dimensional,
geometry.
But at the same time,
system also generates
a corresponding 2D cloth pattern.
So if the user print them, cut them,
stitch together, and it's ready.
And then you'll get the 3D,
physical 3D shape.
So that's the idea.
Let me show you a video.
So here's the overview.
The user input is three-dimensional
sketching input on computer screen.
And then, giving the user input system
automatically generate a 3D shape and
then corresponding 2D equals patterns.
And then after having closing patterns,
the user sew together and
then you get the physical stuffed animal.
There are operational.
The user interface is very similar
to the original Teddy system.
User just get his outline,
and the system But
at the same time you get
a two-dimensional cross pattern, and
what's happening here inside is that we
learn a simple physical simulation inside.
So the system predicts what happens
if you stitch them together and it.
And the system shows
a predicted 3D geometry here.
And after having some geometry,
you can interact and edit it.
Like like any system, you can cut object
and the system automatically gets
3D shape and as well has
a two-dimensional close pattern.
So user continuously edits the shape, and
the system continuously presents
a two-dimensional shape.
This is a operation.
So here we generate two
possible operations.
So one is like this one.
So last base are these holes and also,
we also support [INAUDIBLE] this
is useful for making an ear.
We also implemented a cover of editing
operations such as pulling the shape.
So here the system concurrently edits,
modifies the 3D shape and
also two-dimensional patterns.
Now this is in, in, interesting so
you can actively add or
erase a seams on top of a colored pattern.
So this is interesting I think.
So, now you have, we have three pieces and
a single 3D object.
But if,
here the user tries to erase the seam,
which means that these two
parties will be merged together.
So you will end up having two parties.
Our system outlines this
computation in real time.
So as user erases a patch boundary, the
system merges the two patches together,
and then you will have now a two,
patches, and
the system also applies the physical
simulation to the result.
So user can also operate
directly on the 2D pattern, and
then you will get a modified 3D shape.
So you can easily directly
working on 3D shape,
or you can work,
directly working on 2D pattern.
So this two way agent
can be very flexible.
And this is an example
of modeling sequence.
So use a fast generator base shape, and
then you operate cut operation
to get more control.
So basically by repeating
simple sketching,
editing operations, you can generate
reasonably complicated shape.
Here we, we did not show in this video,
but in the actual printout, system also
gives, hints or information, which,
which edge to be connected with which end.
So, the construction is also guided by
the computer generated annotations.
So after having this 3D model,
the user print this pattern into paper or
cloth and then you will manually
create 3D stuff animal.
So this is 3D model, and then this is
a generated real physical stuffed animal.
So you take four or
five hours to get this.
Yeah, you can also create a big
one by using, you know, inflation.
So this is a big balloon,
like two meter size, a big balloon.
So traditionally this kind of balloon is
designed by professional designers, and
it requires many testing and
trials and the prototyping.
But here, the computer can take care
of the prototyping or simulation.
So even any inexperienced people can
design it, so, his or her own balloons.
So we learned our simple study.
So, we asked kids to design
their own stuffed animal.
So traditionally,
these people can buy existing pattern and
they create, the stuffed animal.
It was almost impossible to design new
original character, stuffed animal.
But here, you know, even students,
kids can design their own stuffed animal.
And after finishing the design, you know
print then cut and then stitch together,
and then you will get a final 3D model,
oh no, no, final press toy.
So, you can design their
own original model.
Yep.
So, let me briefly,
describe the algorithm.
For the inflation algorithm, for
the inflation simulation, we use a very,
very simple, basic mass-spring method.
So, close 3D model mesh vertices
move outward over the time
by air pressure or cotton pressure.
So it tries to inflate.
But at the same time the system
tries to pull them back,
depending on the edge length.
If edge length is too long
then it will pull back.
And then we repeat these two processes,
and
then at the end you will
get a stable result.
We must say that this simulation is not
accurate simulation of real physics.
There will be more other bonds physical
simulation methods, but you can get more
accurate result by using more accurate
methods but it is also interesting to
see that you can get basic result
with basic simple simulation method.
And another interesting issue is that
adjustment to the sha, to the patterns.
So, so, algorithm first takes user inputs,
this red one and
then direct to the,
use it as a 2D pattern.
However, if you start with 2D pattern and
inflate it,
you know,
inflated you inflate in Z direction but
if you pull in D direction then X Y
frame become's get's smaller right?
So in order to prevent it,
the system tries to adjust the shape
to compensate this difference.
So after, after the initial configuration,
system tries to gradually
inflate the 2D pattern so
that the resulting 3D inflation result
matches exactly to the 2D input sketch.
So that's, you know,
inflation algorithm you saw in the video.
So this shape adjustment
is very important.
You know, if user draw let,
box, as a input, and
if you dive to use this
box as a 2D cross pattern,
then if you generate a 3D shape or
2D shape, you will get shape.
So resulting shape is not
exactly match this rectangle.
But if we apply the shape
adjustment maths algorithm,
then system automatically
inflates the input to the shape.
Then physical result will,
publication result matches,
more closer to the rectangle.
So, yeah, this is interesting.
So if you want to have a rectangular,
pillow,
you should start with this kind
of pattern, not start from here.
So, to learn more,
original paper was published as Plushie,
an Interactive Design System for
Plush Toys.
And this work, it was strongly inspired
by previous work on paper craft model.
So this work making the paper
craft toys from meshes using
strip based approximate for unfolding.
So this one starts from giving 3D model,
and then automatically generates
a 2D paper craft pattern.
So you can generate interesting,
3D shapes just by using a paper craft.
We use a surface flattening method
to generate moving from 3D to 2D.
And surface flattening is also a very
popular topic in computer graphics.
It's been used to compute a texture map
co-ordinates, and if you learn more,
one starting point would be this
mesh parameterization method and
the applications.
So that's [INAUDIBLE] this week and
this video.