Our next topic is soft folding.
This is a work we published in 2013.
So as a program, we want to address is
the design of softly folded shapes.
So origami and others, paper folding
is always sharp, rigid folds.
But, many of the things like, things
designed we've crafted from leather.
They have soft folds.
So our motivation here is to assist design
of this kind of softly folded object.
And here's our approach.
So traditionally only the sharp fold
was used in the design of origami and
folded shape, but here we allow the user
to paint soft folds like this one.
You know, these thin,
narrow strokes represent a sharp fold, and
then also this big,
wide stroke represents soft folds.
So this is the 2D user input.
And then given this 2D input,
system automatically folds them, and
then you will get the 3D shape.
So that's a basic workflow.
So user paints flow map.
Fold the map and
then use a system that has 3D folded view.
In addition to it, not just study
from 2D fold them up to 3D model,
our system allows very fast
feedback as you change control, and
thus change the properties of the fold.
So, the user interacts with,
controls the magnitude.
Or it gives you a fold.
And the user can also change
the sharpness of individual folds, so
you can smoothly go back and
forth between sharp fold, smooth fold,
sharp angle, no angle and so on.
So, let me show you.
So, yeah, here's the basic operation.
So.
So user specifies a sharp fold here,
and then you change the angle.
Then you get this result.
So you see that as the user change
the fold angle system interactively,
very quickly shows the folded result.
So this is far for now.
User is changing the softness of the fold.
So, as you, the user is moving
from sharp fold to soft fold.
And then as again, the system continuously
shows the simulation of folded result.
So this is a basic operations.
So by combining this,
we can design multiple shapes.
So if you design curved line and then
tries to then you will get this result.
And you can also control
the softness of this curved fold.
Now a couple of examples.
So use our interactively drawing folds and
the system quickly provides feeder box so
you can explore many different
designs using soft folds.
And this spear is most important.
You know, if you are [INAUDIBLE] physical
simulation, you can [INAUDIBLE] dissolve,
but standard physical simulation
is too slow to do this.
Yeah, so use a space variety
as a very soft fold and
then change the folding angle,
and then you will get this shape.
So let me skip this.
So here is an, another example.
So use the sign the wide fold here,
and the other fold, other fold,
other fold.
And they start bending.
As you see,
some contradictory force can be nicely
handled as a result of computation.
So
important point is that
everything is interactive, so
you can incrementally add more folds,
test many fold angles.
Looking at the 3D view it
changes configuration and so on.
So here's another example.
So user specifies sharp folds first.
And then specify a soft fold here.
And here you just specify
the connection between two corners and
then you will get these connected
corners in the 3D view.
Here's another example.
I think this sequence is
showing the creation of a mask.
Yep.
Okay, that's it.
So, yeah he has a couple more results,
you know,
this is sharp folds, and this is soft
folds, and this is physical construction.
And here's our examples.
And here's a laser bag design or
a shopping case or masks and shoes.
And so let me describe the details.
So user input is given as a fold map,
sharp folds and soft folds.
And then the last one is 3D result.
But in the middle,
a fast computer fold field.
So for the field computes gives the for
the orientation, for the magnitude,
for the individual pixel.
So it has implementation.
So I use, I,
input is given as 2D vector graphics and
then after that we compute
2-dimensional mesh.
And then once the two-dimensional
mesh vertices,
we compute fold field one by one.
And they are coding
through the fold field,
which means we specify forwarding angle,
and orientation, for individual vertices.
And then, by assembling this information
together, we get a global folding.
And then we would get a 3D result.
So, fold field generation works like this.
For each user-specified folds if you,
first, the system generates a mesh so
that they align the fold curve's tangent.
And as for soft folds,
we diffuse fold orientations in
the non-overlapping regions.
And then for the overlapped regions, we
blend overlap fold orientations together.
So if you have this orientation folding,
this orientation folding,
you get in the middle.
So after getting a fold field, and
then system computes a global folding, so,
which means assembling two-dimensional
local folds, and then you get a 3D fold.
And most important thing here is that
we do not use physical simulation here,
because physics is very slow.
Instead we take a comparative
geometric approach.
So here is the overview.
So you get local folds, where individual
local regions folded independently.
And then we basically stitch them
together, to get global fold.
So in this 3D view,
you get the local fold, one by one.
And they're stitched together.
And then, eventually,
you get a large fold.
And the technique we used here is
borrowed from our previous work on
a linear rotational-ivariant coordinates.
So to learn more, original paper was
published Soft Folding in 2013 and
there are lots of discussions
about developable surface control.
And one starting point to look at is
Flexible Developable Surfaces
published in 2012.
And there are a couple of works on
origami folding, always has folds.
One example is origami plane
simulator in the module space.
And also origami assembly has a lot
of interesting assemblies behind it.
If you want more,
I recommend you to take a look at the book
titled Geometric Folding Algorithms,
Linkages, Origami, and Polyhedra.
Thank you.