[MUSIC] What's the derivative of a
product of two functions? The derivative
of a product is given by this, the
Product Rule.
The derivative of f times g is the
derivative of f times g plus f times the
derivative of g.
It's a bunch of things to be warned about
here.
This is the product of two functions, but
the derivative involves the sum of two
different products.
It's the derivative of the first times
the second plus the first times the
derivative of the second.
Let's see an example of this rule in
action.
For example, let's work out the
derivative of this product, the product
of 1+2x and 1+x^2.
Alright, well here we go. This is a
derivative of product, so by the Product
Rule, I'm going to differentiate the
first thing, multiply by the second, and
add that to the first thing times the
derivative of the second.
So, it's the derivative of the first term
in the product times the second term in
the product, derivative of the first
function times the second, plus the first
function, 1+2x, times the derivative of
the second.
So, that's an instance of the Product
Rule.
Now, this is the derivative of a sum,
which is the sum of the derivatives.
So, it's the derivative of 1 plus the
derivative of 2x times 1+x^2 plus 1+2x
times the derivative of a sum, which is
the sum of the derivatives.
Now, the derivative of 1, that's a
derivative of a constant function that's
just 0,
this is the derivative of a constant
multiple so I can pull that constant
multiple out of the derivative,
times 1+x^2+1+2x times, the derivative of
1 is 0,
it's the derivative of a constant, plus
the derivative of x^2 is 2x.
Alright.
Now, I've got 0+2 times the derivative of
x.
The derivative of x is just 1.
So, that's just
2*1*(1+x^2)+(1+2x)*(0+2x).
So, there it is.
I could maybe write this a little bit
more neatly.
2*(1+x^2)+(1+2x)*2x.
This is the derivative of our original
function (1+2x)*(1+x^2).
We din't really need the Product Rule to
compute that derivative.
So, instead of using the Product Rule on
this, I'm going to first multiply this
out and then do the differentiation.
Here, watch.
So, this is the derivative but I'm going
to multiply all this out, alright? So,
1+2x^3, which is what I get when I
multiply 2x by x^2, plus x^2, which is
1*x^2+2x*1.
So now, I could differentiate this
without using the Product Rule, right?
This is the derivatives of big sum,
so it's the sum of the derivatives.
The derivative of one, the derivative of
2x^3, the derivative of x^2, and the
derivative of 2x.
Now, the derivative of 1, that's the
derivative of a constant,
that's just 0.
The derivative of this constant multiple
of x^3, I can pull out the constant
multiple.
The derivative of x^2 is 2x and the
derivative of 2-x, so I can pull out the
constant multiple.
Now, what's 2 times the derivative of
x^3? That's 2 times, the derivative of
x^3 is 3x^2+2x+2 times the derivative of
x, which is 2*1.
And then, I could write this maybe a
little bit more nicely.
This is 6x^2+2x+2.
So, this is the derivative of our
original function.
Woah. What just happened? I'm trying to
differentiate 1+2x*1+x^2.
When I just used the Product Rule, I got
this, 2*(1+x^2)+(1+2x)*(2x).
When I expanded and then differentiated,
I got this,
6x^2+2x+2.
So, are these two answers the same? Yeah.
These two answers are the same.
let's see how.
I can expand out this first answer.
This is 2*1+2x^2+1*2x plus 2x*2x is 4x^2.
Now look,
2, 2x^2+4x^2 gives me 6x^2.
And 1*2x gives me this 2x here.
These are, in fact, the same.
Should we really be surprised by this? I
mean, I did do these things in a
different order.
So, in this first case, I differentiated
using the Product Rule and then I
expanded what I got.
In the second case, first, I expanded and
after doing expansion, then I
differentiated.
More succintly in the first case, I
differentiated than expanded. In the
second case, I expanded then I
differentiated.
Look, you'd think the order would matter.
Usually, the order does matter.
If you take a shower and then get
dressed, that's a totally different
experience from getting dressed and then
stepping into the shower.
The order usually does matter and you'd
think that differentiating and then
expanding would do something really
different than expanding and then
differentiating.
But you've got real choices when you do
these derivative calculations, and yet
somehow, Mathematics is conspiring so
that we can all agree on the derivative,
no matter what choices we might make on
our way there.
And I think we can also all agree that
that's pretty cool.
[MUSIC]