[MUSIC] We can drive the product rule by
just going back, to the definition of
derivative.
So what is the definition of derivative
say? It tell us that the derivative of
the product of f of x and g of x is a
limit.
It's the limit as h approaches zero.
Of the function at x+h, which, in this
case, is the product of f and g, both
evaluated at x+h, because I'm thinking of
this as the function, so I'm plugging in
x+h, and I subtract the function
evaluated at x, which is just f(x)*g(x),
and then I divide that by h.
So, it's this limit of this difference
quotient, that gives me the derivative of
the product.
How can I evaluate that limit? Here's the
trick, I'm going to add a disguised
version of zero to this limit.
Instead of just calculating the limit of
f(x+h)g(x+h)-f(x)g(x), I'm going to
subtract and add the same thing.
So here, I've got f(x+h)*g(x+h), just
like up here.
Now I'm going to just subtract
f(x+h)*g(x+h), and then add it back in,
plus f(x+h)*g(x).
This is just zero,
I haven't done anything.
And I'm going to subtract f(x)*g(x) right
here and I'm still dividing by h.
So these are the same limits,
I haven't really done anything, but I've
actually done everything I need.
By introducing these extra factors, I've
now got a common factor of f(x+h) here
and a common factor of g(x) here.
So, I can collect those out and I'll get
some good things happening as a result.
Let's see exactly how this happens.
So this is the limit as h goes to zero,
I'm going to pull out that common factor
of f(x+h) [SOUND].
And I'm going to multiply by what's left
over g(x+h)-g(x) [SOUND] and I can put it
over h.
So that's these two terms.
Now, what's left over here? I've got a
common factor of g(x).
And what's left over? f(x+h)-f(x) I'll
divide this by h,
and then the factor I pull out is g(x).
So this limit is the same as this limit.
Now this is a limit of a sum.
So that's a sum of the limits provided
the limits exist and we'll see that they
do.
So this is the limit as h goes to zero of
f(x+h)*g(x+h)-g(x)/h plus the lim as h
goes to zero of f(x+h)-f(x)/h*g(x).
Now what do I have here I've got limits
of products which are the products of
limits providing the limits exist, and
they do and we'll see, so let's rewrite
these limits of products as products of
limits.
This is the limit as h goes to zero of
f(x+h) times the limit as h goes to zero
of g(x+h)-g(x)/h.
You might begin to see what's happening
here,
plus the limit as h goes to zero of
f(x+h)-f(x)/h times the limit as h goes
to zero of g(x).
Okay,
now we've got to check that all these
limits exist, in order to justify
replacing limits [INAUDIBLE] limits.
But these limits do exist,
let's see why?
This first limit, the limit of f(x+h) as
h goes to zero, it's actually the hardest
one I think, of all these to see.
Remember back, we showed that
differentiable functions are continuous.
This is really calculating the limit of f
of something, as the something approaches
x.
And that's really what this limit is, and
because f is continuous, because f is
differentiable, this limit is actually
just f(x).
But I think seeing that step is probably
the hardest in this whole argument.
What's this thing here? Well, this is the
limit of the thing that calculates the
derivative of g, and g is differentiable
by assumption.
So, this is the derivative of g at x
plus, what's this limit? This is the
limit that calculates the derivative of
f, and f is differentiable by assumption,
so that's f (x)'.
This is the limit of g(x), as h goes to
zero.
This is the limit of a constant.
Wiggling h doesn't affect this at all, so
that's just g(x).
And look at what we've calculated here.
The limit that calculates the derivative
of the product is f(x)*g'(x)+f'(x)*g,
that is the product rule.
What have we really shown here? Well,
here is one way to write down the product
rule very precisely.
Confusingly, I'm going to define a new
function that I'm calling h.
So h is just the product of f and g now,
h(x)=f(x)*g(x).
If f and g are differentiable at some
point, a, then I know the derivative of
their product.
The derivative of their product Is the
derivative of f times the value of g plus
the value of f times the derivative of g.
This is a precise statement of the
product rule, and you can really see, for
instance, where this differentiability
condition was necessary.
In our proof, at some point in the proof
here, I wanted to go from a limit of a
product to the product of limits.
But in order to do that, I need to know
that this limit exists.
And that limit is exactly calculating the
derivative of G.
So you can really see where these
conditions are playing a crucial role in
the proof of the product rule.
[MUSIC]