[SOUND] Hello, welcome back to the online
course on web connectivity and
security in cyber physical systems.
This lesson starts a module on
a cryptographic solutions for
cyber physical systems.
It is the last module of the course.
In this video lecture,
we will look into basic concepts and
techniques of cryptography.
Cryptography is a scientific and
engineering field which develops and
analyzes mathematical techniques for so
many different information, security, and
privacy issues such as confidentiality,
data integrity,
entity authentication and
data origin authentication.
Cryptography has a long and
fascinating history.
Egyptians used some kind of encryption
in their messages about 4,000 years ago.
In the 20th century,
during the World War I and
II, cryptography was used to protect
sensitive war related information.
Even though the usage
of modern cryptography
originally focus on military applications,
today it's widely use for
protecting our digital information
in general, everywhere.
This development began in 1960's and
has been boosted by the proliferation
of computers and communication
systems during the last decades.
The main goal of cryptography
is to hide and protect sensitive
information which is called a plaintext,
from the adversaries or attackers.
You can imagine that you protect your
belongings inside a suitcase with
a padlock.
The idea is that one needs
the key of the padlock to get
the stuff out of the suitcase.
The cyber system essentially
works in the same way.
The plain text, is encrypted,
using a cryptographic algorithm,
which corresponds to the padlock.
The algorithm takes the plain text and
encryption key as input, and
as a result, a cipher text is generated.
The cipher text is a new form or
combination of the plain text.
It is not readable by a human or
a computer without decrypting it.
And therefore, the cipher text can
be safely sent to another party.
On the receiver side, if the receiver
has the right decryption key, he or
she will be able to decrypt the cipher
text to discover the original message.
The secrecy of a cipher system is highly
dependent on the secrecy of the key.
So, the exchange of the decryption key
should be done in a very secured way.
From the attackers perspective, the main
challenge is to determine the plain text
from a cypher text
without knowing the key.
The decryption key does not have to
always be the same as the encryption key.
There are two types of cipher systems,
a symmetric key cipher system and
an asymmetric key or
public key cipher system.
In a symmetric key cipher system,
the decryption key is identical
to the encryption key.
Or can be easily obtained
from the encryption key.
In this case, there is a need for
a secure channel for key exchange.
In an asymmetric key or
public key cypher system,
the encryption key is not
the same as the decryption key.
It is computation or in principle and
practical to obtain the decryption
key from the encryption key.
In this case theirs a pair
of different keys, one for
encryption and the other for decryption.
The encryption key is publicly available,
so
everyone who has the public
key can encrypt the message.
The decryption key is secret and
is referred to as the private key.
So only the one who has the private
key can decrypt the message.
Establishing a public key cipher system
is computationally more complex and
requires more resources
than symmetric encryption.
Therefore, it is usually used for
shorter messages.
In practice, a public key system
is used for encrypting and
transferring the encryption
key of a symmetric key system.
Symmetric ciphers are far further divided
into stream ciphers and block ciphers.
In a stream cipher, the plaintext is
encrypted bit by bit or byte by byte.
For simplicity,
we call this unit of encryption a digit.
So instead of one single key,
the stream cipher requires a stream
of keys to encrypt every digit.
In this model, the cipher text stream is
calculated as an exclusive or
a modular to addition of
every digit in the plaintext stream with
the corresponding digit in the key stream.
The same key stream is then used for
decryption on the receiver
side in the similar manner.
The key streams are generated as random or
pseudo-random digits.
So, the security of a stream
cipher is highly dependent
on the key stream generation process.
Stream ciphers are small and fast, and
that's why they are suitable for
embedded resource constrain devices.
In contrast to a stream cipher,
a block cipher
uses a single key to encrypt fixed
size block of plain text at a time.
Blocks of cipher text
are produced as the result.
Block ciphers are mostly used for
encrypting large data.
The most of the well-known and widely
used symmetric ciphers are block ciphers.
These include, for example,
the Data Encryption Standard, or DES,
triple tests and the more recent
Advanced Encryption Standard or AES.
Block ciphers are first as components in
designing many cryptographic protocols.
The block ciphers can be implemented
in different modes of operation,
offering different levels of
protection and performance.
Common examples are The cipher
feedback mode or CFB,
the cipher block chaining mode or CBC,
and the electronic code block mode, ECB.
We are not going to cover
this mode in this course.
However, you can read more about them
on the internet if you are interested.
Breaking a cryptographic system
involves finding the plain text without
the decryption key.
The attack models of a cyber system
depend on the amount of information
that is available for the attacker.
Based on this the main attack models
are classified four categories.
It is always assumed that the encryption
algorithm is known by the attacker.
In a ciphertext-only attack,
the attacker has access only
to the encrypted content.
In a known-plaintext attack,
the attacker has access to
some plain text ciphertext pairs
which correspond to each other.
In a chosen plaintext attack, the attacker
has access to the encryption process and
is able to generate the corresponding
cipher text for a chosen plaintext.
In a chosen ciphertext attack,
the attacker has access to
the decryption process and
is able to generate the corresponding
plaintext for a chosen cipher text.
In all of these attack models,
the ultimate goal is to
find out the secret key.
In addition to the mentioned
attack models,
if there is no such information available,
the attacker has to try all
possible combinations of keys
until the correct one is found.
This kind of attack is known as
an Exhaustive Key Search attack or
a Brute force attack.
The Cipher System can not be considered
perfect if the exhaustive search is
the only way to find the key.
When designing cryptographic algorithms,
the time that
a message needs to be in the encrypted
form should be taken into account.
This period is called a Cover Period.
For example, in a banks transaction
a message needs to be in
the encrypted form for a few seconds
until it reaches the receiver side.
While in a database, a file needs
to be kept in a encrypted form for
a longer period of time.
The design of a cyber system should
always ensure that any type of attack to
successfully find the key, would take
longer time Than the given cover period.
In this lesson we learned about
basic concepts of cryptography.
We also got familiar with different
types of encryption algorithms, and
more specifically, we learned about
symmetric key cipher systems.
In other video lectures, we will learn
more about public key cryptography.
And its usage for
securing digital communication.
[MUSIC]