[MUSIC]
When we first learned about definite
integrals, we
learned about them as limits of remind
sums.
And in a few cases that definition was
good enough.
We are able to use a complicated looking
summation formula, and take a
limit and end up evaluating a definite
integral just with our bare hands.
But usually that was much too hard.
So we very quickly learned about the
fundamental theorem of calculus.
That reduced evaluating definite integrals
down to finding anti derivatives.
Now it turns out that finding anti
derivatives is also really hard to do.
So, at this point, what we need are some
better
techniques, or just heuristics for how to
find those anti-derivatives.
And a big one is called U-substitution or
maybe the substitution rule.
And what it really amounts to, is just
running the Chain Rule in reverse.
And, if you think back to how many times
we're using the
chain rule, when we were differentiating,
we were using it all the time.
Right, there was all kinds of
differentiation problems that involved the
chain rule.
Well, if the chain rule appears so often
when we're differentiating,
we're going to need some way of running
that chain rule in reverse.
And, that's exactly what substitution will
do for us.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]