This is the first of our lectures for
people who are doing this course but are
new to programming.
If you've got no programming experience
you're probably going to have to work a
little bit harder in this course.
It will be a little bit more challenging
though we will guide you through it, and
this, these lectures will explain the
major concepts.
And we're also going to put up a bunch of
other materials that can support you.
before we talk about programming we need
to think a little bit about what a
computer is, in order to understand how
to program.
this is a computer, the inside of a PC,
I, I just got off flickr.
and you can see it's messy.
There's lots of microchips, there's sort
of motherboards, wires everywhere.
But actually we don't really, to program,
we don't need to know what a computer is
in all it's complexity.
Actually all we need to know is some very
simple things, and And really we just
need to know two things that make up a
computer.
This is the processor.
It's not actually a processor, it's a
fan, but underneath that fan is the
processor.
The processor is the thing that does
calculations.
It does actions.
It really is the core computer.
And the other main that we need to know
about is memory.
This is where we store data.
And anything that is, you know, any form
of data that we are processing in the
computer must go through memory.
And really what a computer does and what
a computer program does is.
The processor does actions on memory,
memory is composed of very very simple
output, so it's, what we call bits.
Each bit can, is like a switch.
It can be on or off.
And we normally represent that as a zero
and a one.
So, really memory is along Series.
And the processor, what that does is very
simple operations on memory.
It can add two elements of memory
together, multiply those mathematical
operations, very simple ones, and it can
move things around in memory.
And that's It's a little bit more compelx
than that, but really not much at all,
it's, you know, what, it's only these
very simple things.
So, why are computers so powerful, if all
they can do is, is, move around and add
together zeroes and ones.
Well, the reason is, because memory is
very, very big.
So it's measured in gigabytes, that's
billions, American billions of, of bytes.
A byte is eight of these bits.
So there's a lot similarly processes
summations in gigahurtz which essentially
billions of these very simple
instructions per second.
so a computer program is really about
doing a simple things.
But very, very fast and lots.
Luckily we don't have to think in terms
of the very, very simple operations that
can, that processors we can do when we
want the computer to programs.
We turn them into what we call high level
languages, that have, that combine lot's
and lot's of these, very simple
operations into bigger ones.
this still may not look very readable to
someone that's new in programming.
But you can see that, at least we've got
much higher level concepts like
Backgrounds, in the background color of
the screen, rotating things around,
drawing images, stuff that's, that's at
least a bit more in the, the realm of
what we think about as humans.
Similarly those, those ones and zeroes in
memory, we can interpret them in many,
many ways to create many complex forms of
data.
A single bit can't tell us much, but it
can tell us if something is true or
false.
It can be this kind of binary division.
But normally you would combine bits
together into more complex things, the
basic level with calculating numbers.
Whole numbers or fractional numbers, we
actually leaps rather differently I'll
come back to that in a later lecture.
Text, and then much more complicated
things like images or sound waves.
All of these things are essentially
longer and longer strings of ones and
zeros and this course will cover a little
bit about how the last two represent when
the main merges.
Okay so let's try writing a simple
program.
This is processing.
it's a piece of software.
it's a program language and also it's a
piece of software for writing programs in
that language.
We have this area here where we can type
the text of our program.
But let's start by playing with, pressing
the Play button to run our program.
And here we are.
We've got a program, it's a very small
window, it doesn't do very much, but
that's not really surprising.
We haven't actually written any program
text.
At least even with writing nothing there,
we do get a program.
Now I can close my program in the normal
way with the close button, or I can also
press stop to stop it running, and then
we can actually try writing something.
Okay.
I'm going to first write this command
size 640x480.
And let's see what that does.
There we go, we've got a much bigger
window.
and I've, what has happened here.
Well I've called a command size and that,
what that does, size is the named
command.
And it changes the size of the screen.
And you need two numbers in order to
change the size of the screen.
And one of these numbers is the width,
640, the other is the height, 480.
And These numbers are put in brackets, so
every time you're calling command you
need brackets.
There are commands which don't need, any,
numbers.
What we call parameters, parsed in.
But we still need brackets.
Empty ones, which show that we're not
parsing anything in.
The commands are separated by commas.
And at the end of everything we have a
semicolon.
Now the first thing to really notice when
we're writing new programs when you're
new to programming is that grammar and
punctuation are vital, what we call the
syntax of the program.
So computers, in many ways, are very,
very stupid so they don't understand
things very well, unless you've got very,
very precise punctuations to tell them
what to do.
It needs these brackets, so that it knows
we're calling a command, and it knows
where all the values we're passing into
the command, what we call parameters are
know, needs those, the begin and end
brackets to know when these parameters
stop.
It needs a comma to know when, parameter
has ended and the next one has started.
It needs a semi-colon to know when one,
when each command has stopped.
Don't have those things it will get you
[INAUDIBLE] out/g.
For example, if I leave off the setting
[UNKNOWN] it gives me unexpected token
null.
It doesn't, it's something it hasn't
understood.
And often these errors can be quite hard
to understand.
so it's important to be quite careful.
Okay, let's try doing another thing with
background 255, 0, 0, and there we have
arrange background.
I will do, while it's slightly not the
program that draws a pointed screen, I
will show this in more detail in me main
lecture, might want to take a look at but
I can do that to set position and give it
a certain width.
Otherwise we're not going to be able to
see it very effectively.
And if you do that some [INAUDIBLE]
stroke weight length.
so this is a typical thing, I did it
accidentally, but I've written the name
of the command wrong.
It didn't understand it.
The function stroke width does not exist.
I made an error, it told me that it
wouldn't work.
Very common easy mistake to make um,.
It was completely accidental in my
[INAUDIBLE], in my case but I'm going to
leave this in the video because it helps
you see exactly the kind of areas you
get, and what happens when you get that,
you get this little red bar coming out
and you know something is wrong.
And it gives you some information which
can be used for the function strokewidth
does not exists.
[INAUDIBLE] What's one of them, stroke
width and then [INAUDIBLE] points.
I'll go over these commands in the main
page.
And there we are, we've got a dot on the
screen.
There are two other things that I want to
show you that can be useful.
Firstly we sometimes want to write notes
in our programs, if we want to sort of
explain them.
So maybe I want to explain them so even.
Explain it to somebody else using your
program or simply if you're going back to
your program later it's useful to have
notes to remind yourself what's going on.
We call these comments and we create a
comment by putting these 2 slashes in
front of the line and anything else on
that line is ignored.
I could do it at the end of a line a
well.
[SOUND] And sometimes if I want to get
rid of a line of code temporarily as I'm
testing what I'm doing I can comment it
out like this, so I can put a comment,
turn it into a comment and all of these
comments are going to get ignored.
And as we'll see now, the stroke weight
is no longer being called and my dot is
very tiny you may not even be able to see
it.
The other thing I'd like to do, show you,
is another very useful thing when you
can, you're, when you're programming, is
that you can also print stuff out.
If you do print ln, that stands for print
line, and some text.
Like that, it will print it out.
Note that I'm putting all the text values
in these double quotes.
You need double quotes so that the
program knows this isn't the name of a
function or anything, this is actual text
you want to use.
So you need to have that in double
quotes.
And when I'm on my program, it will print
heavily down here at the bottom of the
screen.
That's useful for you, we'll see in the
future, as a way of getting information
about the program when it's running, and
some debugging.
Okay, so let's recap that a little bit.
The core of writing a program is the
number of commans.
Each command has a name.
It has parameters, these are values that
we pass to the command to change how it
works.
For example, the size command takes a
width and a height.
These parameters are inside brackets and
we need commas to separate them.
And then we need a semicolon on the end
of the line.
All this punctuation is very important,
and you mustn't forget.
We can use comments to get the computer
to ignore certain bits.
Okay, so the last thing is, I showed you,
is this println command, and its for
using to print things out.
Print out text, you can also print out
different values like numbers and
variables which we'll come to in the
future.
And you can use the plus to combine
together text and values, so that'll be
quite useful in a number of ways later on
That way, we keep blocking our programs.
Okay.
So that's a very brief introduction to
the basics of programming and I'll do a
couple of extra lectures this week on
specific topics and will be covering
various topics next, next couple of weeks
to explain some of the concepts we use in
the main languages.