Welcome to the second lecture on
introductory programming for those of you
doing the course we need for programming.
So in this session I'd like to talk about
variables, but before we start let's have
an example.
So let's write a simple processing
program,
Correct the size of the screen, set as
background, which I might if you haven't
looked at our main videos yet, you'll
find out why number 255 is right in
there.
And let's draw points, let's set stroke
rate say see the point and then draw,
draw a point, position 100, 100 say.
That's a fairly basic processing program.
And now we gave, it's just a point.
Where ever you want to draw a point in
the middle of the screen.
Well, we can do something like this.
The middle of the screen is half the
width and half the height, and we can do
width divided by 2, height divided by 2.
And there we go to the point in the
middle of the screen.
Now, what exactly have I done there?
So we're quite used to, where the last
session we saw, we saw how we could call
a command like point, using numbers.
But now we've used that's something
different we've called point with width
divided by 2 height divided by 2.
And so what is width?
It's a, it, behind the scenes, it's a
number, a number that gives us the width
of the screen.
And in the case of the example, it was
640.
But here it's a name that stands for that
number, and I can use that name in the
program Instead of using a number and I
can do calculations with it I've divided
by 2.
That slash sign as we'll com to later is
is division in the program, because we
don't have an easy like divide symbol in
the, in the in the keyboard.
So That's a new element.
And it's something that's called a
variable.
A variable is essentially a name that can
stand for a number.
It's called a variable because not only
can it stand for a number, it can change
the number it stands for.
It can change.
so what does that mean?
And what if we want to create own own
variable?
And we'll see in future examples, it's
very useful to have a, a name by which to
refer to a particular number.
So, this is how we create a variable, and
I'll go through this in detail.
If we're creating a known variable, it
will look something like this.
we're correcting a variable that is a
number that starts off equal to 0.
We first, we need to go back to our
example of what a computer is, you can
think about what really is happening.
So this is our computer, it's got a
processor and a memory, variables, astute
memory.
And what happens?
What a variable is, is a little box in
memory.
And, inside that little box of memory you
can put memory or different things.
The first part of the of this command to,
create a variable, int We'll come back to
exactly what that means but it's
basically saying this is a number.
So create new box big enough to hold the
number.
Next thing we do is give it a name.
Call is pos X, for example.
That's just the name of the value.
Call it anything, alright.
Call it John, call it Mark.
In this example, I'm representing the X
position of something.
So I'm going to call it posX.
And then we set it equal to a, to 0.
That means we're putting in the number 0
inside our little box, in memory
[INAUDIBLE].
So what we do in a case of variable is, a
variable is basically a box in memory.
It has a name.
And then can have values in.
those values can be numbers They can be
other things.
So let's go back to what we were talking
about in our.
Previous lecture about how memory is
composed of a whole lot of 1s and 0s.
And think about 1s and 0s, what we said
is that we can create lots of different
things after these 1s and 0s, interpret
them in different ways.
So we could have basically true, false,
very simple one bit.
There is [INAUDIBLE] one bit in reality
but think of it as 1 bit.
You can have numbers as we saw we can
have whole numbers, factional numbers, we
can have text, we can have really complex
things like images and audio wave forms.
And each of these we can have variables
to represent any of these things.
But the key thing is that they take
different amounts of memory.
So a number, a whole number is actually
[INAUDIBLE] different need from a
fractional number.
And both of those things need a lot less
memory than text and certainly than an,
than an image.
So when we're creating that little box in
memory for a variable, we need to know
roughly how big it is and what kind of
thing we're going to put in it.
And for that reason, we give names to all
these different types of data.
And that this we call the different
types, types and There's a tight Boolean,
which can be true or false, and that's
it.
A tight int, that means integer, which is
a mathematical word for whole number.
Float, a floating point number.
Means a fractional number, sort of
decimal number.
the reason it's called flight is slightly
complicated, but it's due to the
representation of the number in the
computer.
String is a word for a text, so it's this
little string of characters.
And then there are complex types of
PImage and AudioBuffer that are specific
to processing [UNKNOWN] Not, not yet.
Come back to those in a minute.
We've also got a special type void.
Which we will come back to in a fu,
future lecture, which represents nothing.
Come back to why we might want trips in
life.
So that's, comes back to our little int
in there.
That int And that posX represents the
fact that posX is a number.
A whole number.
So we can we know exactly what the
computer knows, exactly what kind of
thing you want to put in.
That's why we can put zero in there, we
can put a word like thread.
We can in turn say float instead of int
and that will give us a factual number or
string if you want to put text in there.
So, let's look at something else we might
do with the variable, setting its value.
So this is saying that our variable when
setting in X position.
Becomes equal to a number 34.
Now, let's just go back.
Becomes equal to, that's an important
thing.
Equal, those equal, that equal sign's, in
programming is what's called an
assignment operator.
Takes one value on the left side of it,
and sets it to be the new value.
So it changes the value of posX.
It's not saying that they're equal to
begin with, but once you've done posX
equals 34, after that posX is now 34.
That equal sign is how you change the
values.
You can set a variable to equal to
another variable.
So pos X is now going to have be equal to
the width of the screen.
Or a function, certain functions do
calculations and.
Can give you back numbers, or other
values.
Up to now, the functions we've seen just
do stuff like drawing.
But sometimes we have a function like
random, a very useful function, which
generates a random number.
So this call is going to give us a random
number between zero and 100.
But he's going to set posX to be equal to
that random number.
So after that posX is a random value.
And we'll see in the main lecture how we
can use a number of these functions to do
calculations and then give us back a
value that we put in the variable.
So we're giving numbers to, this random
function, we're giving it zero and a 100.
That controls How it works.
Basically, for say, 0 and 100, the
random, it will give us a number between
0 and 100.
If I say 0 and 10, it'll give us a number
between 0 and 10, and then it gives us
back a number if you present posX to
there.
Some functions return And return strings,
texts, Boolean variable values, images,
it can return any kind of type, but
something that we, can be put in a
variable.
We can also do calculations and put the
results in a variable.
So we can take a value, which in this
case.
It is another there.
For mouseX.
MouseX is a variable which represents the
position of the mouse.
The X position of the mouse.
And we add something to it.
We add 1.
That gives us a new number.
Whatever mouse X is plus 1 set for mouse
X.
It's 100.
It's 101 If you can do basic math.
And we take that value and put it in
posX.
.
and we can do something else.
We can take the value and change it based
on it's own old value.
So we can take posX, make it equal to.
Itself but the old value of posX plus 1.
So if posX is 30, we add 1 to 31 and set
posX to that.
That's a way of changing a variable as we
use it.
in in future lessons we'll see how we can
use that to animate things.
By every time changing the value of the
variable, if that position, variable is a
position or something similar, we can
make things move around.
This is such a common thing to do,
there's this little shorthand for it.
PosX plus equals one means posX equals
posX plus 1.
It means exactly the same thing.
It's a way of adding a value to itself.
posX plus, plus is an even shorter
shorthand when the, you know the value of
adding is 1.
posX plus, plus just means add one.
PosX.
PosX plus equals means add a number to
it.
All these three expressions are showing
you, these three lines of code, are the
exact same thing.
But in the first two, I could change the
value of 1 and add 2 instead.
The last one is always been adding 1.
So, let's look at some of the, things you
can do with calculations.
You can do some basic maths.
We've seen how to add; you use the plus
sign.
Straightforwardly, to add two things
you'd do plus equals.
If you want to add something to a
variable And plus, plus if you want to
add one to a variable, could do exactly
the same with subtract, minus signs, take
two numbers and subtract them, minus
equals subtract number from a variable,
minus, minus, subtract one.
Star is asterisk, is used for
multiplication, because there's no sort
of multiply sign on the standard
keyboard.
And we can do star equals to multiply the
value of err by something that no
equivalent to plus, plus.
The slash is the divide symbol, star's
the multiply.
So those are some basic math, there're
more operations.
That's it for now.
another thing you need to think about in
terms of calculations is brackets.
If you want to do multiple calculations
on one line and combine them together,
you can put brackets 'round them as you
would in standard maths to constrain
which happens first.
So, this stuff in the inner brackets is
done first.
You calculate the first brackets, and
then use the results of that calculation
in the outer brackets.
So you'll, what's happening here is
you're multiplying x by 3 and you're
adding 1 to the result.
Okay, so let's get back to various types.
We've talked a lot about Variables now
and how we can have different types of
boolean, int, float, string.
it mostly talked about numbers because
that's mostly what we're going to be
using in graphics.
In the future we will talk about boolean.
But now I want to talk basically about
things like PImage and AudioPlayer,
because they're actually much more
complex than something like a number.
Obviously a, a whole audio file is more
complex than a number, but even the way
the variable works is slightly different.
So this week Matthew's going to talk
about AudioPlayer; let's have a look at
it.
So just as we did int pause x, we get the
type of the variable and the name.
Here we give the title variable audio
player, and the name, is player.
You can give it any name you like.
if it's a high hat we can call it high
hat, if it's a violin sound we can call
it violin.
We can call it anything we like.
so that's essentially the same thing.
and Minim is another aud type we use in
audio.
Matthew will talk about exactly what all
that's used for, but here is how we
create Minim objects.
So, just as we set the value.
Of our int variable to 0.
You can set the value of an object, and
so I didn't use the term, but these
complex types are called objects.
Our object's called Minim.
Now, we need an extra bit in here,
because there's no easy way of saying
Right?
We can just write three, if you want a
new variable, a new number.
But there's no quite so easy way of doing
that.
We need a new command called new, and
what new does is create a new object.
And it does it by calling a function.
Called a constructor.
This is like a command but it has the
same name as the type, as the object.
And it's used to create any value of
those objects.
They're new in the constructor.
By the name of the type combine together
to create a new value of the objects.
And you can [INAUDIBLE] pass parameters
in just like any other command.
Matthew will explain this, but this
essentially means, the, it's something
that wraps into programming, you don't
have to worry about it too much.
But it's an example of passing something
in, so that can be used in creating an
object.
So, In an audio file, you might pass in
the file name.
In an image, you might pass in how, the
width and height of the image.
There's lots of things you could pass.
And then there's another important thing,
big difference between types like numbers
and objects.
A number Is just a number you can do some
calculations on.
In a, in an object, as well as having its
value, you can call a function on that
object.
What that means is, if you're calling a
function play, but that's not a generic
function, that doesn't apply everywhere,
you know, you can't just play.
You're playing a particular audio file.
'Kay, meaning to play an audio file.
And that's why we do this little bit of
style of code where we're doing
player.play.
Recalling play On a specific object.
[INAUDIBLE] specific audio file, not
general audio file just one particular
item.
And we're using this little dot.
What a dot does is links the function
you're calling to things have been
called.
So you do, player.play Cause of function
one specific object.
A very useful capability.
So this is something that Mathew's
going to use and that Nick and I are
going to use in the examples a bit later
in this lesson.
So that was a very brief introduction to
variables.
You'll see a lot of examples in the main
lessons.
And and hopefully that will help you
understand these concepts that we build
on programming.
If you need some more help we've provided
a bunch of links relating to programming
on the main site.