Hi, and welcome to the fourth
segment of space craft kinetics.
Here, we're going to be looking at the
complex equations of motion that you have
of a rigid space craft.
But on it, we now have a series of fly
wheels or other momentum exchange devices.
We'll be first studying
the different types of devices.
There's reaction wheels,
there's control moment gyroscopes, and
then there's also variable speed CMGs.
And then we'll develop the math.
We'll actually develop the math in a more
complicated way than most general way with
the variable speed
control moment gyroscope.
And then I'll show you how you
could simplify these equations
to retain the classical CMG and
reactional equations of motion.
So this is a great classical treatment,
reaction wheels are used very,
very generally on spacecraft.
Their big benefit is they
only need electrical energy,
there's no thrust involved
to do the attitude.
Same thing with control
moment on the gyroscopes,
they're more expensive, but
they produce much bigger torques.
And yes,
as you will see in the mathematics.
They also give you more headaches and
much more mathematics.
So it's a lot of fun.