We're going to be talking about
momentum exchange devices.
This still belongs to the category of
kinetics in the sense that we're
trying to find equations of motion.
We have found equations of motion and
you started that with blobs,
let me frozen so
we have a nice rigid body.
Then we found them for a single rigid
body, studied equilibrium, stability,
all the uncontrolled things.
Then we had systems of rigid bodies
where we had maybe a dual spinner, so
it was a craft in one wheel.
Now we're going to go a little bit crazy
here, not just do craft in one wheel but
craft in n wheels.
And not just body fixed wheels but
even ones that can spin and
twist relative to the body.
Those things are called
controlled mono gyroscopes.
So with all these extra things
there's benefits but also challenges.
The mathematics gets a lot more complex.
So in your last homework actually you
derived these in via CNG equations,
the path is all in the book.
We're covering everything in class, so
as we go through these I'm
going to show you some highlights.
Maybe go through some of these equations.
Show you how you can get
from this step to this step.
But I'm not going to do every
single mathematical detail.
You do that actually at the end when you
put it back yourself in the homework.
But then you see all the sub steps.
You can see yep this is
what I should be getting.
Great I'm on track.
If you're stuck with a sub step you can
use the next sub step and move on, right?
And then come back to that
one later if you have to.
So everything's there.
So the way I'm teaching
this is more of a overview.
We want to cover the topics and
concepts and how this comes together.
So we'll talk about
momentum control devices.
There's some pictures and
just conceptually why do people like this?
It's kind of an icing.
And then we can get into
the math equations of motion and
we're going to derive it
in the most general way.
There's something called verbal
speed control moment gyroscope.
Typically there's just CMG's
within a single axis or dual axis,
double gamble CNG devices.
But there are also some that have been
researched that have been variable speed
and you'll see the benefits.
If we do a variable speed
control moment job scope upfront
we're doing the most complex version.
And then at the end we can go well,
what if it is just a reaction mill?
What if it is a CMG?
So we can free certain modes in the
mathematics and certain terms go to zero.
And you regain the classic reactional
solution or CMG solution or the hybrid,
right?
So instead of doing this two, three times,
we'll do it once in the most general and
then specialize.
That's the approach that we're doing.
So we'll go through a single VSCMG first,
talk about the motor torque calculations.
Clusters often too,
that's we have multiple devices.
Basically comes to summation,
once you know how to do one doing
the others is kind of a ditto.
It's more of a bookkeeping step so
it doesn't take long to do that.