Okay, so we've done a review
of what these devices are.
There are certain benefits,
everything has drawbacks,
now we need to get into the math of it.
How do we get the equations
of motion of these things?
So we're going to be stepping
through this carefully.
We are going to do it for
spacecraft with a single VSCMG.
So that's a single variable-speed
control-moment gyroscope.
That's a single axis
There have been a few
that have flown this way.
Yes, Jordan?
>> Sorry,
going back really quick to the CMGs,
do you know if there are any that use
like flux spinning to do like, so
that could just levitate the bearing and
rotate them?
>> There are, yeah.
because, especially, well,
with the variable speed,
the Air Force had a nice program,
Fred Levy was running that,
to look at energy storage, because as you
spin up this wheels, as you de-spin them,
you can actually pull and you could turn
mechanical energy in the dimo effect.
You can turn into electrical energy,
so this could replace a battery.
But you have to spin to pretty high
speeds to make them efficient.
So they're looking at 30,
40,000 RPM's, really fast and
mechanically with worrying about friction
and little imbalances is quite tricky.
So there's some that are looking at
magnetic bearings, levitation, and
those kind of things.
Not necessarily flux pinning, I haven't
heard that one being used but, magnetic
bearings, absolutely, you will find
some of those devices looking at that.
Yep, so there's a lot of mechanical
challenges and how to do this well,
robust, it survives launch, where you
get shaken to death, almost hopefully,
not slight.
So anyway, so think of VSCMG as a Hybrid,
we'll have the math for
the CMG and for
the reaction wheel all embedded in one.
So we can talk to this once.
I want you to understand this path,
deal the parts of just specialties of it,
that's going to be our goal.
So goes with time, to wrap this up.
So very convenient because
we can run both but,
this VSCMG's are devices
being researched and
done actually phoned some small sats via
CMG and tested those as well already.
So this is not just theoretical,
this is starting to happen.
But this is stuff I did way back for my
PhD, it's one of my chapters in the PhD.
So we're going to try and look at this.
One of the niceties I'm going to
highlight is we talked about CMGs having
singularities.
What we'll find is VSCMG actually avoids
this by move, by changing the wheel
speeds, I can actually produce torques
about axis or to the tork direction.
And that can be useful,
it's highly redundant, each device
if it's a variable speed you could use
it as a reaction wheel, and as a CMG.
So that's two control modes that are for
devices that gives you
eight control modes, and
it's still a three degree problem.
So you've got a lot of redundancy
built in which is sometimes nice, and
also combine power energy storage,
something we just discussed.
That's something people have been
researching and looking at and
would be nice,
that we didn't need batteries as much.
So how do we get equations of motion?
It all basically boils down to this one
little, simple equation, all right?
How hard could that be?
It's kind of like, hey you're doing
your whole dissertation f=ma, that's it.
Right, if you're doing orbits,
trajectories, unstable manifolds.
All you're doing, and Daniel's laughing,
that's really that's all
you're doing is f=ma, right?
How hard is that, in attitude it's
h.equal to l how hard can that be?
And I'll show you here
this is the hint of that.
If you want some more fun go chat
with Cody and John from my lab,
they've been doing these imbalanced VSCMG
equations that are quite interesting.
So let's review this,
what is h.equal to l?
What is l here?
Start in the right hand side, Andre?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Be more specific.
on the body.
>> Which body?
because we now have multiple.
>> Rigid body.
>> Only on the rigid bodies and
not on the wheels?
No, external torque.
>> Exactly, right?
If this is a dynamical system,
this applied to blobs in space,
jello flying through space.
But it was the net external torque
acting on this dynamical system.
Now we don't have blobs but
we will have systems of rotating,
it's a multi-rigid body problem
essentially that we're solving here.
So that's just the net external torques.
We don't need motor torques.
Whatever that reactional spin
torque is doesn't appear here,
because that's an internal torque.
The Gimbal access motor torque does not
appear here it's also an internal torque.
So just the externals, gravity gradients,
solar radiation pressure drag,
maybe you have thrusters to augment this.
Because maybe for momentum dumping
people still use thrusters sometimes,
that could be good.
Now what is the h on the left hand side?
Robert.
>> On the tip of my tongue, I'm just-
>> The total angular momentum.
>> Total angular momentum, right?
All of this dynamic assistance.
So if it's a blob, it's just the entire
thing, it's not quite a blob here.
For us it's a spacecraft, plus the wheels,
plus the frame whatever
holds these things together.
Everything that has momentum,
angular momentum, we have to account for.
And then what's this Baud up here, what
type of time derivative are we taking?
And as you know we often for
good reason do things in a body frame, but
transport theorem is
going to be all over this.
We have to do that, right?
We're also about which point have
we taken torks in momentum here?
Center of mass, actually.
So this either has to be a center
of mass point or taking moments and
torques about an inertial point.
Then h equal to l is true.
If you're talking about a body fix point,
that's anything else than center of mass,
there was extra turnums
that have to appear here.
So again these inbalance things makes
things immediately much more complicated.
So h equal to l.
We can assume this is all about
the center of mass of this system.
All the wheels are balanced so
even when I'm trying gyrating
I'm not really changing.
When I'm putting the gimballing angles in
I'm not changing the center of mass of
that CMG configuration, I'm just
changing where the axis is pointing.
I'm changing the inertias but
not center of mass, so
that makes huge simplifications.
So we need some frames to define this
stuff, and I've got this gimbal frame.
So you will have gs is my spin axis,
so this is your wheel,
if it's just the reaction wheel
this is all you would have.
A reaction wheel in a gimbling frame, this
is how we can twist that spinning wheel,
GG is the gimble axis, and that other.
And the CMG devices solves a pancake with
the motor knob sticking out left and
right, it's actually the gg axis.
And so gs is the spin axis, gimble axis,
and then gt is at the transverse axis,
it's the third axis that
cannot complete a full frame.
GS crossed to GT gives you plus GG, okay?
So that's what these are,
we've defined them.
Big omega here is going to
be the wheel speed and
we're treating it here as time varying.
Later on we can freeze it to make it
a CMG device, not a variable speed CMG.
Gimbel angles are defined through gamma,
so the gimbel rate
at which I am twisting these things is
gamma dot, and that's what that's defined.
So that's the rotation
rate about this gg axis,
so kinematics is going to come back in.
And then so the full frame is gs, gt,
gd, that's the g frame that we have.
This is the one we'll use a lot.
So let's talk about angle velocities,
the angular velocity of the gimbal
frame relative to the body.
This is where we attach this device to
a body, because the motor is taking it and
it's twisting it left and right, right?
And so this is the twist rate and the axis
about which you're twisting is gg.
So the angular velocity of the g frame
relative to the b frame is just going
to be gamma times gg.
It's the classic kinematics we did
in the first part of the class.
There's a wheelframe,
I'm going to introduce this quickly, and
then within a few steps,
we're going to ignore it again.
We'll make some arguments
why we can ignore it.
So the wheelframe needs three axis.
I'm picking principal axis, so the spin
axis, ds, I can reuse it just to be lazy.
That's my first one and
then I have a wt and
a wg which are two axis that
are fixed relative to the wheel,
so as the wheel rotates, these axis
are going to rotate with the wheel, right?
So if you look at the wheel frame,
you can go ahead and
get the angular velocity of the wheel
system relative to the gimbal frame, and
that's simply going to be the wheel's spin
rate times the wheel spin axis, that's it.
So if you sat on the wheel frame it's set
all this gimbal frame, look at the wheel
you would see the wheel's spinning about
that axis at that rate and vice versa.
So now we have our two.
If you need omega of w, relative to b,
you would just add up the two of course,
and that's how, so we can get any
combinations of omegas that we need.
Let's talk about inertias.
I'm assuming this thing is built in a way
such that I have three principal inertias
of this gimbal contraption and
they'd line up with the gs, gt, gt frame.
Recently good assumption,
may not be perfect but
it's a good simplifying in the analysis
that we're doing right now.
So I have IGS, IGG, GT and IGG.
So IG is the inertia's of the gimbal
frame along the ST and G axis.
That's where the subscripts
are coming from.
For the wheel, we can write that in
the wheel frame, you're going to have
an inertia about here so that's going to
be the wheel inertia about the s axis.
And then I have Iwt, because the wheel
is perfectly symmetric, right?
No imbalances, no other warping,
all these kind of stuff.
It's going to be the same
inertia about the any
two orthogonal axis in the plane
of the disc, of the wheel, right?
So I just have Iwt, Iwt.
Now, here I'm saying the wheel
inertia in the gimbal frame,
is actually going to be the same as wheel
inertia expressed in the wheel frame.
Why does that happen?
I think this is really,
that's an inertial tensor.
This is a matrix representation
of the inertial tensor,
where I picked the w frame.
Here I'm claiming if I
picked the W frame or
the G frame,
they both give you the same answer.
Why do you think that is?
>> There's a degenerate
Eigenvalue in the w inertia.
>> You're getting mathematical.
No, but you're right.
There is a repeated Eigenvalue in here.
That means that these axes are actually,
the Eigenaxes that generates
these inertias are not unique.
If we go back and look at that.
We talked about Eigenvalue
of an axis symmetric body.
Where we had IS and
IT in some of the torque
free motion of an axis symmetric body,
all of that stuff.
So you don't have to pick.
I could really, to get this diagonal
from I just have to pick this axis and
I have to pick any two axis that
are orthogonal to GS will do.
If any two axis will do,
I can always pick GT and
GG if you wanted to, and
they'll give you the same answer.
So actually I wrote up
a quick mathematical thing.
So really I'm going to evaluate this now,
I'm pulling in library.
I'm going to define now here
this as a diagonal matrix
in this case the g frame, I've got this.
Now, since GS is my first axis,
I'm doing what we call
m1 basically that was the one axis
rotation that we needed with an angle.
So, you'd have 1, 0, 0 or
I can do metrics form of wg, right?
So that's the classic note, that's
the rotation because we're doing one axis
rotation where the GS is the first axis.
So if I translate here from
the gimbal frame to the wheel frame,
this is what I could do,
I get this answer and then you can
identify what does this cosine
squared the same thing sine squared.
Those things are just
going to drop out to b1, and
after all this math you get nothing but
exactly the same result again even though
we did this code of transformation.
So if you don't believe the geometric
arguments, you can quickly do the math and
validate and go, yeah.
Actually, this inertia tensor is
diagonally both in the w frame and
in the g frame, that's all we need,
because that saves us a lot of transpose
without then end up all you're
doing is creating a lot of trigs that
become one in the end and not needed.
Good, so that's kind of helps
explain that one last slide.
Now I need to get some corner frames and
attitudes.
We have the body attitude,
we know how to describe that already,
MRP's, DCM,
Cortanians whatever you want to wish.
We need to get the attitude of the gimball
frame relative to the body frame.
And if you go back and
look at how we defined DCM's, right?
It was basically the mapping from N to B
and I'm just going to write that one out.
If your recall BN ended up being n1,
n2, n3 in B frame components,
that was one way to write it or each row,
Was the b1, 2 and 3 in N frame components.
So if we go back and look at those
definitions, if you have the three axis,
you can actually construct
the DCN very quickly.
And in fact here, I'm using this one, so
instead of having, what do i have here?
Let me go back.
Here we have BG instead of BM.
So instead of n1, 2, 3, I have the G
first, second and third axis I put in.
And then the B frame component
which is how we define them and
that's give you to DCM.
So that works.
So if we have BG.
Now if I need to get the inertia
tensor which was diagonal in
the G frame which is great.
But I typically will need it in the end
in the body frame, we'll do a lot of body
frame relative derivatives, I would have
to reimposed multiply with the DCM, right?
To map it from one frame into
another frame and you can do that.
The mathematics here become quite simple,
IG is a diagonal and
this one I can write out like this.
So, let's just kind of
do this by hand once.
So, if I have BG is equal to my first
vector, my second, my third,
and then I need to compute BG times
I in G frame components times B,
now G transpose, right?
That would give me IG and the body frame.
Now, if you write it in the matrix form
like this, it's going to be nothing but
gs, gt, gg that's the BG times
this diagonal which was Igs 0,
0, 0 Igt, 0,
0, 0 Igg times the same matrix transposed.
So, this transpose becomes gs transposed,
gt transposed gg transposed, right?
And now you can just start to carry
out all this matrix math here.
If you look at the second part,
this is going to be Igs times gs.
You can think of this like a vectrix,
matrix of vectors that
we talked about earlier.
So out of this, all you'll going to
get is Igs times gs hat transpose Igt,
the second row, 0 times this,
0 time this, drops out, gt
transpose plus Igg, gg transpose.
So that's that part times this, so,
[LAUGH] GS's, let's see.
Actually that's not right, hold on.
This is not a single line.
This is a three by three
times a three by one.
This is not plus, that's wrong.
This would have to go here,
and this goes here.
This should be a three by one.
It's a three by three
times a three by one.
That should be a three by one,
one by three times three by one.
Now all I have to do is gs times
this term, gt times that term,
gg times this term, and
that's where you get the final answer.
So from here, if I go backwards, IGs, Gs,
Gs transpose plus these other terms.
That's all we're doing.
So it's a nice analytic way that
we can do these projections
from the inertia of one frame to another.
And you will see this is a handy result
to what we'll use several times as we go
through that.
So that's what was done here.
This one also in the gimbal frame,
I can just do the same thing, but
instead of IGs, IGT,
I have IWs, IWT and that's it.
It's a little bookkeeping.
So you get exactly the same result.
So now we have the inertia's
written in two different frames.
Good, next step, Angular Momentum.
You guys said H had to be the angular
momentum of the total system.
The system will be composed
of a single VSCMG, so
it's a spacecraft,
that's part B, that's the body.
Then I have G that denotes the inertia and
momentum of the gimbal frame that has
some mass and it rotates and does stuff.
And then you have HW which is
the momentum of just the wheel
itself spinning about that.
So we have to add up all these momentums.
And each one of these momentums
is of these bodies relative to
the inertial frame.
So for the body this is dead simple,
you've done this.
I'm using IS now, that is my
inertia tensor of the spacecraft.
You'll see a different
I appearing later on.
So this one right now is just
of the spacecraft itself.
It has the center of mass
of the reaction wheel,
CNG devices already accounted for in that.
But what we're not doing is the momentum
of the wheel-disk part spinning about
the center of mass of those disks.
So a lot of it is already lumped in there.
And this part will be easy to go forth.
The other ones get more complicated.
So for the gimbal frame,
it's the same math at the first step.
We have IG times,
now I need omega G relative to N and
omega G relative to N is omega G relative
to B plus B relative to N, right.
Earlier we kept calling this just omega,
here and being a little explicit
because we've got lots of different
frames and lots of different omegas.
So it's a little bit
easier to keep track of.
So we need both.
This one was simply gamma dot times Gg and
that's put in here.
And the other one is omega BN.
The inertia one I've written with
this projections into G frame
components already.
So, IG times omega BN
gives me this answer, and
IG times this one will
give me this answer.
Now, again,
I'm jumping through a few steps directly.
So let me just look at it once.
This is a tricky one to do yourself in the
homework and different ways to solve this.
One thing you could say is,
you know you have IG like this,
and omega G relative to B
is just gamma dot times Gg.
Well Gg times Gg here
transposed just gives you 1.
That's good.
Gg times Gt transposed,
what's that going to happen?
The dot product between Gt and Gg.
Zero, they're orthogonal, right?
So that drops out.
And same thing with the Gg times Gs.
They're also orthogonal, they drop out.
So that's one way to do it.
I think on the next slide I show you
another way with the matrix method.
That will give you
the same answer hopefully.
It's the same physics.
Now these terms, gs transposed
with omega BN will happen a lot.
If you look at,
if we were showing the definition,
let us recall how we
typically write omega.
So omega BN, we typically write it as
omega 1b1 + omega 2b2 + omega 3b3.
So we have a reframe, the omega 1, 2,
3s are nothing but the 1,
2 and 3 access components.
Omega 1 is really defined
as b1 dotted with omega BN,
or in matrix form this is equivalent
to b1 transpose omega BN, all right?
Now, here we don't have b1 dotted with
omega, we have gs dotted with omega.
So if you have omega BN,
gs hat, this is really what is going to
give you, if you think of this,
if this is your omega vector.
And here is your gs vector.
It's giving you the gs component
of that omega vector essentially.
And we're just going to call that, instead
of omega 1, 2, 3, we've already used 1, 2,
3 for the body frame stuff.
So I can't reuse the same names,
I'm just going to use omegas, omegat and
omegag for the gs, gt,
gg axis of that stuff.
So a slight notational thing but
it helps us.
So that's what you see defined right here.
Where we have Omega s is gs
hat transpose with omega.
Omega T is gT transpose with omega and
gg is the projection of g onto omega.
So the omega vector, this is again without
any subscripts, we imply it's omega BN.
At some point it just gets old to write
all that stuff over and over again.
So this is omega BN is equal to
these three vector components
of that along the g axis.
So if you use that definition then you
have here gs transpose times omega and
that becomes nothing but
this little omega s.
So, the same momentum expression here can
be rewritten a little bit more compactly
in this form and that will help us
in same label keeping that we do.
So, now we have to angular momentum
vector off the g frame relative to
the inertial frame.
What we need next is the angular
momentum of the wheel.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Itself.
Then it's the same formula.
You need the angular velocity of
the wheel relative to inertial, and
we know the angular velocity of
the wheel relative to gimbal.
That was big omega times gs.
That was the spin axis side.
Gimbal relative to body,
that was the gamma dot times Gg,
that's the gimbaling rate.
And then of course, this is the classic
spacecraft body rate that you'd have.
If you plug that in you now have
three of these terms to evaluate.
And I will just to show you different ways
to do it, I'll do it different ways here.
This first term I've written out, and
it's going to be this inertia tensor
which we rewrote earlier as a result of
the principal inertias times
these outer products times omega.
And in here quickly you can see
again gs hat transposed omega.
That's what we defined to be omega s.
The projection of the gs axis onto
omega was the omega s component.
Same thing with omega t and omega g.
So that's one way we can
get that first term.
That gives us this one.
Now we want to get the other two.
I'm showing you a matrix representation,
for
some people this might be
a easier way to think.
Both of them should all
give you the same stuff.
This term I can write in G frame
components as this diagonal matrix.
G relative to B,
that was gamma dot times Gg.
So, in g frame component it's
00 gamma dot, all right?
And then you just do your typical matrix
math with which will give you 00 IWt that
along the third axis,
as the vector representation of that.
That's the third axis is Gg, so
you always get back the same answer.
You could do the same thing also for
this one, just here omega w relative to g
was big omega times gs, so it's big omega
along the first axis of the wheel frame.
This inertia tensor in the wheel frame.
You carry out the matrix math,
you get just something in the first axis,
which is the gs representation.
So, this ties back to the, you know,
week one stuff that we did.
Vector matrix representation.
You should be able to go back and
forth and
whatever's most convenient It'll get you
there, it should be the same answer.
Now, we have these, we add them up
to the other term, you combine them,
this gives us now the angular
momentum of the wheel that we need.
Okay, great.
A few more things, as we take derivatives,
we'll want inertial derivatives and,
of course, we'll use transport theorems
because a lot of these inertia tensors
are fixed by the body frame.
And also some of these
other axis have benefits.
So, the gs, gt,
gg axis you could write analytically if
you know their orientation at launch.
I locked them down and gs was pointing
here and gt was pointing here, and
there's no gimble angle, right?
And after launch, you rotated 15 degrees,
you can actually compute with
your classic cosines and sines.
What are the current
orientations of those axes?
gg stays always the same, hopefully,
that means you bolted it down correctly,
all right?
The gimbal axis is supposed
to stay body fixed, always.
But for a VSCMG, the GSGT, we have
to treat generally as time varying.
So, you can write this and
in code in fact, it would simulate this.
If I know my gimbal angle I
can't compute at any instant.
If I know my initial orientations at
launch what are my current orientations of
this frame of the wheel?
How far has it twisted?
All right, so
we will need derivatives of this stuff.
If we take body frame derivatives,
different ways you can do it.
If you want to, you could just use this
expression here and take derivatives.
because these are actually
fixed as seen by the body.
And cosine becomes minus sine,
which is right here.
Sine becomes cosine, and
you can see the derivative of this is
going to be the gt direction and
vice versa.
And the derivative of this one is just
common sense, is going to be zero.
That's one way.
Or you can also use a transport
theorem and say, well wait a minute,
instead of taking the b frame, what if I
took the g frame derivative of this stuff?
And if you have the g frame
derivative of gs that is zero,
I see by the frame itself
these axes don't move.
Plus you would need the omega g
relative to b, which is gamma delta gg,
crossed with this axis, you get a g,
a third axis cross with gs,
the first axis which gives
you plus the second one.
You can see the transport theorem,
you get the same answer.
Different ways you can approach it.
I like the transport, it's very compact,
you can get there very,
very quickly without writing it out.
So, we can get the body frame derivatives,
the key is the third one,
that's where it's locked down.
That one doesn't vary, the other two
are a function of the gimbal rate.
If you need inertial derivatives,
which we can do it here,
we've chosen to do b-frame derivatives.
We've already got these
answers as a sub-result,
plus the omega crossed these axes again.
And you can do that, and
carry out, if you write omega.
The easy trick here is to get this
answer in your homework I would say.
Write omega node as omega 1 b1,
omega 2 b2 because you're crossing the gs.
Instead write omega as omega s gs,
omega t gt, right?
Use the g frame components of omega and
those definitions and
that's where these terms come in.
And then, it's just a classic
cross products between vectors in
the same frame.
So, 1 crossed 2 gives you 3, 3 crossed 1
give you minus 2, all the usual rules.
And that's how you can
get there then as well.
So, that would work.
So then,
you should derive this yourself then.
I'm just kind of showing you
the highlights and how we go after it.
Since we have omega s, omega t and
omega g, the vector components of
the body rate in the g frame components.
We will also have derivatives of this.
Omega s, omega t, omega g are scalars.
So, what type of derivative am
I taking on the left hand side?
Tebow.
>> Time derivative it's-
>> As seen by what frame?
>> Doesn't matter.
>> Doesn't matter, right?
Just a scalar, so
that stuff comes back again.
If it's just a scalar it's
just a time derivative.
Over here, Tebow, what type of
derivative have I chosen to use here?
>> An inertila derivative.
>> Inertial derivative.
But that was purely a choice, I didn't
have to use an inertial derivative.
I could have used any,
as long as I'm consistent,
you can't use these derivative chain rules
into one part in a and one part in b.
If you've taken a, make everything a,
if you've taken b, make everything b.
The math will work itself out.
So, you can do that, so
that term is just okay,
the angular acceleration dotted
in the the gs direction, great.
This term here, gs hat transposed omega.
If you go back and look at gs hat is here,
so we have all this math times,
what did we do,
times omega, gs hat transposed omega.
So, if you can see here, gs hat,
this stuff, transposed omega,
gt transposed with omega,
what does that give me?
>> Omega t.
>> Omega t, exactly.
That was the projection.
Gg transposed omega gives you omega g.
And you're going to have an omega g, omega
t with that product and here omega t,
omega g with the product.
1 plus, 1 minus, they both cancel and all
you're left with is here times gt times
that term, that second term, which was gt
transposed omega which gives you omega t.
Let's say we did body frame.
How is that going to look different?
Let me do that by hand.
So, just so I can prove, so if we use this
formula, I don't need to fire here, okay.
If we use this formula as Tebow says,
that's just a time derivative.
Now, let's say,
I'm going to use body frames.
I'm going to use primes as a body frame
instead of writing ddt and b's and
all that stuff.
You would have gs transposed prime,
right, times omega plus
gs hat omega BN prime.
Well, one thing, omega BN prime, how does
that relate to the initial derivative?
It's the same thing, right?
Omega, the B and the N frame is the same.
So, that's kind of cool.
We get right away gs hat transposed
omega BN dot, the inertial derivative.
So, that's good.
This one, we need the body
frame derivative of gs, and
if you go back, we did that actually and
I had showed you the results.
Here we go.
The body framed derivative of that,
different ways you can derive it, but
I'll use the transport theorem,
was nothing but gamma dot gt.
And if I plug that one in,
gamma dot gt transposed omega BN,
this whole thing is nothing but
the definition of that and
you get the same answer.
So, as expected, hopefully, we took here,
b frame derivatives, in the slides I'm
taking n frame derivatives,
I get the same answer both ways.
So, that's always a good thing to practice
then you know you're doing all your
math correctly.
So, you do this and you apply this now for
all the three axes and
now we have the inertial derivative
that you will need as a sub result
once we start to take H dot and
start grinding.
So, we have that.
One other thing we'll use is
you will see a lot in the math,
we have ig plus iws appearing.
And that's the inertia of
the wheel plus the inertia
of the gimbal frame that
holds the wheel and twists.
And so, we can sum them up.
If you see js, it's nothing, but
basically the inertia of the combined
wheel gimbal frame system.
So, just a notational thing,
because there's lots of stuff happening.
And now the fun, you need to do this
yourself, I'm showing you the highlights.
[LAUGH] But this is now where you
apply your excellent skills on
transport theorem and differentiation,
we need H dot = L, so
I would say since we've broken it up
as H of the hub B H of the gimbal and
H of the wheel, do each separately.
It just helps manage all the algebra.
Otherwise you're bound to get
one letter crossed with another.
Do one by at the time.
So if I take H dot using
the transport theorem.
I take the derivative as
seen by the gimbal frame,
because I'm using a lot of
gimbal frame components.
But then I need to add plus
omega of the gimbal frame,
relative to the inertial, right?
because dot is still the inertial
derivative, cross with that H expression,
carry all that algebra.
This is what you get,
I'll let you do that.
You guys are very good at this now.
You do the same thing for
the gimbal stuff and this is what you get,
the gimbal frame stuff.
And then for the body itself, well that's
pretty trivial, we've done this before for
a single rigid body, you regain
the same derivative expression, right?
Now we pack it together H dot
= L is a sum of all three.
We're going to use this definition,
J was the inertia of the gimbal frame and
the wheel, the combined VSCMG device.
This is the inertia of the rigid
part of the spacecraft.
So this one is actually constant,
as seen by the body frame.
This one isn't, because inertia,
everything is spinning and twisting.
And I now is the combined spacecraft
inertia, that's the full thing.
The rigid part plus all these spinning,
twisting wheel parts, all combined.
That means I in this notation
actually becomes time varying.
If you simulate these things,
every time step,
you have to recompute where are these
axes, where are these inertias and
sum up all these inertia
contributions again.
So it becomes even as seen by the body, I
is time varying but IS is the rigid part.
That's what you took advantage of when you
did the earlier differentiation of HB,
that it was fixed as
seen by the body frame.
Yes, Louis?
>> How do you guys account for
the center of mass of the gimbal system,
in the body or no?
>> So all of these things have
been taken in account for.
IS here actually already accounts for
the parallel axis part.
That if the CG of the wheels aren't
mounted in the center of the spacecraft,
center of mass of the spacecraft,
but they're offset somehow.
That is a fixed offset, and
that's already accounted for
actually here when we derive this stuff.
So here these are just the wheel
parts that that's the momentum and
inertia is spinning about their
own perspective center of masses.
So center of mass is all subtlety.
I'm glossing over somewhat, but
this is rigorous, this works,
it's just you have to account for
depending on where you place them, okay.
There's this much mass out there,
that M distance squared term
is already put into this part.
because that part is fixed,
relative, it's a balanced wheel.
If it's inbalanced, your question would be
very good, because then with an imbalance,
as I'm rotating, then the center of mass
of the wheel is actually orbiting inside
the craft and then this wouldn't work.
You'd have to be much more careful
about which points you do it so.
Being balanced allows us to,
as complicated as it is, and I'm sure
you'll agree in the homework, being
balanced makes this much, much easier.
So that's a key assumption, so
now we throw this all together.
H dot = L, and I combine terms,
which you will do as well,
you can come up with
these kind of a terms.
Now this is the I inertial
tensor of the hub,
the rigid plus all the spinning stuff.
You can write it out into this form,
which is our equation of motion of
the spacecraft with a single
variable speed CMG.
L is still the net external torque
we were talking about earlier, so
that could be your gravity gradient torque
acting on this or deviation pressure,
if we have thrusters acting for
generating pure torques.
But it's all about
the system center of mass.
And then inside you have all these terms.
So the first thing I always do is let's
make sure these equations make sense if we
simplify them.
If we bolt down like on launch, we have no
gimbling, we have no wheel acceleration,
everything is locked down for launch, I
should get back the equations of motion of
a single rigid body, which was
this part and this part and the L.
Everything else should vanish.
So if you look at that and you see, okay,
if I have gamma dot, if I'm locked down,
there's no gimbling going on.
So gamma dot has to be 0.
This vanishes, this vanishes, let's see,
gimbal acceleration vanishes.
That's 0 and this is 0, so
no gimbling makes a lot of them vanish.
If you take the remaining
equations you've got one here,
IWS omega dot, and you've got this
is all vanished, that vanished.
You got this term that's non-zero,
and this term that's non-zero.
Go back and look at your dual
spinner equations of motion.
There we lined it up with the real
axis being along B1 or something.
So if you make GSB1,
you get exactly the same equations again,
so that's a nice validation.
If the wheel is locked down,
then big omega is 0.
That means this term vanishes as well,
this term vanishes as well,
and there's no wheel acceleration.
So, as expected,
all these terms vanish once you
lock it down, which is always good.
Now, so this is good for both devices, but
you can see the gimbling
adds a lot of terms.
There's gamma, gamma, gamma,
all the stuff that happens here.
What if you have a reaction wheel mode,
we talked about that.
We basically get a double spin
equations of motion, way simpler.
What if we make it a classic CMG?
In that case, the wheel's speed has
to be constant, not variable speed.
Let's see how much it simplifies then.
One term, woop-de-doo.
You got all this other stuff, so
the CMGs really aren't that much
easier than the variable speed CMGs,
you just now accounted for
all the other stuff spinning and gyrating.
>> Why is it that they
haven't flown VSCMGs?
>> They have, and in fact every
CMG is in fact a variable speed
CMG because it launches spun down and
they have to slowly spin it up.
But what they do is a simple control
that they, it's complexity of the stuff.
Here, let me show you what generates
the control that you have.
We have body rates are pretty small.
I mean, we're talking small.
People freak out when this craft goes
more than two degrees per second,
that's nothing.
The wheels will be going way, way faster.
So CMGs, we're looking at 10,000 rpm.
So the big omega is going to
be the big honking elephant.
So this is small, gimbal rates are small,
this stuff is all small.
What's going to give us the big torque?
It's going to be this term, right here,
that's the wheel speed, which is huge.
IWs, which is your biggest inertia of this
disk because we move the mass out about
the GS axis, that give us that ring,
the pancake shape.
And gamma dot is directly
proportional to that.
So, if you hold the fixed wing speed, this
is the control torque that we would use
in a control application, and
that's what they're after.
You could make everything else variable,
but that's really more in a later
research, we've been finding in
how we can avoid singularities.
But the trick is, with the reaction wheel,
what generates the torque is this one.
I'll show you the motor torque
equation in the next class.
But as you accelerate a wheel you get,
with a minus sign,
an opposite torque back onto the craft.
But you only get one Newton meter in,
you get one Newton meter out.
Here though, if I gimble, with a little
effort, the faster the wheel is going,
the bigger the torque I get.
And that's what they've been focusing on.
So, devices could do this.
The issue is the motor torque about the
spin axis typically are not that strong.
If you have to muscle through a
singularity acting like a reaction wheel,
you're simply going to saturate that
little motor very, very quickly.
So the way they're designing it,
they're doing the minimal effort required,
which means it tracks it within a simple
bound, but it's not very tight bound, and
it doesn't have much.
It may take, it just needs you to spin it
up and keep it roughly at the same speed,
that's all they need.
So it would be a hardware change.
So some have flown them like this and
actually demonstrated that you can do it,
it's just a little bit more complexity
in the control and people, air force in
particular have been looking at these
form of energy storage devices and
to account for them.
There's extra complexity,
they feel like I can do it.
Or some CMG manufacturer who was
chatting with me during my PhD too, and
they're saying well, we could also take
a reaction wheel off the shelf and a CMG
off the shelf, and combine both devices
to get the same mathematical benefits.
Off the shelf is always
cheaper than trying to custom
design specifically for something.
So until these become common,
there's different ways you can do it.
But for here, this is kind of,
where are we going to go?
So what we can see, my final comments on
this is, with these equations of motion,
you see now there that as the wheel speed
grows, we can get a very large torque.
But also there's limits in each reaction
wheel, how fast you can spin it and
that's that big omega dot.
The gimbling is a nice mode, but
you will also have singularities.
Actually, I think I could
show those as well.
This will be something about the gt axis,
that's one axis.
If I have four devices,
I'm going to have four gt axes.
And depending on how you've lined it up,
you can have all those
axes become coplanar.
And if your control is outside of that,
which will happen commonly with external
disturbances, that's
a gimbal lock situation.
Because these axis about which I get these
nice generous torques vary with time,
it just makes a lot of
things more complicated.
But that was the singularity that
we have so, anyway so you can see,
CMGs, definitely a lot of benefits,
the amplification but
also mechanical challenges,
more expensive.
But you get a lot of bang for your buck,
way bigger torques than what you
get with a reaction wheel, but
it comes at a cost and
the controls get more challenging, too.