[SOUND] Welcome back.
In this video lecture, we will look
into the technologies that allow you to
interact with the different web services.
The benefit of web connectivity
is that you can utilize and
interact with different web services.
Services developed and
perfected by other vendors.
For example, if you want to build user
authentication into your product,
you can just use Authy.
Authy is a web service that
provides two factor authentication.
In another video, we discussed
a temperature sensor with a web server.
If you want that temperature sensor
to send you a tweet for every alert,
you can just call Twitter's API or
Application Programming Interface service.
Are you running out of on-board storage?
Call the Amazon Web Services API and
off load all the data to
Amazon's data centers.
All of this is possible because we have
standard ways to connect
to these web services.
In this lesson,
we will look into two of the major classes
of such technologies, REST and soap.
But before we get into that, we will look
into the data formats that they use.
Let's start with JSON.
JSON is a text-based data
serialization format.
It stands for JavaScript Object Notation.
JSON is made of two structures,
objects and arrays.
Objects start and end with curly brackets.
Arrays start and end with square brackets.
The data is in name value pairs and
one set or
pair of data is separated
from another with a comma.
And this is pretty much
the basics of JSON.
On the screen you see
an example JSON object Plants.
The data is in name value pairs, the pairs
are separated from each other with commas.
We also have an array
with three objects in it.
In JSON, everything can be nested.
As you can see here that we have an array
of objects that itself is a part
of a larger object, Plants.
If we want to represent that same
data in XML, it will look like this.
XML stands for Extensible Markup Language.
It is another data encoding format.
And like JSON it is also text-based.
The chat protocol XMPP uses XML based
objects to send and receive messages.
The example that you see on
the screen is pretty simple.
But XML is relatively complex.
Old Microsoft Office Word files
had an extension of doc or
d-o-c and
the newer ones have docx or d-o-c-x.
That last x in docx stands for XML.
This is because the whole structure of the
newer Word documents is formatted in XML.
And because XML is an open standard,
other applications besides
Microsoft Office can also accurately
read and format docx files.
Now back to our web services.
We just describe two
data exchange formats.
And now we will describe two of
the common specifications for
implementing a web service.
REST stands for representation or
state transfer and
lays out some ground rules on
how to design web services.
REST is not a protocol but
a style of designing services.
It is also protocol independent,
but is generally paired with HTTP.
Some salient features of REST
are shown on the screen.
We will discuss it in much
more detail in a later video.
As this style of designing web
services can be easily translated into
embedded systems.
In short, for every service,
we have a URL and
we interact with that service via HTTP and
its methods.
Some of the basic principles of REST are,
Keep your design limited to
HTTP methods like get and put.
Each request should be independent
of the previous or next one.
For each service you should
have a separate URI.
The data exchange format can be JSON,
XML or both.
Generally, it is JSON.
SOAP stands for
simple object access protocol and
is another method for
interacting with web services.
It relies on XML and like REST,
it is protocol and platform independent.
The protocol has three
main characteristics.
Extensibility, meaning it
supports expansion and
there are several extensions available
that you can use with that SOAP.
Neutrality in this case means
is it protocol neutral.
Independence from the platform and
programming language.
The developers can use any
programming model they see fit,
whether it is object-oriented or
agent-oriented or dataflow-based.
So, which one should you use?
Sometimes you don't really have a choice.
If you are interacting with a web service,
you will have to use the technology
that they have used.
If you're building you're own web service,
then you do have a choice.
The basic difference is between our
two candidates are outlined here.
REST is lighter than SOAP in
terms of network resources.
REST is more power efficient than
SOAP in small embedded systems.
It is also simpler.
On the other hand,
SOAP offers better security.
It has many extensions and
it is inherently protocol independent.
Also REST is protocol independent in
principle, but is generally bound to HTTP.
In this lesson,
we looked at the technologies and
data formats that allow us to
interact with web services.
In the next video lecture, we will learn
about RESTful web services in detail.
[SOUND]