[SOUND].
[BLANK_AUDIO]
hello, this is week two of interactive
computer graphics.
And the topic of this week is, 2D Drawings
and Animations.
And here's a list of topics, we discuss in
this week.
The Diagram Beautification, Pen-and-ink
textures,
Shape Manipulation, and then Dynamic
Illustrations.
The first one, is Diagram Beautification.
The work we introduce here, is called
Pegasus.
And the problem we discuss here, is a
drawing of this kind of geometric
drawings, and it's very tedious to draw
this kind of diagram, using traditional
drawing systems.
For example, if you want to draw, this
kind of symmetric diagram, you have to
draw
first half draw, draw half of it and
duplicate it, and then flip it and move
it.
So, you have to combine three, two or
three commands to do a symmetric drawing.
If you do something like, like this, like
symmetric, perpendicular, and the same gap
and connect it.
And then, it becomes too difficult to do
it, with combining appropriate commands.
So, what we propose is to automatically,
have the
system automatically take care of these
kind of constraints.
Here is our demonstration.
So, this is again designed for pen
computing.
So, you directly draw a line on
the whiteboard, and the system
automatically provides feedback.
So here, you draw a line, and then the
system automatically beautifies it.
And if you draw a line, system
automatically beautifies it.
So, this point is automatically aligned to
this point.
And then you draw a line here.
And the system automatically beautifies
it.
And if you do a line here, this is almost
perpendicular to the slope.
The system makes it perfectly
perpendicular.
So, in this way, you just draw freeform
lines.
And then you will get this kind of
diagram.
Traditional, in, in traditional systems,
you have to draw rectangle
separately and then move it, rotate,
connect, and so on.
So, it can be very tedious.
But here, you just draw six lines and the
system automatically beautifies it.
And you can do many more things.
For example, if you draw, almost symmetric
line.
System makes it, perfect mirror image.
And you just draw three more strokes and
then you'll get this diagram.
And if you draw right here, this is
identical, very similar to the
previous one, and the assistant makes it
an exact copy, of the previous stroke.
So again, you draw three lines.
And you'll get, you will get a copy
without
using Copy or Duplicate command and we
also provide equal distance between
lines, so in this way, you can get this
wizard specifying
grid, before hand and also, you can do
something like this.
System automatically makes the distance,
between two lines are identical.
So traditionally, you have to draw two
lines duplicate it,
rotate it and trim it, so it can be very
tedious.
And one important aspect of this kind of
automatic system is that, user input can
be ambiguous.
So, if you draw a line here, this is
ambiguous, right?
So, user may want to draw a mirror image
here or you
may want to connect these points or user
may want to do this.
So, system automatically infers multiple
candidates and then presents a user and
you can choose one of them later, and this
is very important to handle ambiguity.
And that's beautification.
And we also implemented a prediction in,
in this system.
So, suppose, you have this kind of
illustration already and you draw a line
here.
So, here, system knows that this red
segment is identical to this one.
So, system automatically predicts or
infers that, now that, you draw the
same thing, you probably, want to draw the
same thing around it.
So, here's a prediction.
And if you like one of them, just click
it, and the next prediction appears.
So, as long as the prediction is correct,
you complete drawing
just by successive clicking, and if you
prediction is not use,
useful, you can just ignore them and you
draw it by
yourself, and you again, activate
prediction and then click and draw.
Yeah.
And this prediction is very useful
for multiple purposes, like drawing
repetitive illustration.
Then you can again click here and
then type, touch, [UNKNOWN] segment, and
[UNKNOWN].
So, this very useful for repetitive
drawing.
And this is also useful for symmetric
drawing like this one.
So, you can tap, and then prediction
appears.
And then tap, tap, tap.
And then you will get this kind
of symmetry doing, just by drawing and
prediction.
So,
that's the demonstration.
Let me briefly describe the algorithm
behind it.
The beautification algorithm and
prediction onwards.
So beautification, works this way.
So far, user input is this red one.
And then, looking at this input, system
first the first, learns constraint
inference engine.
And then, getting segment coordinates
positions.
And then, infer multiple constraints.
So, in this case, the system infers that
this should be connected,
this should be perpendicular, this should
be, horizontally aligned and so on.
Given this possible geometric constraints,
then constraint solver,
tries to combine them and then solve it
here.
An interesting point here, is that
these constraints can be, contradictory
features.
So, constraint solver needs to find valid
combinations and after having multiple
candidate system, evaluate them, in which
is most closer
to the user input and then pick some more,
plausible one
as a first candidate and then return it to
the user.
And let me, more describe constraint
solvability more.
So, Constraint Solver, as I said, takes
multiple infer for the constraints, and
then identified by the combination, and
then returns the result, for each
combination.
And, the details, let me describe the
details using one example.
Suppose you have these four constraints.
x equal 1, y equal 2, x minus y equal 0, x
plus y equal 2.
So, suppose you have these four
constraints
and then tries to find valid combinations.
One combination, is one and two.
So, if you combine these two, you would
get one and two and it's here.
And if you combine this first and third
one, x
equals 1, and y equals 1 and you get this.
However, you cannot combine these three
because it's
contradictory, so that's what we try to do
here.
And in the system, the algorithm works as
follows.
For each constraint you apply, you make up
[INAUDIBLE]
We have a set of intermediate valuations
like
this, so far as no valuation is given.
And then for x first constraint, you apply
it or not apply it.
So, if you do not apply it same thing.
If you apply it, you get one and not
valuated.
So, in this way, you just kind of
basically binary tree and you can sort of.
Intermediate valuations grows
exponentially.
However, in some cases.
Variations can be the same.
For example, this variation combining fast
one and this other one,
is identical to combining this one and
this one.
So, some solutions are merged together.
So, this is a kind of thing happening
behind the consonant solver.
And let me briefly describe the prediction
algorithm.
Prediction works as follows, so you have
these kind
of existing segments and you get the new
input segments.
At first, system searches for identical
segments, identical to the new input
segment.
And after identifying the matched existing
Then system collect, aggregate, nearby
segment to the different
stroke and they copy them to the new,
segment.
And the addition to that, we add vertical
and horizontal flip, over the predictions.
So, that's the way, the prediction work,
works.
So, that's a,a system and its original
paper was published as Interactive
Beautification, a technique for rapid
geometric design in 97.
Constraint based drawing, is a popular
topic.
An original paper was published as
Sketchpad and this is,
a very old paper published in 1963, but
this is still.
Very powerful tool.
And I recommend you to take a look at the
video.
This was a very fast computer graphics
and also very fast interactive computer
graphics.
And if you want to see the recent one
I'd recommend you to take a look the
Cinderella system.
This is this kind of constraint-based,
geometric drawing system.
And this is very useful for mathematical
education and so on.
Thank you.