So next topic is shape manipulation.
And the method we introduce
here is called, As-Rigid-As-Possible Shape
Manipulation.
The goal of this work is to move and
deform 2D shapes
on the screen, as if manipulating real
object.
So in the real world, you can pick up an
object, with your
both hands, and you can manipulate it,
moving around, rotate, and pull, or
squash.
And also you can, you know, shake his head
or wave his hand and so on.
So you can do many things to interact with
it, using your hands on the real world.
That's what we do, on a computer.
And there are a couple of previous works
shape, manipulation shape deformation, but
they have couple problems.
The most popular approach is space walk,
using a simple function you can can deform
the space, and then you can deform the
images in, in embedded in the space.
So this is very efficient for compute.
However, the resulting deformation is like
swapping
space and the result is not very
realistic.
And the other possibility is use physics,
or simply meant mass spring water and
others.
And this is a kind of simulation with real
world, so can be very realistic.
While this is very slow to converge and
can
be very unstable, and also cannot handle
contradictory configuration.
So,
let me show you what we do.
So, again let me fast describe of the
current state of the art.
So, this is typical drawing generator.
So you can, do the basic things.
You can, draw something
and then you can select an object.
And then move it around.
So, you can do it.
And you can rotate, and you can also scale
them.
However, [UNKNOWN] if you want to, like,
shake his head or swing
his arm, it's suddenly become very
difficult and you have to redraw
everything,
basically.
And, here is a system we implemented.
So basically the same, you draw three
dimensional illustration,
however, after you finish drawing you can
use push pin tool, so you
put pin here, and then you can manipulate
them, by using these pins.
So, if you pull this, you can pull his,
his ears.
Or you can you can, you know, shake his
head, or make him run this way.
So you can, deform the illustration very
[UNKNOWN].
And this is very useful for making
animation.
Example if you draw this kind of
character.
And then again, this is just two
dimensional nothing special drawing.
But as soon as I put push pin, then you,
you
can make them deform, as if this is a
physical object.
And then, you can also press leg hold,
[SOUND] to make motion.
And then, in this way.
So you can easily make him run.
And also you can drag him around, and
you can get an interesting animation very
quickly.
Traditionally, if you want to make this
kind
of animation, you have to draw many, many
drawings.
But here you can just draw something, and
they're moving around, and you will get an
animation.
And here's an example.
Again, nothing special.
Just 2D drawing.
But we can press push pin, and press
record,
and then you can get this kind of
animation.
A kick, a kick.
And then you can draw something else here,
[SOUND] and press record.
And you can get this kind of animation.
So of course, this is not designed for
professional animations, but
we can quickly generate interesting
stories with this kind of technique.
Let me show you one more example.
So, suppose you have a is here, have a
worm here.
And then that's a frog fill.
And then let's and then let's put push
pins,
and then for a select code, and one and
two.
[SOUND] So in this way you can make
a crawling worm very easily.
And then of course, it's a computer so you
can multiply
the main very quickly, and you can make an
army of worms.
And so far, I only used hand drawings.
But [UNKNOWN] is basically just a shape to
formation.
And you can apply the same technique for
images,
so this is again just a two dimensional
image, photograph.
But if you put push pins, then it starts
to move as if there is a physical 3D
object here, and then you're going to
generate interesting animations.
[SOUND] And so far, I have been showing
just mouse
operations, but if you have two hands, you
can do more.
For example here, you have two handed
mouse,
and then, two handed mice, so, then you
can grab screen with your two hands and
then moving around a little bit and
deform.
And if you have a multi touch device, here
we use Sony
computer science research laboratories
smartskin system,
and it can detect your fingertips.
And you can directly grab object on the
screen,
and manipulating them as if you have a,
physical object.
So, this is very new way of making an
deformable object animations.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So you can use both hands.
Also, two people can work together.
[SOUND] And a little bit more.
So, so far, I showed the deformation of a
lesion but shape but
you can also apply the same technique for
the deformation of a car.
So suppose, you have a cob this way and
you
can grab a cob and then deform it this
way.
And if you pull more and more, and you get
a larger region will be deformed.
And then you pull more, and you can deform
the entire shape.
[SOUND] And finally, this is not very
essential, but we, another convenient
operation is.
smoothing.
So this smoothing will remove small noise,
and then after
you rubbing, then you will eventually get
a very beautiful shape.
So by combining this pulling and
smoothing, you will get a very
professional looking smooth illustration,
just by starting from a rough sketch.
[SOUND] So okay.
So now, let me briefly describe the
algorithm behind this technique.
So here this is our input.
And then this is output.
A traditional approach is as I said is
physical stimulation.
So, moving the handles, when it tries to
deform.
Say a little bit by little, by converting
fours.
In acceleration.
And so, for this kind of a step by step
computation and it can be very slow.
Here what we propose is a kind of instant
computation.
Or final results from this kind of input
information.
So input information is initial lets the
shape.
And handle positions.
[SOUND] And then target locations of
handles.
And then we compute the final result.
And what we do is minimize shape
distortion, satisfying constraints.
So let me describe a little bit more.
So again, input is coordinates of handles
and new handle positions.
And they output this coordinated mesh
vertices or free vertices.
So these as I input on the system copies
all these other vertices.
And what we do is we minimize the
distortion of triangles.
So there are many possible mesh particle
positions.
But one particular shape, minimize
distortion of individual triangle.
Here, in this blue, blue triangle,
corresponds to
this triangle, and then we try to find the
shapes that minimize the deformation or
distortion of these
triangles, so that's a problem we want to
solve.
And mathematically, this is defined like
this.
So what rate is to minimize, this
function, so this function
is what is triangle t, we compute the
formation.
For distortion, depending on the given by
a products position.
And then we aggregate [UNKNOWN]
distortions.
And then, we try to find mesh [UNKNOWN]
positions that minimize this energy.
And what we want is energy function.
Specific definition of it that holds no
cost.
For translation and rotation.
Translation means moving around, and
rotation is rotation.
So these are called alleged deformation
because
there is no deformation to this guy.
And in this kind of alleged deformation,
there should be no energy.
However, if you scale, make bigger or
smaller.
Or stretch or press here, if you cause
this kind
deformation to triangle, it should be a
cause of energy.
So we need very particular energy or cost
function or distortion [UNKNOWN] that
satisfies this [UNKNOWN].
Another important requirement is that E.
Energy, or cost, should be quadra,
quadratic in you.
Which means if u, if this energy is
a quadratic to u, then its derivative is
linear.
So you can solve instantly by solving si,
simultaneous linear equations.
So that's what we want.
So okay, ideally we want the [UNKNOWN]
functional, and that causes zero energy
for translation or rotation, but [UNKNOWN]
energy for scale, stretch or shear.
Unfortunately, we don't [UNKNOWN].
So there's no such energy in this world
for quadratic energy.
So we therefore combine two complementary
sub-optimal energies.
So here's a description.
So ideally, we want to have this.
But in this world, what we have is only.
Two kinds, so E1 and E2.
So E1 is basically, similarity transform.
It supports translation and rotation, but
also scales and then
causes no energy but it can detect stretch
and shear, so this is kind of lose energy.
And another E2 is more strict energy.
It only allows translations, no rotation,
no scaling, no stretch, no shear.
And then we can have quadratic function.
So E1 is a little bit too relaxed.
E2 is to a little bit strict.
So we combine these two.
So what we do is fast apply E1.
And their scale is wrong and they're
waiting www E2 to fix the scale.
So, here's what we want.
So as far as the input positions, we fast
obtain intermediate result, like this one,
by using another E1.
And, in this case E1.
Appropriate handles minimize the, shearing
and scaling and
scaling [ and stretching, but scaling is
allowed.
So you get this kind of inflation in this,
you know left arm.
And then after step 1, we.
Correct size or individual triangle and
then we
use energy two, to get the correct answer.
So that's the algorithm and, refer to the
paper for the details of these energies.
[SOUND] So original paper is published
is As-Rigid-As-Possible Shape
Manipulation, [UNKNOWN] file.
And they [UNKNOWN] serious paper to see
the details of the energy definition.
And as I said, previous existing technique
is popular [UNKNOWN] space walk.
And representative work is called feature
based image metamorphosis.
Published was published in 1992.
And our technique is using segregation of
triangular elements.
And this work is inspired by
As-Rigids-Possible Shape interpolation
technique published in 2000.
And also, our work is related to recent
works on shape deformation.
And I recommend that you to take a look at
this [UNKNOWN] paper called on linear
variational surface deformation methods.
Published in, 2008.
[INAUDIBLE]