[MUSIC].
Welcome to calculus one.
I'm glad you're in this course, or maybe
quest for understanding calculus.
Alright, we really are on a quest, you
know, we're taking thousands of years of
human ingenuity.
Right?
The sort of triumph of humankind to be
able to understand numbers and functions.
All of these insights that humans have had
for thousands of years,
and we're just distilling all those down
to short videos and exercises.
You know, and it's not going to be easy,
all right.
To take thousands of years of insight, and
try to cram that in to
short online learning modules, it's going
to
be challenging to understand all this
stuff.
But I think the payoff is worth it.
You know?
Anf for me the payoff is worth it,
because the concepts in calculus are just
really cool.
Calculus is a huge subject, and it
combines just a lot of different topics.
You know, a calculus course and this
course, introduces things like functions
and limits, talk about infinity, talk
about derivative, talk about area and
integrals.
And the big surprise is that all of
these seemingly unrelated topics, end up
being related.
Right?
There's connections between all of these
different concepts that are appearing in
calculus.
And I think those kinds of connections are
just very exciting.
Another cool thing about calculus, is that
we get to do a lot of neat computations.
Alright, we're going to learn how to
compute derivatives, compute areas.
You know, but don't get me wrong.
Right?
At the end of this whole process, the goal
isn't really to be able to compute things.
Right?
The goal is insights, it's understanding,
it's some appreciation
of the concepts, and how these concepts
connect together.
And doing the computations is certainly a
prerequisite to being able to understand
those concepts.
But I really hope to, to dig deeper, you
know, and to be
able to see how all of these different
ideas within calculus are related.
It's going to be a challenging quest, but
I think it's
a worthwhile quest, and I'm glad that
you've chosen to join us.
Good luck.
[MUSIC]