[MUSIC]
My other massive open online courses are
built around a calendar.
There's a start date, an end date, and
then new material gets released every
single week.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
In contrast, this course is self-paced,
meaning that not only can you sign
up at any time, but you can start this
course at any time.
And then you can work through the material
as quickly or as methodically as you'd
like.
My hope is that this new format will just
let a
lot more people learn a lot more math, but
it's an experiment.
You know?
And I hope that you'll be able to provide
some feedback
as to what's working well and what still
needs to be improved.
So I personally just really appreciate any
feedback that you can
provide about this course and about how we
can make it better.
You know, I hope that working together we
can really produce just a fantastic
experience learning calculus.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]