In addition to storing your data securely,
you should also make sure
that you backup regularly.
Keeping backups is probably the single
most important data management task.
There's a real risk of loss through hard
drive failure or accidental deletion.
The basic 3-2-1 principle of backup
is that you have three copies
of your files on at least two
different media with one offsite.
You should also test your backups
regularly to make sure that you could
restore from them if needed.
There's a long list of questions
you should ask when considering
your backup strategy.
How will you back up your data?
How regularly will backups be made?
Will all the data be backed up, or
just that which has been changed?
A backup of changed data is
known as an incremental backup.
While a backup of all data
is known as a full backup.
How often will full and
incremental backups be made?
How long will your backups be stored?
How much drive space or
how many CDs or DVDs will be required
to maintain this backup schedule?
And how can you keep track of
different versions of data,
especially when backing
up to multiple devices?
Once you understand what you
require in terms of backup,
check what services are available
to meet these needs.
It's also important to ascertain
the backup schedule and
retention policies of any centralized
backup services you may use.
For example, under the grandfather,
father, son, rotation scheme, files may
only be available for two to three months
before the storage space is overwritten.
There are various cloud services that
you can use to backup your data.
These typically allow you to store and
synchronize your files online and
between computers.
Most offer a limited amount of space for
free and will charge you for
additional storage or premium services.
Common service providers are Dropbox,
Google Drive and OneDrive.
You can take a look at Wikipedia,
which has a through comparison.
There are some obvious advantages
to using cloud services for backup.
No user intervention is required, so you
don't need to change tapes, label cd's or
perform other manual tasks.
They provide a remote offsite backup copy.
Most provide encryption and versioning,
and they're multi-platform.
There are, however,
significant risks to using cloud services.
Some providers may store data outside
of the European economic area, so
you may be in breach of
the European Data Protection Directive, or
your research funder's policy.
Restoration of the data may be
slow depending on your bandwidth.
The stored data may not be entirely
private if it's unencrypted,
and the service provider
may go out of business.