We recommended that you encrypt your
data a few times in the last section, so
what do we mean by data encryption?
Encryption is the process of converting
your data into an unreadable code.
A user would need the encryption key or
secure password in order to read the file.
Encryption will protect
your data from disclosure,
in the case that your laptop or
storage device is lost or stolen.
The University of Edinburgh Data
Encryption Policy, warns that medium or
high risk personal data or
business information must be encrypted
if it leaves the University environment.
Encryption is reliant on
the creation of a strong password.
The data can't be recovered if
this encryption key is lost.
So you should establish a reliable and
secure backup procedure for
the data and any associated passwords.
Encryption is an obvious step for
laptop security, however there's
no one size fits all solution.
BitLocker, Pretty Good Privacy.
And other commercial software
packages are available, but
you'll need to consider
your operating system.
If you keep sensitive
data on USB flash drives,
it's recommended that you use
drives with encryption software.
These give protection to
the data if the drive is lost.
Especially if the data contained personal
or commercially sensitive information.
Compared with ordinary USB flash drives,
they only cost a modest amount more, so
are a good buy.
Your local IT support service should be
happy to advise on the suitability of any
encrypted flash drive that
you plan on purchasing.
So what happens to sensitive data
when it's no longer required?
You may have anonymized your data and
now want to dispose of
the identifiable portions, or
you may have agreed to delete your data
at the end of your research project.
File deletion is not enough to completely
remove sensitive data from your computer,
it only removes the pointers to the disk
sectors in which the data reside.
The deleted files can be easily recovered
with commonly available software.
So let's take a look at how you can
permanently remove sensitive data.
There are three main options available.
Data erasure, also known as data clearing
or data wiping, uses special software
to remove all data, while leaving the hard
drive or storage medium still operable.
However, you should be aware that
current techniques may not be completely
successful on solid-state drives and
USB flash drives.
Degaussing is another way to remove data,
it disturbs the alignment
of magnetic storage media.
But in many cases, it makes new media
such as hard drives and tapes unusable.
Physical destruction through shredding,
pulverising or
incineration is also an option.
You've now completed this module.
If you take a look at the further reading
on the next slide, you'll get additional
references and resources, so you can learn
more about storage, backup, and security.