So in the previous lecture, we saw that
switches show up very naturally,
especially in robotics where we're going
to switch between different modes of
operation.
And what I want to do today is talk a
little bit about the models that we're
going to use to describe these phenomena.
And the models that we're going to use
are called Hybrid Automata.
And these are models that contain both
the continuous dynamics.
Meaning to x dot part and the discrete
switching logic that says oh, if you see
an obstacle you should switch to an
obstacle avoidance behavior, or something
like that.
Now, what this means is that the discrete
logic will be modeled as a finite state
machine that moves between different
discrete states, so that's the discrete
logic.
But just a finite state machine on static
steroids in the sense that inside each
state we have a continuous dynamics
loraking so.
Having said that, what we need first of
all is the notion of a state.
So x, as before, is the continuous state
of the system.
This is the physical state typically of
what a robot is doing.
But then what we're going to do is we're
going to add a discrete state that I'm
going to call q.
And q is going to tell me which different
continuous mode I am in.
So my dynamics now can be encoded not As
xdot=f(x,u) but xdot=fsubq(x,u).
Where this q now tells me which mode am I
actually in.
And what we're going to do is transition
between different discrete modes in a
state machine where here I'm having mode
q.
So really, xdot inside that mode.
Is going to, be fsubq and xdot inside
this mode is going to be xdot is, fsubq
prime.
Now, these are called transitions right,
so when you jump in between different
discrete modes you're making transitions
between different states in the finite
state machine.
Now what we need to understand is, when
do we actually make these Jumps, well for
that we need something called a guard and
the guard is something that checks
whether or not you should jump.
And then we're also, [COUGH], excuse me,
also going to add something else which is
called a reset which is going to tell you
not when you jump but where you end up
after you made the transition.
So the guard condition is a condition
that tells you when it is time to jump.
So let's say that I am in mode q and I
want to jump to mode q prime.
Well, what I have, is I have a guard that
says, if.
x belongs to this guard, let's say that
this is, I'm going to switch from one
gear to another gear if my rpm is above
3,000 then I'm going to switch.
This is a guard condition that encodes
when it is time to jump.
Now, when I'm jumping I may actually
reset the value of my state.
For instance, if I'm dropping a ball,
whoop, onto this desk, and it bounces up,
it loses energy in, in the bounce so what
we're doing is we're subtracting a piece
away from the state.
At each bounce.
This way of messing with the state at the
moment the transitions occur is called a
reset.
So, if I am going, I'm here in mode q.
[SOUND].
And then my guard is true, so I am moving
to q prime.
Well, what's happening here is that x
changes for instance, x is now lets say,
the old x/5.
That would be a guard that says, oh I'm
getting only a fifth of the energy
somehow after this jump.
So, what we need are dynamics, individual
dynamics which are called modes.
We need transitions which tell us, tells
us which discrete states are we moving in
between.
We need guards which tell us When we're
going to make these jumps and we're, need
resets to tell us how these jumps end up
effecting the state.
So if we put all of this together, we get
a rather arguably messy looking thing.
But it's very rich.
This is the hybrid automaton.
Singular, or hybrid automata, plural
model. And the way this works is, let's
see here, we start with x equal to x not,
we end up in this mode, which is q=1,
where we are evolving according to this
differential equation.
Right? Okay, if in this case, x belongs
to G12, then x, we're going to move, over
into this mode. And on our way.
We're going to reset the state.
Now the state is here.
This is my dynamics.
I'm in q2 mode.
Well if, G21 becomes true, I jump this
way.
But if G23 becomes true, I jump that way.
So let's say G23 became true, I jump this
way.
I change my state, possibly according to
this reset map.
I have a third dynamics, q=3.
And then when x enters G31 guard, it
jumps back into q=1, with a new possible
reset.
So this is the general model that we're
going to work with.
Now, it looks a little bit messy, but
it's actually really not.
In most cases, these models are going to
look rather, innocent.
So, here's for example, a very very
simple Hybrid system.
it's a thermostat, or it's my idea of a
thermostat.
Typically, the way a thermostat works, at
least cheap ones, is you set some
temperature you would like.
The thermostat is on the heater is on
until you reach that temperature, or
typically, go a little bit above it.
And then, it turns off, and then you cool
down, and then, when you're too low, you
turn it on again.
And you've heard this all.
In buildings with, with heaters, or that
turn on and off.
So, what we're doing is, we're heating it
up until we're comfortable and warm.
And in fact, this is my desired
temperature and you typically want to add
a little slack that says that I'm going
to, shut this thing off when I'm at,
whatever I want to be 70 degrees.
Plus a little slack, let's say.
By the way, this is 70 degrees
Fahrenheit.
For you Celsius people out there, let's
say it's 20.
so now, we're above 20 Celsius, and now
we're going to cool it down.
And then we're cooling it down until
we're,in this case, below, well, 20
degrees Celsius, or whatever it is in
Fahrenheit, - epsilon.
And the reason why we need this epsilon
is.
If we didn't have it, then this guard is
true.
And this is guard is immediately true.
'Cuz if t is = to t desired, we're just
going to start spinning around
indefinitely here.
So, the little epsilons are important.
So, this would be 1 way.
In which we will model a thermostat.
There are no resets here just current
conditions because we're not magically
making the temperature jump just because
we're changing the heaters from, from on
to off.
Well, here's a gear shifter, right Well,
we have some dynamics.
v is the velocity of the car.
We're now in first gear.
This is our dynamics.
u is our smashing the break of the gas
pedal down.
So this is how we are driving.
When we have the RPM above some threshold
then we change gears.
We switch up to second gear which is
here, right.
So now we are having the second gear.
If we keep pressing the gas.
So that the RPM goes up beyond, beyond
some c2, then we switch to third gear.
Apparently this car only has three gears.
but, we go to the third gear, and the
same thing here with a downshift.
And note this here that I have c2 prime
and c1 prime.
And c1 and c2 here.
This is again, because you want to build
in a little bit of slack.
This is my way of hiding an epsilon
inside there so we don't immediately
transition between, between gears.
So this would be a hybrid atomaton gear
shifter.
And I'm not writing out these dynamics.
Because the particulars aren't that
important right now.
The important thing is, the switching
logic and the way the guards operate.
Well finally, let's look at the
behavior-based robotics system.
What I'm doing is I'm running the robot.
So let's say at x is the position of the
robot.
According to a go to goal behavior.
So f go to goal of x.
This is me having to assign that.
When the distance between where I am and
where the closest obstacle is when that's
less than some sum d, meaning I'm too
close to an obstacle, then I'm going to
switch to another mode or another
behavior which is Avoid obstacles.
So now I have decide my avoid obstacle
behavior and it's safely taking me away
from the obstacle and then when the
position of the robot is greater than
some other distance, the prime away from
the obstacle then I switched to goal to
goal again.
And the way this would look is, let's say
here's the obstacle.
Here's the goal.
Here's my robot.
[SOUND].
My robot is doing fine.
Here's the ball of radius d.
Once I get in here, I'm going to switch
to a goal to goal behavior.
That's going to take me away from the
robot.
Let's say here is a larger circle of
radius d prime and when I'm here, I'm
going to be safe and I'm going to switch
to goal to goal behavior.
So this is what would happen in practice
if you ran this hybrid atomaton as a
behavior based robotic system.
Now, unfortunately, things aren't all
rosy in the hybrid world.
And what we'll see in the next lecture is
that things may actually go wrong even
the we are meaning very well when we
start building our systems.
So the next lecture is a Danger:Beware
sign that we need to put up whenever we
are designing hybrid systems, as opposed
to standard standalone linear time and
variant systems.