What we saw in the previous lecture was
how to model switch systems in a rather
general way using these things called
hybrid automaton.
today, I want to show that just because
we know how to design good linear time
invariant controllers and we know how to
draw a hybrid automaton, doesn't mean
that we can just say, [SOUND] we're done,
we can do everything we want to be able
to do.
In fact, what I want to do today is talk
to you about a rather famous counter
example that makes thinngs hard when
you're in the hybrid world.
So, I'm going to answer the following
question, what can possibly go wrong when
you start switching between different
controllers.
And this tangle of yarn here is supposed
to illustrate what can happen when you
start switching and messing things up
together in, in rather surprising
manners.
Well, lets let's start rather modestly.
Let's say that I have two modes.
I have x dot is equal to A1x and x dot is
equal to A2x and this A1 and A2 matrices
they look rather
innocent, if you ask me.
Some small negative value on the
diagonals, same small diagonal negative
values, their epsilons is positive.
And then, on the off-diagonals, you have
one and negative two here, and two and
negative one there. Well, well let's
check the eigen values,
that's the first thing we should always
do.
Well, it turns out that no matter which
system you have, both A1 and A2, the
eigenvalues are both -epsilon plus
-1.41j.
Well, what does this mean? Well, the real
part is equal to -epsilon, which is
strictly negative, so both systems are
asymptotically stable,
meaning that x will die down to the
origin.
And both of them have a nonzero imaginary
component,
which means that you're going to have
oscillations,
alright? So, we have asymptotically
stable systems with oscillations.
And, in fact, let's see what happens when
we start combining these different modes.
Before we do that though, let's actually
look at the modes a little bit more
carefully by themselves.
So, here is mode 1, x dot is A1x and what
I've plot that here on this axis is x1
and what I've plot that here is x2.
What this would look like if I have time
here and let's say, x1, is I would gets
decaying oscillations.
Well, we don't have that now because I
plotted x1 and x2.
And this is where I start, in this case,
I guess, I started at 1,1 and the system
starts flowing.
And because epsilon is small, you're
going to get closer and closer to zero
but slowly.
And you're going to spiral in like this.
And, you know, t goes to infinity.
You're going to end up at the origin
because you have indeed an asymptotically
stable system.
So, A1 is well-behaved.
It spirals a little bit but what do we
care? We're not afraid of spirals.
Here's A2.
It also looks like a spiral but instead
of a tall and skinny spiral, it's a short
and chunky spiral.
Again, we start at 1,1.
And this system starts spiraling and it
goes inwards and then, [SOUND] it goes
like this so it's also asymptotically
stable as it should but because of the
particular eigenvectors of these two
systems, we end up spiraling in slightly
different ways.
But the point is we have two stable
systems.
Now, let's put them together in a hybrid
automaton.
So, this is hybrid automaton number 1.
I'm going to spiral, tall, and skinny,
until [0 1]x=0.
this means that the second component, so
x2=0 is what this guard means, right?
And when x2=0, I switch to my short and
chunky ellipsoid or inward spiraling
system.
And then, when x1=0, I switch back.
So, this is my first hybrid automaton.
Well, let's see what that actually looks
like if you do it.
So, as always.
we start at 1,1. I start in mode 1
[SOUND] until this point, right, where
x2=0, then I switch to mode 2 which as
the short and chunky ellipsoid.
Here, x1 becomes 0 and now I switch to
mode 1 again so we have 1,2,1.
Now, we switch to mode 2, to mode,
mode 1, and so forth.
And as we keep doing that, we spiral in,
and one thing that you're going to notice
then is that we're actually ending up at
the origin at a much faster rate.
So, this system is not just
asymptotically stable, it's
asymptotically stabler, which is not a
word, by the way than the original
systems, because it actually converges at
a faster rate.
So, by switching, we were able to get to
the origin faster, which makes you
wonder, why am I calling this a counter
example?
Well, this is not a counter example.
But aha,
hybrid automaton number 2,
maybe that is the counter example.
It's the same as hybrid automoton number
1, but I switched the guard conditions.
So I'm switching from mode 1 to mode 2,
when x1=0 and I'm switching from mode 2
to mode 1, when x2=0.
This seems like a modest enough
modification if you ask me, but modesty
in all modesty,
it turns out that that is a huge deal.
Now, 1,1 is hiding somewhere here and
what's happening is that we're now
starting to spiral out.
So now, here we have, for instance, that
x1 became zero.
Now, we're switching to the, the fat
spiral.
Here, x1 becomes 0 and we're switching to
the skinny spiral.
And in this way, we're going to end up
getting further and further out.
And this is indeed an unstable system and
this is a little bothering to us because
I took two stable systems and I put them
together in a hybrid system, and I got
instabilities.
So the punchlines here is, first of all,
stable modes by themselves,
that's not enough to guarantee that the
resulting switch to hybrid systems is
stable.
In fact, you may induce instabilities
through switches.
And that's a little bit of a downer, to
be completely honest.
The other thing is that you can actually
reverse this and say, you could even
design unstable modes, which we're never
going to do.
But you could and actually get a switch
system that is stable.
So basically, you could reverse time when
we, what just looked at.
And we get to unstable modes that renders
the switches But here is how we actually
will approach this.
We will design stable modes because it
would be suicidal to design unstable
modes and then hopefully, miraculously
hope that the switches will, will take
care of it.
So, we're going to design, design stable
modes but we need to be aware of the fact
that the new system is not stable.
And, in fact, it would be nice if we
could check that either analytically or
at least in simulation because the hybrid
world is a little bit scarier than the
nonhybrid world.