So welcome back.
today, I would like to investigate a
particular hybrid system that has to do
with a bouncing ball.
So, that is, I take a ball and I drop it
on a surface and I would first of all,
like to model it.
And secondly, like to figure out how the
ball behaves.
And the reason why I want to do this is
not necessarily because I really like
balls but because this bouncing ball
example holds the key to another little
peculiarity of hybrid systems that we
should be aware of.
So, here is the set up.
I have a ball.
It's h above the ground.
Now, what happens in between the bounces?
Well, Newton tells me that force is mass
times acceleration and, and the
acceleration is, in fact, -g, where g is
the gravitational constant.
So, if I let x1=h and x2 be equal to h
dot, which is what we always do,
then what I get is that x dot is this
thing, 0100 x, which is just the point
mass, plus this gravitational force
that's pulling it down.
Now, let's say that the thing that I'm
interested in also is, where the ball
actually is, how high, how high up it is,
so y is going to be 01 x.
So, that is my model of the ball.
What happens at the bounces? Well, you
could try to model ball deformations and
whatnot, but that seems rather
complicated so what we're simply going to
say is that these are what's called
inelastic bouncers which mean, which
means that a little bit of energies
sucked out of the ball every time it
bounces.
And in fact, what we're going to say is
that velocity, this is the velocity, so
if the ball is coming down here [SOUND]
hits the ground then the velocity
instantaneously flips, it means, that's
why we have a minus sign there because
the ball instantaneously flips but we're
also scaling it with this gamma constant,
so we're making the velocity change
direction from downwards to upwards, but
a little bit less, which means we lost
some energy in the bounce.
Well, the position doesn't change in the
bounce, so this means that my reset
condition is going to be this.
This is just encoding this fact that I'm
flipping a little bit, I'm flipping my
velocity, and I'm loosing a little bit of
energy at the time of the bounce.
Alright, so lets see what this bouncing
ball hybrid automaton might look like.
Well, x dot is Ax+b, in this case, not Bu
and b is 0-g so this is this forcing term
that is gravity, no big deal.
Now, what's going to happen is I'm going
to switch from that mode to itself when
I'm bouncing.
And we already saw that the reset
condition is this inelastic bounce
condition that says that we're losing a
little bit of the velocity at the time of
the bounce.
So, that's the reset condition.
Now, the guard condition is what? Well,
clearly, we're bouncing when we're
hitting the ground.
So, we would like the height to be less
than or equal to 0, right?
Well, let's see what happens.
Here comes the ball [SOUND] hits the
ground, now the height is 0, we're
switching and now the first thing we do
is we reverse the velocity but, meaning,
we're switching.
But hey, wait a second, the height is
still less than or equal to 0.
The height is still 0.
So, what we're going to do is we're just
going to end up spinning like crazy if we
have this guard.
So, this is not a good guard.
Let's get rid of it.
Instead, what we need to do is we're,
we're going to switch when we come down
to the ground and the velocity is
pointing downwards.
Meaning that h needs to be negative or
less than or equal 0.
And h dot has to be less than or equal 0,
meaning, we're facing downwards.
Or since h and h dot constitute our
state, then the guard should really
simply be that x is less than or equal to
0.
That's the guard condition.
Well, it could be it's just a, the height
is just 0, but this is really the
condition that tells us that it's time
to, to switch. Okay, good.
So now, we have that.
Is this any good?
Well, I mean clearly, it's good.
It's pretty and we have guards and
resets.
But does it model, first of all,
faithfully what balls do when they
bounce? And secondly, are there reasons
why a model like this would cause us to
be a little bit nervous? To answer that,
we need to figure out what the ball is
actually doing if we have this model.
So, first of all, we have this system
again now.
What I would like to know is what is the
output of this system.
Well, fast forward, sorry, not forward,
reverse two weeks and we go back to
linear time-invariant systems.
We know what the solution to this system
is.
We know that the output is C times this
bad boy here, that we call the state
transition matrix, which was fancy speak
for this matrix exponential times the
initial condition plus C times this
rather awkward-looking integral there.
Now, all of these is, is, is not
particularly pleasant.
And I remember vividly how we struggled
to get through this because there were so
many integrals to keep track of here.
Now, in this particular case, we're a
little bit lucky because this A matrix is
what's called nilpotent because if I take
A to the power two, or three, or any high
there, higher exponential here, then I
get 0 out.
And that turns out to be quite wonderful
for us.
Why is that? Well, remember, that e^At is
really this infinite sum.
A, there should be a parentheses here, I
apologize.
0 At to the power of k divided by k!.
Well, in our case, all the higher order
A's are equal to 0, so I get first k=0,
which gives me the identity matrix.
Then I get k=1, which simply gives me A
times t.
And then, I have all the others which are
equal to 0.
So, e^At, in this case, is simply this
matrix.
Here is the part that comes from the
adjacent matrix and since A is simply
that times t, I get the t up here.
So, this is my e^At or my state
transition matrix.
So now, I should be able to plug this
back into the equation for y and get a
rather nice looking expression.
So, let's do that.
Well, here is C.
Here is the state transition matrix.
Here's my initial condition.
Here's this rather awkward-looking
differential equation sorry, integral.
now, we can try to solve that.
and if we do that, instead of actually
doing the math,
I did the math,
I encourage you to go home and do that.
I'm just going to write down what the
solution is.
It's going to be h0 times the initial
velocity,
h dot 0 of t-t0 and that's then minus g/2
t-t0 squared.
So, this is what the output looks like in
between bounces.
Good.
Now, that we have that, let's figure out
how long it takes in between bounces.
So, let's say that we start at zero o
clock, at height zero.
This is when the bounce is about to start
and then, [SOUND] we want to know how
long this, this took.
We want to know how long it took us to
get back the ground.
Well, that's simple.
Let's pick a big time, big T and say,
well, y at that time t has to be equal to
0.
Well, then we plug that in.
h0=0 not so we don't any turn there we
just get h dot 0 times T minus this
thing.
or another way of writing it is like
this.
And you know what, this needs to be equal
to 0 because h is 0 there and h is 0
there,
which is why we have two solutions.
So, one solution corresponds to T=0,
which is at the beginning of the bounce.
And the other solution is when we return
down.
So, this is how long it took me to go
from the ground, up into the air, and
then back down to the ground.
This is the time in between bounces.
Let's compute the accumulated bounce
times,
just because we find it amusing.
Well, the velocity at the beginning, so
at the first time, let's just say that
the velocity is v,
right? So then, the time of the first
bounce, instead of h dot 0, I just plug
in v there.
I get 2v/g, that's the time of the first
bounce.
Well, the velocity after the first
bounce,
well, the reset condition says that I
have gamma times v, so okay, I have a new
v here.
That's what I'm going to plug into my h
dot 0 here that immediately tells me that
the time of the second bounce is, well,
it's the time of the first bounce plus
the time it took for the second bounce
and instead of v, I have v divided by
gamma there.
So, that's how long it took me to perform
two bounces, and so forth.
This tells me that the time of the nth
bounce is given by this 2v/g which is
this term that shows up over and over
again.
And then, every bounce gets this gamma to
the power of k accumulated.
Now, this is what's called a geometric
series.
And if you look that up or you happen to
know it, if gamma is less than one, which
means that you're not adding energy at
the bounce times,
this thing will actually, okay, and we
have gamma less than one,
this will actually converge in the sense
that when n goes to infinity, this thing
becomes equal to this expression.
Well now, maybe some of you are asking,
so what? [LAUGH] Well, you shouldn't be
asking so what.
Well, what's going on there? This is the
time it takes to perform infinitely many
bounces,
infinitely many bounces, and this is less
than infinity.
What that means is this bouncing ball is
going to go [SOUND] infinitely many.
And there is some time t infinity here
where this system is just going to grind
to a halt and our model is just going to
keep computing bounce after bounce after
bounce after bounce faster and faster and
faster.
And this is actually a serious problem
that causes our system to actually crash.
So, the ball bounces in infinite numbers
of times in finite time.
And like I said, this is not just a
mathematical curiosity that shows that we
can compute geometric series.
It means that if I'm simulating it, then
my simulation would crash.
In fact, I encourage you to write this
exact model into your favorite simulator
and watch it crash.
This also means that if I write down my
hybrid system like this, then it's
undefined beyond T infinity because it's
not clear what's happening beyond there.
Time is not allowed to go to infinity.
So, stability, which says what happens
when T goes to infinity [SOUND] you can't
even ask that question because t doesn't
go to infinity.
what's worse obviously is that real balls
don't do this, real balls bounce and
after awhile they lay still, right?
So, this is also an indication that our
model is not particularly good.
And, in fact, this type of phenomenon
where you have infinitely many switches
in finite time is known as the Zeno
Phenomenon, after the philosopher Zeno,
that had the a tortoise race, a hare.
And the paradox that Zeno came up with
was the fact that the hare never managed
to overtake the tortoise.
And in the next lecture, we will see,
first of all, why the tortoise is able to
beat the hare and what to do about it,
meaning how do you make the rabbit
overtake the turtle? Well, that, my
friends, is the topic of the next
lecture.