So, in the last lecture, we investigated
this innocent-looking model or system,
which was a ball bouncing on a surface.
And we saw something rather strange
there, which was that, that the, the ball
ended up bouncing an infinite number of
times in finite time.
And this is part of another potential
complication that comes from hyberdizing
your model, namely, that you have these
kinds of infinitely many swicthes.
And this is known as the Zeno Phenomenon.
And in today's lecture, we're going to
dig a little deeper into the, the Zeno
Phenomenon and see what we can do about
it and if you can understand it.
But fundamentally, what I would like to
point out is that Zeno is bad, because if
you're actually running something that's
asked to do an infinite amount of things
in finite time, it crashes.
If you're running this on the computer,
the simulations crash.
another thing is that we know that there
is something inaccurate or wrong with our
model because the ball, if I drop a ball,
it doesn't bounce an infinite number of
times,
it bounces 17 times and then it stops
bouncing.
So, there's something wrong with our
model.
That's another warning flag.
And the third warning flag is that we
don't actually know what the system does
beyond the, the Zeno point, meaning the
time up to which we have an infinite
number of switches.
So, since we can't really define what the
system is doing beyond that point, things
like asymptotic stability is meaningless
because time is not allowed to really
progress off to infinity.
So, first of all, why is it called the
Zeno phenomenon? Well, there was a Greek
philosopher, Zeno, Zeno of Elea who spent
a lot of time thinking about movement and
the dynamic world and basically his point
was that our perception of the world is
wrong because clearly there are all these
problems out there. For instance, here's
one of his famous paradoxes.
We have a hare racing a tortoise. And the
tortoise is a little slower so the
tortoise gets a head start.
In fact, the tortoise starts there and
then, the race is on.
And at some point, the hare reaches the
point were the tortoise started from but
at that point, right, the tortoise has
moved, not much but it has moved a little
bit.
This is how far the tortoise has moved.
Okay. The race goes on.
And at some point, the hare catches up to
where the tortoise was last time but now,
the tortoise has moved a little bit more,
not much, and then this repeats.
In fact, here is the, the paradox. The
paradox is that the hare never catches up
with the tortoise because every time it
reaches the step that the tortoise was
last time, the tortoise would have moved
a tiny bit.
Now mathematically,
this is nothing.
We know now about convergent series.
We know that even though there are
infinitely many of these small intervals
the sum of them will converge and there
is indeed a point where the hare will
catch the tortoise.
but the problem for us is that if I model
this as a hybrid system, I have, again,
infinitely many switches in finite time.
So, this is why this kind of infinite
amount of switches is called the Zeno
Phenomenon because it can be traced back
to Zeno's many paradoxes about motion.
Now, let's look at another example, one
that's not a hare and a tortoise but one
that's rather innocent-looking.
Let's say that x-dot is negative, for +x
- 1 and it's positive for -x.
Okay, so we have this.
If I write this as a this is a hybrid
automoton, so let's see what's going
there.
An if I draw this little plot here,
right, here is here is time and here's x.
Let's say that x starts there.
Well, it starts positive so x-dot is
going to be -1, so it's going to decay
down with a slope of -1 and then it
becomes tiny bit negative, and then oh,
it's going to switch back up to plus, and
then it goes up and in a second, it
becomes just a tiny bit positive again,
it switches down and, in fact, really
what's happening is that once it hits 0,
it starts switching like crazy here.
In practice, it would chatter but in
theory, it starts switching like crazy
here and this is actually not good at
all.
So, this is really a Super-Zeno
Phenomenon because not only do we have
infinitely many switches in finite time,
we have it at the single time instance,
which is when the system actually hits
x=0.
So, for that reason, we typically talk
about two different kinds of Zeno types
to, so type 1 Zeno, which is what I now
call the Super-Zeno. It says that you get
infinitely many switches in a single time
instant.
In this case, again, I want to reiterate
this, the ball came down here and then,
not the ball, this system came down here
and then it started switching infinitely
many times right there.
Now, type 2 is Zeno by not type 1,
meaning, you have infinitely many
switches but you have that over a time
interval and the bouncing ball is really
an example of that.
So.
there are some good news and bad news in
all these rather messy switching
situation.
The bad news is that Zeno is a problem as
we've seen.
However, type 1 which is arguably the
more common type is not only detectable,
meaning, it is easy to see if you're
going to end up in a situation where you
are going to switch infinitely many times
at a single time instant.
But the other good news about type 1 is
that we can actually deal with it because
you know what,
what should this system do? It should go
down to zero and then it should stay at
0.
It's clear that that's what we want the
system to do and, in fact, you can do
that as you will see in the next lecture.
Now, the last piece of bad news though is
that type 2,
the bouncing ball type, that is hard,
it's hard to deal with a bouncing ball.
It's hard to detect it, it hard, it's
hard to remedy it.
and this is again, a situation where you
really need to test your system and see
do I get something like this where you
start seeing an accumulation of switch
times.
And if you do, you need to go back and
revisit your model.
But in the next lecture, we will see how
to indeed overcome the, the problems that
a type 1 Zeno system will will cause us.