Last time we saw that not only we have to
worry about Zeno.
This zeno problem or the zeno phenomenon
comes in two different flavors.
And one thing that I stated was that type
1 zeno which is infinitely many switches
in zero time or in one timing sense here
represented by this system where.
Again, if I have x here, and time here,
and I start positive, then x is going to
be -1 until x becomes, just, just
negative.
And then, we're going to get this
infinitely many switches going on right
there.
that's type 1.
Well, it turns out, that we can actually
remedy this.
And the reason for it is, you know what
is very, very clear what should happen.
The system shouldn't grind to a halt.
It should just nicely keep continuing on
like this
Like x is equal to 0.
So how do I take this intuitive notion of
that x should just keep saying and be
equal to 0 and make that mathematically
sound.
What, what's the topic of today's
lecture, and this construction by which
we can continue beyond the zeno point in
the type 1 zeno system, using something
that's known as.
Sliding mode control.
So, let's be a little bit general here.
Let's say that I have one system, x dot
is f1(x) and then I have a switching
surface, g(x).
And when g is negative, I switch to f
two, and when it becomes positive I
switch back to f1.
So here it is, here's my switching
surface, g(x) = 0, that's where the
action is.
Now on this side I'm going to be using
f1, and da, da, da, da, da, da, da, when
I hit this point, well let's say that f1
is pointing inwards.
Well on this part of the world I am going
to be using f2.
Well, let's say that f2 here points
outwards.
This means that when I hit this point
again, I grind to a halt.
so this is really what's going on is that
both of the vector fields both f1 and f2
point in the wrong direction.
So f1 points over in to the f2 territory.
f2 points over in the f1 territory, but
again it's clear what should really
happen.
We should somehow slide along the
switching surface here.
That's clear because f1 and f2 are
pulling in different directions and this
is why it's known as sliding mode control
because what we do is we slide along the
switching surface.
So let's see how to actually make this
sliding happen.
Again, I have g positive on this side, g
negative on this side, and the switching
surface is g = 0.
f2 wants to drive me in this direction,
and f1 wants to drive me in this
direction.
I want to slide along the surface.
That should be the right solution.
Well first of all what are the conditions
under which I'm going to slide.
Well f2 needs to point in the positive
direction of g because on this side g is
positive.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to
find this thing, the vector that's normal
to the switching surface and it turns out
that luckily for us this is the gradient.
The partial derivative of g with respect
to x, transpose.
And now I take what's called the inner
product, so, with this thing and this
thing.
So the inner product is just a
multiplication.
and if this inner product is positive, it
means that this one and this one are
pointing.
in the same direction.
I also take the inter-product with this
and that, and if the inter-product is
negative, it means that they're pointing
in, in different directions. So what this
means is I actually have a condition for
sliding.
I need dg the x, where this is actually
dg, dx1, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah,
dg, the xn a roll vector like this times
f1, well f11 to f1n, 'cause these are all
vectors.
If this is negative, that is code for
having this arrow and this arrow pointing
in different directions.
So, f1 points into negative g territory.
f2 points into positive g territory.
if this happens at the switching surface,
then we have sliding.
And, one way we can think about this
object here, it's the derivative of g, in
the direction f1.
And this is the derivative of g in the
direction f2, and there's actually a
fancy term for this.
it's called the Lie derivative.
So the derivative of G in the direction
f, we're going to write this Lfg which is
simply code for dg/dx * f.
So when I write Lfg, this is what I mean.
It's the lead derivative of g in the
direction of f.
So, using our slightly fancier notation
we know that sliding occurs.
Meaning we should slide if the
derivative, g, in the f1 direction is
negative, which, again, means this and
this have different directions, and the
derivative of g in the f2 direction is
positive, which means this and this have
the same signs meaning they point in the
same, in the same directions.
So this actually tells us whether or not
we have sliding and wallah, we actually
have a test for type 1 zeno that says
that sliding occurs.
If Lf1g is negative and Lf2g is positive,
and this is at g(x) = 0 so this is along
the switching surface when we're inside
the different mode regime.
We don't have to worry about this.
But on the switching surface,
this our zeno type 1 probe that we have
to use to see whether or not we slide.
And this nice because this is something
that's easily implemented.
We still don't know what actually happens
beyond the zeno point, meaning, how do we
slide.
And that is going to be the topic of next
lecture.