So last time we saw that we could
actually test for type1 zeno and the way
we could test this was to see whether or
not the gradient dg, dx transpose points
in the same direction as f2, in the
opposite direction of f1.
So if I have that, then I do have type 1
zeno.
And we came up with a little probe here
to check whether or not, this is indeed
happening.
So, the first thing we do is we check
LF1G negative, and LF.
2 G positive.
Where LFG was this thing we called the
lead derivative.
Which was simply just fancy speak for DG,
DX times, in this case, F1 of X.
That's all it means.
So this is the probe that checks whether
or not sliding occurs.
Today, I want to talk about what's called
regularizations, which is.
Code for okay, let's say we have that, we
have sliding, how do we compute how we
slide? And it turns out that this is
going to be very important when we move
on to robotics because this occurs quite
a bit when you actually start running
robotic navigation systems.
So today's lecture is all about How to be
actually slide along this surface.Well,
lets actually try to be a little careful
in [UNKNOWN].
So if I'm sliding here, what is
characterizing that motion well, i know
that g(x)=0 which means that if i take
the time, the relative of g, we respect
to t Then it should be 0 because g is not
going to change when I'm sliding because
I'm staying at g=0.
So one thing we need to do is say that
dg/dt=0.
Well, let's see where that takes us,
dg/dt It is equal to dgdx*xdot.
So now what is x dot along here.
Well, what I am going to postulate is
that it's a combination of f2 and f1.
In fact let's say that is equal to
sigma1*f1+sigma2+f2.
So it's a convex combination of, of these
two Vector fields.
So if I do that, I get instead of x dots,
I get this thing here sigma 1 f1 plus
sigma 2 f2.
Well, since these are scalars, I can
actually pull them out here, which means
that I can write this expression that's
is a little bit messy looking like sigma
1 times the lead derivative of g along f1
plus sigma 2 times the lead derivative of
g along f2.
So that's what the time derivative of g
actually is.
But I want that to be equal to 0.
This needs to be equal to 0 because that
was our condition.
So if I put this thing equal 0 then I can
solve for instance for sigma 2 and I get.
This expression right here.
So I know how σ2 is going to depend on
σ1.
Well that's a good start.
We also know that both σ need to be
positive because I'm not allowed to
always start flowing backwards and they
also should sum up to 1 because otherwise
they can go super fast along this
direction which I typically don't want.
I want it to respect the dynamics.
So.
I have additional constraint too.
So the sigma needs to be positive and
they need to sum up to 1.
Well.
let's see how we can actually solve it.
So, let's go back to our old friend, the
example.
And again this example.
Looks like this, where, you know what?
I'm sliding down with slope -1.
Here's x and here's time.
And when I hit the switching surface, I
stay with x=0 for the duration.
Okay, what is the switching surface,
first of all? Well, it's x=0, so g(x) is
simply x=0.
Okay,
let's compute some of these Lee
derivatives.
So, lf1g.
It's, it's the derivative of g, with
respect to x.
So, the derivative of that with respect
to x, is simply 1.
F1 is simply negative 1.
So, the Lee derivative is negative 1.
Which is 1 of the things we needed for
zeno.
We needed, or for sliding.
We needed this to be negative for, type 1
zeno to occur.
That's the first.
Well let's do the same for f 2.
Sorry this is an f 2 right here,
apologize about that.
l f 2 g well it's a dgdx which equals the
derivative of that with respect to x
which is 1, and f 2 which is plus 1.
Right, so I get 1*1, which is equal to 1,
which is positive, which was the other
condition for having Type 1 Zeno.
So we know that we actually have Type 1
Zeno, or sliding, here.
okay.
So now, let's try figuring out what what
the The sigmas should actually be.
Well, we had a formula for sigma 2..
It is equal to -sigma1 and these two Lee
derivatives divided by eachother.
Well, this was -1 and this was +1 so
sigma 2 is simple equal to sigma 1.
Rather simple.
[INAUDIBLE].
But what, what are they? Well, recall
that the need to sum up to 1.
Which means that they both have to be a
half.
What this actually means, then, is that
we can compute what the induced mode,
sliding mode, actually is.
Well, I take sigma 1 * f1, which is half
of f1.
And then i take sigma2 times F2 which is
half of F2, well F1 is negative one and
F2 is plus one so i get -0.5 + 0.5 and
that's equal to 0.
So I know that my induced mode, in this
case, is x dot = 0, which is exactly what
we wanted.
because remember this picture that we've
drawn over and over again.
We want to start here, get down there,
and then keep staying at 0.
And the math turns out to work out, in
this case.
Now, let's find the induced mode in
general.
I know that the general formula for
sigma2 and I, I want to point out that
this is not a formula any one in their
right mind should memorize, but we should
know where it comes from and be able to
use it when we need to.
But, here is the general formula for the,
for the induced mode.
Well, we also have that sigma 1 plus
sigma 2, is equals to 1, which means that
I can take sigma 2 here, and plug it in,
because this is what sigma 2 is.
So now I have an expression on sigma 1 so
if I solve that, I acutally know what
sigma 1 is.
I encourage you to go through the math
yourself, it's a little bit of a mouth
full, but what its, what it tells me is
that I compute sigma 1, and I can compute
sigma 2, just as well.
And, if I now sum all of this up
together, I get this expression inside
the pink box there.
And I recognize again, this is a little
bit of a mouthful, but what this tells me
is Exactly what the induced mode is.
So I am going to put a sweet heart around
this thing, not because it's particularly
pretty but because it's systematic and it
tell us how to actually find the sliding
mode controller or the induced mode which
means that we know Exactly, not only when
type 1 zeno occurs.
But how to progress beyond it.
So, let's figure it out.
If I have, this is my hybrid system.
And, if this is a type 1 zeno hybrid
automaton.
How do I regularize it? What do I do to
add this extra sliding mode? Well, this
is what I do.
Now, let's parse this, even though it
looks a little bit like a mouthful, let's
figure out what it means.
So let's say I'm here, g is positive.
G is positive and all is, all is well.
Then, if g becomes 0 and the sliding
condition is satisfied.
Then I move in to what we just computed
here which is the induce mode.
And again it's a little bit of a mouth
full but we will see later on that in
robotics we have no choice but to
actually use this.
So then I'm going to use this mode until
if g becomes positive I jump back to f1.
If g becomes negative I jump to f2.
And of course we don't always have Type 1
Zeno some switches are nice if I simply
end up g negative, I jump directly from
mode 1 to mode 2 and vice versa.
So, this is how you take a hybrid system
and make it immune to the Nauseous and
bad effects of Type 1 Zeno.
And the nice thing is that this is
completely general, and we don't ever
again have to worry about Zeno.
Type 1 Zeno, Type 2 Zeno we already said
them about.
Having said that this actually brings me
to the summary of this entire model and
hybrid systems.
So, what do we have, we have models, we
have very rich models which are the
hybrid [UNKNOWN] models.
We have something what we call Stability
Awareness or just We're aware of the fact
that, just because the submodules, or the
submodes are stable themselves doesn't
mean that the hybrid system is stable.
And we need to be aware of it, test for
it.
We also have seen zeno as another awkward
hybridization that occurs.
Or an awkward phenomenon that can occur
when you go hybrid.
we have 2 classes of zeno.
1, which is type 2, which is the bouncing
ball.
Infinitely many switch, many switches in
finite, but not, not zero time.
That's bad and scary, and we can't do
anything about it except, look out for
it.
But then, we have type 1.
And we now know, not only how to check
for it.
But how to get around it using these
things that I call regularizations or the
induced sliding mode and with that if I
had, you know a confetti, I would toss it
up into the air because this ends the
massive part and the pre-robotics part
really of this course.
So what we're going to do in the next
module is go back to robotics.
Apply, all of our new and awesome tools,
and see, how we can unleash them to
actually make mobile ro, robots do cool
things in the real world.
Well done.