Welcome back.
This is week five.
In week three we wrote a controller to
take our robot from point A to point B.
This was called the go-to-goal controller.
And in week four we designed a controller
that avoids obstacles.
So, what we want to do this week is
combine those two.
So that our robot can drive from some
point in the world to
some other point in the world without
colliding with any of the obstacles.
And the way that we're going to do that is
to arbitrate
between the go-to-goal and avoid-obstacle
controller.
And that really means, think about how
should we
combine these two so that we make the
right decision.
Should we be, should we be avoiding
obstacles?
Or should we be going to goal?
So the two techniques that we're going to
be using is blending and hard switching.
And in blending what we're going to do is
we're going to
create a new controller which combines
both the go-to-goal controller and the
avoid-obstacle controller.
Then what we're also going to test is
switching between the go-to-goal and the
avoid-obstacle controller.
So we'll either run the go-to-goal
controller
or we'll run the avoid-obstacle
controller, and we'll
switch back and forth depending on whether
the robot is close to an obstacle or not.
And then we're going to do a third
experiment, which is
to use the blended controller as an
intermediary between the two.
So we're going to go to goal when we're
away
from any obstacles, if we're getting close
to obstacles, we'll switch to the blended
controller.
And if we're within a dangerous distance
of the obstacle,
we'll switch over to the intermed, into
the avoid-obstacles controller.
So, what do we do when we, when we, when
we blend?
What we're going to do is create one
single controller that does both.
And what we'll do is first compute our
go-to-goal vector which is U
gtg, and then we're going to compute the
obstacle avoidance vector, U ao.
And we will know how to compute both of
those from the previous weeks.
And what we want to do is we want to
combine these two in some way.
And, one way to combine these two is to do
this in a linear fashion.
So, what I'm going to do is take a
fraction of the obstacle-avoidance vector
and take another fraction of
the go-to-goal vector and just add them
together.
And then what I should get is this vector
U ao go-to-goal.
So so this is a combination of these two
vectors.
And this vector will point us in some
direction that is both somewhat in
the direction of the goal, and somewhat in
the direction away from the obstacle.
And what I really want to point out here
too, is that I'm
using u ao,n, and that just denotes that
fact that I'm using the normalized version
of the
vector, and that's nothing but, taking the
vector itself
and dividing it by the magnitude of the
vector.
And that way you get, a vector that's
a, a unit length rather than some
arbitrary length.
And that just allows us to if we take the
normalized
version of the obstacle avoidance vector
and add it to the normalized
versions of the go-to-goal vector.
Then we get an equal balancing of the two
vectors
rather than having to worry about what
their respective magnitude is.
Hard-switching is going to work in a
little bit different way.
What we're going to do is, we're going to
just use one controller at a time.
So, for example, is like I said, if we're
close
to the obstacle, we're going to want to do
obstacle avoidance.
But, if we're clear of the obstacle, we're
going to want to just do go-to-goal.
So, if we're away from the obstacle, use
the go-to-goal vector.
If we're close to an obstacle, use the
obstacle avoidance vector.
And the way we're going to do this is
we're just going to make
a decision about how close the robot is to
the, to, to an obstacle.
So for example, if one of your infrared
sensors on the robot
senses a distance less than say, 15
centimeters,
we might want to switch over to avoid
obstacles.
But whereas if we're greater, at a
distance greater
than 15 away from, 15 centimeters away
from the
obstacle we can go, we are safe and we can
go ahead and do, just go to goal.
And then the last one is to, is to use the
go-to-goal if we're some
distance away from the obstacle, if we're
getting closer we're going to switch
over to the combined blended version of
the vector or of the controller.
And, then, if we're too close to the
obstacle, if it's unsafe for the robot
to do, be worrying about where to go to,
worrying about going to the goal.
We're going to switch over to avoid
obstacles.
And that way we're going to ensure that
we're
definitely not going to slam into any
obstacles.
Now, the logic for deciding which
controller to
use is going to end up in the supervisor.
And the supervisor really considers each
controller to be its own state.
And the supervisor can switch between
these states.
Which means we're switching between the
different controllers.
So, we're going to have three different
controllers.
And, kind of going back to week three, an
example of this is if you look
at, at the ex, execute function of the
supervisor and QB supervisor dot m, you
may, might have seen that I had a
statement that says switch to state stop.
And this means that I'm switching from the
go, go-to-goal controller that
we were using at that time and switching
to the stop controller.
And the stop controller is nothing but a
controller that
sets the linear angular velocity of the
robot to 0.
Now, we,
we also had a condition when we wanted to
switch over
to the start, to the stop controller from
the go-to-goal controller.
And that condition was that the robot was
at its goal.
So, and the, and the check_event function,
what it did,
is it looked at, well, is this condition,
at_goal, true,
and it was true whenever the goal or
whenever the
robot was within a distance of d_goal of
the goal location.
So that, that statement then becomes true,
which means that we have
switched over into the stop controller
from the from the go-to-goal controller.
And that was a very, very simple state
machine.
because all it said was, that we start off
in the go-to-goal state, or we're using
that controller.
And then when we're close enough to the,
to
the goal location, we switch to the other
state.
Which is the stop state which corresponds
to the stop controller.
It's very, very simple.
What we're going to have to do this week
is going to
be a little bit more complicated.
And here's one example of a state machine
that you could implement using all three
controllers.
Or actually, four controllers.
We're going to start off on the
go-to-goal.
Because we're going to assume that the
robot starts somewhere.
It's not going to be near an obstacle.
It wants to go to the goal.
Then, if, we are at the obstacle, so
meaning that we're at some distance
close to the obstacle, we're going to
switch into the blended controller
with is the ao and go-to-goal controller.
And if we leave the obstacle, meaning
we're
some distance farther away from the
obstacle, we're
going to, the condition obstacle_cleared
will become true,
and we're going to go back to goal.
And so, we could, you know?
You can imagine that we can switch between
these, whenever either one of these
conditions is true.
And,
but this gets a little bit more
complicated than that.
If we are in the state ao_and_gtg, so if
we are in
this state right here, and the robot is
some distance
less than, dsafe.
So what I want, we want, we're going to be
less than dsafe away
from the obstacle, then this will become
true.
And in that case, what happens is that we
switch
from this state into this state right
here, which is avoid_obstacles.
Because this is kind of like a last resort
of, avoiding any collision with any
obstacles in the world.
Now again, if, if we, if we're, end up in
a, if we avoid the obstacle and we end up
in
a, at a distance that is safely away from
the obstacle,
we can switch back to the blended
controller in the middle.
So you can kind of think about your, you,
the robot is always in some
state so, in some state, and it takes a
transition if one of these is true.
And then it switches to this other
controller.
So then it ends up here.
So if, if this one becomes true, it
switches back to this one.
So you can just follow the, these
conditions from state to state to
state to figure out where the robot, what
the robot is going to do.
And I said that we're going to have four
states and four controllers.
It's because I also have one for stopping.
So, if we are, if we
are in this case in the go_to_goal state,
in the, in the, in, in this controller,
end state.
Then, [COUGH] if at_goal becomes true,
then we go ahead and stop.
And, what you will probably notice here,
is that I don't have
a connection from any of the other states
to the stop state.
So, in this state machine, the only way
that the robot will
stop at the goal location is if it's in
the go_to_goal state.
If it's executing the go-to-goal
controller.
So maybe a better design would be to also
have some paths down
here, that's at, at_goal.
And the same thing for here.
So maybe this was a better one.
But you're free to design the state
machine
whichever way you want, so long as you
make
sure your robot doesn't collide with the
obstacle
and ends up at the goal and stops there.
Now, as far as implementation is
concerned, the files that you'll be
interested
in are first of all, the execute function
and the supervisor, so QBSupervisor.m.
That's where we're going to implement the
logic for the state machine, where we're
actual, well, I should say we're
implementing
the state machine in the execute function.
And the other file of interest is going
to be this new controller which is
AOandGTG.m.
So that's where you implement the blended
controller.
And, of course, we'll also take advantage
of GoToGoal.m and AvoidObstacles.m.
Not only in the design of the blended
controller, but also, we're
going to switch it back and forth between
these controllers that we've already
written in the previous weeks.
So, let's see the blended controller in
action in MatLab.
See here, I'm going to go ahead and launch
it, and
of course I've already implemented it, and
we're going to run this.
So, this is the blended controller.
I'm going to click on the robot and follow
it.
And, as you can see, the robot is avoiding
the obstacles.
But it's also going to go to the skull
location, which is -1, 1 up here.
And also has a condition for stopping.
So what I've done here is I'm running the,
the, the blended controller.
And if I am at the goal, then I stop.
And so, this is a success.
Now, my tips for this week are, as usual,
make sure you read the
section corresponding to this week's or
week five in the manual for more details.
I also encourage you to really experiment
with
different ways of blending the go-to-goal
and avoid-obstacles.
So I showed you in an earlier slide one
way of combining the two vectors together.
But I'm sure you can think of, of even
better ways of combining those.
And also experiment with
different state machines.
So there's different, definitely different
ways of combining
the different controllers or the different
states and conditions.
To construct a state machine.
And just explore and see what works the
best for you and good luck.
[BLANK_AUDIO]