[MUSIC]
In the sixth module, we are discussing
weak interactions, and in this tenth video,
we talk about oscillation between
different neutrino flavors.
After following this video, you will know
how to describe the quantum mechanism of
oscillation between neutrinos
of different generations and
the key methods used to
detect such oscillations.
You may have wondered why the particles
nu_L, nu_M, and nu_H, which were
introduced in module 1, do not appear
in reactions via the weak force.
There reason is just that, as for
quarks, the neutrinos which interact
with the W are superposition
of these real particles.
Consequently, a phenomenon
analogous to quark oscillations
happens in the family of neutrinos.
Vacuum oscillations between
different neutrino flavors
can occur if neutrinos have
even zero mass and
if their mass is different
from generation to generation.
And these two conditions are indeed met.
Let us first consider two
flavors of neutrinos nu_mu and
nu_tau for
example, involved in weak interaction.
And two mass eigenstates, two real particles, nu_M and
nu_H with masses m_M and m_H.
The relation between the two classes
are unitary rotations in flavor space.
The angle theta_MH is the equivalent of
the Cabibbo angle in
the quark sector which we have
introduced in video 6.7.
The two particles nu_M and
nu_H propagate in the z direction,
for example, with different wave functions
because of their different masses.
The second equation is valid in
the ultra relativistic approximation,
where p is equal to E-m^2/2E
and t is equal to z.
Now take a nu_mu beam at
t = 0 created for
instance by π+ -> µ+ nu_mu.
At a later time t, so
at a distance z from its origin,
this beam will be composed differently.
The probability to find a nu_tau in
this beam will therefore not be 0.
The factor 1.27 takes into
account the constants
as well as the conversion
of units such that we can put
delta m^2 which is equal
to (m_H^2 - m_M^2)
in eV^2, E^2 in GeV^2
and z in km.
The two factors in the equation
correspond to the amplitude and
phase of an oscillation.
By choosing a distance z, which is
of the same order of magnitude as
delta m^2/4E,
one can thus make a part of the nu_mu
disappear and convert them into a nu_tau.
This nu_mu disappearance
was first observed for
the so-called atmospheric neutrinos.
Cosmic rays incident on
the Earth atmosphere are mostly protons.
The hadron shower they cause in the atmosphere
is dominated by pions.
In their decay, pions produce nu_mu and
nu_e in a relative proportion of 2:1.
Thus there ought to be twice as many nu_mu
and anti-nu_mu in the atmospheric showers
than nu_e and anti-nu _e.
If on the other hand
neutrinos undergo oscillation,
the ratio of both neutrino flavors
will vary with distance.
Fortunately, Earth
provides the means to vary the distance
between the source and
the target without moving the experiment.
Neutrinos from the nadir
travel a distance
larger by the Earth diameter
compared to those from the zenith.
As the primary flux of cosmic protons
is homogeneous and isotropic and
since low energy neutrinos hardly
interact with the terrestrial matter,
any change in the ratio
of nu_mu to nu_e
with the zenith angle is
an indication of oscillation.
It is evident from the unitarity
of the operation that for
the probability of survival, where
the nu_mu which stays a nu_mu,
is equal to one minus
the probability of oscillation.
Experimentally one averages
over the unknown neutrino energy at
a known propagation distance.
The oscillation curves for different
energies, shown here by different colors,
are thus averaged over
the spectrum of neutrinos.
This gives the black curve as a function
of distance indicated on the top scale,
or as a function of the angle of
incidence indicated on the bottom.
The neutrino flux is measured and
their flavor identified
by measuring the reaction rate
of charged current interactions,
which produced either a muon or
an electron in the final state.
With a known cross section
the reaction rate is proportional
to the incident neutrino flux.
One finds experimentally that the observed
flux ratio is compatible with
the calculated oscillation probability.
Please note that the scale of length over
energy in this plot is the opposite of
the one we have shown in
the slide just before.
The observed oscillation
amplitude is quite large,
and therefore corresponds to
an angle theta_MH equal to
45 ± 13 degrees.
The difference of square masses is of
the order of 3 10^-3 eV
and thus extremely small.
Furthermore it is more likely that the
oscillation of atmospheric neutrinos happens
between the second and third generation
that is between nu_mu and mu_tau.
In general the relationship
between the states participating
in leptonic weak interactions,
nu_e, nu_mu and nu_tau,
and eigenstates of
the mass operator, nu_L, nu_M, and
nu_H is described by a unitary
matrix of 3x3 elements,
analogous to the Cabibbo-Kobayashi-Maskawa
matrix for hadronic currents.
For leptons it is called the Pontecorvo-
Maki-Nakagawa-Sakata matrix.
Like the matrix for quarks,
the one for leptons may contain
a nontrivial phase that would violate
CP symmetry if it existed.
Future neutrino experiments
will show its existence or not.
Different types of neutrino
oscillations have been observed to date, and
an inexhaustive list is the following.
The disappearance of atmospheric nu_mu,
disappearance of the nu_mu
produced by accelerators,
appearance of nu_tau and nu_e in
a nu_mu beam produced at accelerators.
Disappearance of anti-nu_e which are
abundantly reproduced in nuclear power plants.
For each of these measurements we give you
a resource of information that you can
use to find more details.
As an example we show
here the interaction of
a nu_tau appearing in a nu_mu beam
produced at CERN and observed
by the OPERA detector situated in the Gran
Sasso underground laboratory in Italy.
The neutrino interactions are observed
using photographic emulsion,
which are then developed.
The dE/dx of charged
particles thus becomes visible.
This animation shows an enlargement around
the vertex of the neutrino interaction.
The reconstruction shows in the final
state a charged tau lepton
in red which decays into π- in cyan and
a π0, which is invisible.
The kink between the parent and
other tracks is a clear
signal of a tau lepton decay.
The photons from the π0 decay
are shown in yellow and
they point to the decay vertex.
This topology is a clear signature
of a nu_tau interaction
which had appeared in the nu_mu
beam by flavor oscillation.
Neutrino oscillation are a very lively
research sector in the United States,
Europe, and Asia.
And we can expect spectacular results
by experiments which are in progress
and under construction.
In the next video we discuss the fact
that mass is not an intrinsic property
of particles, but it is dynamically
generated by the Higgs mechanism.
[MUSIC]