[MUSIC]
In the beginning of last century,
Geiger and
Marsden have measured
the Rutherford reaction.
They have counted scatters by eye.
In this little video we will convince
ourselves that this is indeed possible.
Geiger and Marsden took a source
of polonium 210, an alpha emitter
collimated to an intensity of
about 1,000 particles per second,
which scattered off a gold foil
of 100 nanometers thickness.
And they counted the number of scatters
per second by eye at angle of ten degrees at
a distance of ten centimeters and over
an area of about one square centimeter.
Let us first compute
the properties of gold.
It has a density of about 2 times 10^4
kilogram per cubic meter.
Its charge is 79 and
its mass is 197 atomic units which gives
us a number density of about 0.6 times 10^29
nuclei per cubic meter.
Alpha particles are He-4 nuclei
with charge 2 to 4 mass units and
an initial intensity of 10^3 per
second comes out of the collimator.
The cross section for Rutherford
scattering is proportional to the product of the two
charges squared inversely proportional
to the incident energy squared and
the sin^4 of half
the scattering angle.
Using the correct conversion factors,
we thus obtain a differential cross
section at an angle of 10 degrees of
2 times 10^-24 square meters steradian.
This corresponds to a fraction of the
initial intensity of about 1.3 per mil,
which is scattered into
the observed solid angle.
That is to say the count rate is about 1.3 Hz,
easily observable by the naked eye.
[MUSIC]