We'll now consider the three main criteria
that you need to think about when
you're deciding how to name and
label your research data files.
First up, is the organisation.
This is important for future access and
retrieval and should take into account any
file naming constraints that are applied
by the system where you store your data.
Second up, is the context.
This may include content specific or
descriptive information,
irrespective of where the data is stored.
And the third one is consistency.
You should choose a single file naming
convention and apply that consistently
throughout by including the same
information in the same order.
So for
example if you're going to use dates,
you could follow a model like the ISO
standard, which applies four digits for
the year, two for the month and
two for the day, such as 20150907.
Whichever method you decide to adopt,
just make sure you apply it consistently.
There are a number of common
elements that you should consider
when you're developing
your file naming strategy.
These include a version number,
the date of creation,
the name of the creator, the description
of the content, the name of the team or
department associated with the data,
a publication date, and a project number.
Finally, you want to think about scalable
your file naming policy should be.
If you want to include a project number,
don't limit yourself to two digits, or
you can only have 99 projects.
Don't use generic file names either,
that may conflict if your data were
moved from one system to another.
And if your working over
more than one computer,
make sure your files are synchronized.
File names should outlive the original
person who named the file, so
your best to adopt group guidelines rather
than everyone having their own procedure.
File and folder naming conventions
are key to maintaining
a well-organized electronic directory and
drive structure.
A file name is the chief identifier for
a research data file.
In most cases,
the policy for file naming is left down
to individuals or research groups.
There are a number of easy rules
that you should be following
when naming your files.
Firstly, you should keep file
names short and relevant.
Generally about 25 characters
is a sufficient length
to capture enough descriptive information.
You shouldn't use special characters in
a file name, as these are often use for
special tasks in different
operating systems.
You should use underscores instead
of full stops, or spaces, and
if you include dates,
you should format them consistently.
Never assume that
a software application or
instrument uses case dependency when
naming and renaming your flies.
So how do you rename hundreds of files?
Well most operating systems have
in-built tools for file management.
There are also a number of software tools
that can help you to manage your data
files and folders in a more automated and
consistent way through batch renaming.
Batch renaming software exists for
most operating systems.
There are many situations in which
batch renaming may be useful.
For example, where images from digital
cameras are automatically assigned
base file names,
consisting of lots of sequential numbers.
Where proprietary software, or
instrumentation generates crude,
default, or multiple file names.
And where files are transferred from
a system that support spaces or
non-English characters,
to one that doesn't.
Batch renaming software can be used
to substitute such characters with
acceptable ones.
There are some bulk renaming tools for
different operating systems
listed in the Mantra course.