It's also important to distinguish between
the different versions of your data
files consistently.
This ensures that there's a clear audit
trail so you can track the development of
your data files and
return to earlier versions if needed.
You should pick a method of versioning
that makes sense to you and
makes it clear to differentiate
between the different data files.
A common form for expressing data file
versions is to use ordinal numbers such as
1, 2, and 3 for major version changes and
decimals for minor changes.
For example, version 1.1.
You should avoid using confusing
labels such as revision, final,
final2, or definitive copy.
You may find that these accumulate and
it becomes difficult to understand
which version proceeds which.
You should always record changes to
your data no matter how small or
insignificant they seem at the time.
You can use an auto backup facility for
this,
if one's available, rather than saving and
archiving multiple versions.
You can also use a tracking facility on
software such as Google Docs or on Wiki's.
There are a number of version control
softwares, such as Subversion and
TortoiseSVN which are commonly used for
software code.
Remember that you can also delete or
discard obsolete versions of your data.
Just always be sure to retain
the original rule copy.
So, you've now completed this module where
we've introduced you to the concepts of
good research data organization, including
file naming conventions and versioning.
You can take a look at the further
resources, where you'll find additional
references and links that you can
follow up for more information.
You may decide to come back
to these later on, and
start another module in the meantime.
If you do so, we recommend you move
on to the data file formats module.