[MUSIC]
To motivate the Friedmann equation,
we are going to consider
the movement of mass m
at a cosmological
distance R from us.
At cosmological scales,
the Universe is isotopic and homogenous,
such that the test mass will be attracted
by a mass M, which is
4π/3 r^3 times the average mass
density rho of the Universe.
Newton's Law gives us that
m times the acceleration
of the test mass is equal
to minus Newton's constant
times the test mass times
the mass M divided by R^2.
We can reorder this equation to have
all terms on the left of the equal sign.
Let me integrate this second equation.
We get that
1/2 n times the test mass velocity
squared minus Newton's constant
times the product of the two masses
divided by R is a constant of motion.
This is equivalent to saying that the
kinetic energy plus the potential energy
is a constant of motion.
You can easily verify that this is correct
by taking the time derivative of this
result.
Now, if you set the constant of
integration equal to -1/2 k and
introduce our result for M,
then we get this equation.
If we now multiply both sides by 2/R^2,
we get that (R-dot/R)^2,
which is in fact the Hubble constant
squared, is equal to 8π Newton's
constant divided by 3,
minus k/R^2.
Now we can still add to this a
cosmological constant as Einstein did and
obtain thus the complete
Friedmann equation.
[MUSIC]