Okay, so let's take this a step further.
This is exactly the same pipeline that
we looked at in the previous lesson.
The difference is that we're
now going to begin to do
a little bit more sophisticated
work within our project stage.
In order to handle some other problems
with the data in this particular data set.
So here you can see the same pass throughs
and these split operations again.
But for released,
if we take a look at what we have for
values in this collection,
it's just a string.
We can do quite a bit more in terms
of range filters, searching for
all movies released at a particular
time of year, in a given month etcetera,
if we actually convert these to dates.
So that's what we're doing here.
Let me explain this a little bit.
If it wasn't for
the case that values could be empty,
this would be significantly simpler.
We would simply need to use
date from string operator to
parse the date out of the string.
But because we can have empty
strings as the value for
released, we need to
use the cond operator.
Cond is simply a conditional expression.
We have an if, then, and an else.
Because everything is
document based in MongoDB,
we express this using this
document based syntax.
So the cond operator has as
its value a document, and
that document has three keys within
in it: an if, a then and an else.
For if, we specify a conditional
expression, and the conditional expression
we're using here is making use
of this dollar ne operator.
$ne simply means not equal to.
$ne expects an array as its value where
we have two values to be compared.
Here we're using this field path
specifier to get the value for released.
And we're simply saying, if that value
is not equal to the empty string,
then we want to go ahead and
parse the string from it.
Otherwise, just go ahead and
let released equal the empty string.
Let's talk a little bit about the meat
of this particular reshaping,
which is really parsing
the date out of a string.
$dateFromString is an operator
that expects us to specify
the value we want to parse as
an expression that evaluates to a string.
Here we're using a field path specifier,
so
whatever the current value for
released is.
And we have to specify that
as the value for dateString,
there are some other options you
can specify to date from string.
We're not going to talk
about those right now.
But that's why this has
the structure that it does.
The result here is that,
if the expression is true,
then the value that will be assigned
to the release key, in this projection,
is the date value parsed
using the dateFromString
operator from the current string
representation of that date,
which is the current value
of the released field.
Otherwise, we simply make released
have the value of the empty string.
Again, as we build up this reshaping,
we're just looking at the first 100
documents and we are again outputting
to the movies_scratch collection.
So let's run this.
And if we go into Compass and refresh,
we see that now we have a real
timestamp as the value for released for
all documents that actually had some sort
of string representation as their value.
For others,
we'll just have the empty string.
But we can see several here that have had
their released field updated
to have a real time stamp,
which we can then filter on in
a variety of interesting ways.
So that's an example of how we can do
a little clean up with respect to dates.
Now, one other thing that I want to point
out is dateFromString is an aggregation
operator that is only available
in MongoDB 3.6 and later.
So, if you're using an earlier version
of MongoDB in your atlas cluster, or
in say a local installation that you have
created, you'll need to upgrade to MongoDB
3.6 in order to take advantage
of this particular operator.