All right, so now let's talk
about how this script works.
Let's begin at the top of the for loop.
Here we're using find as
we did previously, but
the filter that we're passing here is
an empty dictionary, or an empty document.
The semantics of this for MongoDB
are that we expect this to retrieve as
results from this query every
document in the collection.
Now here what we're doing is limiting
it to the first 100 documents retrieved
using the limit method.
Limit is a cursor method.
So find, as we know, returns a cursor,
which allows us to iterate over
the documents that are retrieved.
Limit is a cursor method which will
restrict the number of results that we see
to, in this case, to the first 100.
I could pass 1,000 here.
I could pass 365.
It just depends on what you need.
Limit also returns a cursor.
Now doing so as part of a for loop means
that Python will iterate on that cursor,
and each time through movie will be
the next document in the collection.
Suppose that we hadn't set a limit here,
or that it was quite large, thousands and
thousands of documents.
PyMongo and MongoDB work together
to do the right thing here which is
to return the documents
in batches of many dozen.
So with each batch, we have that many
documents on the client's side and
are processing them.
And as we get close to exhausting a batch,
PyMongo
will go fetch more documents from
the server in another batch.
And so rather than pull documents
across from the server one at a time,
we're pulling them across in batches.
And that's how we end up looping through
each of the documents in the collection.
Now the next thing to look at
are these fields_to_set and
fields_to_unset dictionaries.
In the body of this loop, this is where
we are building those dictionaries
that we see as the values for set and
unset in the update document.
So the first thing that I do here is
loop through all of the fields, pulling
out the individual keys and values for
each document as we pass through the loop.
If the value is some
version of an empty string,
then I remove it from
the movie dictionary.
Note that I'm using copy here so
that I can do that without getting
the dictionary change size error.
I remove it from the movie dictionary, and
I create an entry in the fields_to_unset
dictionary for that key.
That's how I end up with, for
example, this metacritic entry in
the unset dictionary for this document,
because there simply wasn't
a metacritic value for this particular
document that I'm going to update.
It was just the empty string.
So I can save space and
make my data a little bit more readable
by getting rid of all that empty data.
And then we dive into a block
of code where I'm splitting
string values into arrays.
Note that for each one of these,
I'm checking to see whether it actually
exists in the movie dictionary,
because if it was the empty string,
I would have deleted it here.
And note that for director,
writer, genre, and so
on, I'm specifying that that field
should actually be eliminated
as part of the update operation,
if it wasn't already eliminated here.
And I'm saying let's add a field
called directors in this case that is
the array that I get by splitting
that string value of directors.
Likewise, for writers,
genre, language, country.
Note that for cast,
I do the split, but I don't unset
the cast field because I'm
using exactly the same name for
the array version of that field,
rather than some plural form of cast.
Here I'm simply changing the name of
fullPlot so that it is camelcase,
and doing that same change here
to use rated versus rating.
This is the chunk of code that
creates the embedded document.
And here I'm converting string
representations of dates to date
times using the datetime class.
Finally, this is one of the more
interesting bits of this
particular script.
It's something we actually can't yet
do in the aggregation framework.
Here, I am changing
the data type of runtime.
More specifically,
I'm really doing two things.
I'm first running a match on runtime,
because if you take a look at
any runtime you'll see that it's this
ridiculous string of 1 space min,
6 space min, 190 space min.
It's not an integer, so
we can't do range queries.
We can't do any of the types of analysis
we'd really like to be able to do because
it's a string, and a string that's
in an inconvenient form at that.
So here at the top I've compiled this
regular expression that will do a match
and will group the different
components of the match in such a way
that I can pull out the integer
component for that value.
And then I simply convert
it to an int here, and
make sure that runtime gets
added to the fields to set.
So that here when I
construct the update doc,
that's one of the changes
that will be made
as we call update_one in order to make
the necessary updates to this document.
Now something I want to point out here is
that note that we're not doing anything
with title, nothing with year,
nothing with plot,
nothing with any of these fields
where we've just got a 1 here.
We're essentially we're just
passing the value through.
As long as there is a value other than the
empty string, we're doing nothing with it.
That's because to update,
we only need to identify the fields
that we want to change in some way,
whether it's setting them to a new value
or eliminating them from the document.
Now in this example, we're using just two
of the update operators, $set, and $unset.
There are a number of
other update operators.
See the lecture notes for this lesson for
a link to the relevant
MongoDB documentation.
I can increment values.
I can take the min and max,
multiplication, a number of operations
with arrays and a whole host of other
types of updates that reflect the variety
of different things we have to do when
we're transforming our data from messy and
somewhat ill formatted to data
that we can actually use.
So take a look at the docs to see what
else is possible in update operations.
Lastly, I build my update_doc
from the fields_to_set and
the fields_to_unset, those two
dictionaries I've been building all along.
Note that each one of
these creates a new entry
in either the fields_to_set dictionary or
the fields_to_unset dictionary.
That's how I end up with
output that looks like this.
Then if I were to run this,
eliminating the limit, and
uncommenting my call to update_one,
I would,
one at a time,
update each document in the collection.
Update_one is great when I'm
updating a few individual documents.
But when I'm trying to
reshape an entire collection,
this is not a terribly efficient strategy.
I'm going to change this script so
that I'm actually doing bulk writes,
rather than writing one document
at a time back to the server.
I'll show you how to do
that in the next lesson.