In this lesson,
we're going to talk about the different
data types that MongoDB supports.
And we're really going to get into some of
the different data types that MongoDB has.
But not only that, we're also going to
talk about how we can query for
documents by the data
type that a field is.
So by now, you already understand that
MongoDB stores data in documents and
you're already somewhat familiar with the
different data types supported by MongoDB.
For example, here I go ahead and query for
a random movie and print it out.
And as you can see,
we know that title is a string.
We know that runtime is a number.
We've also looked at more complex data
types in Mongo DB, like how cast is
an array, or like how imdb is
actually an embedded document.
But let's look at all of the different
data types that Mongo DB supports.
And here is a list of all the different
data types supported by Mongo DB on our
documentation page.
And we don't have time to talk about
all these different data types, but
in this lesson we're going to talk
about three of the most interesting.
So we're going to talk about ObjectId,
Date, and
finally we're going to
talk about Decimal128.
So coming back to our notebook,
here is the random document that we found.
We can go ahead and
look at the specific _id field.
And you'll notice that
it has this ObjectId
wrapper around this random
string of letters and numbers.
And so, this ObjectId is
actually a MongoDB data type.
And it's special because what it allows us
to do is it allows MongoDB to identify,
uniquely, every document in the database.
And it's able to accomplish this because
this random string of characters
is actually composed of
the current time in unix,
the ID of the machine that is
running this, the process ID,
and as well as a counter that
starts with a random value.
And through all of these different pieces,
MongoDB is able to,
with somewhat good certainty,
ensure that this ObjectId is unique.
And is able to therefore uniquely
identify every document in the database.
And so that's ObjectId.
Now let's talk about the Date data type.
So I can go ahead and import datetime.
And then I can go ahead and
look at this example test collection
that I've created called dates.
So here's this dates database, and now
I'm just going to go ahead and insert one
document where I say dt, which is date
time, is the current time right now.
And so when I run this,
you can see that it was successful and
now I should be able
to find it right away.
And so, this is really cool.
It's really awesome that MongoDB allows
us to natively insert dates into
MongoDB because this allows us to query
for dates in a lot more interesting ways.
We can now query for dates using
logical operators like less than and
greater than and a lot of other
interesting things, like it allows us to
use advanced aggregation operators that
allow us to pull out different components
of this date, like I can figure out
the day of the year that this date is.
Or I can figure out
the year that this date is.
And all this wouldn't be really possible
if we were just storing this date
as a simple string.
And finally,
I also want to talk about this really
interesting data type called Decimal128.
And so we already know that MongoDB allows
us to store floating point numbers.
But more than that, MongoDB also
lets us store decimal numbers.
And this is really important whenever
you're storing numbers that represent
something that has to be strictly
precise and strictly represented.
And a great example of this is money.
So we don't want any rounding errors
when you're doing math with money.
And so when we are using money and
storing it in MongoDB,
we really want to use the Decimal128
data type so there's no rounding errors.
And so MongoDB natively supports this.
And so we can go ahead and import this
special data type from the bson library.
And then insert a document,
pretty simple, the API is very simple.
You just wrap your number as a string and
then wrap that in the Decimal128 function.
And then, as you can see,
we've successfully inserted it.
And now I can easily find it.
And you can see that this is stored kind
of exactly as the way we would expect.
MongoDB is powerful, not only because
it lets us store data with this rich
variety of different data types, but also,
it's really cool because we can actually
query for documents based on their type.
So in this case, you can see here,
I'm writing a query where I want to find
movies where the year is of type integer.
And so when I run this,
exactly as we would expect,
here I'm able to find a movie
where the year is an integer.
And this is useful for
two common-use cases.
Firstly, this can be useful
when we want to clean our data.
We can use the $type operator to find that
every field is the exact type
that we expect it to be.
But second, this can be very
useful if we have a schema
where a field has multiple
data types across documents.
For example,
maybe we the director field as a string
if a movie only has one director.
But we store it as an array
if it has multiple directors.
In that case, we could use the $type
operator to find movies of that specific
type, whether it be string versus array,
and go from there.
So let's go ahead and
recap what we discussed in this lesson.
We saw a list of all the different data
types in MongoDB and, specifically,
we talked about three special ones.
We talked about ObjectId,
we talked about Date, and
finally we talked about Decimal128.
And then we saw that we can actually
query MongoDB based on data type,
which is useful for cleansing data.
And it can also be useful when we have
documents with different types for
a field across multiple documents.