From this course title, you might
get an impression that you will be
building a bunch of codes and
you'll actually be building an app.
Well, that is almost true.
In reality, we are going to provide
you with an app, a backbone app.
And you'll be tasked along the way to
see how it works, to understand how it
operates, and to manipulate the data
that it generates and reacts with.
You'll also be tasked along the way to do
some things slightly of MFlix to either
improve it or to just change a little
bit of the application behavior.
But more of that's ahead of us.
For now, we are just going to be looking
to how this application actually works and
which dependencies we have.
The application that we're
going to build is called MFlix.
Now any resemblance with the popular media
streaming service is pure coincidence.
This application concretes our MFlix
will have a few considerations in
functionality.
First, we will have some sort of user
management where we can create users and
log in users, and so on.
We will have a video catalog, where we
can scroll and see some interesting
information about popular videos
that are available on the platform.
With a list of details of the movies
based on several different rankings,
or some other sets of different
filters that we can create, and
obviously, the actual
detail of the movies.
So once you log in and have your account
created, if you look for videos,
the application will allow you to look for
them, and find them.
And obviously,
we can also look into the details, and
have some sort of user interaction
with this particular application.
Okay, so this is how the application
is supposed to work.
We're also going to see internally in
terms of code, how it is actually being
composed, and which are the components
that make for the application.
The application itself, it's built so
that it can run on your local laptop,
and using Atlas to store all the data.
For that, the version that you will be
downloading from the lecture notes and
from the handout material will have
some slight code gaps somewhere that
we will ask you to download and
improve, or complete the functionality.
But more of that's a little
bit further down the road.
For now, what I will ask you
guys to do is pretty much just
have a folder path that you
will be using for this course.
In my case, I'm going to be
using users/mongodb/coursera.
And in it, I'm going to have a folder.
And I'm going to call it first_app or
building app.
Whatever you choose, it's okay.
Once I am inside my first_app, my working
data set for my MFlix application,
and after downloading to my local
laptop the handout material,
I will unzip inside this folder,
my working folder, that same code.
This is running code that you should
be able to run in your local machine.
I also recommend you to, on this working
folder, create a notebooks folder.
Now this is where I'm going to be
storing the handouts that we're going to
be providing to make sure you can
follow through with the lectures that
we are going to be
teaching in this course.
So this is where I'm going to
put all my Jupyter Notebooks.
Not needed for now, but
will be needed later.
Once I have the folder for notebooks and
unzipped my MFlix application,
this should be the directory structure
that I have in my working folder.
As in any application, the README
file is always convenient to have,
and this is no exception.
This here will tell you the dependencies
that you need to install for
running our application, and
some other instructions like
the run.sh file that will allow
you to run the application.
It will be our executor.
Now make sure that you have all
the dependencies installed.
As you figured out by now,
we are going to be using Python, the best,
most beautiful language in the world.
Flask, which is a very popular
web framework for Python.
PyMongo, obviously, we need to talk to
MongoDB and PyMongo is the way to do so.
And some other libraries like Faker and
flask-login and
bcrypt, all nice libraries to work and
to use for our needs.
Now before we go and
run our init run file,
you can see it here that it will launch
an application, a Flask application.
There's a couple of things that
we need to edit before hand.
The first file that we need to
be editing would be our db.py,
this file here that will control
all access to the database.
Now the first thing that we need
to edit on this file will be
the MongoClient connection string.
As you can see here,
I already done my due diligence and
added up my own personal
MFlix cluster on Atlas.
You should do the same thing, and
put your connection string here.
Once you've added it to your db.py file,
you are ready to run your run.sh or
run.exe.
Once we have it up and running, you will
see that we're going to have a up and
running server on 127.0.0.1 and
port 5000, right?
And as you can see,
this will be the exact same location that
I'm going to be connecting to
show you MFlix up and running.
Sweet, but let's understand
what's going on under the hood.
Now, the MFlix app itself,
it's composed by a couple of
different interesting modules.
The first one is our mflix.py.
This is where we are going to actually
instantiate all the Flask application
library and consequent libraries
that we need to run the application.
Then we have another Python
module called db.py.
Now db.py is responsible for
the connections between
the application and the database.
Think about it as our model layer,
if you're coming from
an MVC kind of standpoint.
Therefore the db.py talks to MongoDB.
In our case, in Atlas, this is where we're
going to store all of our information.
And mflix.py instantiates and
uses the db.py methods to
forward all the requests.
There are other things like the templates
that we'll be using to prettify and
show you their correct HTML.
Well formatted with all
the information that we need,
that you can have access and
scroll around within the templates folder.
There's also obviously static information
like the CSS that we are using or even
the source data file, movies.json, that
you previously imported in other lectures.
Another important one, or not really
that important, but just a important
functionality of our application is
that we allow you to log in and log out.
And that's controlled by the auth.py file.
Give it a look to understand how we
are dealing with the authentication.
So to sum it up, our MFlix application
is a runnable application.
You need to configure the connection
string to Atlas, and put it up and
running with run.sh that will
instantiate the Flask application called
db.py to request and submit any
information to MongoDB on Atlas.
Once you have that, the only thing that
you need to do, go to your local browser
and browse away the magnificent interface
that we built just for this course.