In this lesson, I want to talk
about how mflix queries MongoDB
to generate its homepage.
By examining how the mflix page is
generated, we'll actually get to
learn about the following cursor methods,
sort, skip, and limits.
So let's take a closer look at this page.
I want to point out a few
interesting characteristics.
First, you'll notice that there
are 46,000 movies in mflix,
but this homepage is only
displaying the first 20.
Moreover, you'll notice that
the 20 that we're displaying
are all very well known
films here in the US.
And the last thing I want to point out,
is if we go ahead and scroll down and
click Next Page, you'll see that the next
page displays the next 20 movies,
movies 21 through 40.
So let's go ahead and look at the code of
mflix to see a little bit how this works.
So let's go ahead and
take a look at mflix.py,
this is where our function
exist to generate the homepage.
And this is the function,
and we know this is the right function
because of app.route being /.
So whenever you go to the route,
part of the website,
the homepage,
this is the method that will get called.
In the first 25 lines or so
here are just about making sure that
we understand what page we're on.
Seeing if a certain genre was selected or
seeing if a query was
made about a text search.
But we're going to ignore all of that for
the most part.
Really all we care about here
is this call to get movies.
And this is where we actually
make the call to the database.
So as you can see here,
we pass in three parameters,
pass in our filters as we set them up.
We pass in the page that
we're currently on, and
we pass how many movies
we want on each page.
And that's going to return
to us a list of movies,
as well as the total number of
all the movies in the collection.
So let's go ahead and look at get movies.
This is in db.py, and
here you can see the get movies function.
Now let's go ahead and copy this and
put it in our Jupyter Notebook so
you can actually play around
with the function a little bit.
So the first things I'm going to do here
is define the parameters that we go ahead
and pass in to get movies.
So this is a very simple example,
we're not making a text search or
searching by genre.
So our filter's just going to
be an empty dictionary.
And, we want this query to be for
the homepage.
So we're going to say page is = to 0.
And just like on the homepage,
we're going to render 20 movies per page.
Now I've gone ahead and simplified the get
movies function a little bit, by removing
the function and kind of splitting
up the code across multiple cells,
so that we can more easily
see what's happening.
And in this first cell, this is
where we ensure that the homepage is
filled with movies familiar to our users.
So by default, when we query MongoDB,
the documents are returned
without any particular order.
But to make sure that these
movies are relevant to our users,
here we're going to sort them by
the number of reviews they have.
Now obviously, there are many different
ways that we could implement this but
this naive approach works pretty well for
this example application.
And as you can see,
our sort key uses dot notation.
And that's because we're
sorting on a value that is
nested through a series
of nested documents.
And this is the exact same dot notation
that we use when we're filtering for
embedded documents.
In this case,
we're now using it for sorting.
So very simply,
we just pass in our filters to find, and
then we append the sort method,
passing our sort key.
And then, of course, similar to
how we do sorting in aggregation,
we also have to pass a direction.
So we want to sort things so
that the most reviews are at the front, so
we're going to sort this descending.
And then second thing we want to do is
go ahead and get the total movie count.
So this query is going to currently
return all of the movies, and so
when we run count you can see that,
indeed, it does return all of them.
And so the first thing this
query does is go ahead and
counts how many documents
are on this cursor.
And we go ahead and store that in this
variable called total num movies.
And this is one of the return
values of the get movies function.
Now, would it be very cool to send
all 46,000 movies to our user?
They certainly don't have time to look at
all of them, but moreover, it would take
a long time to send them over the network
and to render them on the page.
And that's why we limit the number
of movies that we're sending.
Or specifically we're limiting
our results to 20 per page.
When users aren't on the homepage,
we're going to need to go ahead and
skip over the entries that precede
the pages that they're currently on,
and that's what skip will let us achieve.
In this case, since page is 0, moves page
are still 20, this is going to evaluate to
0, so we're not going to be
skipping any for the homepage.
And then when we go ahead and
turn this cursor into a list, and
look at its length,
you see that we're getting 20 movies.
And if we look at the first movie,
if we look at tomatoes and look at viewer,
and look at the number of reviews, you can
see that there are quite a few reviews.
And that's why Titanic is the first
movie that we see on mflix.
Now we can go ahead and simulate going to
the next page by setting page equal to 1.
And then running the same query
again where have no filters.
We're sorting on the number of reviews,
and then this time we're skipping,
hopefully, 20 movies.
And as you can see, we are now
returning 20 less movies than what
would have been returned if we
returned all of the movies.
Let's recap what we
discussed in this lesson.
We looked at these three
common cursor methods.
But moreover, we saw how, together,
they can be used to generate our movie
homepage, as well as through the use
of skip and limits support pagination.