A movie streaming service that does
not let their users make comments on
the movies they like.
It's probably not a very good one, and
there's a lot of improvement room for
their user experience.
Mflix is nothing like that, and it does
allow you to provide feedback for future
analysis and for us to do something more
interesting with the service later on.
Obviously, Mflix will be storing
that information in MongoDB.
And for that, we have a particular method
I would like to be talk to you guys
today about,
which is this insert_one method here.
It allows us to insert a documents
into MongoDB collection,
in particular to our comments collection.
Now this is probably the simplest
command that you can find in MongoDB but
I still like to tell you all about it.
So let's see this in action.
And for that I'm going to use again,
our Jupyter notebooks.
There's one called insert-one for
this lesson.
And let's do the typical imports of
importing everything that we need to use
this particular notebook.
We start by pymongo, pprint, and
we're also going to import bson.objectid.
And the built-in date time support of
Python, which is datetime datetime.
Now as usual we need to provide
our MongoDB Atlas URI so
we can connect to our instance.
And it would be a nice idea for
me to just print it out to see if we
actually get a correct connection
in place, so let's do just that.
Once we run this you can
see that the connection to
the database is well executed,
so we can move along.
Now for
inserting a single document we are just
going to insert in this
particular example, a dictionary.
I'm going to create here, dictionary,
then I'm going to call
comment with some data on it.
The data that we are storing
in MongoDB is name,
email, movie ID, text, and date,
all of them of different data types.
Name and
email are the typical string data types.
Movie_id will be a bson id, which I'm
going to generate one right here,
it's going to be fake a comment,
so it's all good.
Text, again, string, and then date,
while we will be using datetime.utcnow.
Another object I'm going to create here
is this bypass validation flag that I'm
going to put to false.
Now the last thing that I need
to do is call my mflix comments,
insert_one method passing along
my fake comments and this flag.
Now why is this flag here and
what is it's purpose?
MongoDB allows us to define
on a collection basis
a validation of our documents.
Obviously if we don't have one or
if we just simply want to bypass it,
MongoDB currently supports
that in a very easy manner.
We just need to pass the flag saying
if we want to bypass evaluation or not.
For this particular example I am going
to do that just to show that we can.
So if I do that, I get back an insert_one
result that I'm storing in this
variable here insert_results.
Insert_result has two different fields
as one field called acknowledged which
will tell me if the command that I just
emitted was acknowledged by the server.
In this case, it's true, so we got there,
we got to the server, fantastic.
And now it also can tell me,
if it's been acknowledged,
what's the insert_id of our document,
because we are not providing an _id field.
And as you know,
if we do not provide such _id field,
MongoDB will create one for
us, and there it is.
But obviously we can, in fact,
provide an _id, if we wish to do so.
For example,
here we are going to set our _id field to
a string with the value some_id_field.
If we do so, we can see that it is true,
it has been acknowledged, and
the inserted ID is the name or
the string that we provided inside of
the document, all checks correctly.
And lastly, we need to also realize that
a primary key cannot allow any duplicates.
So if we try to insert
the same document again or
even just this different document with the
same _id field, an error will be raised.
MongoDB makes sure that
if you tried to store
two different documents with
the same field value for _id,
a DuplicateKeyError will be
raised as you can find it here.
And this is all on insert_one method.