In this video I wanted to talk
about how when we make a comment
in mflix like when I say what
a great movie the Titanic was.
When I submit this comment and
the page reloads, I can go down and
you'll notice that I'm also able to delete
the comment that I created for myself.
In this lesson we're going to use
this feature of MFlix to explain
how you can delete data in MongoDB.
Specifically we're going to look at
how to delete data in MongoDB using
the delete_one and delete_many commands.
So here we are in the comments list,
the HTML template file here in Sublime.
And, you'll notice right here,
I'll select these lines of text,
that this is what allows us to
delete comments that are our own.
So we check for
each comment that we're rendering here,
we check if the current user's email
is equal to the comments email.
And if so
then we produce this additional HTML,
where we create a form that deletes this
movie content, this is the action URL.
And there is of course
a little Delete button.
So let's go ahead and go into MFlix
to look at delete movie comment.
And as you can see this code
is pretty straight forward.
Pretty much most of the heavy lifting is
done by delete comment from movie, so
let's go ahead and now look in
that comment in the db.py file.
And as you can see,
there's a lot going on here.
And that's mostly to deal with
the fact that we're caching
the last ten comments
on our movies document.
So I really want us to just focus
on just this first line of code,
on this use of delete one.
And we're going to go ahead and
look at our Python notebook to
look at how this method works.
And the code that we were just looking at,
the comment was deleted
by the comments ID.
But we can actually use any kind of filter
that find supports to delete comments.
So in this case here I made a filter
here that says what a great movie,
which is the comment that
I just made on Titanic.
I'm going to store this
inside the filter variable.
And now I can go ahead and run this query,
and find this exact comment.
And there you go, you can see
that here is the comment I made,
What a great movie,
on this is the movie ID for Titanic.
But we already know how to find documents.
But I want to show that
using the exact same filter,
we can actually also delete comments.
And so, here's our delete result.
And so now when when we run this
command we would expect it to no longer
return this document because it was just
deleted, and that's exactly what we see.
Moreover, if we go back to MFlix and
refresh this page, we would expect this
comment to go away, but it doesn't.
Why doesn't this comment go away?
And that's because,
this specific comment is actually
stored on this movie's document.
We cache the comments on
the movie's document so
that we don't have to make an additional
call to the comments collection,
when they're just viewing this page.
However, we can scroll to the bottom here,
and actually look at all 405 comments and
actually just make a single call
to the comments collection.
And in here, my comment doesn't exist.
And that's because we
actually deleted my comment
if you look back at the Python notebook
off of the comments collection.
And that's how the delete one works.
But now what if we want to delete
more than one document at a time.
Well that's exactly what
the delete many method is for.
Here, I create a variable that
has the Titanic's object ID and
then I go ahead and
put that into a filter.
And so this should delete all comments
in the comments collection for Titanic.
So there should no longer be any Titanic's
comments after I execute this cell.
So now, when I refresh this page here,
we're looking at all comments,
we would expect them to all go away.
And they're all gone,
I can no longer scroll on this page.
There's no more comments.
But you'll notice that it still
says we have 405 comments, and
that's because this number is actually
stored on the movie's document.
So, let's go ahead and go back to
this view of our ten cache comments.
And let's go ahead and
remove these 10 cached comments, and
let's also go ahead and update that number
so that we don't see all 405 anymore.
So here, I can go ahead and do that.
Here I go ahead and
create a movies variable,
which acts as the movie's database.
And here I'm using the $set operator
to turn comments into an empty array,
and reset our number of MFlix comments
to 0 with the update one command.
And now when I run this,
it looks like it worked.
But let's verify by going to MFlix.
All of our comments are still here, but
when we refresh the page you can now see
that there are no more comments,
which is exactly what we would expect.
So let's recap what we
learned in this lesson.
We learned that there are two methods for
deleting documents in MongoDB.
They both act very similar to find one and
find, but
they're called delete_one and delete_many.
They accept a filter expression
just like find would,
but instead of returning documents,
they actually end up deleting them.