[MUSIC]
Calculus is rich enough that there's a ton
of
different ways to think about the concepts
in calculus.
Think about the derivative.
One way to think about the derivative is
as the
ratio of output change to some small,
infinitesimal input change.
But another way to think about the
derivative, is in terms of linear
approximation.
And that's the idea that we want to
exploit right now.
This is really the story of, of all of
calculus.
You know, you want to understand curved
objects.
I want to understand some graph of a
function that's very curved.
And that's hard to do.
But, if I zoom in close enough on the
functions graph right, if the
function's differentiable, then when I
zoom in,
that graph looks like a straight line.
That's the idea of linear approximation.
We can study these complicated curved
graphs by zooming
in and imagining that, at least
approximately, they're straight lines.
And there's a couple of huge benefits to
doing this.
One thing that we can use this for, is to
approximate values of the function.
And the other thing that we're going to be
able to use this for, is Newton's method.
We'll be able to do things like, at
least approximately, find roots of very
complicated looking polynomials.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]