We've already have been thinking about
functions and about limits.
And now I want to think deeper into those
two ideas.
In terms of functions, I want to think,
what does
it even mean for a function to be
continues.
How does that relate to limits.
And what are some consequences of a
function's being continuous?
And in terms of limits, what would I think
about different kinds of limits now?
I want to think about one side of limits.
I want to know what can I say about a
function's output if
I'm looking at input points that are just
a little bit below some point.
Or if I'm just looking at input points
that are a little bit above some point.
It'd be a one sided limit.
I want to know what happens when I
evaluate a function at very large input
points.
That'd be a limit as x approaches
infinity.
I want to be able to say, maybe, that my
function's output value is as large
as I'd like as long as my input point is
close enough to some chosen point.
That'll be saying that the limit equals
infinity.
So, these are some of the ideas I want to
look at.
I want to look at limits that are
approaching from one side.
I want to look at limits involving
infinity in various ways.
I think there's a lot of really
interesting questions
to ask along these lines, so let's get
started.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]