[MUSIC] Here is the question that I want
to address right now.
What's the derivative of some constant
multiple of some function? Now, in this
case the constant multiple is 2 but of
course that 2 could be replaced by any
sixth number.
If you don't like the D D X notation,
another way to ask this question is this.
If you've got some new function G and
it's the constant multiple times F, again
in this case I'm using 2 as the constant,
the question is, what's the derivative of
G in terms of the derivative of F?
To gain some intuition, let's pick a
specific example, and look at a graph.
So here's the graph, of, just some random
function.
Let's suppose that I stretch this graph,
in the y direction.
So now I stretch the y axis, and that
corresponds to multiplying the function
by a constant value.
In this case, to,
how do the tangent lines change when I do
this stretching? So if I double the Y
axis, the function changes by twice as
much for the same input change.
So if I double the Y axis, the slope of
the tangent line also doubles and that
makes sense numerically.
Here's what I know.
I know that g of x is twice f of x.
G is this constant multiple of f.
I also know something about the
derivative of f.
The derivative encodes how input changes
become output changes, or, a bit more
precisely, the derivative in the limit is
the ratio of output change to input
change.
So if I multiply the ratio of output
change to input change by an actual input
change, this at least approximately is
telling me how much the output should
change when I move from x to x plus h.
Right, f's new output at the input x plus
h.
Is it's old output plus how much I expect
the output to change.
This is a really nice way to summarize
what the derivative's saying.
I know another thing.
I know that g of x plus h is twice f of x
plus h just because g is twice f for any
input value x, so in particular that's
true when the input is x plus h.
These two statements are connected.
Alright, G of X plus H is twice F of X
plus H and F of X plus H is approximately
this.
So I can combine those two statements
together in this statement.
G of X plus H is about twice f(x)+h is
approximate value, right.
2f(x)+2h*f-prime(x), which I've written
as h*2f-prime(x).
I made this a little bit nicer.
Since 2f(x) is g(x),
I can replace this 2*f(x), with g(x).
And this is really looking good.
This is telling me that g's output at x+h
is about, g's output at x, plus how much
I change the input by, times some
quantity.
Now, considering that the actual
derivative of g would tell me some
information like this.
That g's output is about, g's old output
plus how much I change the input by times
the derivative.
You're beginning to see what's going on
here, right? Look, I've got the
derivative of g here.
And I've got twice the derivative of f
here.
And if you sort of believe that these
statements are connected in this way, you
might then believe that the derivative of
g is twice the derivative of f.
The derivative of g here is twice the
derivative of f.
We can formalize this as a rule.
Here's the constant multiple rule.
So let k be constant and suppose that f
is just some function which is
differentiable at the point a.
G is that constant multiple of f, so g of
x is k*f(x).
Given this setup, what the constant
multiple rule is concluding, is that the
derivatives are related in the same way.
The derivative at the point A is K times
the derivative of F at the point A.
Now if you don't like this prime notation
you could also write it using the D D X
notation.
So here's how I write the constant
multiple law using the D D X notation.
The derivative of k times a function is k
times the derivative of that function.
I encourage you to keep practicing.
With time, you'll be able to calculate
the derivative of just a ton of different
functions.
[MUSIC]