[MUSIC]
We calculate the attenuation
of a photon beam
of energy 1 MeV by a one
centimeter thick lead plate.
The attenuation of the beam intensity I
is exponential with three
factors in the exponent:
the cross section sigma
between photons and lead nuclei,
the density rho of target nuclei and
the thickness ∆x of the target.
Let us first consider lead properties.
It's mass density is about 10,000
kilograms per cubic meter.
The molecular weight is
0.20 kilogram per mole and
the number of nuclei per mole
is given by Avogadro's number.
The second major ingredient is the cross section
between 1 MeV photons and lead nuclei.
We get it from the data collected
by the Particle Data Group.
And 1 MeV we find a huge cross
section of about 10 barns.
With this we can calculate
the attenuation of the beam.
First, the number density of lead nuclei
is approximately 3 times 10^28
per cubic meter.
The exponent of the attenuation
law is thus of the order of 0.33.
That is to say that the beam is
attenuated by only about 28%.
There is no less than 72% of the beam
which passes this one
centimeter thick lead plate,
despite the enormous cross section.
[MUSIC].