Continuous system, basically jello,
blobs of jello, right?
This is kind of what
we're starting out with.
So we have a dynamical system, that's this
and our every self-respecting dynamics
class has to have these
amorphous flying potatoes right.
It's just a general thing and we want to
now compute certain properties of it.
Newton's Law is simply F = MA,
written in this form.
You can see.
And now, because I have a continuum, it's
kind of hard to do it for the full thing,
a blob of Jello, right?
Different things will have
different forces acting on it.
So what we want to do is track
infinitesimal little elements here, and
that's my little box that's
DM infinitesimal object.
Just like classic calculus that you've
seen many many times before hopefully.
So df is the force that's acting
on the differential element, dm.
R is my inertial position vector, so
big R is the inertial position vector.
Little r is my position vector relative
to the system's center of mass.
So whatever this bulb is you have
an infinity of little DM's that all add up
to this thing.
They have in common at this instant
that's where the center of mass is so
that's a classic location.
We'll be writing all our equations
about that point so that's it.
That's basically F = MA times that.
So but for F = MA it was important
that we have an inertia derivative so
these dots are derivatives as
seen by the inertial frame,
and you have to write your position
relative to the inertial origin.
That's why you wouldn't do little r double
dot, you have to do big R double dot,
relative to the inertial frame then dF.
Now these forces,
we can categorize them generally.
There's external stuff and internal stuff.
Who can give me an example of an external
force that might be acting on
a spacecraft?
>> Drag.
>> Drag, right, atmospheric
drag is one of them definitely.
Gravity could be an external
force acting on it.
You could have solar radiation pressure.
You may have your thrusters.
This is a man made object,
maybe you have some way to control it.
Now you have to do some stuff.
That's all the external things, so
what are examples of internal forces
acting on this blob of jello?
>> Torquers?
>> Actually, good question.
So magnet torquers are actually objects
that push off the external magnetic field.
I would see them as external [INAUDIBLE]
influences acting on these elements.
The element might be inside the craft, but
it's still pushing off an external field.
So what would be an internal
force then that you might have?
>> Reactions.
>> Reactions is a good example.
because you have these
fly disks that we put in,
sometimes called flywheels or
reaction wheels or
control movement gyros that are all
spinning objects inside our spacecraft,
and then they have motors attached that
will spin them up or spin them down.
That motor is taking the wheel and
it's pushing off the space craft.
So as a dynamical system it basically
means some part of jello is pushing
off the other part of the jello and
that's what cause the spinning.
This would be an internal force for
the system all right?
If you do a free body diagram of just the
reaction wheel then maybe we can treat it
as an external one on that system.
But here we have space craft jello
could be fuel and all this stuff.
Fuel's another one.
Fuel slash backing back and forth.
Those are all internal forces.
And that will be key because we'll
be talking about internal forces,
external forces, and
how do things impact momentum and energy.
And there are some good high level things
that are really useful as a spacecraft
analysts.
So we're going to break
it off in two ways.
Now if I need a total
force acting on jello,
I have it gazillion dm's,
I have to integrate over them.
So if you look at chapter 2 we do
a summation because we have a gazillion
of them.
And if you have a continuum you
simply replace the summation
with an integral sign.
That's really, if you go back and look
at calculus and how you did integrals,
you kind of broke it up into
little bitty chunks and
then made those chunks
infinitesimally small.
It's basically this big summation.
So if you're summing up over this,
the claim here is the total force
acting on this blob is the sum of all
the forces acting on the individual DMs.
Which is simply going to be
the sum of the external forces.
What happens to the internal forces?
>> It blots it, it cancels out.
>> Yeah, which law is that?
>> Newton's third law.
>> Yeah, it's one of Newton's laws, right?
So if you take a wall, and push against
the wall, the wall is actually going to
push back with you exactly the same
amount but in opposite directions.
So as I'm torquing on a spacecraft,
applying forces to the wheel,
you're getting equal and
opposite forces applied to the spacecraft.
When you sum them up all those
things have to mutually cancel.
So internal forces never contribute
to a net force on the system,
only the external ones do that.
So I'm sure you've seen that before.
Now some basic properties of jello is
any continuum, any dynamical system is
whatever the mass distribution is,
it will have a center of mass location.
And there's many ways to define it.
I'm going to show you
it's at least two here.
One of them is the center of mass is
essentially your mass averaged location.
So Rc is the center of mass of this blob.
If you look at R times dm.
You really, you think of it you got
one kilogram, half a meter out.
Two kilograms, a full meter out.
And five kilograms,
a half a meter to the left, right?
You would add them up with
a distances divide by a total mass.
That's going to be
the center of mass location,
if you have this mass
distribution on a system.
If it's continuum, instead of
summing you do integrals of mass,
you know,
the mass of the object times its location.
And then we divide by
the total mass to get Rc.
So that's a classic
definition of center of mass,
this works for
any continuum dynamical system.
Now we can break this up because these
are vectors, the inertial position vector.
So we can say R here has
to be RC pass the r.
Again, this is done in
a purely vectorial way.
I'm not saying r has to be expressed in
the body frame or in the inertial frame.
That's a book keeping
element we keep to later.
Right now we're just adding vectors.
Vectors plus vectors and doing with that.
So if you do this you can see
this will actually break up and
let's do that one quickly here.
We had that.
Rc + r.
Dm that's the sum of two vectors.
So I'm going to do this, and say okay.
That's going to be Rc dm + rdm.
And my little subscript b that notation
is actually a triple integral.
I have to integrate over the entire body.
But instead of writing triple integrals
with all the limits, this is a short kind.
I just do one integral with b that mean
it understood to be integrating over
an entire, whenever this body is,
all right?
So we can break these things up.
That's nice.
That should be a vector.
Then there's some simplifications
that are going to happen.
We knew earlier, by definition,
this was M times Rc right?
This term can somebody say how
this is going to be refined?
All right?
Kevin.
>> You'll get RC out of the interval
>> Okay.
>> We get big M times R.
>> Yeah this is nothing but the sum of all
the mass elements which is the total mass.
You can get there.
So now Kevin can you explain
to me why it's okay to take
Rc varies with time and everything.
Why is it okay to take
it outside the integral?
>> because we're only
intergrating the phase.
>> Right.
>> We're integrating over the body.
So when you see these B integrals,
think of that, over this body,
let's say my center of mass was right
here by the microphone just easy right?
Stop I'm looking at this and
going at this instant,
whatever the mass distribution is,
my left hand is part of the system
the center of mass for the left hand is
still down here, right, for the system.
That Rc location for
the right hand is also going to be here.
Every element of my body,
because it's a continuum,
it shares the same
center of mass location.
So as far as the body integral goes,
it's just a constant.
Just like integral of 3 times x.
You pick the 3 outside the integral and
just do integral of x right?
And continue, that's how we can treat it.
So this is just a spatial integral.
Yes rt varies with time but
we're doing a spatial integration
over the body volume right?
And that location is a fixed it doesn't
change depending on if you're looking at
the nose of the spacecraft or
the tail of the spacecraft.
It's one system and that system
has one center of mass location.
So yes that's the reason, and
we'll use this trick several times today.
So if it didn't quite make sense now
hopefully it will sink in more and more.
So you can do all of this.
That gives me MRc Plus
little rdm = MRc.
These cancel and
you will have little r times dm = 0.
This is the other way.
If you do your classic sophomore
level center of mass stuff,
you have 5 kilograms here,
2 kilograms there, you add them up.
If all your positions are taken
relative to the center of mass.
All these mass times positions
have to sum up to be 0.
That means you've balanced it perfectly.
And that's what it looks like for
generally speaking.
We have the little r dm's body
integrals have to be equal to 0.
That's just a complete 3D version
that works for any jello.
So good.
So that, from here,
a few steps you can prove this.
These are the kind of things
I would definitely expect you to be able
to do easily and quickly in an exam.
So if you haven't done much of this,
practice.
Now, what we're going to do next is
we're going to differentiate this.
So we're going to take that
definition that we just had,
the center of mass location,
all this is good, and
I'm going to take two
inertial time derivatives.
So that means on the left hand side,
mass is constant.
I'm not losing or
gaining mass in this dynamical system.
And RC, I just have to put two
dots over it and I'm done.
This is kind of like homework 3.6
that you guys did that had inertial
derivatives and stuff.
In vectorial form this is dead simple,
two dots and you're done.
The right hand side dm I guess
doesn't change, we're not losing or
gaining mass with the system.
This is a body integral,
as Kevin was saying.
And so the only thing that varies is r.
So we get big R and
it has two dots over it.
But then you go back and look at Newton's
equation that mass times inertial
acceleration is the force
acting on that one.
And so
this can be replaced with also the force.
The integral over the DF force and
we show that the integral of the DF force
is nothing but the net external force.
You can ignore all the internal forces.
So you end up with an equation that
should look pretty darn familiar.
Mass acceleration equal to force.
But you've used it primarily
I'm assuming on particles.
This is the particle, here's the mass,
here's the force this is
where it's going to go.
This actually also works on a continuum.
Blobs in space.
Anybody seen the Muppet Show?
There was pigs in space, you know,
a lot of jiggling going on.
That's that kind of stuff.
This works for anything, even muppets.
Okay, so this is the key thing.
We call this the superparticle theorem.
What this basically says,
no matter what the dynamical system is,
this complete closed system,
you can treat the center of mass of that
system will act just like a particle.
If I know there is two forces
acting on it from a megatometer and
maybe from the atmospheric drag force
that Daniel was talking about, that's it.
Then those are the only two forces I have
to consider acting on the center of mass
and I will predict
the translational motion perfectly.
Now that blob may pull apart.
It may do all kinds of weird stuff.
So if your external force depends on
the shape, then it gets more complicated.
So if this blob would be pulling apart,
then with gravity gradients the part's
closer to the planets would have
different force than the parts top.
The net forces change
because of the shape.
That makes it more complicated.
But we didn't have gravity.
We have just net thrusters
you've got blobs in space.
Somebody fires a thruster.
And this thing is going to take off and
go.
Just by looking at the force and
knowing the mass, I can predict what's
going to happen to the center of mass.
I don't know what happens
to the shape yet, but
I do know what happens to
the center of mass of that system.
Which is a very powerful argument.
So that's what's called
the super particle theorem.
Any blob in space.
If you just are concerned
with the center of mass,
the center of mass will
act like a particular.
F = Ma holds but
F has to be the net external force.
M is the total mass and Rc double dots has
to be the inertial second time derivative.