Let us do some more fun.
Kinetic energies for
particles, you guys know that.
That's mass over two times
velocity squared essentially,
that's what you've had.
This is the vectorial form of that.
I have dm, so
instead of mass I just have dm over two.
That's essentially what that does.
Times my inertial speed squared.
I'm doing this in a vectorial way,
so R dot is my, you
know if R is my inertial position vector,
I need to have my inertial velocity.
That's the first inertial time
derivative of R, that's an R dot.
I'm dotting it with itself,
that's going to give me my inertial
velocity magnitude squared.
It's just a vectorial way to write it, but
it's a very general way to write this.
So that's it.
Now that's for one dm,
I need it for the whole blob.
You simply integrate again over the body.
That's where the integral comes in.
It's just summing them all up.
So good, now we have kinetic energy.
That's not the most convenient form.
We don't typically write it this
way because it's kind of hard.
We would like to break it up in terms of
rc and kinetic energy off the center of
mass and then we're looking at kinetic
energy about the center of mass and
that will help us separate rotational
stuff, deformational stuff and
translational stuff.
That's what you'll see
popping out of this.
So let's do this.
R dot.
R was defined as Rc + r, so R dot,
you just put dots everywhere.
Again, vectorial form, dead simple, right.
The 3.6 comes back.
Don't do part b any more.
Do part a where we only take time
derivatives and vectorial parts.
You plug this in and
you carry out the various dot products.
You guys know how to do basic
dot products in calculus.
I'm not going to do that again.
So we end up with these terms.
And, as Kevin was saying earlier, in these
body intervals, anything that's RC and
RC dot, those are all going to be things
that are fixed over the body interval.
Because every point in that blob
has the same center of mass.
Therefore, it has the same
center of mass velocity.
So we can always treat these quantities
as constants over the integration.
So when you carry, you know,
this is a step I'm not doing here,
I'm purposely not, because I want you
guys to, you should do this yourself.
[COUGH] Run through the notes,
that's how it's going to stick.
If we do that, these can be pulled out.
Same thing gets pulled out here.
And at the end there's a factor of
two with the half that cancels, and
you have also this other term.
Now one of these will go to zero.
Medal.
Which one of these is going to be zero?
>> Tom Tom.
>> Why is this one going to be zero?
That's always my second question.
First part is 50/50.
Might be lucky.
Who recognizes this part?
Trevor?
>> Well, we just went over that the body
integral of the radius times the-
>> That's the vector.
It's not radius.
Let me correct quickly.
That's the position vector.
>> Position vector, yeah,
that's [INAUDIBLE].
>> Radius would be a scalar.
>> [CROSSTALK] And so
that's equal to zero.
>> Yes.
>> Take
the derivative of that
that should still be zero.
>> Exactly without the dot this is nothing
but the center of mass definition.
We rewrote that instead of the mass
average location also saying that if
all locations are relative to the center
of mass those summing ups have to give
you zero.
So integral of little r times dn is zero.
So therefore, the derivative of
zero is still going to be zero.
So this one, the center of mass location.
This is, basically,
using the center of mass definition.
That one will go to zero leaving
us with this term and this term.
Now this term is nothing but
total mass again.
So I have a big M.
So mass over 2 velocity squared,
so you can see for
the blob, the center of mass acts like
a particle again, which is really nice.
And if you're doing an orbit problem,
this would be your orbital energy
of your spacecraft basically.
And then the second part is this integral,
body integral of r dot, so
that's the position vector,
of each DM relative to the center of mass.
Get its inertial derivative though.
That's important.
This is a dot.
This is not a body frame derivative.
That's the inertial derivative and
we sum them up.
So this is basically your kinetic
energy about the center of mass.
And in this form it contains two parts.
One part of kinetic energy
comes from rotation.
If all the stuff is rotating then
these things could be spinning, and
that gives you all that
kind of kinetic energy.
The other part is because this is blobs,
you might have deformational energy,
where things are changing shape as
well and you're redistributing mass.
I'm not gaining or losing mass in this
system, but I'm just redistributing.
So if you had fuel slosh bouncing around,
that's one example you know.
So you might have deformational
energy happening here.
So that's what that is, but
this is the kinetic energy of a jello,
written in the very form, basic form.
Now, we very often want to have power,
that means the time
derivative of kinetic energy.
We have that expression, broken up into
the translational part of the cm and
energy about the cm.
If you differentiate this,
you come up with these here.
Let me show you that one trick.
If you don't see that,
how to go from there.
If you have a vector, x dotted with x.
If I have a scalar x squared and then
I take a time derivative of the scalar
I will simply have 2 times x times x dot,
right?
Very simple.
Here, if you have this vectorial
quantities I mean these expressions
we see a lot of vectors dotted with
vectors again, especially themselves.
If you have this and you take a time
derivative and here, I'm going to
take an inertial time derivative, so
I can just put dots over my vectors.
With the chain rule, you would have x dot,
dotted with x,
plus x dotted with x dot, right?
Why is this the same as 2
times x dotted with x dot?
Why can I simply add these two things up?
>> [INAUDIBLE] Reverse the order.
>> Right.
The answer here,
the dot part is actually a scalar.
So if you do this in vector form
a dotted with b is the same thing as b
dotted with a.
If you're doing it in matrix form this
would have been written as a trans x
transpose x.
Right?
It's equivalent.
And in that case too,
the answer is a scalar.
So any scalar you can transpose and
it's the same scalar.
So it allows you to reverse the matrix
order with the right transposes on it.
This is nothing but the vector form of it.
So here, here we just end up
with 2 times x times x dot, or
you could've rewritten this by
putting the dot on the first one.
Whatever's more convenient in
your analytical development.
So practice that if you haven't.
That's how I go from R dot R dot.
The one half cancels with the two.
Same thing here.
Little r dots there's a one half in front
of it that cancels with the two that
comes out of the differentiation.
This is what you end up with.
Now we're going to apply some stuff.
We know from the super particle
theorem that the mass time initial
acceleration of the center of mass
is equal to the net external force.
So that's good.
So we can plug in this becomes nothing but
f.
Over here little r dot we have
to do a little more math.
We knew that big R is Rc plus little r,
so you just put two dots over everything.
Now we have the inertial derivatives
of all these quantities, and
I can plug that one in.
So that will break up this integral as
being Rc double dot, dotted with R dot.
And, sorry, there's an R double dot and
a Rc double dot that plugs in.
You break up the math, this is
the form that you're going to have.
So this part is actually pretty much done.
So the power equation gives you
force dotted with velocity.
The shift makes sense,
hopefully with high school physics,
if you look at power stuff.
That's typically always the force
times a velocity measure.
That's the instantaneous power
being produced mechanically.
These other parts,
we're going to have to look at.
Now here, anybody see a term
that's going to go to zero?
>> How about the one at the end?
>> Yep, this one again, right?
Due to the center of mass property.
These things will pop up everywhere and
we love that, because zero is great.
It really simplifies the stuff.
So we're going to see that one go
to zero and this is nothing but
mass times the initial acceleration of an
infinitesimal element that was nothing but
dF, that little force.
So on the body, this is your general power
expression that you would have to do and
you can write, if you have to
energy change between two points,
you would integrate these
equations over time.
And this is one form or
you can do a substitution of variables.
This is a classic thing you've probably
seen where you can also do it force times
distance gives you the energy
take put into this system.
So, you can replace it.
There's different forms
you can write this.
This is the general one.
What we'll use in class will be
the rigid body specific one, but
I just wanted to highlight
first the general formulation.
We're going to then write it later on.
because this one doesn't make much
sense practically for you right now.
Once you make it rigid, we'll have
a turn that would be very very clear.
This is how we compute this.