A little bit more curious,
angular momentum.
With angular momentum we have to specify
about which point we're taking moments.
We take torques about a certain point and
we'd measure angular momentum about
the same point typically in a system.
So here, I mean people often use
center of mass, but I'm not that nice.
I'm giving you a general point p.
And so sigma is now my position vector
of dm relative to this moment point.
>> [COUGH]
>> This is the hinge point.
For some reason I want to know
momentum about this on my body
is tumbling out here.
How does that behave?
So we'll derive the general formulation
and then you will see when it sympathize
down to the down to the classy
answers many of you are familiar with.
The momentum here H about
point P angular momentum.
It's always position crossed linear
momentum of that same quantity.
So sigma, that was my position
vector relative to P, so
I have a dot, inertial derivative on that.
And you plug it in.
Sigma is R.
RP would be the position vector going
from here all the way up, right?
So sigma is nothing but R- RP.
You should start plugging this in.
Let's see, we do it with differentiation
so that we get a dot here and
then we get a double
dot on the second term.
>> This first one, trivially, goes to 0,
a vector crossed itself is always 0,
that's kind of boring.
But it's nice because this will vanish and
we're left with this term.
So, you're going to see okay.
Now, what happens with this term?
And we plugged instead of sigma
double dot, we have R double dot and
Rp double dot.
And I plugged those in.
Now, you notice R, I cannot take
outside of the body integral because
R depends on which element in
the body am I pointing to.
So that's going to be different for
every dm.
You just can't take it outside.
Rp on the other hand that's
a general hinge point that I have.
It's not really connected to the body and
keeping it very, very general.
And so that one is just fixed Rp.
Might be stationary, it might be moving,
it might be spinning or
who knows what it's doing.
And whatever it's doing,
if I differentiate it twice,
I need its inertial acceleration.
Its second order derivative.
But that one I can take
outside of my body integral.
So good, we're left with those term.
Now let's look at this one.
If we focus just on what's
the body integral of sigma dm.
So sigma, again, is r minus rp.
So I can break that up as the integral
of Rdn minus the integral of Rpdn, but
Rp I can take outside
of the body integral,
which allows me to just
get a mass times this.
And this part, if you recognize it,
that was the right hand side of
the center of mass definition.
Right?
n times Rc was equal to body integral
big Rdm.
So I'm using that definition from
the other center of mass definition.
So this just becomes M Rc,
this one here becomes M and then a Rp.
So this term here,
I can rewrite as given by there.
Okay, where's this going?
If we look at torques,
the torques about point B is
basically the moment arm cross with
the force acting on that particle.
So, if there's a magnetic torque
bar as mentioned earlier,
it may have a particular torque,
force acting.
Once the moment of that
force relative to point P.
All right, so
it's sigma crossed R double dot
dm which is the same thing as
the force acting on that element.
If you write this,
we can rearrange this, and so
you can see this term
actually appeared over here.
Here, we've simplified that term to here,
but
this first term appears as being nothing
but the torque around that point P.
Minus this, well that was it,
that is the talk about p.
So I can use this,
the inertial derivative of H about point p
is equal to the torque about point p,
plus this other stuff.
And I'm leaving it as slightly greyed,
because we typically,
a lot of dynamics books don't
talk about this, at least.
Many people just remember the inertial
derivative on momentum is torque
which is true at times.
So what must be true of point p
to make this second term vanish?
Tosh, how can you make
this term go to zero?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> No because [INAUDIBLE] or
not this doesn't matter actually.
This only has Rc which is,
this true for continuum as it is for
rigid one and RP is just an arbitrary
point outside of the body that I picked.
And I could place it anywhere.
CK.
>> RP at RC.
>> Yeah, if you set RP,
it happens to be equal to RC.
In that case, this one minus itself
is zero and that will vanish.
And then probably the most common use
of h dot equal to l is they've assumed
implicitly that is about a center of
mass location, all moments are about Rc.
And for spacecraft staff and
if you keep spinning things, we will tend
to use the center of mass as a point,
a pivot point about which
we take all of the moments.
But it doesn't have to be.
Sometimes you have a space craft and
a CAD drawing, and for some reason
what you got with the mass distribution
is all the locations are not about that.
It's like an off-balanced wheel.
All of the sudden you have to account for
that difference, and
this is what you would have to do.
What's the other way?
There's a second way we can
make this term go to zero.
Evan.
>> You can make
the difference between Rc and
Rp perpendicular to
the acceleration of Rp.
>> Okay, there's a third way
you can make it go to zero.
[LAUGH] That's kind of a hard
way to retract that but
you might come up with
a condition that would do that.
Good point.
What's the second way?
What do you guys think?
Roda what is that?
We have almost exhausted all the terms,
what's left?
>> RP is constant.
A treat of.
>> Okay if RP is constant
the RP double both is zero.
But that's true but I would say RP
being constant is a little bit.
>> RP dot is constant.
>> Could also be constant right?
So what do we call emotion that has,
either it's fixed in space or
it's only moving inertially
at a constant rate?
What do we call such motion?
No not nonlinear, inertial, exactly.
The definition for something being
inertial, an inertial point typically is
it's a non accelerating point,
and that's what's required.
The condition is really just
RP double dot has to be 0.
If that point is non-accelerating.
So if it's moving in a constant line,
we're fine.
If something is spinning immediately
it's centrifugal accelerations and
stuff, you know,
it's not going to to be inertial.
But you could take a point that's not
center of mass, but it's an inertial point
about which you take moments and
then H dot equal to L holds as well.
So in fact, some of the homeworks we'll
be getting into you need to use both.
Sometimes you take Hs and
Ls about center of mass.
And sometimes you're finding this inertial
point, o, and you can do it there.
And both sets will give you some
information that you can use to do
that, all right?
So we're not going to do much
about general body fixed points or
other different formulations of that
that exists, you can look them up.
Just be aware Hr is equal to
l is not universally true.
It's only true if you take your
moments about center of mass or
inertial points then we're guaranteed
this is going to go to zero.
Those are two conditions
we'll use in class.