Okay.
Linear momentum,
just kind of wrapping things up for
blobs, since we're onto blobs.
The linear momentum is always mass times
velocity, is your linear momentum.
Then a completely vectorial way in
a blob you would have your mass is DM,
your velocity inertial is R dot,
and P is my linear momentum.
So DP is my linear momentum of that
differential element that you have.
If you want the total linear
momentum of a system,
you have to integrate over the body again,
and you just plug in all these things.
Then same rules, we will plug in,
instead of R we have Rc + little r,
and we can break this up.
We can pull this Rc out again.
And this integral by now, hopefully
boring you can go yep, that's zero.
Right, that's the center of mass property
again, and that one's going to vanish.
This one we've replaced with total mass.
So that's it.
So for a blob, again,
like the super particle theorem, need to
know what is the total mass of the system
and how is the center of mass moving?
And then we know what's going on.
If you differentiate it, this is how
you come up with Newton's equation for
a constant mass solution.
So mass is preserved.
We're not gaining and
losing mass in the system.
Taking the inertial derivative
of linear momentum and
you plug that into this equation,
this R dot becomes an R double dot.
This is nothing but the force acting on
that element but integrated over a body.
You only care about
the external forces again.
Which is a very powerful statement.
So if you go to space station
have flew away from earth and
she's going through deep space.
And astronauts in there all of a sudden
start running up on a treadmill.
Are they ever going to change the
center-of-mass motion of the spacecraft?
No.
They may change the orientation,
they may change the shape.
But these internal forces can
never change your linear momentum.
That's what we saw in
the superparticle theorem, too,
that only external forces impact how
the center of mass evolves through space.
So, this is a kind of handy,
handy, formula.