In this segment we're gonna take a look at
box logic. Unfortunately, we cannot do
that here on the studio so we're gonna
have to take a road trip. Today we're
headed for Stanford University's renowned
logic laboratory. Follow me. And here we
are. This is the logic laboratory. It may
not look like much at least not
superficially but this is where we
investigate some of the latest innovations
in logic technology. Today our goal was to
look at box logic. Now the language of box
logic is pretty simple. There are really
just three constants. There is large box,
there is medium box, and there is small
box and they are all oriented one way or
the other. Forming compound sentences from
our consonants is easy. If we want to
negate a sentence, we just invert. Not
medium box, medium box. If you want this
form of this junction from our constants,
we stack them up. So here we have small
box or medium box. And a conjunction is
formed simply by placing multiple boxes or
stacks of boxes on our table. So it's
effectively colossal for. Okay. Now, let's
try to use our logic to solve some
problems. How about the problem case of
Mary Patton Quincy? We call that. If it's
Monday, Mary loves Pat or Quincy and
Quincy, if Mary loves Pat, Mary loves
Quincy. Let's see how we can represent
that information using our new language.
So first of all, if Mary loves Pat, Mary
loves Quincy let's, let this medium sized
box represent the fact that Mary loves
Pat. This one represents Mary loves Quincy
and the large one is going to be Monday.
So we wanna say, if Mary loves Pat, Mary
loves Quincy. How do we do that? Recalling
the rules for converting to colossal form,
we know that p implies q as equivalent to
not p or q. So if you wanted to write
that, we would write not Mary loves Pat or
Mary loves Quincy. So, not Mary loves Pat
or Mary loves Quincy. If Mary loves Pat,
Mary loves Quincy. How about our other
sentence? If it's Monday, then Mary loves
Pat or Quincy. It's Monday, let's see. We
need to say not Monday or Pat or Quincy.
So it's not Monday mo re quick copies. Or
Pat or Quincy. So there we have it. If
it's Monday, Mary loves Pat or Quincy. If
Mary loves Pat, Mary loves Quincy,
represented, representing the premises of
the problem. Now you may recall that the
object of the problem was to show that if
it's Monday then Mary loves Quincy. So how
could we do that? What we have done is
representing but we can also do
computation, deduction with box logic. Any
rules are pretty simple. If we ever have
one stack which has a constant. Literal
which is the complement of literal on
another stack, we can do resolution on
them. So here we have one stack with
medium box down, here one stack with
medium box up. We can combine the two
stacks and eliminate the complementary
literals and form these answers and since
it's a duplicate, we can throw that one
away and we're left with our conclusion.
If it's Monday, Mary loves Quincy, nifty.
Okay, what's the point? The point is that
the language of logic is not about
particular sets of symbols. And the active
deduction doesn't mean necessarily that
we're operating upon those particular
symbols. Logic is an abstraction. Any
instantiation of the symbols is equally
good and any operations on them is equally
good provided that it respects that basic
abstraction. Okay. That's it for our visit
to the logic laboratory today. We'll be
back again later in the course with some
additional demonstrations and we'll see
you then.