[MUSIC]
Hello, and welcome to this third module of
our introductory course, where we'll touch
upon the basics of particle
acceleration and detection methods.
In this video,
we will explain the physical principles
of linear and circular accelerators.
Afterwards, you will be able to
answer the following questions.
What are the principles of particle
acceleration by electromagnetic fields?
How does an electrostatic
accelerator work?
And how do cyclotrons and
synchrotrons work?
The force acting on a particle of
charge e, in an electric field E, and
a magnetic field B, is given by
the Lorentz force that is quoted in blue.
Electric fields are used to accelerate
particles by increasing their momentum.
Magnetic fields serve to deflect
them from their original direction,
to store them in a ring, or
to focus a beam of particles.
The simplest accelerator for
electrons is the cathode ray tube,
that you may remember from
your grandfather's TV set.
An electron emerging from a heated
filament is accelerated by a potential V.
The energy of the outgoing electron
is then obviously V electron volts.
Electrostatic accelerators chain
together stages of this type as shown in
this photograph.
Their energy is limited by the stability
of the high voltage insulation.
Thus, it does not exceed
a few million electron volts.
To reach a higher energy requires that
the projectile passes several times by
an accelerating potential.
The simplest circular
accelerator is the cyclotron.
In a uniform and constant magnetic field B,
a particle of charge e moves on
a circle of radius rho equal to p
divided by eB where p is its moment.
The angular frequency of this movement
is called cyclotron frequency omega_c.
It is proportion to the ratio e over
m of the particle charge and mass and
proportional to the magnetic
field intensity B.
The particle is accelerated
by the electric field present
between the two D shaped cavities.
This field is provided by
a radio frequency generator
such that its frequency is equal
to the cyclotron frequency.
In the non relativistic domain,
this frequency is constant because
the circumference of the orbit increases
proportional to the velocity
of the particle.
Thus, we can inject particles
in a quasi continuous manner,
if the accelerating RF
frequency's high and
an even multiple of
the cyclotron frequency.
You can find a calculation of
the cyclotron frequency in video 3.1a.
The cyclotron has its limits in
that the velocity of the particle does not
remain proportional to the momentum, but
approaches the speed of light
in an asymptotic process.
In the relativistic limit,
the velocity barely increases
despite a steady increase in energy.
Acceleration radio frequency and
particle revolution frequency dephase
thus quickly at an energy of some tens
of MeV for protons.
One must thus adjust the radio
frequency to the relativistic velocity.
For example, the proton cyclotron at
the Paul Scherrer Institute in Villigen,
Switzerland accelerates protons to
nearly 80% of the speed of light.
And you can see a picture of this
accelerator in this photograph.
The asymptotic saturation of the speed of
the particle to the speed of light is, on
the contrary, very useful, provided that
the radius of curvature is held constant.
In this case, the rotational frequency,
again, is independent of energy.
This is the principle of the synchrotron.
By increasing the magnetic field
proportional to the momentum of
the particle,
the radius of curvature remains constant.
One does not have to fill a large
volume with a magnetic field, but
can concentrate it inside a vacuum
chamber, whose shape approximates a ring.
The synchrotron frequency becomes
constant at high energies if the field B
is kept proportional to the momentum.
We can then work with a constant
accelerating radio frequency.
The RF field is transmitted to
the beam by resonant cavities.
The synchrotron principle requires
a certain initial velocity
sufficiently close to the speed of light.
The beam is thus usually pre-accelerated
before injection by say,
a linear accelerator.
The acceleration process must stop
when one reaches the maximum field of
the dipole magnets.
One then either extracts the beam or
converts the accelerator
into a storage ring.
In this latter operational mode,
it provides at each turn just the energy
lost by the beam via bremsstrahlung.
This loss of energy will be introduced in
the next section of the module, video 3.2.
The separation of functions and
the concentration of the components around
the ring, allows to combine two rings
to construct what is called a collider.
A historical example is the Princeton-
Stanford storage ring, an early example
of a particle collider.
It worked with electrons in the two
rings which interact in the middle,
where the two storage rings touch.
The detector was rather
primitive, a spark chamber, but
it did allow to determine
the scattering angle.
Obviously, one can also fold the two
accelerators on top of each other, or
even combine them if you want to
collide particles and antiparticles.
Examples of the latter type of
colliders are the Tevatron at
the Fermi National Laboratory
close to Chicago in the US,
which collided protons and
antiprotons until 2011.
And also the Large Electron
Positron collider, LEP at CERN,
which collided electrons and positrons.
It was in operation between 1989 and
2000 in the tunnel which now houses
the Large Hadron Collider, LHC at CERN.
We will return to the LHC in
the next video of this module.
[MUSIC]