[MUSIC]
I will first show you the effect of the Lorentz force
with a cathode ray tube
filled with a rarified gas.
This gas is fluorescent, and thus makes the particle passage visible.
A heated filament emits electrons,
which are then accelerated by an electric field.
They leave the cathode pointing upwards.
The Helmholtz coils,
in front of and behind the tube, generate a magnetic field which points towards you.
The electrons are thus deviated towards the center of the tube.
With ambient light, one cannot see the faint fluorescence of the gas.
When we dim the light, it becomes visible.
Now I increase the magnetic field strength.
At constant electron momentum, the radius of curvature becomes smaller.
The electrons circulate around the magnetic field direction,
with the cyclotron frequency.
If I now reduce the magnetic field strength,
The radius of curvature increases, and the electrons hit the glass of the tube.
Let us quickly calculate the cyclotron frequency with which
The electrons circulate in the tube.
The Lorentz force q(v x B) gives us the centripetal force, which makes them follow a circle,
if v is orthogonal to B. The absolute value of the force is simply
(evB)
and must be equal to mv^2/rho, where rho is the radius of the circle.
This gives us v = e B rho/m, the velocity is thus constant.
The frequency with which they circulate is v/(2 pi rho),
which equals (eB)/(2 pi m). This is thus also a constant in the non-relativistic case.
This gives us an angular frequency of (2 pi f)= eB/m, the cyclotron frequency.
[MUSIC]