[MUSIC]
Welcome to the lesson on
RESTful web services.
In this video lecture,
we will have a deep look at REST.
But what is REST, actually?
REST, or Representational State Transfer,
is an architectural style.
A set of guidelines to
serve network applications.
It specifies a set of constraints
on developing web services, and
if those constraints are met
we call that service RESTful.
The first constraint is the separation
of the client and server functions and
architectures.
The client doesn't care about
the task executed on the server.
For example, database access or
memory management.
And the server doesn't care
how the client operates.
This way they both can be
developed independently.
Clients can send multiple requests, but
these requests should be
independent of each other.
Responses should be clearly identified
as cacheable or non-cacheable.
This is more of a performance constraint.
Multiple clients might request
the same resource, and in this case,
caching will help in reducing response
time and reducing a server load.
There should be a uniform way of
identifying and accessing resources.
Each resource must have a URI and
representation.
The representation can be in JSON or XML.
The last constraint is that
an application can have multiple layers.
Layers between client and server,
like cash servers and load balancers.
If there is a load balancer
between a client and a server,
the client shouldn't see
beyond the load balancer.
And the server shouldn't be concerned
with who the load balancer is talking to.
This restriction reduces complexity and
makes it easy to add and remove layers.
As a design consideration
rather than a constraint,
there should be one to one
mapping between CRUD operations.
That is create, read, update, and
delete operations, and
operations provided by the server.
In light of these constraints,
let's look at how HTTP fits REST.
HTTPs is stateless,
it has a client-server model,
it supports caches, and
uses URLs to identify resources.
The last design consideration
is mapping of craft operations.
This can be done by a HTTP
methods as shown in the table.
We see that it is simple to build
a RESTful web service via HTTP.
But why should we use rest when exposing
the functionality of an embedded or
cyber physical system to the web.
First of all,
a central idea of rest is a resource.
A resource is a component
of an application
that can be uniquely identified.
The same logic applies
to embedded systems.
We have resources in
the form of sensor and
actuators, which need to be
individually identified and accessed.
Identification is achieved via URI's,
and they're representation via JSON.
An access comes by a HTTP
methods like GET and POST.
In REST, we call for CRUD operations,
create, read, update and delete.
In most cases, these are the only
operations that we need on our sensors.
Create the stages,
update them, or shut them off.
REST and JSON, used together,
create a lightweight
representation of resources.
Being lightweight makes
it more power efficient.
The statelessness of REST means that
it is more memory efficient as a server
doesn't store our main information
about the state of the connection.
So, not only does rest fulfill
our design considerations, but
it also fulfills real-world considerations
related to limited power and memory.
We looked into REST, and its applicability
to embed in systems in general.
Now we will talk about some best practices
to follow when designing
web-enabled embedded systems.
First of all, identify the sensors or
functionalities that are available to you,
and then decide which ones you
would like to enable as a resource.
Each of these resources
should have a simple and
focused URI to identify and access them.
And finally, what actions would you like
to allow on each of these resources?
To better understand, we will look
at an example development board.
On the screen, you see a Texas
Instruments Smart RF06 Evaluation Board.
It has an accelerometer,
light sensor, LCD display,
an SD card slot, and
some push buttons and LEDs.
In this case,
it is easy to identify our resources.
All of the mentioned
components are resources
that can be uniquely identified and
accessed.
The next step is to assign each
one a unique and logical URI.
Here you see an example mapping
of URIs against each resource.
The next step is to specify which
operations you would allow on
each resource.
So when you enter in a browser the URL
of whichever sensor you want to access,
the response will depend on whether the
specific HTTP method is allowed or not.
If it's allowed you will
get an okay status message
with the value of the sensor.
If the method is not allowed, you will get
the method not allowed status message.
On the screen you see an example
mapping of methods to resources.
As we will be only reading data
from the accelerometer and
licencer, the only method
we can use is GET.
An LED can have a GET method
to tell us it status on or
off and
a PUT method to change that status.
And LCD can be updated to output certain
information, and for that we need PUT.
If we are reading and writing to the SD
card, we can have all of these methods,
create a file, update a file,
read it, and delete it.
In this lesson, we looked at how
the REST style of designing web services
is beneficial for
cyber physical systems, and
then we described an example mapping of
REST to an embedded development board.
Next we will learn about another type
of service called cloud computing.
[MUSIC]