In 2014,
a group called Force11 issued the Joint
Declaration on Data Citation Principles.
This has been endorsed by
a number of scientific bodies and
publishers, as well as individuals.
So why cite data?
By providing a citation for your data,
you make it easier for other users
to identify and acknowledge it.
Data citation helps promote
the reproduce-ability of research results,
it allows us to track the usage and
impact of data and
it provides a structure by which we can
recognize and reward data creators.
So whats the best practice
in citing a data set?
As a general rule of thumb you want to
make sure you include enough information
for another use to be able
to locate the data set or
the part of the database
that you're referring to.
DataCite, an international
standards body founded in 2009,
recommends the following five
minimum citation elements.
A creator, a year of publication,
a title, publisher, and identifier.
Here, identifier refers to any persistent
ID which uniquely identifies the object,
including a DOI or even a URL,
though this may be less persistent.
Two additional properties which may be
added are Version and ResourceType.
ResourceType refers to the class
of object that is being citied,
such as a dataset, database,
map, sound file or website.
The UK data service recommends using
a title that indicates the subject matter,
geography and
time period that the data covers.
Let's take a look at an example.
When citing data it makes sense to try and
adopt the same style and
order of references as your other works.
Bibliographic style guides and
reference management software may help.
But inevitably,
some judgment may be called for.
If so, err on the side of caution, and
always provide more information than
less to help the users find the data.
In the case of a dynamic database,
that is continually updated,
it may be near impossible to refer back
to the exact version that you used.
In such circumstances always
include a date of download.
In the life sciences it's common
to include an accession number
with the database name when
you're referencing sequence data.
You can see this in
the examples on screen.
So what if you're using
an unpublished data source?
Informal data sharing
is relatively common.
But even if the data are unpublished,
the citation principles still applies.
If somebody shared data with you,
for example,
via an email attachment, you can reference
this as a private communication.
Let's take a look at an example.
Last but not least, good practice in
data documentation and citation can
contribute to reaching a better standard
of reproducibility of research.
Reproducibility is a fundamental
principle of the scientific method.
So you've now completed this module.
If you take a look in the further reading
section you'll find additional references
to get more information on
documentation and citation.
You can also move onto the next module,
which is on storage and security.