Next topic we discuss is, Spatial Key
Framing for character animation.
And, the work we introduce here was
published Spatial Key Framing for
Performance-driven Animation.
So the motivation here is, creation
of character animation is tedious and
difficult.
So here's a list of, popular techniques,
so Key framing, Motion capture, Physics
and Scripting.
Keyframe is by the way the most popular
technique.
So you set key bodies of each time frame.
So, as a program we want to address here
is the creation of character animation is
tedious and difficult.
Here are a list of current popular
techniques
of Key framing, Motion capture, Physics,
and Scripting.
So by ways the most popular technique is
key framing.
So you get a character and for each time
you place a pose
like time zero, this pose, time one, this
pose, time two, this pose.
So individual key framing.
But however, this is very difficult to do.
Especially, for now we use to get a smooth
animation using this key framing.
If you do it poorly, it's like a robotic
motion.
And the another popular technique is
motion capture.
You can directly record body motion using
the tracking systems.
However this one requires special device,
special space,
and also scale, skilled actors which is
difficult.
The physics simulation is also used for
but not good for designing character
animation.
And scripting is also used for a robotic
motion, like change angle this to change
this angle.
However, this is not good for expressive
character animation.
So what we want to do is easily sketch
or create, you know dynamic form motions
or character.
So the basic idea is very simple.
We believe that the best, easiest way is
to
directly manipulate a character in front
of the camera.
And then press record, and then
manipulate, and then
stop and play back and do the same thing.
So direct recording of performers should
be the best way to do it.
One problem here is that the typical input
device is very limited degree of freedom.
So for example, if you use a mouse, you
only have X and Y inputs, two dimensional
inputs.
However, character usually has a high
degree of freedom.
So each joint has three degrees of
rotation freedom, and you have many many
joints.
So you have to control many joints with
single
mouse, which can be very difficult for a
performance-based recording.
So our proposal is to use spatial
key-framing, so user or designer first
specifies or
prepares key poses in the 3D space and
then blend them, depending on the control
handle.
So let me show you a demo.
So, here is a character in the 3D space
and then we make an animation of this
character.
And as I said, difficult project is key
framing.
You know, this time, this pose, next time,
this pose, next time, this pose and so on.
And it's very, very tedious to do this for
a long animation sequence.
So, our process is to directly record a
motion.
Particularly, if but, if you use one by
one, it's very tedious.
In this you can only head, arm, or
leg, but you cannot manipulate all of them
together.
So our approach is to use a predefined key
frame.
So you say, this pose is associated with
this
position, and then next pause is
associated with this position.
And then, so you have two key frames.
So, standard key frames associate with
timeline.
But here, key frames are associated with
spatial locations.
And by clicking you can jump to the key
frames and by dragging you can plan these
too.
So now, you can only control three joints
by a single mass.
An interesting point here, is that you can
add more, and more key poses very easily.
So, you know have three key poses.
And they blend together, and then you get
a reasonably interesting motion already.
And you can add more, and more operation
of
key poses, like a kick and kick and so on.
All right, let me show you a couple more
examples.
So, so
here, again, individual poses are not so
complicated.
However, if you hide, and then start
moving around the ball, now you can
make this teddy bear doing the juggling,
just by using a two-dimensional mouse.
And then another example is this one.
So again, each individual coordinates are
not so expressive.
However, as you start moving them around,
you can make him dance like this way.
So here you know, your hand motion is
directly
appears in the character motion, so that
the resulting motion is very expressive.
So of course, you can let go of this
motion: you know, one, two, one, two, mm.
So now you can get this animation and then
now you get a motion.
So
you can see it from many different
locations.
Okay.
Now let me show you a couple more
examples.
So here is a kicking motion.
So you have many, many couple of key
poses.
And then by dragging this lead ball you
can make the
teddy bear make a high kick, as well as a
low kick.
And this is a mushroom, jumping, so you
have five or six key bodies
and then by directly manipulating that
ball you can make this animation.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And this is a teddy bear in trouble, I
think six key poses.
And then, you know, he says no first, and
they get idea, and be happy.
So, you can make this kind of expressive
emotion
by using your hand motion integrated into
the final.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Here this eyeballs also have a separate
joint so you can control their rotation.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, so let me briefly describe the
algorithm to do this.
So input to this system is handle
coordinates.
So, you have 2D mouse, and then you
control the lead ball position using a
mouse.
And the output is the orientation of each
joint.
So, you have many in rotation angles.
So, the question here is how to represent
orientation angle, rotation joint angle.
And there are a couple ways to represent
joint angles like euler
angles or quaternions but here we use a
rotation matrix, so nine elements.
Like this way, so each joint has a three
by three
matrix for these represents also on our
axis for each joint.
And then what we need to control these
nine
parameters for each joint depending on the
user input.
So let's take this joint.
So, this joint has suppose we have three
special key frames,
and then each key frame has this nine
parameters for each joint.
And then as user specifies the new handle
position and then we
need to compute three by three matrix for
this position for this joint.
To do this we basically blend these nearby
three key poses.
So you won't have to do this.
Let's take, we compute interpretation for
individual elements
or individual entry of these three by
three matrix.
So this is just a simple skeletal body
interpolation and
here we use a technique called radial
basis function interpolation.
So this is a scattered data interpolation
using radial basis functions.
This is a kind of stand out technique
and you can use as a possible
interpolation techniques.
This is very easy to implement, very easy
to use.
The idea is very simple.
So for a supposed example you have three
skeletal bodies with special location.
And then for each location, we have a
kernel function.
Kernel function, and then we eh, compute
most appropriate waiting or coefficients
for each kernels.
And then just by adding them together,
you will get a very smooth, interpolating
function.
And if you want to know more, you can, I
recommend you to take out paper by Turk in
2002.
So
after computing this up line, this
skeletal body interpolation for individual
elements, you have nine elements in a
three by three matrix.
But unfortunately, if you apply our
interpolation independently to these
entries in resulting matrix, is not
necessarily orthonormal, you know.
Rotation matrix needs to be, orthonormal.
And also perpendicular to each other and
also the directions should be equal to
one.
So after that we apply orthonomalization
operation to
these three by three matrix to get this
one.
I always skip details of this
orthonormalization but there's a standard
approach.
Okay, so here's a summary.
So we introduce spatial key-framing for
creating character animation quickly and
easily.
As a user defines key poses in the screen
space, and then the system automatically
blends nearby key poses.
In order to do so, we use rotation matrix
and then
we use radial basis function interpolation
for each element in the matrix.
So to learn more, original paper
was published as Spatial Keyframing for
Performance-driven
Animation, and if you want to learn
more about interpolation by radial basis
functions.
There's a paper titled Modeling with
implicit surfaces that interpolate.
Here's an example.
So use a space prior positions in 3D
space.
And then this technique generates a
very beautiful smooth surface
interpolating these points.
And interpolation of 3D angles is popular
topic discussion in graphics community.
And the popular technique used is
Quaternion interpretation.
And then I recommend you take a lot of
original paper published in SIGGRAPH 85.
Thank you.