[MUSIC]
In this module, we discuss searches for
new phenomena beyond the known ones
described by the Standard Model.
In this video, we will talk about
the life cycle of a collision event.
From the time the event is produced
in the heart of a detector,
until it gets ready to be
processed in a physics analysis.
After watching this video,
you will know why we trigger on physics
events in the collider experiments.
How we translate the analog and
digital signals of the detectors
to physical objects
that we associate with
Standard Model particles for
the events we have triggered on.
And how we deal with the large amounts of
data that are produced in the collider
experiments.
All that in connection to what we
need to search for new physics.
As you already learned in module 3,
proton bunches each containing hundreds
of billions of protons collide at the LHC
in collision points where
experiments are installed.
This is one of the general purpose
detectors of the LHC, the ATLAS detector.
We have already gone through its elements
and their functions in video 3.10a.
If you take a look at the transverse
view of the detector you will see
that it has an onion structure.
It is made up of various layers
of different detectors.
An inner detector inside a solenoid
used for tracking charged particles.
Calorimeters for electromagnetic and
hadronic shower measurements.
And a muon spectrometer in
toroidal magnetic field, for
muon momentum measurements.
Proton-proton collisions result
in many particles which decay to
the lightest elementary particles
compatible with their quantum numbers.
These leave their signatures in the
detector as digital and analogue signals,
which reconstruct as objects that we
associate with elementary particles.
So the particles we reconstruct in the
detector are electrons, and photons, and
muons and quarks, and
gluons as particle jets.
Details about the detector
response to various particle types
are given in video 3.10a.
Events that contain sufficiently
interesting features to be further
analyzed are triggered on and
stored for further processing.
These events go through
event reconstruction.
To ensure an accurate measurement of the
properties of the reconstructed objects,
a calibration procedure is applied.
Calibrated objects are now ready for
analysis.
In our analysis,
we need to compare our
data to theoretical calculations.
To achieve this, event simulations called
Monte Carlo simulations are performed,
which create artificial events based
on a specific theoretical assumption.
With these components in place,
reconstructed and
calibrated data on one hand,
and data simulated according to
theoretical predictions on the other hand,
we are ready to search for
new physics in our data.
But let's first understand
these components better.
And let's start from the trigger.
What does this actually do?
The LHC is colliding proton bunches
with a maximum rate of 40 MHz.
Each event recorded by the
experiment, containing all digital and
analog information from the detector,
has a data size of about one megabyte.
So saving all events would lead to
about 40 terabytes of data per second.
This is a huge amount of data to store,
but also to process.
Furthermore, most of these events
only contain known physics, so
we need to select which of them to keep.
This is where the trigger system comes in.
The trigger system of the large
multi-purpose experiments
consists of two main components,
a hardware based one and
a software based one.
The trigger system is built
to be extremely robust and
fast as it needs to take a reliable
decision in a very short time.
The trigger helps the selection
of interesting events,
but also applies upper limits in
the number of events we select after
each of its steps.
Triggering on events that contain new
phenomena is an extremely big challenge.
We don't know a priori how
these events would look like.
We therefore have to build our trigger
selections generic enough to ensure we
don't lose anything interesting,
as events we don't trigger on
are are simply lost forever.
For events that were triggered
the detector tells us about the elementary
particles that were created
in the collision process
as well as their properties.
Typically most of these particles are
relevant in the searches for new physics.
And we will see why in the following
videos of this module.
An overview is given in video 3.10a.
Here, we summarize the detector response
to the main types of particles.
Electrons and muons both leave
tracks in the inner detector.
The electrons are reconstructed
by matching the track with
the electromagnetic shower.
For the muon,
the inner detector track is matched to
a muon track in the muon spectrometer.
Photons, being neutral,
leave no track in the inner detector.
And are therefore associated to
an electromagnetic shower with no track
pointing to it.
Quarks and gluons are much more
complicated objects to reconstruct.
They can't live by themselves.
They have to exist in bound states,
as was already explained in module 5.
They hadronize and
are therefore reconstructed in
the calorimeter as a hadronic shower.
Algorithms scan the calorimeter
data in order to identify the most
significant energy depositions,
corresponding to quarks or gluons.
The resulting objects are the jets.
It's worth pointing out that
the dominant process resulting from
a proton-proton interaction is
the production of quarks and gluons.
Therefore jets dominate
the detected final states.
Neutrinos do not interact with a detector
and therefore escape undetected.
However, we can get
information about neutrinos
using the knowledge that
in the transverse plane,
because of conservation of momentum,
the vector sum of the momenta of
all the objects has to be zero.
So neutrinos are associated with a
missing momentum in the transverse plane
Any neutral and
weakly interacting particle,
such as dark matter candidates,
will in fact behave just like neutrinos.
And will be identified as missing
transverse momentum in the detector.
Missing transverse momentum is extremely
important in our searches for new physics.
W, Z, Higgs bosons, top quarks, and
tau leptons decay immediately
to elementary matter particles.
And we reconstruct them
through their decay products.
In a detector, we can therefore
observe various event topologies.
And based on their characteristics
we can classify the events.
This is in fact what we are doing
already at trigger level.
We are running algorithms that
perform simplified reconstruction.
And based on the characteristics of
the events, we accept or discard them.
For example, events with high momentum
objects, or large multiplicity of objects.
are accepted by the trigger for
further processing.
Events with only low energy particles
are not generally accepted,
as these are of no general interest
since they correspond to
low q^2 processes.
It would also be impossible to store and
process those as they
are the most common ones.
Despite the fact that we are finding ways
to reduce the amount of data we need to
process,
we are still generating
incredibly large amounts of data.
Such large amounts are needed to ensure
that the rarest processes will be produced
and saved in our data.
Such would be processes
coming from new physics.
This data gets reconstructed and
calibrated as we said.
It is the products of this
process we are eventually using
without ever discarding the original data,
since we often need to reprocess them to,
for example,
improve reconstruction or calibration.
In order to make the best use
of the large amount of data,
we use sophisticated methodologies,
such as machine learning techniques or
other statistical methods
which are often CPU intensive.
This adds to the computing
needs of the LHC experiments.
It is not only data and simulation storage
we need, but also processing power.
This is a combination that
creates a great challenge.
This challenge is being addressed
using major innovations in computing,
such as the computing grid.
Numerous computing centers in universities
all over the world are interconnected,
forming a computing grid.
They receive copies of the data.
And give the capability to
scientists to run their analyses
processes on this grid in an automatic and
transparent way.
Research and development in the computing
domain is in active progress.
And the task is always
extremely challenging and
rewarding at the same time.
This concludes this lecture.
In the next video we will talk
about a specific type of searches.
The so called bump searches.
[MUSIC]