[MUSIC]
When thinking about and doing data
management, it is critical to understand
data in terms of their lifecycle and
the research project’s lifecycle.
For project planning to archiving,
proper data management happens
throughout the research lifecycle.
Each stage of the lifecycle
produces specific data products and
requires a variety of considerations,
responsibilities, and activities.
There are numerous lifecycle
models from simple to complex.
Let's look at a few.
Here is the research lifecycle
model from the UK Data Archive.
Once data are created, which is
represented in the circle at 12 o'clock,
the data undergo subsequent stages,
processing, analyzing,
preserving, providing access to,
and re-using the data.
The University of Virginia library created
this research data life cycle model,
which I think directly aligns
to common research practice.
Here is the more complex and
comprehensive data lifecycle model
developed by the Digital Curation Center.
With data at the center of the graphic,
you can see the various data
curation activities as you
move to the outer rings.
This model brings together data,
researchers and curators.
Now that you have been
introduced to data and
understand that data management refers to
activities throughout the data lifecycle,
please take a moment to introduce yourself
on the forums and tell us about your
data experiences, or maybe even questions
you have about data or the course.
We have also provided some
additional readings for
you to explore if you're
interested in learning more.
And make sure you check out
the resources for this module.
[MUSIC]