[MUSIC]
This new content marks a sudden departure
from
what we've been doing in the course do
far.
Practically everything that we've done in
the course
up til now has involved derivatives in
some form.
And this is now a sudden departure from
that topic.
Now we're going to be looking at area.
You might be thinking that this means
we're going to
be computing a bunch of areas, but it
would
be more precise to say that this material
is
about defining what the very idea of area
even means.
Think way back, to when we were first
learning about the derivative.
When we first learned about the
derivative, you
might have thought that we were computing
instantaneous velocity.
But it would have been better to think
that we
were defining what the very notion of
instantaneous velocity even means.
Right?
We needed all this machinery of limits to
even think about precisely what those
concepts mean.
And the same is true for the material now.
Yes we're going to be computing areas, but
really we're setting
up the machinery so that we can even
define what area means.
Of course you might be wondering why is
this in this course.
Well it turns out that this really does
fit
into the narrative of the course as a
whole.
We just saw anti differiantion.
And the next thing after looking at area
is going to be the fundamental theorem of
calculus.
And what the fundamental theorem of
calculus is going to do for us,
it's going to relate anti differentiation
and this process of, of computing area.
Unfortunately we've got to wait a little
bit longer to see that story.
And for the time being we really going to
focus on just defining what area means,
we're going to review summation notion so
that
we can write down these kinds of formulas.
But hang in there, the connection between
this material
on area and all the stuff that we're doing
on differentiation is going to become
crystal clear very soon,
once we get to the fundamental theorem of
calculus.
Which it is arguably really the triumph of
the whole course.
We've got a little bit longer to wait.
Good luck.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]