[MUSIC]
In this second module, we deal with
nuclear physics and its applications and
we're discussing radioactivity.
In this video, we calculate how many
decays per second can be observed
from an initial sample of nuclei,
that is to say, we discuss the decay law.
Radioactive decay is
a statistical process.
Every nucleus has the same
probability lambda
to decay in a given interval of time.
This means that a constant percentage
of the nuclear existing at the time t,
N(t), will decay in
an infinitesimal elapsed time, dt.
The number of remaining nuclei then
diminishes in an exponential manner.
The inverse of the decay
probability lambda
is what is called the lifetime tau = 1/lambda
of the nucleus.
When one lifetime has passed, a fraction
e of the initial sample will remain.
One also defines the half life,T_1/2,
which is the time interval leaving
half of the initial sample.
And the activity of a sample,
which is a number of decays per second.
It obviously depends on
the decay constant, and
the sample size which
diminishes exponentially.
The natural activity of Ra-226 is
used as the unit of radioactivity and
it's called the Curie.
A more practical unit is the Becquerel
which corresponds to one decay per second.
[MUSIC]