This week's additional programming
lecture is on arrays.
So last week we talked about variables.
And I talked about how a variable is a
place in memory or a box in memory where
you can put some data.
and that's obviously very useful for
storing most types of data, and being
able to access it via name.
But it's really suitable only for one
particular item of data, a single number,
a single image.
Now part of the benefit of using a
computer, is that you can compute lots
and lots of data.
and we'll see in this week's lecture, how
we can use lots and lots of images to
create an animation.
But to do that you need, a way of storing
all of those images in a convenient way,
and not having a hundred variables, if
you have a hundred images in one
dimension.
And, that is where you have we use
something called an array.
Now an array variable is created very
much like any other variable, except you
have these two little square brackets.
makes it look a little like a box, but
I'll come to exactly what those mean in a
minute.
But we just put between the type of the
variable, int, and the variable name plus
X.
We put these square brackets in that, it
tells us that it's an array variable,
which is to, stor, study, storing one
int, can store many integers.
And if we see down here at the bottom in
memory, rather than a single box, it's a
lot of boxes, each with their own value
of memory and number.
And you can access with a single name,
posX with this, all of those boxes
together.
It's a single variable, we can have lots
of different bits of data.
So how do you access an individual item
of data?
You access it with a number, and you use
these square brackets, this is where the
square brackets come in.
There the way you get access to a
particular item of the array, and inside
the square brackets, you put a number.
So each of those boxes has a number, and
this is the way you get box number three,
and you would get an item out that.
one thing to note, very importantly, is
that it starts at 0, so the first element
in an array is element 0.
you would naturally think it's element 1.
It is not, it's 0.
And that will influence how you do
everything right.
It's very important to be clear on that.
And that means if you've got a number
element with 10 elements in and an array
with 10 elements in, the first element is
on 0, and the last one is over 9, it is
not over 10, because it starts with 0.
It can be a little bit confusing.
Unfortunate, that's just the way it
works, and you will get used to it very
quickly.
So this is how you set an element to the
array, just like you would set a variable
to be, using the equals command.
You can set element 3 here, again using
equals, but we have to use the square
brackets to get hold of that value.
It's just like any ordin, ordinary
variable.
This is how you create an array, one way
of creating an array.
in the example we'll actually use a
function to create an array, but we
declare a new variable.
there many type of create box in memory,
to do this you say the type It's a,
called a floating point.
When we have the square brackets, those
square brackets tell us it's not just one
floating value, it's an array.
Give it a name, like any other variable.
And then you create an array.
And this is, these curly brackets and a
list of numbers.
That gives you an array.
But we'll see in the actual example,
we'll do a different, use a different
mechanism, and next week we'll use yet
another mechanism.
but, but here is an example of creating a
very simple array, and then you can use
element zero.
And you can use this syntax with the
square brackets, the name of the array,
square brackets and number, to get any
element.
And once you've got that element, you can
use it in any way you'd use any other
variable, by any way you'd use a number.
So it can just print it out, or you can
use it as inputs to do any command you
like.
So you could do translate vals at zero,
rotate, wrecked, any of these commands
that you're familiar with.
So we can use rectval zero, we could use
fill vals zero, any of the commands
you're used to.
Wherever you would use a normal variable,
you could use an array variable, plus
squared brackets and a number.
And that would just give you a number
value, like any other value.
Very simple, and we'll in the main
example how you can use them with images,
to create an animation.