This lecture I'll talk about
conditionals.
which statements, which of the mechanisms
we use in programs to make decisions.
So, up to now, our programs have been
responding to use an input in various
ways, but always kind of doing the same
thing.
Sometimes we want to do different things,
depending on whether the user does
different stuff, or different conditions
happen in our program.
So, we want to do a different thing when
the mouse button is down from when it's
up.
we've seen some ways of doing that for
the mouse button being up and down.
We used the dragging mouse, mouse
dragging method.
And we'll look at a very general way for
making that kind of decision in
programming.
So let's look at an example.
So this is a very simple program that
does roughly what we've done before.
it draws points at the mouse position.
This is not very different from the
programs we've looked at last week except
for.
This draw method.
Rather than doing it in mouse drags, so
when the mouse was moved, we're doing it
in draw, and that means it's happening
every front.
that's a useful thing.
We'll talk about it this week in terms of
doing animations, where rather than
simply responding to input from the user,
we're.
We're proactively animating the stuff.
We need to do, do drawing actions and do
animation actions constantly.
Not just when there's user input.
That's why [INAUDIBLE] So what's
happening is every frame we're drawing a
point and, for the moment this doesn't
get us very much but uh, [UNKNOWN] But
we'll see there are other things we can
do and draw in todays lecture.
But in particular I'd like to look at
copying the kind of functionality we had
with mouse dragged using this draw
method.
Now the main difference here is that when
we use mouse dragged it would only work
when the mouse is down, now it's working
when the, both when the mouse is up and
when it's down.
If we do it this way, how would we go
about, only drawing the point, when the
mouse is pressed.
So, we need to only draw the point, if
the mouse is pressed.
We need to make that decision, if the
mouse is pressed, draw a point.
If not, don't draw it.
And the way we do that is use a method
called an if statement.
So we say, if mouse is pressed.
Draw a point [INAUDIBLE] this.
If I drag the mouse pointer around The
window, without the mouse pressed does
nothing, the minute I press the mouse we
start drawing.
So that's really nice.
Now, I'm going to go back my slides to
explain that.
So this is roughly what we saw, I'm using
an elipse rather than mouse points but
Pretty much is the same code of what if.
and something inside the if, which is
mousePressed, it's a variable.
and this is a variable which takes on two
values, it's either true, or it's false.
I'll come back to that in more detail.
And then, depending on whether it's true
or false it does different things.
So what that if does is if, the thing
inside the brackets, the variable inside
the brackets, in this case mousePressed
is true, then we do that line that comes
after it.
Good.
We draw the, we draw the ellipse to the
point.
And then we carry on and do the rest of
the program.
If this thing inside the brackets is
false, is not true - mousePressed is not
true, so the mouse isn't pressed (no
period) We don't do the line after each
statement we just carry on straight
ahead.
So this if allows us to make a decision
based on whether something is true or
false.
Wherever in this case, when the mouse is
pressed or not, we do different things.
If the mouse is pressed, we draw the
ellipse.
If it isn't pressed, don't.
We can do more complicated things.
So the first thing is, well what if I
want to do something special when the
mouse isn't pressed.
This is another example.
If the mouse is pressed, if mousePressed
is true, we draw a white background.
Then we do whatever else we want.
But in this case, we've also got
something different.
We've got, as long as the if, we've got
this thing, else.
What this means what happens when the if
bit isn't true.
So when mousePressed is false.
We do this other line, background zero,
we do the bit that's attached to else.
So we have an else, if which happens when
it's true and and else which happens when
it's false.
We draw the background and then we carry
on and do the rest of the [UNKNOWN].
Note that I've indented the two bits Of
code that controlled by the if and the
else.
That's not necessary, it's not a, a
crucial part of the program.
The program won't complain if you don't
do that.
But it makes it a lot clearer to
understand your code if every time you do
an if, you indent it a bit.
And that's just telling you.
O so you better move it in a bit.
And that tells you that this bit is
controlled by the if statement.
So this bit, is part of the code that's
Another thing you can do, is you can have
multiple commands from a single if
statement.
By combining them in these special curly
brackets.
You saw those curly brackets before, at
the start and end of setup and draw, and
mousePressed this is another instance.
And they're really, curly brackets are
always used to glue bits of code
together.
So that they can be used as if they were
a single line of code instead of context.
In this context, they're grouping them
together, so they're all controlled by
the mousePressed, and in this context,
your, or both these lines of code will
only happen if mousePressed is true.
[NOISE] So let's look.
What is mousePressed?
Well, I've shown you the slide a number
of times now.
There's lots of different types of data
that could be, you know represents on the
computer.
mousePressed is a variable that can only
take on two values, true and false.
It's what we call a Boolean variable.
It's named after the magician George
Bool, who developed a system of
mathematical logic based on values true
and false.
We can create a Boolean variable just
like any other variable.
We give it a title, we need to give the
title to the variable.
That is Boolean.
And when we set a value, we have to set
it either to false or to true.
So if we want to, can have a variable
which says whether the, background is
black, we can set that to true or false.
We can change the value of that variable
just like any other variable and this is
like a clever trick to do that.
The exclamation mark means not.
What that means is it means the opposite.
So not black is the opposite of black.
So if black is true, not black is false.
Black is false, not black is true.
So it inverts it.
And by setting black equals not black, we
switch it to its opposite.
So it's like, just like a little switch,
light switch
If we, if black is true and we hit not
black, black equals not black then
becomes false.
If it is false, it becomes true.
This is very useful because we can for
example when we click, we can have put a
line of code like this in mouse clicks.
And, as we as we turn that varlible,
variable on and off, whenever it's, mouse
is clicked we can switch the value of one
of our variables.
And maybe we can see that as an example.
So, let's first give an exam, a different
example of using the example I gave with
the else, [UNKNOWN] background.
[SOUND] Just going to swap things round.
So now we're using both an if bit and an
else bit.
So that something different will happen
in either case if the mouse is pressed.
Or the mouse is, to code the in
background.
And I'm not holding the mouse button
down.
And the background is white.
The minute I do it turns black.
Okay, let's try creating our own reading
variable.
Our own version of mousePressed.
And we can make that bo, be created
boolean variable.
Give, give it type boolean.
Set it, call it black.
And set it initially to false.
[NOISE] And we can use the variable black
in this if statement and, and, when you
run the program, it's not going to do
anything in interesting because black is
always false, you can't change it.
So let's change it when we click the
mouse.
[NOISE] So you put it in the
mousePressed, and we did, black equals
not black, exactly what I showed you.
And every time I click the mouse The
value of our black Boolean variable
switches, and the color of this, the
window changes.
Now, we can do other useful things.
We don't just have to use Boolean
variables.
what's happening here?
Well, this is what's called a Boolean
expression.
So we, we can use expressions as well as
variables, and a boolean expression is a
bit of maths that is a literal false.
This boolean expression is checking the
value of a key.
Has been pressed on keyboard.
What it's saying, if this key expression
is equal to the character bits so I'll
press the B key.
Now you notice I'm using two equal signs.
That's because a single equal sign as we
saw last week, means becomes equal to.
So, we're setting the value of the
variable.
Two equals signs, we're not setting the
value of the variable key doesn't become
b, we're checking if it is b.
We're, we're checking the value of a
variable.
So, we have to remember the difference
between these two equals signs, and
that's an common thing to trip up on.
It's easy to forget when there's single
equals and when there's double equals.
If you're using inside an if statement,
you should always be using a double
equals.
just to let you know, just, the single
quotation marks means I'm working with a
single character.
Double quotes means I'm working with
words and not strings of characters.
[SOUND] So we've got a bunch of specials,
we've seen a double equals and that's our
first boolean expression.
So if we have two values, a variable or a
value, we can check if they are equal to
each other And that's true if they're the
same, false if otherwise.
We can also test out things like we can
test whether one value is less than
another value.
So this little arrow here is true if the
thing on the left of it is less than the
thing on the right of it.
You've got a variant of that called less
than or equals.
The straight less than is false if the
two are the same.
Less than or equals is true if they're
the same, and if they're, if the thing on
the left is less than the thing on the
right.
Same goes for the greater than, the thing
on the left is more than the thing on the
right, or more than or equal to it.
We've already seen not, that means the
opposite of a Boolean value, and we also
have not equal to, so we can check if
something is worth checking they are the
same, we can check if they are different.
[NOISE] So we can think of, look at some
more complicated examples.
For example, what if we want the position
of the mouse to change the background
color?
And this is a boolean expression which
checks if the mouse position Is less than
half the width of the screen, so the
mouse position is less than the middle of
the screen the mouse x, so the mouse is
on the left of the screen.
So if we look here we have mouse position
there, where the red circle is.
Well, mouse x is going to be less than
half the width.
That's going to be true.
You're going to draw the background in
black.
If the mouse pointer is there on, where
the other circle is.
Mouse actually is going to be more than
the width of the screen.
So it's going to hit the else part.
Which is going to About them once.
We can even combine these things.
So we can have an if statement inside an
if statement.
So we can check if the mouseX is less
than the width divided by 2 and inside
that, we can check even further down,
divide this screen up again check this.
More than the width divided by 4.
So we can create a little line down the
middle of the screen.
So, if we look at the red point there,
that's less than half the width.
That's true.
It's more than a quarter of the width.
So that's true.
So we draw the background in black.
Put a point there.
Then it's still less than half, half the
width but it's more than a quarter of the
width.
So it's less than a quarter of the width.
So that the second if statement is false.
And we can engage down to this else bit.
Which is the else bit that the e no if
statement.
The secondary statement.
[UNKNOWN] in white.
The point's all the way over there.
The first if statement is false.
We never get to the second if statement
because the second if statement is inside
the first one.
We just get to the else part of the if
statement and it draws the screen white.
[SOUND] We can also combine together
boolean expressions in other ways.
So if you have two boolean expressions A,
A and B, we can combine them together
with this double ampersand here which
says If A, both A and B are true, so both
of these things are true, do something.
Or we could do it the other way around
and do these two lines, which say if A is
true or B is true, or both are true, so
only one of them have to be true and
[INAUDIBLE].
Together.
Let's have a look at this example.
This is a, an easier way of writing what
I've just done.
Doing this line.
So what that double-edge statement I
showed you a couple of slides back did,
was check basically if the mouseX is on
the left or the middle of the screen And
on the right is a line that's a quarter
of the way across the screen.
Instead of doing 2 if statements, we can
use an and.
Which checks, this expression.
If this point it's true.
Checks that expression, which is also
true.
For the total expression here both of
them have to be true 'cause I'm using
that double and, what we call and, and
because they're both true we do the true
part of the if statements.
If we move here, the first part is still
true, but the second part is false.
They're not both true so we'll move down
to the else part.
Assuming over there they're both false,
neither of them are true, use the else.
Now if we change from and to or we have a
different effect, so we're looking this
time if MouseX is more than the width
over two or less than width divided by
four, so we're doing kind of the
opposite.
We're looking at, you know, the side of
that little bar down the middle of the
screen.
So if we look at this one here, it's not
more than the width divided by two, but
it is less than width divided by four.
So that's true.
So one of them is true, so only one of
those needs to be true to, for the whole
all statement to be true, if we're using
all.
So we do the true part of the if
statement.
If we look there, well, mouse x greater
than width is still false, it's still not
true.
And this time, but it's no longer less
than width divided by 4, so that part's
also false.
They're both false, so we get the else.
If you look over here, well, mouseX is
more than width, that's true.
The other part is not true, it's still
false.
So we've, but one of them is still true,
so we go to the if path, because we use
them all.
So, that's the end of my lecture on
conditionals, if statements and we'll be
using some examples of if statements in
the main lectures.
Thank you very much.