Welcome to another additional lecture
about programming.
And so, this week I'm going to talk about
functions.
Now, we've actually seen functions
before.
In fact, we've seen them in two different
contexts and at the time they have seemed
like very different things but they're
actually the same thing and I"m going to
slide a detail what they are and how you
can work with them.
So this is the first time we have seen
functions.
Where we called above the surface line of
code we have to write size brackets 400,
600.
That is a function.
That is a call to a function, size of the
function, and by we're calling that
function in order to get its
functionalities [UNKNOWN] change the size
of the screen.
So, this line of code is what we call a
functional call.
We're using a function that somebody else
has created.
Let's look again in a little bit more
detail what this line [INAUDIBLE] does.
It's got a name, size, the name of the
function.
It's got parameters.
These are numbers that we are passing in
to the function.
Giving to the function, in order to
change the way it works.
And you've got these little bits of of,
of punctuation.
The parameters of a function always have
brackets around them, and they're always
separated by a comma.
And that's an important part of what
makes a function and a function call.
And then we have a semi-colon on the end
of the line, as we normally do.
This is the other context in which we've
seen a function.
Void draw.
Void draw is, we've seen it before, it's,
last week.
It's where, it's a container in which we
put code that we want to be run every
time the screen is refreshed.
Every time the screen [UNKNOWN].
So its a way of grouping k together and
have it happen at a set time but its also
a function and this is a function
definition.
On the last slide, we're looking at size,
where we're using an existing function.
Here, we are creating a function that's
processing the use.
So processing calls the draw function
when it's ready to redraw a screen.
So these are two sides of the same thing.
This is what it looks like when we create
a function so lets look again a little
bit more detail what happens.
Got the name of the function and the name
will be the same name we'll be using in
the function call.
The function has some content, the code
deduction happens when the function is
called.
It has the beginning, and an end and
they're defined by this curly bracket.
And I will come back to this later.
In the previous lecture, I said come back
in a few, feature we will come back to
them very soon to explain what they are.
But just now to imagine that really all
that's happening when we were on the
previous slide we talked about size, when
size is called, is that when we call
size, it's a function that contains a lot
of bunch of codes just like the draw
function contains code.
And that code as well, so that code
happened.
So when line is, draw is called here, the
line command will happen.
Which is itself another function, of
course.
Okay.
So, [SOUND] what can we do with that?
Well, the great thing is, we can create
our own functions.
We created our own function when we
created draw.
But we can create new functions that all
I've got to rewrite call them, and then
we can call those functions later.
So, at the top of the screen here we've
created a function called updateBall, and
it has two lines of code in it, so what
it's doing is not terribly important but
we've got one variable and we're adding
another variable to it.
That is our function and its pretty much
the types of things we've seen in void
draw or mouse pressed or set up.
All the things that we've used already
but draw setup, mouse press, mouse drag,
these are all built in things to
processing.
Their names have special meaning whereas
update ball that could be anything I just
created that's my function I can call it
whatever I want.
And I call whatever I want because it's
me that's going to call it.
And I'm jsut going to the use the name I
call it and the button here and draw
that's what I'm doing.
We've got update ball is being called.
And, as we can see, the name of the
function is the same as the update ball
function, up here, and that's how
processing knows that I'm referring to
this bit of code up here.
And we've got those brackets in there,
which we always need.
Well we've got a function.
Now this function has not parameters, I'm
not passing any parameters, but we still
need the brackets, so processing those
that I'm calling a function.
Even if they're empty, there's no
parameters, we still need the brackets.
Okay.
Good.
So, what does this give us?
Why is it useful?
Well it helps us in a number of ways the
first way is that it can break up your
code a little bit if you've got very
complicated code it become very difficult
to read.
And if you divide up your code so, if you
have hundreds and hundreds of lines of
code in draw you wouldn't know where
anything was.
So if you divide that into functions that
can get called and draw it simplifies
things.
We'll see another benefit of that system
in a minute.
Let's look at another example.
So, here's a slightly more complex
example.
So, this time UpdateBall has two
parameters.
Here we are.
This is how you create a function which
has parameters.
So it's all function, calling functions
with parameters like size, we've done
that quite a lot.
You're passing numbers in that gets you
to the function.
But this is how you actually create that
kind of function.
And it looks a lot like, well, it looks a
lot like a call in that You've got
brackets.
And inside those brackets are the two
parameters.
And they're separated by commas.
And that explains why we have brackets
after void draw.
Because it's a function.
And though it, and [INAUDIBLE], though it
doesn't have, take parameters.
Other functions do take parameters, and
functions and no parameters still have
the brackets to show that they're
functions.
It looks a like a variable definettion
because it's got a type and a name jsut
as variables have types and names and in
fact it is a variable you're creating a
variable.
And it's a variable that you can use
inside your function just like any other
variable.
So we're using it here.
SpeedX is used inside the function.
it only exists inside the function.
So you can't use it outside the function.
But within the function it's just like
any other variable.
If its like a variable where do we get
the value?
We don't, we're not doing float of speedX
equals to a, as we would if you are
creating a variable.
So where does the value come from?
Well, the value comes when we passing a
[INAUDIBLE] to it.
So when we call update ball.
If we pass a value in ball speed Y but it
could be a number it could just be 3.
That value is copied into the varible
that is that parameter in this case speed
Y.
Which can then be used inside the
function so that's how.
Parameters work.
So if you think when we're passing the
width, somewhere where size is created
there's a there's a parameter that says
float width and inside the size function
that float width variable gets used.
So To summarize, we define a parameter
with a type and name just like a
variable, we can use it just liek a
variable but the value of that variable
comes when we're passing a parameter in
as we call the function.
Okay so that's functions with parameters.
One last thing, as well as parameter all
these functions we've had to far have got
void.
This one's got somethign different in
there.
It's got float.
What does it mean to have float there?
Well sometimes as well as passing values
into a function you can get values back
out of the function.
And this is called the return value.
And by putting a float there, we're
saying the type of what is returned by
the function.
We're saying the return to float.
It means we can get a float value back
out of that function.
So if we're doing a calculation, we can
get a value back out.
Up to now, it's been void.
And void literally means nothing.
It means there is no value coming out of
this function.
It just does its stuff, but it doesn't
give anything back to you.
By saying float before update ball it's
saying, I'm going to give a float to you
after I'm done with my stuff.
And the thing that...
At she does that giving back is the
return command, return keyword.
What that does is hmm, it says what value
to give back so when I say return the
function stops and gives back the value
and after the return statement.
Just after return, I put whatever value I
wanted to give back.
So in this case, I'm returning the value
of the variable newBall ballX.
And what happens?
Well, when I make a call like this,
ballPosX equals updateBall, once the
function finishes.
I copied ballpos the value that's
returned new ball pos for X into my
variable ballpos X, so ballpos X is now
equal to whatever new ball X is.
I'm copying one into another.
So if we think of, of that whole process.
As I toss my parameters in they're copied
into variables in my function and can be
used in whatever way I like to do
whatever calculations or functionality I
want.
And then if I want I can have a resulting
calculation that ends up with a value
that I want to pop back In this case
newBallX and that gets copied back out of
the function.
So value is going to come back out of the
function copied into variables at the
point which we call the function outside
the function.
So we can get two way flow of
information.
From the, from the function inside in and
out of the function, which is where it's
useful in multi contents.
So, this is a classic example, a function
to add 2 numbers together.
It's going to name add.
It's got a content which does some
calculations.
A beginning and an end with those code
brackets.
It's got parameters to floating point
numbers a and b, they get added together,
and the.
That calculation produces the result,
which is the return type to pass the
[INAUDIBLE] and the return value is c,
this variable that I have created by
adding a and b together.
So I can pass values into this function,
doing calculations that pass them back
out and that's probably about the
simplicity.
And you can do the dozen of those things.
Okay, one last example.
So, don't bother, worry about what all
this code means, apart from that the fact
that we've got a complicated function
collideWithPaddle that has two
parameters.
Now the great thing about function is
that, because you've got a bit of code
that change, does different things
depending on different parameters there
are there, you could call it multiple
times with different parameters.
So, I can call collide paddle once.
With details of one paddel this comes
from a palm game where the paddle is
basically a tennis racket.
I can one set of parameters and pass them
in and do as functionality once.
And I can call an exactly same.
Function with another two sets of
parameters to do something different.
So, if I've got a tennis game, with two
paddles, the tennis rackets.
If I call it once with one with the X and
Y of one paddle, and once with the X and
Y of the other paddle, I only need one
bit of code.
But I'm handling [UNKNOWN] paddles.
And that's part of the benefit of doing,
sort of, a little bit more advanced
programming, because you can work how,
actually you can save a lot of time and
effort by realizing, well, I'm doing one
type of thing on lots of different types
of data, lots of different types of data.
Doing one action for lots of data.
One action for lots of objects.
If you can put that one action into a
function, then you can just record,
recall it multiple times with different
parameters.
And you don't have to rewrite much other
than that one line function.
It simplifies your code a lot, saves you
a lot of work, saves you a lot of errors.
You can miscopy the code, or if there's
an error in one bit of code, you can
forget to copy the fix into another code.
If it's all in a function, it becomes a
lot simpler
[INAUDIBLE].
Okay.
Thanks a lot.
That's all I want to say on function.