[MUSIC]
For those unfamiliar with
the notion of natural units,
we will briefly introduce
it in this short video.
High energy physics
deals with relativistic quantum processes.
The scale of the action is
the Planck constant hbar and
the scale of velocity is given
by the speed of light, c.
In the system of natural
units we set hbar = c = 1.
This means that we define
hbar as the unit of action and
c as the unit of velocity.
In such a system 1 second is equal to
approximately 3 x 10^8 meters.
As an added value the electric
charge is now dimensionless.
It often shows up as the fine
structure constant alpha,
which is the electrostatic potential
energy of two electrons at unit distance,
divided by the mass of the electron.
This constant is equal to 1/137
to a good approximation.
The system of natural units is of
great practical value since it
eliminates a lot of
constants from equations.
It does make them less heavy and
more easy to understand.
The basic unit, the electronvolt,
is defined as the gain in energy of
an electron when it traverses
the potential difference of 1V.
In the system on natural units,
the electronvolt is the common
unit of energy, momentum and mass.
A billion of these units correspond
roughly to the mass of the proton,
and thus sets the natural
scale of energy physics.
Whenever you want to convert a result
to units of the international systems,
you need to multiply by a combination
of hbar and c as shown in this table.
[MUSIC]