[MUSIC]
For those who do not feel sufficiently
familiar with the concept of virtual
particles, we propose a small review
of the phenomenon.
In a field theory, the field, or rather the potential
is created by emitting a vector boson,
which has a certain probability
of traveling to its destination.
We will compute a small example coming
from electromagnetic interactions.
Consider an electron which enters with
an energy E and a momentum vector p.
It emits a photon with an energy k_0 and
a momentum vector k,
and thus, changes its energy to E’
and its momentum to p’.
The energy-momentum
four-vector must be the same before and
after the emission of the photon, and
in particular the square of its length
must be the same before and after.
On the left, we get the mass
of the electron squared, and
on the right,
the expression I'm writing down here.
On the right, we obtain, thus,
the mass of the electron squared,
plus the mass of the photon squared,
plus a mixed term.
The mass of the electron cancels on the two
sides, and the mass of the photon is 0.
One obtains, thus, a relationship
between outgoing energy and
outgoing momentum,
which is in conflict with reality,
because the energy becomes smaller or
equal to the momentum.
But the outgoing photon did
not necessarily have a 0 mass.
It can be a virtual photon, which is the
mass squared that I'm now writing down.
It is not equal to 0,
indeed it can even be negative.
It is clear that such a virtual particle
cannot propagate in space and time.
I just remind you that the Feynman
diagrams are defined in
energy-momentum space.
Everything you see in the Feynman
diagram happens at the same time and
in the same place.
So we must, of course,
immediately reabsorb the virtual
particle by another pair of real
particles, as shown in this diagram.
There's a second current consisting
of an electron, which by entering and
exiting a second vertex,
will absorb the photon.
[MUSIC]