So, congratulations, all that hard work
paid off.
Or at least, congratulations if you
managed to hang in there this far.
and claiming all that hard work paid off.
My job now in this module is to show that
it indeed did pay, Because we're going to
unleash our Newfound powers on mobile
robots.
And this entire module is, dedicated to,
what's known as the Navigation Problem,
which means how do you make a robot drive
around in a world populated by obstacles
without slamming into things, and getting
safely to landmarks or goal positions.
So, in the first lecture, we're going to
return to this idea of behaviors.
And we're going to use control theory,
now, to describe what's actually going
on.
And I don't know if you remember.
But, we actually talked about behaviors
before.
These were these atomic primitive things
that the robots should be doing.
And then, by connecting them all together
we get the overall navigation system.
Now we probably know that behavior is
just code for a sub-system or a
controller, and connecting them up
together is code for a hybrid system.
So this is really what we need to do, we
need to revisit behaviors in the context
of control failure.
So first we need a model and in fact
almost always it pays off to start simple
so we're going to start with old friend
this point.
So the position of the robot is X, so X
is in R2, and I mean its a plain
[INAUDIBLE].
And I'm saying that I can control that
velocity, of this robots direction.
Now to compare us, as we've seen are
differential drive robots.
You can't really do this.
Instead, you have to control
translational velocities and rotational
velocities.
So, we can think of this really as for
the purpose of planning how we want the
robot to go.
And then we have to couple this to the
actual dynamics.
But, to start with, let's just say that
x.
is equal to U, well first of all what
does that look like in the ax plus bu
paradigm.
Well A is equal to zero so this is my A
matrix simply go to zero and my B matrix
is simply the identity matrix.
Well before we do anything else we need
to see whether or not we can actually
control this system and we formed a
controllability matrix B AB.
Well, A is zero, so this term is zero.
B is the identity matrix, so this is the
identity matrix.
The identity matrix is as full rank as
any matrix anywhere come.
So, clearly the rank of gamma is equal to
2, which by the way is the dimension of
the system.
So, we have a completely controllable
system.
We should be able to make the system do
What we would like it to do.
So we're going to start with what I call
the dynamic duo.
These are the key behaviors that you
always need.
No matter what your robot is going to do,
you always need to be able to go to a
goal location.
Or a landmark, or a waypoint.
You always need to be able to go to
somewhere, and you need to be able to do
it without slamming into things.
Without either one of those two, your
robot just ain't going to be able to do
what you want it to do.
So our job now is to design these two
behaviors using What we've already
learned.
So, we're going to do it rather simply.
We're going to actually simply say, you
know what, if my robot is here, and I
want to go in this direction, well, why
don't I simply say that this is equal to
my u, because that's equal to x dot.
So that's going to tell me, this is the
direction in which The robot is actually
going to do.
It's going to be moving or using my
handwriting but some pretty graphics.
This is what we are going to do.
We're going to figure out the direction
in which we want to move and then set u
equal to that desired direction.
Okay,
let's start with Go-To-Goal.
This is where the robot is.
Let's say their goal is located at x of
g.
Well, I want to go to the goal, so it's
really clear where I would like to go.
I would like to go in this direction,
xg-x is this vector, and I'm going to
call it e.
So, why don't I just put u=e, or u equal
to some constant k? Times Z,
well let's see what E dot in this case,
actually becomes.
Well, E dots is X gold dot, which is 0,
minus X dot.
And X dot, well, that's equal to U which
is equal to KE so E-dot becomes -ke.
Well, that's kind of good so if I have E
dot is -ke, does this work, does it drive
error down to zero.
Well, we know we have to check the
eigenvalues.
So, if k is just a scalar, as long as
this scalar is positive, we're fine.
If we want, for some reason, the matrix
k.
We just have to pick a matrix k that has
positive eigenvalues.
So, if k is a scaler and positive, we
know that the system is asymptotically
[INAUDIBLE] stable.
If we pick k as a matrix.
For instance, it could be a diagonal
matrix, you know? 10, and A 1000, say
seems silly, but why not.
This is a positive, definite matrix means
that the eigen values are all positive.
I have a minus sign here so I need to
worry about the negative of K in this
case the eigen values would be all
negative.
So, if you have that I would go with K
constant but if you have this you will
indeed drive the error to 0 which means
that we have solved the go to go problem.
There are some concerns, though in fact
there's just one.
A linear controller means that you have a
bigger vector the further away you are,
which means that you're going to go
faster towards the goal.
The further away you are.
Which doesn't, to be honest, make
complete sense.
So what we should do, is we should, in
practice, moderate this.
To make, maybe the game smaller, when
we're far away.
Or make the game constant somehow.
Because we don't want to go faster when
we're far away.
That doesn't quite make sense.
And you can play around with this.
As long as K is positive we're actually
fine.
And what we're going to implement on the
robot is this choice of K.
It's a K that makes the norm of U reach
some Vnot, so here is Vnot when you're
kind of far away, and then it's going to
not go faster when you further way, and
then when you get closer to the goal,
meaning when the arrow goes down You
start slowing down, and in fact, if you
try to be a little creative in how you
pick your K, this K here is the K that
corresponds to this plot then.
That's the K that we're going to be
looking at, but you don't have to do
that.
in fact, a lot of robotics involves
clever parameter tuning and Tuning of
these weights.
But the whole thing, point here, I want
to make is that you want to make sure
that you don't go faster when you're
further away because that actually
doesn't make entirely sense.
Okay, we know how to go, you to go to
goal.
Let's avoid obstacles.
Well, if I wanted to go towards the
obstacle, I would simply pick xo-x=u, or
some scaled version of that.
Well, now I want to avoid the obstacle.
Why don't I just flip it? And that's now
x-xo, instead, so flipping it means, I'm
just going to avoid the obstacle.
And in fact, that's what we're going to
do.
Let's just pick u=K*e, where K is a
positive constant,
and e, now, is x obstacle minus x.
Well, if I do that, I get E dot is ke,
which is actually an unstable system.
And it's unstable in the sense that the
error is not stabilized.
'Cuz the error is the distance to the
obstacle instead.
We're avoiding the obstacle.
Obstacle.
Now it's a little scary to have on
purpose an unstable system in there but
as you will see we don't worry too much
about it because we need to make sure
that the robot actually does not drive
off to infinity which it would if we were
was unstable.
the other thing that a little weird, so
this is if I use u=k(x-x0).
The other is, that it's, it's a rather
cautious system in that we seem to be
avoiding obstacles that are also behind
us even that doesn't entirely make sense
and we also cared less about the obstacle
the closer we get which.
Absolutely makes no sense, because we
should care more the closer we get.
Well, the solution is again, make k
dependent on e, or actually the
distances, so the normal e.
And to aviod this being overly cautious,
we are actually going to switch between
behaviors, and in fact, what we're going
to do is using something like a induced
mode, the sliding mode to very gracefully
Combine goal to goal and avoid obstacles
but for now let me just point out that
one clever thing for instances is say
that you want to care more about to
obstacle u closer you get, so you want u
to be bigger the closer to the, the
obstacle you get.
So in this case this was the K that we
used, then in fact this is that K that
I'm going to use to implement things but,
again I want to point out that you want
something that you don't care so much
when you far away.
And you care a lot when you close.
The reason I have an Epsilon here which
is a small number is just to make sure
that this thing doesn't go up to infinity
when they normally is 0.
Things going off to infinity is typically
not that good of an idea.
Okay so we know how to build the
individual control modes.
Now we also saw that choice of weights
matter.
you should be aware, again, that there
isn't a right answer in how to pick these
weights, and depending on the
application, you may have to tweak the
weights to make your robot more or less
skittish or cautious.
But the structure still is there.
What's missing, though first of all, is
to couple this X dot is equal to U model
to the actual robot dynamics.
And we're going to ignore that question
all through this module.
And devote the last module of the course
to that question.
But what we do need to do is make
transitions between goal to goal and
avoid obstacles.
And that's the topic of the next lecture.
Before we conclude, though, let's
actually deploy.
This dynamic duo on our old friend, tho
compare robots, to see what would happen
in real life.
So, now we've seen, in theory, how to
design this dynamic duo of, robot
controllers.
In par-, in particular, we've seen these
2 key behaviors, goal to goal and avoid
obstacles.
And, now, let's actually deploy them.
For real on our old friend, the [UNKNOWN]
mobile robot.
As always, I'm joined by with Sean Pierre
Delacroix here, who will conduct the
affairs.
And, first we're going to see the go to
gold behavior in action.
And.
What we now know is that what this
behavior really is doing is looking at
the error between where the robot is,
right there, and where the robot wants to
be, in this case this turquoise piece of
tape.
And then globally asymptotically
stabilizing this error in the sense that
it's driving the error down to zeros.
So, JP why don't we see the [INAUDIBLE]
make the error go away.
So, as you can see, the robot is going
straight for the goal, and the error is
indeed, decaying down to zero.
And this is how you encode things like
getting to a point.
You make the error vanish.
Very nice.
Thank you.
So now, we're going to run act two of
this drama.
now the robot's sole ambition in life is
not driving into things, and things, in
this case, is going to be me.
one thing that's going to be slightly
different from what I did in the lecture,
is that I am not a point, meaning it's
not just a point but in fact an obstacle
with some spread that the robot is going
to avoid.
In fact, what we're going to do is we're
going to first of all ignore everything
that's behind the robot because it
doesn't care about avoiding things that
are behind it.
And the things in front of it, it's going
to sum up the contributions from all the
sensors and it's going to care a little
bit more about things ahead of it than
on.
Its sight, so J.P., let's take it away.
Let's see what can happen here.
So, here I am.
Oh, no. All right.
Very nice.
Don't hit me. Thank you.
[SOUND] Perfect.
We have a perfectly safe robot that is
not driving into professors at all.
and with that I think we compute.
Thank you.