At the last, lecture we designed the
dynamic duo of robotic behaviors, mainly
goal to goal and avoid obstacle.
And the question I want to talk about in
today's lecture is really how do we
combine these two? So Let's say that I
actually have, as always, a go to here, a
goal here, and an obstacle here with go
to goal telling me to go in this
direction, and avoid obstacle telling me.
To go in this direction which is straight
away from, from the obstacle.
How do I actually combine these two? And
the question is really this, right.
It, is there some blended version of the
two directions we should go in or should
we actually switch between the different
behaviors in a hard way, so that the
winner takes all.
And, these are really the main two
options at our disposal.
And what I want to do today is just
discuss almost philosophically.
What are the pros and cons associated
with these two options?
And then in subsequent lectures, we will
be a little more technical in terms of
how to actually build these so-called
arbitration mechanisms.
Some mechanisms for transitioning in and
out of different behaviors.
So the philosophical question is really
this right.
Can robots can chew gum and walk at the
same time meaning can they do two things
or should they do two things or should
they really only be doing, doing one
thing.
So the same cartoon here over on the left
where the black arrows again are the
directions in which we think that the
robot should go.
So if we're going with the hard switches
paradox time.
What's going on is when we're let's say
far away from the obstacle then the
robots should be doing nothing but going
towards the goal which I've illustrated
here with the, a red arrow saying that
right now that's all the robot is trying
to do.
And then when it gets lets say closer to
the obstacle it switches completely.
To the other direction which is, in this
case, straight away from the obstacle.
And the reason one might want to do
something like this is that, we're
actually designing the behaviors, to do
something really well.
The obstacle avoidance behavior is
designed to, not drive into things.
And hopefully we design it right, so that
we can actually trust that, if we're only
avoiding driving into things, indeed We
do not drive into things, or if we are
only trying to a goal, than we have
designed our controller to be as
methodically stable, so that we can
actually trust, trust that we end up at
the goal.
So, the pro the benefit we're doing hard
switches is then that we can actually
trust these systems, that they are doing
what they were designed to do from a
performance guarantee point of view.
Now there is a drawback with this.
So, if you are a robot and you're just
switching ma, ma, ma, ma, ma, back and
forth between going to the goal and
avoiding an obstacle.
Let's say you're riding this robot.
It's a really bumpy ride.
Or in general it, it's a, you're going to
get, rather, jerky motions out.
And as we've already seen, if we're using
odometry, for instance, to knowing where
we are, then, the odometric readings can
get really, a little bit messed off, up
if you start switching quickly.
So, there is, the, the, the potential for
having a really bumpy ride and
theoretically this bumpy ride can
translate into Zeno behaviors where we're
forced to switch very, very, very
quickly, In fact infinitely quickly in
the worst possible scenario between the
two behaviors.
So on the one hand we can trust that the
system is doing what it supposed to be
doing, but it's doing it in a rather
Bumpy and unpleasant way.
So that's the, the, the deal with, with
the hard switches.
The other alternative, of course, is to
blend the two behaviors.
So the answer to the philosophical
question here would be, yes.
Robots can, indeed, chew gum and walk at
the same time.
They can avoid slamming into things and
going towards goals.
And, I'm going to argue that all of us,
when we're walking around were trying
both, not to walk into other people and
go to the particular place we're
interested in going to.
So we do it all the time.
Why shouldn't we let the robots do it? So
the pro or the, the benefit we're doing
this would be to get a smoother ride when
we're not switching between behaviors
rapidly.
we avoid typically that the Zeno issue.
So this would be an argument for
blending.
An argument against it is that we no
longer can completely trust that we have
guarantees that our system does what it's
supposed to be doing.
In the sense that now we're not only
avoiding obstacles, we're kind of
avoiding obstacles but we're kind of
doing something else and it's not clear
that we can actually guarantee anymore
that we're staying clear of obstacles or
if we are going to the goal while not
only doing that but something then are
going to indeed hit the landmark.
So there are potential drawbacks with
with blending the behaviors and that one
of them that is that it's hard to
guarantee what's actually going to, to
happen.
So, lets first of all build some both of
these solutions and then we're going to
to take some kind of stand here where
we're going to prefer, prefer one over
the other.
So lets actually start with with the
switched hybred atomatom.
So, again we have the robot, the goal,
and the obstacle, and what were going to
do is we're going to used the behavior
that we assigned last time.
So we're saying that we're controlling
the volocity of the robot directly.
So lets say X dot is equal to U.
This is in R2, because this is a planar
robot, so it's a two-dimensional control
signal.
And let's say for the sake of simplicity
that the go to goal behavior is simply a
proportional regulator driving X to the
goal.
And as long as KGTG is positive, we've
seen that this is an asymptotically
stable controller.
And we're also using the avoid obstacle
controller that's just simply pushing us
away from, from the goal.
So this is actually an unstable
controller that's driving us away,
straight away from the, from the obstacle
point.
So let's say that we have these two these
two behaviors.
Then, here would be a hybrid automaton
that switches between these two
behaviors.
So the robot is going towards the goal,
until the distance to the obstacle, so
this distance here, d do is less than or
equal to some critical safety distance.
So when we're too close to the obstacle,
we switch and then after we've switched
we're now avoiding the obstacle and we're
going to do that until we're no longer
unsafe and what I've written here is that
d obstacle should be.
Strictly greater than d safe plus some
epsilon.
And the reason we want this epsilon here
is that we don't want to end up switching
too quickly so if we get rid of the
epsilon, we're immediately in this
situation where we might have ZnO or very
very rapid switches so this would be a
switched hybrid automaton that switches
between behaviors and its kind of clear
how we would design that.
Blending on the other hand is not as
straight forward, so lets say that we
have the same setup as before and lets
define a blending function as a function
of the distance to the obstacle.
So this blending function is going to be
For a given distance do its just going to
take on a value between 0 and 1 and the
idea is that if this is 1 say we're only
going to the goal and if its 0 we're only
avoiding obstacles.
Here's an example, where sigma is 0.75
which means that I take you know 75
percent of this.
Vector and I take 25% of this vector.
That's what the blending is doing and
what I'm doing now is I'm taking this
little snippet, adding it on here and
getting this as my new direction of
travel.
So if I do that I get the green arrow
here and the green arrow would now be the
blended direction.
So x dot is going to be 0.75 in this case
of going towards to goal and 1 minus 0.75
which is 0.25 of avoiding obstacles.
So this is a very natural way in which
you can actually blend blend these two
types of behaviors now you have to design
the, the blending function and the very
standard way to do it is something like
An exponential like this.
So, what's going on is sigma is basically
one for large do values and when sigma is
1 that means they were only going towards
goal. Then as we get closer to the goal d
not becomes or do becomes small, then all
were doing is avoiding obstacle.
And, basically, the parameter here, you
get the tweak, is beta.
Which tells you, how quickly is this
thing going to decay off? Is it going to
go like this, or is it going to be
slower? That's, that's really the, the
design choice we would have to, to make.
If we're using this kind of exponential
blending function,
which for the record is quite standard.
so the punch lines behind this lecture is
really that we,we have two choices when
it comes to, switching, or mixing
behaviors.
One is to
switch hard between avoiding obstacles
and going to goal.
And the other is to kind of blend them.
And as we've seen, there are drawbacks
and benefits with both of them.
So, if you're switching hard, you can
guarantee that your system doesn't do
anything stupid but you get a bumpy ride
potentially out of it.
If you're blending, you get something
much nicer and smoother out but, the
guarantees are kind of gone.
So of course, what we want to do is have
our cake and eat it.
Meaning we want to take what's best with
both of them.
So, we want to get the performance
guarantees that the hard switches give us
but the smooth ride that the blending
gives us.
And the answer to that is surprisingly
enough going to be this induced Sliding
mode that we've already talked about.
That is going to give us the means by
which we can do.
We can walk and chew gum at the same
time.
Yet, somehow guaranteeing that we don't
trip over just because we started to chew
gum.
So in the next lecture, we're going to
start approaching this issue.