So, in the last lecture, we saw that,
even for rather un-, scary looking
environments.
Let's say that we had, slight non
convexities, or even extended convex
obstacles.
the dynamic duo of behaviors, go to goal
and avoid obstacle,
no longer was enough to negotioate these
environments.
And we saw that we really needed some way
of flowing a long the boundary of an
obstacle in order to be able to get
around in the world.
And today, I want to talk about this
missing piece.
The missinig behavior which is a wall
following behavior.
And what I want to do now is really just
introduce it and then in the next lecture
introduce it in a more systematic way as
to induce mode when you're trying to
avoid sliding or avoid type 1 Zeno.
So, here is the question.
How do you actually follow walls? Or when
I say walls what I really mean are
boundaries of.
boundaries around obstacles.
So let's, let's start simple.
Here is, as always, an obstacle and I
have a disk around it where, this is my
safety disk.
Well, avoid obstacle is going to tell me,
you know what, I want to move straight
away from this From this obstacle.
Well, how do I , which direction do i go
in, in order to maintain a constant
distance from this obstacle? Well what I
need to do is, I need to flow, right,
along the boundary of this, this region.
Well, what this means is that here, I
need to go in this direction.
And what I really need to do then is take
The direction, given to me by my avoid
obstacle behavior, and flip it down, like
this.
And this is a negative pi over 2, or a
negative 90 degree flip.
So, that's what I need to do.
I need to flip it down by 90 degrees,
like this.
And now, I'm going to call this FW, for
Follow-wall, and follow-wall is now,
simply, like I said, a flip down of 90
degrees, which this curious looking
matrix here is actually achieving.
And I may want to scale it, so I may have
some scaling that's making this Longer or
shorter, depending on, I don't know.
Whatever concerns you may have.
Now, I should point out that, this matrix
here, I can write as a rotation matrix,
that corresponds to a pi over 2.
Sorry, negative pi over 2 flip.
so I can actually write this as alpha,
which is the scale, times the rotation
matrix, that is, the flip, times u, avoid
obstacle, because that is ultimately the
behavior that I'm, that I'm flipping.
So, this tells me that the way to move
around this obstacle, is to simply take
my avoid obstacle behavior, and flip it.
That's as simple as that.
So, there is a problem though.
I can actually flip in 2 different
directions.
Not only can I go like this, I can also
go like that.
So 1 question 1 should ask of course is
which direction should I go in, but the
other question is how do I even
mathematically describe these 2 options?
Well, what I have, what we saw before
was, we called it U clockwise follow
wall, and the clockwise follow wall
corresponds to a negative pi over 2 flip
to avoid the obstacle.
A counter clockwise follow wall, which
means follow it in the other direction,
well that is simply a pi over 2 flip of
the void obstacle behavior.
So if I introduce this thing that I've
already called the rotation matrix, this
is simply an operation that does this
flip over vector.
If I have a vector here.
V, and I want to flip it by phi.
This new thing here, is simply r of, it's
not phi, it's theta.
R of theta times v.
This is how I get this new, this new
rotated vector.
So the rotation matrix is cosine theta
negative sine cosine.
That's the form of this linear operator
that's flipping vectors at certain angle.
Well what we've already seen is that the
clockwise follow-wall it's a negative pi
over 2 flip so this behavior is simply
equal to alpha times, this matrix times,
uAO.
Now the counterclockwise, while I can
write that in the same way, it's just a
pi over 2 flip instead of a negative pi
over 2 flip, which gives me the following
expression.
So, I actually have very, very clean
expressions for how I should make my
flip,
meaning how I should proceed along the
boundary of the obstacle.
And this works even if their obstacle is
not just a point, because all I really
did was I took a void obstacle, a void
obstacle behavior and, and flipped it.
Now we don't know which direction to go
with them.
So lets say that we have this situation,
right.
[SOUND] I'm going towards the goal,
and then let's say when I'm here, I now
want to switch to a follow-wall behavior.
Which direction to choose? it's not
entirely clear.
Right? I, if the robot only sees what's
going on around here, for instance, how
does the robot know what the world looks
like? We haven't built a map of anything.
So, you could either go clockwise,
which in this case turned out to be the
long way around, or you can go
counter-clockwise, but it's really not
clear how we should make this choice.
But here's one thing one can observe, is
that go to goal here is wants to move you
kind of upwards a little bit.
So maybe we can let go to goal make the
choice for us.
Go to goal once the drive was a little
bit in this direction, not at all in that
direction.
So that's the idea we have here at, that
there is no obvious answer, there is not
then obvious right choice given what
local information the robot has.
The robot doesn't know globally what the
world looks like.
So given that we only know locally what's
going on may be we can lack this goal to
goal behavior.
Decide which direction we should go in.
So let's, let's try to make this a little
bit more mathematically precise, what it
means to let the goal to goal behavior
decide.
Here, goal to goal, the angle was wrong
here.
Goal to goal wants to go in this
direction.
Right? So here, goal to goal wants to
drive us up.
Limit up, so may be we should take
follow-wall up.
So this would be u clockwise.
Well, u counter clockwise or u
follow-wall counter clockwise wants to go
down.
And note, that this angle is less than pi
over 2, but this angle, the absolute
value of it, is greater than pi over 2.
So we should be able to look at this
angle to determine.
Where we should go, but lucky for us
there's a very simple way of checking
these angles.
If I have two rectors v and w I can take
what is called the inner product of those
t which is simple v transposed to w.
Well that's equal to the absolute values
of, or the, the length of vectors times
cosine of this angle in between them.
And if this angle is less than pi over 2,
then cosine is going to be positive.
If it's greater than pi over 2, then
cosine is going to be negative.
So all we need to do.
It's to look at the sine of this thing,
to figure out whether or not we're kind
of pointing in the right direction.
So, here is a test.
Check go to goal inner product with
follow wall clockwise.
If that's positive, we should go
clockwise.
So, in this scenario, again.
Again, we're pointing in this direction,
here is the follow wall, so this, go to
go.
Here is u clockwise.
This angle, is less than pi over 2, which
means that, this situation is satisfied.
Here is u counter-clockwise, so this
angle is greater than pi over 2.
So, that means that the other condition
is not satisfied.
So what we actually have is a local
check.
We compute the direction that two
different follow-wall behaviors would
take us in.
Then we just take this inner product with
go-to-goal behavior, and we check the
sign.
And whoever comes up with a positive sign
is the winner.
and that's the direction we choose to go
in.
Now, there is a problem with this of
course.
And that's that if you remember our
labyrinth, or our little maze here,
right.
If I'm following wall, you know what, I'm
going to follow it all the way around.
And I don't want to keep going
indefinitely around and around, right.
So then I'm just spiraling.
At some point, if here's the goal.
I want to release and go towards the
goal.
So one thing that we don't know yet is.
When do we actually release the
follow-wall behavior? When do we stop
following walls and start approaching
goals again? The other question is, you
know what, we had avoid obstacle we had
the rotation matrix, that flips either up
or down, depending when we're going
clockwise or counterclockwise.
And then I have this little alpha there
Is there some natural or systematic way
on which we can think about the alpha?
And that is going to one One of the
things we will discuss in the next, the
next lecture.