So after all this work that we've gone
through, we've seen how to design control
systems, we've seen how to take different
controllers and put them together in a
hybrid navigation architecture.
We've seen how to deal with practical
issues, like the fact that obstacles are
indeed, not points, and that we're never
going to be able to measure exactly where
we are, so we need to factify the guards.
we have tweaked our parameters.
We're actually ready to do it for real.
So the presentation, or slide part of
this lecture is very short.
It's this.
Enough talk.
Let's do it.
So now, we are indeed ready to, see all
our hard work pay off by deploying these,
rather elegant algorithms that we've
developed on the actual robots.
And as always, I'm here with, J.
P.
DeLacroix/g, and we are going to, take
our old friend, the computer,
differential drive mobile robot, through
a series of.
Obstacle courses where the obstacles
become become more and more complicated
and as you can see, the first set up is a
convex/g obstacle.
We saw in the lecture that in theory, the
robot can actually get stuck in one of
these local minimum where the goal to
goal and obstacle avoidance behaviors
will cancel each other out.
In practice, for an obstacle of this
size, that ain't going to happen.
Because the world is indeed a noisy place
and.
The noise will always kick the robot out
of these particular local minima.
So, what we're going to see first is
goal-to-goal and avoid obstacles and
together that should be enough to have
the robot navigate this single convex
obstacle.
So as we can see the robot starts in a
go-to-goal behavior.
It approaches the obstacle, and there,
the infrared sensors picks up the
obstacle, and the robot successfully
navigates around it.
Now.
It's safe to go back to go-to-goal, and
as we can see, the robot successfully
managed to navigate this particularly
simple environment with only two
behaviors.
So now, let's take our two favorite
behaviors, go-to-goal and avoid obstacle,
and set them up to fail.
As we saw in the lectures, there's really
no way for these two behaviors to
successfully negotiate a.
Non-convex, obstacle.
In this case we have a cul-de-sac that we
will try to get around using onlt these
two behaviors, but we are not, to be
completely honet, honest, expecting this
to go all that well.
So, the robot starts out in a go to-go
mode and it is entering the cul-de-sac,
and it's going to start avoiding the
obstacles here, but it doesn't quite know
where to go, because.
It's pulled away, but the goal to goal is
pulling it forward and the poor robot is
completely confused and really has no of
punching its way out of this cul da sac
with only two behaviors.
And as we can see the end result is
somewhat disastrous.
So that was rather depressing.
The poor robot was stuck in the cul de
sac without really anywhere to go and
obstacle avoidance and going to go and
kept pulling it in different directions
and it ended with a mild disaster.
We have now seen in the lectures that the
way around this problem is really to
introduce a third behavior, induced mode
Follow-wall, which will allow the robot
to purposefully make its way out of the
culdesac and once it has a clear shot to
the goal, and sufficient for forward
progress has been made follow-wall will
be released and go-to-goal will again
take over.
So JP, let's see the grand finale here,
with the full blown hybrid navigation
architecture in.
Action.
The robot starts out, again, in a
go-to-goal mode, and enters the culdesac,
and what's going to be different now, is
the obstacle avoidance is going to be
replaced by a follow-wall, and the robot
purposefully makes its way out of the
culdesac along one of the obstacle arms.
And, as you can see.
The problems we had before with the
confusion.
And being pulled back and forth between
the 2 different behaviors, is no longer
there.
now the robot has successfully navigated
around the obstruction.
And is back into the goal to goal
behavior.