Hello and welcome to Glue Lecture 6.
Today's lecture should kind of walk you
through a little bit of this idea of how
robots are going to behave using the
framework introduced in Module 6 this week
in Dr Edgersett's lecture.
So hopefully it'll help you with Quiz 6.
So this week in lecture, Dr Edgersett
introduced this kind of scary looking
hybrid automaton that has lots of
complicated guard conditions.
And today we're just kind of going to
break through those and sort of show you
how we might move through this automaton
as we try to navigate towards a goal.
So we have these behaviors.
Go to goal, this is actually a controller,
you go to goal, follow wall, navigating
around the obstacle counterclockwise.
Avoid obstacle and follow the wall of the
obstacle navigating in the clockwise
direction.
So, we're going to answer this question,
what does this look like on a robot?
So in our little set up we have some robot
here.
He has a heading, given by this black
arrow.
We have our obstacle in red.
Around this obstacle I've drawn a, a line
in grey that represents this delta
distance away from the obstacle at which
we need to switch to avoid obstacles when
we get inside.
And then here, the little orange star is
our goal.
So now, where does the robot wake up in
terms of this high level description of
the control?
So this, this first arrow points right
here into u, u go to goal, which means the
go to goal controller will be running
right when the robot wakes up.
So this is the behavior we start with.
So what does this look like in our
scenario?
We have this vector here drawn in red.
It points to our goal.
And this is the direction along which u go
to goal will drive us.
And remember that on the robot, kind of at
that lower level, we're thinking of these
controllers with these equations.
Right?
So our go to goal controller is going to
cause us to drive our current state x to
this goal using some gain given in k.
Likewise with the, with the avoid obstacle
controller.
And then with follow wall, we're just
rotating the direction that you AO, avoid
obstacle controller takes us and we're
rotating that by 90 degrees depending on
whether we're going clockwise or
counterclockwise which way the 90 degrees
goes.
And remember that's given by this rotation
matrix here.
So, if you see something like, you know
where you have, say 0,1,1,0, notice that
this could be a rotation matrix.
You know, there might be some theta that
satisfies what this matrix looks like that
means that this matrix is causing a
rotation of a vector.
Anytime you see kind of, of a symmetrical
structure like this in a, in a matrix, say
on Quiz 6, keep that in mind.
And remember that our robot is
implementing this, this, controller up
here U in terms of VNW and our actuator
wheel commands.
And we know how to go with, between VNW
and the wheel commands back in Module 2,
that's where we learned that.
So, while we have this high level kind of
controlling automaton, there are these
other things going on kind of at the lower
level on the robot.
But for now we'll just think okay we know
that the u go to goal is running, our
robot is going to drive towards that star,
directly towards it.
So let's watch that as it happens, they're
driving towards it and now .
All of a sudden, we're at this point
where, where within delta away from our
obstacle.
So let's go back to our automaton, and see
if that changes anything.
And indeed, two of the guard conditions
are that, when we're inside of this radius
delta, we might have the condition where
we need to change.
So let's look at the other half of both of
those conditions, where.
We're looking at this inner product
between these vectors defined by this,
these control laws, the, the go to goal
controller and the follow wall controller,
both clockwise and counterclockwise.
And this is really going to determine,
once we're inside this delta range, do we
follow the obstacle clockwise or
counterclockwise.
And we were talking about vec-, vectors
here in the Euclidean space.
This, so we have our follow wall vector
and our UA, avoid obstacle director this
-- vector, this is the direction we would
drive in if we were operating under this
controller or this controller or this
controller.
So now, how do we kind of decode this
condition of this inner product?
So with these, with these vectors in
Euclidean space our dot, our inner product
is just a dot product.
And so we can write it as the magnitudes
of both of these vectors here, for
example, with the clockwise follow wall
controller.
And then the angle between those two guys.
So, this is really the important term,
right?
Because this is going to vary between 1
and negative 1, in the following way.
So if the two vectors are, are collinear,
then the angle between them is 0.
The cosine of that is 1.
So that would satisfy this condition,
right?
When they're perpendirect, you know, exact
perpendicular to each other, the cosine of
that is 0.
So we did not satisfy this condition.
And then of course, when they're
completely open and the angle between them
is pi, we get this negative 1 value.
So we know that our vector is this cosine
term is going to vary between these values
and if it's 0 or negative 1, no matter
what these magnitudes are, it's kind of
irrelevant.
So really, what we're worried about is
when we're in between these two cases
between 0 and 1 where this is going to be
greater than 0.
So you can kind of see now directly from
the picture in this case, my angle between
the clockwise and the avoid obstacle is a
little bit smaller than between these two.
Right?
Because these are going to add up to 180.
This one looks like a little bit less than
90.
So that means we're going to follow that
clockwise rotation that way.
So we can see that these two conditions
are satisfied now.
And so we move from operating under the go
to goal controller to now the clockwise
follow wall.
And at this point when this is true, we
note the time detail because that's the
important condition for whether we switch
later given by this guy down here.
So we note the, the detail what time it is
or not, not what time it is but, how far
away we are at the goal.
Here at d tal, so we, we mark the distance
from our goal at d tal.
And now we follow wall.
So we're going to follow this new kind of
pink vector.
The robot's going to keep moving forward.
And now, we've actually gotten a little
bit closer to the goal, right?
So let's go back to that automaton.
Let's look at the condition that might
cause us here, we're in this state now.
What might cause us to leave is if we get,
within the distance delta.
Well that's not going to happen, right?
Because we're following the wall.
Or if we get closer to the goal than we
were at time detail or at time tell so the
distance at time tell.
And then again this other inner product
that we need to consider.
So lets look at those two vectors now so
here we have follow wall, avoid obstacle,
and go to goal.
Now, we're interested in whether the
cosine of the angle between these two
vectors avoid obstacle and go to goal is
between 90 and 0.
And of course in this case we can see that
that's more than ninety so we're going to
stay with following wall because we don't
satisfy both of the conditions to go back
to go to goal.
So we continue to follow wall Continue to
follow wall and now, we're getting closer
to that point where, now this angle here
is less than 90.
Our inner product between these two
vectors is now greater than 0, and so we
switch.
These are our two conditions we needed to
satisfy right, we switch back from follow
wall to go to goal.
We've made it all the way, and this is
kind of where we're home free.
Because we're not going to encounter any
more obstacles.
But, if we did, we'd kind of go through
that whole process again.
So you can see how this overall hybrid
automaton switching our controllers.
We get to these, to this what we did,
right?
This path around the obstacle.
And it would make the goal.
So I hope that this helps you with some of
the kind of high-level behavior questions
you are going to have on quiz six this
week and check the forums for more help.
And good luck.