[MUSIC]
I'm gonna say a little bit about how
this course as a whole is structured.
Right, we're really covering three topics.
Covering limits,
derivatives, and integrals.
And for each of those three topics,
we're looking at three different things.
We're looking at the definition,
the sort of concepts behind it.
Looking at techniques,
sort of how we work with those concepts.
And then we're looking at applications,
what can we do with it.
So, take a look at limits, all right.
We learned about the definitions for
the concepts behind limits at first, and
then we learned some techniques for
doing computations involving limits.
Say, using a little bit of algebra or
thinking about infinity.
And now we want to think
about an application.
Why do we care about limits?
Well the reason that we care about
limits was because of the derivative.
Right?
We use the limits to define the derivative
and to introduce some of
the concepts of the derivative.
And now that we've introduced
the concept of the derivative,
we wanna go into the techniques or
the computational questions.
How do you actually compute a derivative?
And in order to do those kinds of
computations, we have to think about
how would you calculate the derivative
of a product of two things,
if you knew the derivative
of those two things.
Or how would you calculate
the derivative of a fraction if you knew
how to differentiate the numerator and
the denominator separately?
Those are the kinds of questions
that'll occupy us now.
[MUSIC]