[MUSIC].
We will quickly calculate the kinematics
for the decay of a heavy parent nucleus P,
to an alpha particle, and
a daughter nucleus D.
The conservation of energy requires that
energy gained in the form of missing mass
will be transformed into the kinetic
energy of the daughter nucleus and
the alpha particle.
The masses of the two nuclei are both
large, compared to the binding energy.
We can thus do a non-relativistic
calculation with T = 1/2 Mv^2.
For heavy nuclei, which have a much larger
mass than the alpha particle, the velocity
of the daughter nucleus will be negligible
compared to that of the alpha particle.
It is in fact reduced by
the ratio of M_alpha and M_D.
Therefore, most of the Q value is
converted into kinetic energy for
the alpha particle, and
the reaction of course,
only takes place when the Q
value is greater than zero.
The kinetic energy of the daughter
nucleus will be much smaller
than that of the alpha particle.
When neglecting the differences
in binding energy between nuclei,
we have an M_alpha/M_D roughly equal
to 4/(A-4).
This allows us to approximately calculate
the kinetic energy of the alpha particle
and the daughter nucleus.
[MUSIC]