[MUSIC]
We've done a bunch of area
calculations at this point, so
let's move up a dimension and
think about volume.
Let me ask, really loudly, what is Volume?
Of course, what is area, right?
Area is the thing that
integrals calculate.
So instead of trying to give
a definition of volume,
let's just focus on how we're gonna
compute volume, whatever it is.
And we're gonna compute volume by
integrating the volume of little,
tiny pieces that we cut
up our objects into.
Let's work through an example.
Here's a cone.
I want to compute the volume of this cone.
Just for concreteness, let's suppose that
the cone has a height of two units and
a radius of one unit, and
I want to compute its volume.
I want to set this thing up
as an integration problem.
I want to cut this thing
up into slices and
add up the volumes of the little slices.
So imagine that I take this and
I just slice it up into
a bunch of really thin pieces.
Now what's the volume of a slice?
Well that slice is practically
a little tiny cylinder.
So what's the volume of one
of these very thin cylinders.
Well let's suppose the cylinder
has some radius r.
And I'm going to call its height,
its height should be really thin, so
I'll call its height dx.
And in that case the volume of this
cylinder is, what's the area of the top?
It's pi r squared times its height,
which is dx.
So, this here will be our formula for
the volume of one of these thin cylinders.
And, once again, we're seeing the
importance of the differentials, right?
We're using the differentials
to write down an equation for
the volume of the thin cylinder.
Anyhow, let's put this
together in integral.
But to set up the integral to
calculate the volume of this cone,
I first have to figure out the volume of
one of the slices that make up this cone.
To do that,
let's turn this cone on its side, and
let's imagine that this is the point 0, 0.
So let's make this the y axis, so
the x axis will head in that direction.
Then what do I have here?
Well, this line is the line
y equals x over 2.
Now I'll use that to figure out
the radius of one of those slices.
Pick some value of x, and
let's think about one of the slices.
One of these thin cylinders that
I'm using to build up the big cone.
I don't know the radius of
that particular cylinder.
Well, it's this distance here, and
I know the Y coordinate up there.
The Y coordinate is X over 2, so the
radius is of this cylinder is X over 2.
I can write down the volume of that disk.
The volume is pie times the radius,
which is x over 2 squared times
the thickness of that disk which is dx.
And now I'm integrating
this from where to where?
Well x goes from 0 all the way down to 2,
so this will be the integral
from x equals 0 to 2 and this integral
will calculate the volumn of my cone.
And now we use the fundamental
theorem of calculus.
I can simplify this a bit, I have some
constants here I can pull out, right.
I can pull out the pie and
I can pull out 1/2 squared.
This is pi over 4 times
the integral from 0 to 2.
Just x squared dx.
Now, what's an anti-derivative for
x squared?
Well, x to the 3rd over 3.
And then, I'm integrating that.
I'm evaluating that at 0 and
at 2 and taking the difference.
So when I plug in 0, I don't get anything,
but when I plug in 2, I get 8.
That's 2 cubed over 3, and then minus 0.
So this is the volume of the cone,
which I could simplify somewhat.
I could write this as 2 times pi over 3.
We did it.
Well, you could have just looked up this
formula in the back of some calculus text
book, but
that's beside the point here, right.
The point here is that we're
teaching you the secrets of volume.
You can now verify that the formulas in
the back of the textbook are correct.
And that's part of the fun of mathematics,
we're not just giving you information.
We're giving you the information and
the tools with which to verify
that that information is correct.