[MUSIC]
I define data very broadly.
I think it's from a digital
preservation perspective,
data can mean digital
information of any kind,
including very specific
outcomes of research.
So structured data, research experiments,
and things like that.
>> Data are those observable
bits of information that
help us understand a political process,
a social process, an economic behavior,
whatever it is that people are doing.
The data is that observable bit of
information that we can record and
later analyze to help
understand those processes.
>> Data is evidence used for research and
scholarly academic research of any kind.
So when you make a statement
about the world or
about anything in it, you're relying
on some evidence for that statement.
If you say Proust has a wonderful passage,
you're probably referring to
a particular piece of text somewhere.
If you say 95% of the people in
the United States like vanilla ice cream,
then there's probably some
evidence underlying that.
They're both, they both can be
data if they're used as evidence.
[MUSIC]
>> Typically, there are multiple types
of data that are being collected.
The data are almost entirely
numeric that I deal with.
I don't really deal with
images or maps or text.
And it's all strange, collected for
the purpose primarily of research,
not collected, say for health claims or
for other secondary purposes.
>> My data in my research,
some of it is simulated data,
some of it is survey data, some of it is
data produced by government agencies.
It's really all kinds,
sometimes experimental data,
most of it is observational data,
data that comes from the world as
it occurs rather than in
a controlled laboratory.
But really, all different types of
data are part of what I look at.
I'm more interested in the question
that I'm trying to answer,
then I go find the data that I need.