[MUSIC]
>> It's important to,
as you start designing a study or
an experiment or an observation,
to think of how,
what are you going to do with the data
you're going to be collecting, right?
And you're going to be producing.
And so, if this becomes part already
of your design and you have a,
you think of long-term accessibility of
that data, preservation of that data,
already you have that in mind as
you're building your study or,
again, your experiment.
Then, there are more
chances that you make it,
that it will be easier for
you to make it accessible to others.
>> So, students in my discipline at least,
I mean,
they need to be aware that data management
is a critical part of what they do,
and will do, as either practicing
engineers or scientists or
researchers
>> It's,
you need to be able to
keep track of your data.
Keep track of the different
changes you've made to your data.
Be able to, if you get sued for
example, as an engineer and
you need to show your calculations.
You need to be able to manage all that
information, and be able to show it.
>> So, I see there being practical and
symbolic benefits.
>> The practical benefits I think are,
there's a plot.
There's a plan, from cradle to grave.
What is the research question?
How are data being used
to address that question?
Are there other aspects of the research
project that are required, the required
data is there, and archiving requirement
for future use, and those sorts of things.
So that's the birth of the data,
the growth of it, and
the final archiving of it.
It's a practical way to begin what
is going to be a bunch of work.
They symbolic part, is it's a reason,
it's a focus for people to talk.
>> I think there's a sense, I certainly
get the sense in libraries that
people feel like we have a completely
known set of data management practices.
I don't believe we do.
I think for a lot of domains those
practices are still emerging.
So, I think that we should be really
open to identifying new kinds of
data management practices, and figuring
out what our role might be in them.
>> You need to have a digital librarian
to do organization of your data.
You need to have a social
scientist who can come and
help you how to arrange things,
how to share things.
And you need to have some sort of
a policy maven who can come and
say what type of policies you need for
these type of working together,
sharing, and collaboration and
things like that.
So, in a sense, you need multiple
communities together to form your,
what you call, a scientific fabric.
And you have multiple people to come and
read that.