[MUSIC] Generally speaking,
anti-differentiating things with radicals
is difficult.
For example, let's try to find an
anti-derivative of, x over the cube root
of x plus 1 dx right?
Let's try to anti-differentiate this.
Can I make a substitution to improve the
integrand?
So what substitution do I want to make?
Well, I really have some choices, I mean,
one thing I could do is I could make ux
plus 1 and in that case, du is just dx.
And if u is x plus 1, then x is u minus
1, and I can then rewrite this
anti-differentiation problem.
instead this becomes the anti-derivative
of that x, but u minus 1 still cube root,
but instead of x plus 1, it's now of u
and the dx becomes du.
And I, I could actually do this, but I'm
not going to head down that path.
Instead, I want to show you a trick by
which you can get rid of the radical all
together.
So instead let's set u, just to grab the
whole denominator.
So u will be the cube root of x plus 1
and in that case, u cubed is x plus 1.
Or, in other words, x is u cubed minus 1.
And that tells me what dx is.
In that case, dx is 3u squared du.
Now I could make this substitution.
This transforms this integration problem
to, the anti-derivative of x now becomes
u-cubed minus 1.
The whole denominator just becomes u.
And then the dx here is now a 3u squared
du, so I'll write 3u squared du.
And that's just a polynomial.
So I'll simplify this a bit, this is the
anti-derivative of, what is this here, u
cubed over u times 3u squared, that's 3u
to the 4th minus 1 over u times 3u
squared that's minus 3u, du.
And this, this is just a polynomial, so I
can anti-differentiate this very quickly.
This anti-derivative is 3 5ths u to the
5th, minus 3 halves u squared plus C.
Now, we'll just replace u with what it
equals in terms of x.
So u, remember, is the cube root of x
plus 1, so putting that in here, I get 3
5ths, instead of u it's x plus 1 to the 1
3rd to the 5th.
So to the 5 3rds power, minus 3 halves x
plus 1 to the 1 3rd squared, which is to
the 2 3rds power plus C.
To make it easy to talk about this
particular technique, it has a name.
The rationalizing substitution.
The original problem had a cube root in
it, but I made a substitution to get rid
of the radical, a rationalizing.
A challenge when doing u substitutions is
that there really are multiple paths that
you can take to the correct answer.
It's not even apparent how successful a
particular substitution might be until
after you've started applying it, right?
You have to take that first bite before
you realize whether or not you're eating
food.