[MUSIC].
Sometimes the best substitution to make
isn't even visible until after we've
messed around with the integrand some
how.
For example, what's the antiderivative of
1 over 1 plus cosine x?
Dx, what can you do?
your first move might be to try the
substitution u equals cosine x, which
case du is negative sine x dx, but
there's no visible sine x in the
integrand.
Well, since we're talking about invisible
substitutions, we should try to mess
around with the integrand.
Instead of doing that, let's try a
different trick.
Let's try to multiply 1 over 1 plus
cosine x by 1 minus cosine x divided by 1
minus cosine x.
This doesn't change the integrand at all,
because this is just 1.
This trick makes a hitherto invisible
substitution visible.
I'm getting ahead of myself a little bit.
Let's first apply a trig identity.
Oh, this is 1 minus cosine x in the
numerator divided by, that's 1 minus
cosine squared x, and then the trig
identity is that 1 minus cosine squared
x, well that's sine squared x.
So now I want to antidifferentiate 1
minus cosine x over sine squared x dx.
Well even that isn't so great.
Let's split it up.
Well then I get, that this is
antiderivative 1 over sine squared x dx
minus the antiderivative of cosine x over
sine squared x dx.
Now that first integral is one that I can
do.
Rewrite it as the antiderivative of
cosecant squared x.
You know, I just have to think, do I know
any function whose derivative is cosecant
squared.
Yes, negative cotangent is an
antiderivative of cosecant squared, of of
x.
What about that other intergral?
Well I could read this as cotangent times
cosecant and just recognize the
antiderivative that way.
But to demonstrate the technique I can
also apply u substitution to that
antidifferentiation problem so let's let
u equal sine x, and in that case, du is
cosine x dx, which is great, because
that's the numerator there.
So this this antidifferentiation problem
becomes what?
This is the antiderivative of du over u
squared.
And I just gotta think, how do I,
antidifferentiate u to the negative
second power?
Well that, is by the power rule plus1
over u plus c.
Alright, If I differentiate one over u,
that gives me negative 1 over u squared.
Okay, but I don't want my answer to be in
terms of u, right, I want my answer to be
in terms of x.
So this is negative cotangent x plus,
what's 1 over u, well that's 1 over sine
x which, if I wanted to, I could write as
cosecant x plus C.
Let's put it all together.
So what I'm claiming here is that the
antiderivative of 1 over 1 plus cosine x
dx is negative cotangent plus cosecant,
plus some constant.
If you have it already, I hope you're
getting the idea that there's some really
clever things that you can try to make
these substitutions work.