[SOUND] Hello, and
good to see you back.
Let me make a small recap
about the previous lecture.
In the previous lecture,
we went more technical, and
gave a general definition of a processor,
and an FPGA.
We also made a comparison between these
two types of processing elements.
I hope you remember the main difference
between them, which is sequential nature
of a processor,
versus the parallel nature of an FPGA.
I hope now you have some basic intuition
on what a processor and FPGAs are.
In this lecture, more details on
an embedded processor will be given.
And we will also discuss the main
features of an embedded processor.
First of all, a processor is an electronic
device that executes instructions.
The processor does not
understand anything but
numbers, and can work with and
manipulate only numbers.
So instructions are not an exception.
They are numbers.
However, unfortunately, humans are not
as fast with numbers as processors.
So instructions are described with words
to make them comprehensible for people.
All the instructions are stored in memory.
And they are fetched from the memory,
one by one, to be executed.
Obviously, there is a wide range
of different applications that
can be run on a processor.
And it is clear that one type of processor
cannot deal with this range of
applications in an equally efficient way.
So it makes sense to have several
types of embedded processors,
which are dedicated to certain
types of applications.
To make an example, let's think
about signal processing techniques,
which are used for image processing.
Signal processing has different, basic
linear algebra routines in it's core.
DSP Processors are designed
specifically for signal processing,
which have dedicated units that deal
with those routines efficiently.
During our course we will mostly talk
about Microcontrollers, or MC use.
And here I want to mention that
Microcontrollers are meant for
general purpose applications, and most of
them are resource constrained devices,
which are not meant for
computationally intensive tasks.
There are also GPUs with thousands
of cores within, which are meant for
extremely computationally demanding
tasks like graphics rendering.
Of course it is sometimes challenging
to choose in a specific type
of embedded processor.
Therefore, we have several
metrics to make such choice.
Some of them, performance,
energy consumption, versatility, and cost.
As it was said a bit earlier,
it is not possible to cover all the types
of embedded processors in this course.
However, we are going to
elaborate on microcontrollers.
I am going to shortly explain each of the
main characteristics of a microcontroller.
A microcontroller has in
its architecture a CPU,
which is in charge of fetching,
decoding, and executing instructions.
The arithmetic logic unit is the unit
that actually performs the computations.
Data is loaded into the CPU's
registers from the data memory
using special instructions.
In the same way, the result of
computations can be stored in memory.
The program is stored in a program
memory as a sequence of instructions.
In order to keep track of where
the execution is in this sequence,
there is a program counter.
There is also RAM memory
available in microcontrollers and
some kinds of non-volatile memory,
such as EEPROM.
Microcontrollers include different kinds
of peripherals such as communication
units, timers, ADCs, DACs, etcetera.
If we think about the instruction's
execution, the question that arises is,
when is it time to actually
execute an instruction?
The answer is that
the execution is clocked, so
it happens according to a clock frequency.
Each instruction takes on one or
several clock cycles to complete.
From this,
you can conclude that the execution
time depends on the clock frequency.
The clock frequency of
microcontrollers can derive from
several megahertz to several
hundreds of megahertz.
There's a special dedicated unit called
Clock Control unit that it's
responsible for managing clocking.
For example, this unit can scale
down an input reference frequency or
multiply it to obtain
a higher club frequency.
A microcontroller may have several
sources of clock frequency.
One of them is an internal RC oscillator.
However, the stability of this kind
of oscillators is low, that's why
external clock sources such as an external
quartz resonator, might be used.
It is important to introduce
the notion of an interrupt,
since it is a powerful tool
to handle real-time events.
An interrupt is
a hardware-generated signal.
Indeed, interrupts are meant to break
the execution flow of a program
when some external event happens.
For example, assume we have
some communication unit, and
we want to check if there is
new data in our receive buffer.
One way to do it would be
to write a piece of code
that checks the input
buffer once in a while.
However, this approach does
not allow to know precisely
the time when the data arrive.
So there is an alternative
way to manage this task.
We can adjust the microcontroller in
a way so the execution of the main
program is interrupted precisely
when the data comes into the buffer.
Moreover, when a certain interrupt occurs,
the program counter jumps
to a specific location in a program
memory assigned to this interrupt.
An interrupt service routine,
written by a programmer,
can reside in this memory location.
Once the interrupt service
routine is finished,
the program counter jumps
back to the main program.
Each interrupt can have a priority.
If two interrupts happen at the same time,
the one with the higher priority
will be processed first.
A standalone CPU is useless if
it is not supplied with data.
Peripherals are exactly for this purpose,
to give a CPU data to work with.
Peripherals can be classified
into several groups.
First, communication units such as SPI,
I2C, UART, Ethernet, and others.
All these units work based
on specific protocols.
Next, there are analog units
which deal with analog signals.
There are ADCs for converting
a voltage level to a number, and
DACs for
converting a number to a voltage level.
Timers constitute another group.
They are powerful tools when it comes to
dealing with clocking and timing issues.
With the help of timers,
PWM can be generator, or
they can be used to
measure time intervals.
There are units to manage memory.
One of them is DMA, which it stands for
Direct Memory Access.
This unit can transfer data from
one location of memory to another
without the CPU's intervention.
Energy efficiency is
an important issue nowadays, and
microcontrollers offer flexible
alternatives to address it.
Modern MCUs have multiple power
modes that provide developers
with fine grain control over the power
consumption of their applications.
This way it is possible to power off
the CPU, the peripherals, or both of them.
Microcontrollers have different
programming and debugging interfaces.
One of the most widely used ones is JTAG.
JTAG programmer is a convenient tool,
especially when it comes to debugging.
However, a debugger is not cheap to buy.
A bootloader can be a solution to this.
A bootloader is a program which
resides inside of a microcontroller.
The bootloader receives a program byte
by byte via any communication protocol,
and writes it into a program
memory of a microcontroller.
Even though a bootloader does
not allow to debug code,
it is a free of charge way to
program a microcontroller.
This is all I have for this video.
I hope now you have a more in-depth
knowledge about embedded processors and
microcontrollers.
In the next video we will
cover MCU platforms, and
we will also describe some real
industrial projects, powered by MCUs.
[SOUND]