[MUSIC]
We've done a ton of differentiating in
this course.
We've learned all these rules for taking
derivatives, and
we've been studying a bunch of
applications of differentiation.
And things like optimization problems.
But now, I want to take all this
differentiation stuff and run it in
reverse.
I want to do anti-differentiation.
Well, what is anti-differentiation?
When we're just differentiating, we're
just taking derivatives.
That means I'm giving you functions and
you're giving me the derivative.
When I ask you to anti-differentiate, I
want you to do that in reverse.
I want to give you a function.
And then I want you to give me a
function whose derivative is the function
I gave you.
That's anti-differentiating.
Starting with the derivative, and figuring
out what function would
I have to differentiate to get that, as
its derivative.
It turns out that’s quite a bit harder
than just differentiating.
No matter how complicated an expression I
gave
you, I know that you can differentiate it.
You just have to carefully apply the rules
of differentiation.
You know, things like the sum rule, the
product
rule, the quotient rule, the chain rule,
derivatives of
certain transcendental functions but I
know that you can
do it, it's just a matter of applying
those rules.
It might be complicated but it's doable.
In contrast, anti-differentiating doesn't
really have
so may rules associated with it.
It involves a lot more creativity, and
therefore, I think it's a lot more fun.
Of course, if it's going to be complicated
we should
ask ourselves why we're doing it at all,
you know?
What's the point of undoing
differentiation?
Why would you want to anti-differentiate
in the first place?
Well, it turns out that
anti-differentiation is like
a bridge between two different parts of
this course.
Up until now, we've really been looking
at, at differentiation.
And then, the end of this course gets into
integration, and this theory of, of areas,
if you like.
A huge surprise is that
anti-differentiation will let us solve the
integration problems that are coming up at
the end of this course.
So you can really think of
anti-differentiation as a sort of bridge
between
the, the differentiation section of this
course,
and the integration section of this
course.
That's a story that's yet to come.
For now, I just want to focus on
anti-differentiation.
[SOUND]
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]