Hi, and welcome to this course
sequence on spacecraft kinetics.
My name is Hanspeter Schaub and
I'm a professor here at
The University of Colorado Boulder.
The sequence will have four components.
The first component we're want to
talk about continued mechanics and
also rigid body dynamics.
How we developed equations of
motion from basic principles?
The next component is going to look
at a rigid body of a space craft and
study how it's being stabilized.
We are looking at torque free motions and
equilibrium exists and
which ones are stable.
The third component talks
about gravity gradients.
This is a common method of stabilizing
the space craft without having
active feedback.
And we'll be looking at the derivation
of this gravity gradient torque, but
also the force, its stability,
and equilibrium.
The last, the fourth component,
is going to look at a spacecraft which has
multiple momentum exchange
device developed.
In fact, you've developed a very
general formulation with variable speed
control moment gyros.
And then we can simplify the formulations
for CMGs and reaction wheels.