Hi and welcome to the first
segment of spacecraft kinetics.
In this section we're going to be
talking about equations of motion of
a space object.
In fact, we're going to
start with basic principles.
We're going to go to a deformable body,
something that can change shape, and
then we're going to move and freeze it to
a rigid body, which is very typical for
many a spacecraft mission.
In all these applications, we're studying
angular momentum on how this stuff spins.
We're looking at the kinetic
energy of these objects.
And we're also showing you how to
use these principles to develop
equations of motion.
Why do you need this?
The equations of motion is a fundamental
property you have to analytically derive,
so then you can demur to simulate it and
predict what the space
craft will actually do.
This is also often used for
mission analysis tools.