We're going to go to kinetics.
We focused a lot on how
to describe orientations.
And there's lots of sets, actually,
there's an infinity of
different attitude sets.
And they all have benefits and drawbacks.
Now we're going to work
on the full dynamics.
And that means we're going to focus
on mass, inertia, forces, torque,
that kind of stuff.
And how do we find,
ultimately always, omega dot.
That's kind of what we're after,
fundamentally.
So, here's some topics, we're going to
start out with a continuous system.
Again, that's from chapter two.
We're going to jump straight
to that formulation.
Derive some fundamental properties.
Do everything in a vectorial
format formulation.
That's kind of important and nice.
So some of you may not
have seen this before.
Then we're going to freeze that blob
of jelly, basically, into a rigid body.
Some of the things will simplify.
And you have to be very careful
as to which terms simplify.
Momentum, energy, all those things
that we use to derive equations.
And we'll talk about the inertia tensor,
energetic equations.
We talk about stability
of torque-free spins,
the different equilibrias that we have.
Why does a body happy, happy to
tumble in one set of direction and
then other directions if this goes crazy?
All that stuff will come from there.
Dual spin spacecraft, those are,
used to be more common platform.
You still see them occasionally.
But they used to make all
the geosats that way.
With, basically, you want the antenna
facing at the earth once per day and
with revolution.
because it's a geo.
It's always point at us.
And then the other part is
spun up at a different rate.
I think Cassini is also a dual spinner.
It's a big antenna platforms that
are spinning at a different rate than
the rest.
And there's instability
that comes out of this.
So this is just basically
a system of rigid bodies.
So what we've done here is
going to be a single rigid body.
And then we have two rigid bodies.
Another one that we want to
derive is gravity gradient torch.
Then we'll go back to very much f=ma,
look at the field equations, expand them.
Why do you truncate?
Because there's simple questions like,
I know that if I change my orbit,
I will change my attitude torque.
The further I am from the Earth,
the smaller that torque will be,
because gravity's smaller, so differential
gravity's going to be smaller.
But is the inverse true?
If I change my orientation,
do I impact my orbit?
And that's the kind of
stuff we'll see there.
And so,
we'll go through in great detail a lot,
again in a vectorial formulation and
go there.
But that's kind of the basic dynamics.
Later on in class we will also do
spacecraft with n-reaction wheels.
In fact, variable speed CNGs,
which then contain reaction wheels.
But that will be at a later stage.