[MUSIC].
Earlier we saw how the sign, the S-I-G-N,
of
the derivative encoded whether the
function was increasing or decreasing.
Thinking back to the graph, here I've just
drawn some random graph.
What is the derivative encoding?
Well here this point a, the slope of this
tangent line is
negative, the derivative is negative, and
yeah, the function's going down here.
At this point b, the slope of this tangent
line is positive and the function's
increasing through here.
All right?
The derivative is negative here, and it's
positive here.
The function's decreasing here, and
increasing here.
So that's what the derivative is
measuring.
What is the sign of the second derivative
really encoding?
Maybe we don't have such a good word for
it so we'll just make up a new word.
The S-I-G-N, the sign of the second
derivative, the
sign of the derivative of the derivative
measures concavity.
The word's concavity, and here's the two
possibilities, concave up where the second
derivative is positive, and concave down
where the second derivative is negative.
And I've drawn sort of cartoony pictures
of
what the graphs look like in these two
cases.
Now, note it's not just increasing or
decreasing, but this concavity
is recording sort of the shape of the
graph in some sense.
Positive second derivative makes it look
like
this, negative second derivative makes the
graph
look like this, and I'm just labeling
these two things concave up and concave
down.
And this makes sense if we think of the
second derivative as measuring the change
in the derivative.
So let's think back to this graph again.
Here's this graph of some random function.
Look at this part of the graph right here.
That looks like the concave up shape
from before, where the second derivative
was positive.
So we might think that the second
derivative is positive here.
That would mean that the derivative is
increasing.
What that really means is that the slope
of a tangent line through this region is
increasing.
And that's exactly what's happening.
The slope is negative here, and as I move
this
tangent line over, the slope of that
tangent line is increasing.
The second derivative is positive here.
You can tell yourself the same story for
concave down.
So look over here in our sample graph.
That part of the graph looks like this
concave down picture where the second
derivative's negative.
Now, if the second derivative is negative,
that means the derivative is decreasing.
And yeah, the slope of the tangent line
through this region is going down, right?
The slope starts off pretty positive over
here, and as I move this
tangent line over, the slope is zero, and
now getting more and more negative.
So in this part of the graph, the second
derivative is negative.
What happens in between?
Where does the regime change take place?
So over here, the second derivative is
negative.
Over here, the second derivative is
positive.
There's a point in between, maybe it's
right here.
And at that point the second derivative is
equal to zero.
And on one side it's concave down, and on
the other side it's concave up.
A point where the concavity actually
changes is called an inflection point.
Alright, the, it's concave down over here,
and it's concave up over here and the
place where the change is taking place,
we're
going to, just going to call those points
inflection points.
It's not that the terminology itself is so
important, but we want
words to describe the qualitative
phenomena
that we're seeing in these graphs.
Inflection points are something you can
really feel.
I mean, if you're driving in a car, you're
braking, right?
That means the second derivative's
negative.
You're slowing down.
And then suddenly you step on the gas.
Now you're accelerating.
Your second derivative's positive.
What happened, right?
Something big happened.
You're changing regimes from concave down
to concave
up and you want to denote that change
somehow.
We're going to call that change an
inflection point.
[MUSIC]