[MUSIC].
Once upon a time, a long, long time ago in
a cave somewhere,
there was some cave person who first
started studying numbers.
And then the cave person had an idea.
The idea is functions.
Instead of just studying numbers, this
cave person is going to
study numbers depending on other numbers,
the relationships between numbers.
There's another way to think about
functions.
A different metaphor is that functions
[SOUND] eat numbers, and after
they're done processing them, they spit
out [SOUND] some other number.
Functions eat numbers and spit out
numbers.
But the food chain keeps going.
The derivative is an operator.
And what that means is that it's like a
function for functions.
The derivative eats a function and after
it's done
with it it spits out a new function, the
derivative.
First we studied numbers.
Then we studied functions, which are
numbers that depend
on numbers or things that you do to
numbers.
And now the derivative.
The derivative eats something which itself
eats something and spits out numbers.
And then the derivative spits out a new
thing that eats numbers and spits out
numbers.
The derivative takes a function and gives
you
a new function, and this ddx notation is
so
powerful, that you can start to talk about
the
derivative even before you've applies it
to any function.
Look at this, this is some sort
of equation, but it's really a nonsense
equation.
The second derivative minus one.
What does it even mean?
Equals the derivative minus one, what am I
doing here?
Who knows?
The derivative plus one?
This sort of nonsense looks similar to
something very reasonable, that
x squared minus 1 is x minus 1 times x
plus 1.
There's actually some sense to this.
So let's try to make sense of the right
hand side.
After I apply it to a function.
So we don't even really know what this
means, but
the notation's so powerful that it's just
going to lead us forward.
So I'm going to copy down ddx minus 1 in
parentheses, and I
have to figure out how I'm going to apply
this thing to F.
I'm going to act like this distributes, so
I'll write DDX of F.
Plus 1 times f.
Now I can keep on going, right?
This, if you kind of imagine, might
distribute over this.
What would that, what would that mean?
I'm going to d/dx this whole thing, so
d/dx of
d/dx of f plus f, minus 1 times this.
So minus d/dx of f, plus f.
And now I can keep calculating, the
derivative of the derivative of f plus f.
Well, the derivative of a sum is the sum
of the derivative so that makes sense.
That's the derivative of the derivative of
f plus the derivative of f minus the
derivative of f minus f, subtracting
summing F, so it's subtracting F.
Now good news, I've got a plus derivative
here, and
a minus derivative of F there, so what I'm
left
with is D Dx, D Dx of F, which I
could write as the second derivative of F
minus F.
Well I could also write this as the second
derivative minus 1, applied to F.
And that's exactly what's on the other
side of this equation.
At this point, this is all a sort of
cheating, so if this doesn't speak to you,
don't worry.
The upshot though, is that differentiation
is
an operation that you apply to functions.
And it's possible to reason precisely
about
differentiation in the abstract just as an
operation.
[MUSIC]