Welcome to the web connectivity and
security course.
In this course we will study different web
connectivity standards, solutions, and
protocols.
We will also study the need for
security as well as protocols,
methodologies and solutions that will
help you mitigate security risks.
Before talking about web connectivity
in cyber-physical systems, the first
question that arises is, why then bother
connecting your embedded systems?
If there is a device that controls
the settings on my microwave oven,
what need does it have to
talk to other devices?
This is a valid point.
Standalone embedded systems do exist and
cater to a specific problem as
in the case of a microwave oven.
Another example is an image
processor in a digital camera.
Whose purpose is handling the light
capture from the sensor and
to digitize, process, and
store that information as an image.
It performs that specific job and
does it very well.
The reality is that devices
are getting more and more complex and
that connection is needed.
The same digital camera now has wi-fi and
GPS modules
to offer seamless transfer of photos and
a geopack then.
These wi-fi and GPS modules have
their own baseline processors
and for all of them to work seamlessly,
you have to bring them together.
You have to connect them.
Any reasonably modern car can
have 25 to 50 onboard processors.
A modern 7-Series BMW has
up to a hundred processors.
All of these control different
functions of the car.
For example GPS navigation, entertainment,
parking distance control,
radar cruise control, and so on.
To make the car really function and
provides a safer journey, the processors
have to communicate with each other.
A classic example is that of a car crash.
In case of a crash, your car will open
the door locks and deploy the air bag.
It may perform other emergency
functions like flashing the headlights
,and sending your location
coordinates to an emergency service.
All of this is possible
because of the in-car network.
If you think this is too much,
NVIDIA announced car computation
platform that has a combined
performance of 8 teraflops.
To put this in perspective,
the world's 418th-ranked
super computer in 2008 had
a computational power of 9.1
teraflops and
that one had 4,096 processor cores.
So, soon your car will have
the same computation or
capability as the super computers in 2008.
And here we only discuss the
self-contained local networks within cars.
Soon cars will be able to communicate
with other cars on the road and
with the traffic monitoring systems.
Thus, the future is connected and
connectivity is not optional anymore,
it's fundamental.
After establishing the case for
connectivity in cyber-physical or
embedded systems, the next question would
be why do we need web connectivity?
Here we need to have a deeper look.
Let's first look into
the benefits of web connectivity.
The first and
foremost benefit is ubiquity.
The web is everywhere, from your PC,
to phones, to even smart watches.
You can access the world wide
web not only on smartphones but
also on dumb phones from a decade ago.
All you need is a browser.
A browser like Opera Mini that can
even be bundled into embedded systems.
Scalability is another important point.
The World Wide Web is
already quite large and
it can accommodate even more
sources of information and users.
Web technologies can automatically scale,
based on demand,
with minimal user intervention.
They can scale to user needs,
computational load, or
network requirements.
The World Wide Web has been with us for
well more than two decades now.
That is enough time to test and
optimize the web-enabling technologies,
HTML, http, and
web servers are fully understood.
There are highly optimized web servers
available for small sensors that take
less than seven kilobytes of space,
which is an efficient use of memory.
One of the main features of web
technologies is that they don't care about
the underlying architecture or
technologies.
One web-supported device can communicate
effectively with another one,
irrespective of the system and
communication infrastructure used.
Lastly, major future technologies
will reside on the web or
heavily utilize the current
internet technologies.
Let's take cloud computing where
you are provided with on-demand
computational power and services.
You can use these services for
big data analytics and
then utilize these data insights for
better decision-making.
Imagine gathering data from
hundreds of thousands of sensors,
then transferring this data to the cloud
for storage and processing, and
afterwards relaying this decision back
to the nodes or an actuator to activate.
Despite the benefits of web connectivity,
it also comes at a cost.
With web connectivity, you get to leverage
the cloud computing infrastructure,
remote monitoring and assessment as
well as remote command and control.
However, the very first thing for
people involved with design and
development of connected embedded
systems is an increase in complexity.
Compared to a stand alone setup,
a network connected system requires
extra effort In network design and
connectivity solutions,
and in hardware and software design
to enable that connectivity.
In later videos we'll discuss
more on the choices you have
when it comes to network connectivity.
Moreover, with web connectivity you
inherit its security issues as well.
When you connect your cyber-physical
systems through the internet,
you open then to roughly the same
level of security weaknesses and
attacks as in other
Internet-connected networks.
Security can't be an afterthought anymore.
If you are building a connected system,
security should be an inherent
feature right from the beginning.
In case of the car example, you have
a network limited to the car's internals.
So, locking the door
will effectively lock out
most thieves from accessing
the computer systems.
But when you connect
that car to the internet,
you can't rely on locking the doors only.
You have opened the car to attacks
from anywhere in the world.
But be assured,
we have technologies, protocols, and
solutions that will help
mitigate these threats.
And we'll discuss them in later videos.
And lastly web connectivity
is resource heavy.
For really small low power devices,
memory and computational power
are a limited resource, connectivity
puts an extra burden on these resources.
Depending upon the connectivity solutions,
solutions that you choose,
you will have to add
the extra hardware and
software layers to communicate and that
takes both memory and processing power.
Some solutions are more
resource hungry than others and
we will discuss that further later on.
But nonetheless,
connectivity adds an extra cost.
Additionally, if you decide to
add security, which you should,
you'll need some sort of cryptographic
algorithm to secure your data.
Cryptographic computations
are processor-intensive,
meaning that they put a lot
of strain on the processor.
This can drive up the energy
consumption as well.
Let's discuss connectivity
in cyber-physical systems
in a general context.
Of course, it's nice to have an overview
of your home when you are on vacation or
remote start your car in a freezing
weather so, it's warm when you get inside.
Or to be able to assess what's
wrong in the production plant
without physically being there.
But, you will come across situations
where you won't need web connectivity.
For our very daily life for example,
do you really need to connect your
stand-alone coffee machine to your wi-fi?
Of course you might think,
it's just a coffee machine.
What can go wrong if
hackers get access to it?
Over boil my coffee to
give it a bitter taste?
The thing is that through your coffee
machine if its security is weak,
hackers will get access
to your network and
from there they can go to your system or
anywhere.
In this case, the coffee machine
is not the target itself but,
another attack vector against your system.
So, yes, there are benefits to web
connectivity and there are the downsides.
What you will need to do is assess whether
you really need web connectivity or not.
Once you decide on the former,
you'll need a proper implementation.
That is where this course will help you.
By the end, you'll be more
informed about the protocols and
solutions available to you.
And you will be able to make informed
decisions when it comes to adding
connectivity to your embedded solutions.
[MUSIC]