Hello, my name is Helen Tibbo.
Welcome to Research Data Management and
Sharing.
Before I describe what we will
be exploring in this course,
I would like to tell you a little
bit about the CRADLE project, and
my background.
This MOOC was developed by
the CRADLE project at the University
of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and
was funded by the Institute of Museum and
Library Services, or IMLS.
The CRADLE project stands for
Curating Research Assets and
Data using Lifecycle Education, and
is a collaboration between the School
of Information and Library Science,
the Odum Institute for Research and Social
Science, and the UNC University Libraries.
EDINA and the Data Library at
the University of Edinburgh
also contributed content to this MOOC.
The folks at the University of Edinburgh
have created another great resource for
learning about research data
management called MANTRA.
We strongly encourage students
to explore this rich resource.
Now, a bit about me and
why I am teaching this course.
I am an alumni distinguished professor
at the School of Information and
Library Science at UNC,
where I teach courses on data management,
digital preservation,
and records management.
I was president of the Society of
American Archivists from 2010-2011,
and I have been the principal
investigator on a number
of IMLS funded projects
focused on digital curation.
I am currently the head of the Standards
and Policies, Community Practice for
the National Science Foundation funded
Datanet Federation Consortium Project
based at UNC.
So, why learn about
research data management?
Today funding agencies and journals
are increasingly requiring researchers
to share, archive, and plan for
the management of their data.
As research and information professionals
respond to these new requirements,
data curation knowledge is necessary for
the effective management,
long-term preservation, and reuse of data.
This course will provide students
with knowledge of data management,
best practices throughout
the research life cycle
from the planning stage all the way to
when data will ideally be shared and
made available within
a trustworthy repository.
Besides responding to requirements,
effective data management
can also help researchers
optimize their research output,
increase the impact of their research and
support open scientific inquiry.
We will begin this course by
building a basic understanding of
research data and data management.
We will then cover data management
planning and funder requirements.
In module three, we will delve more
deeply into some best practices and
suggestions for working with data.
And then in module four,
we will discuss the benefits and
challenges of data sharing, and
some techniques to enable researchers
to easily use each other's data.
We will end with a module
on how to preserve data and
the roles of trustworthy repositories.
By the end of this course, you will have
a firm understanding of data management
best practices, as well as many data
management tools and resources to help
you foster data sharing and the conduct
of better science and scholarship.
Let's start.
[MUSIC]