[SOUND] Welcome back to the video
lectures on web connectivity and
security in cyber-physical systems.
In this lecture, we'll go through
the basics of the internet and
web connectivity, including some
background information on the internet and
the nuts and bolts of its operation,
especially the Internet protocol suite.
The basic communication
protocol of the Internet and
its layer design will be discussed.
Let's start with the Internet.
A group of connected
computers is a network.
A group of connected networks from
a very large scale became the internet.
One way of understanding new
technology is to look into its origins,
why was it developed?
This is a technique we'll
also use in later videos
when we learn different protocols.
So to understand why there is a huge
network of connected computers,
let's look at its history.
The internet came out of
the desire to have a robust,
fault-tolerant network of computers.
There are two key takeaways here.
First, the network had to be robust and
full tolerant, and second,
it was for computers.
We see both in the modern internet.
We have a pocket base network where
each pocket can take a different route
to the destination.
And the effect of being designed for
computers
is that it's essentially not what we would
call lightweight and power efficient.
Take for example ethernet, designed for
computers at a time when
power was not a requirement.
It is one of the most power hungry
connectivity technologies for
cyber-physical systems out of the ones
that we will discuss in this course.
We have been moving from
an internet of connected computers
to an internet of connected devices or
things.
This requires new technologies or
changes to the current ones to suit
the needs of the new breed of systems.
The Internet is the network of computers,
but
what actually carries information
on top of this network?
One of the ways to carry and
display information over this network,
and here we mean Internet,
is the World Wide Web.
The World Wide Web is a way to organize
and present information for people.
This is a common distinction that
many of us generally get wrong.
Internet connectivity means becoming
a part of this large worldwide network.
Web connectivity, on the other hand,
means leveraging the web
technologies to now share
information over this network.
At the heart of these web
technologies are hypertext,
the Hypertext Transfer Protocol or
HTTP, a web server, and a browser.
We need internet connectivity for
these web technologies to work, and
therefore, we will talk about both.
The technologies that enable us to connect
our cyber-physical systems to the Internet
and the technologies that enable us
to access and share over the web.
Here is a short overview of the web and
the Internet.
The Internet enables the existence
of the World Wide Web.
The World Wide Web facilitates interaction
and information sharing over the Internet.
If the Internet is a highway,
the web is the moving cars.
Let's continue a bit with the analogy
of the Internet being a highway and
the web being the moving cars.
There can be more than just one
type of cars moving the highway.
For example, there can be buses,
trucks, vans, and motor bikes.
Likewise, there is more than just
web traffic on the Internet.
There is e-mail, Usenet, File transfer
protocol, peer-to-peer sharing, and so on.
But what enables all of these
to share the same network?
The technology that enables different
types of traffic to share and
go through the same network is TCP/IP or
Transmission Control
Protocol/Internet Protocol, or
commonly known as
the Internet Protocol Suite.
A protocol is a set of rules and methods.
You can think of it as
the grammar of a spoken language.
These rules and
methods facilitates a standard way
of communicating and interacting.
The TCP/IP protocol suite is
therefore a set of standards and
methods that allow different devices and
systems to communicate over the Internet.
Because of the standard, it doesn't
matter what system, operating system,
or application you have.
As long as it can say,
speak TCP/IP language,
it can communicate with
others on the internet.
TCP/IP is divided into layers for
simplicity and understanding.
As there are multiple technologies that
make up TCP/IP, the classification
into layers makes it easy to
comprehend this inherent diversity.
It also enables the decoupling
of one technology from another.
Imagine having a wine glass with
a detachable base and body.
You could change the base depending
on the surface you'll be using.
If you need grip, you would use rigid base
while the body would remain the same.
And if you want to taste
different kinds of wine,
you just change the body on the top.
In the same way with TCP/IP layers
as you go from the top to bottom,
you can decide which technology
to use from each of the layers,
the technology that best suits your needs.
And if you develop your own technology,
you can place it in the appropriate
layers for others to use.
There are four layers in the TCP/IP model,
application, transport,
internet, and link.
We will discuss them next.
Here is an overview of each of
these layers and their functions.
We will discuss the protocols
on each of these layers, and
their specifications in detail later on.
The top-most layer is
the application layer.
If you are designing
a protocol that allows
different applications to communicate,
it will be placed on this layer.
We are not talking about the specific
application software but
the methods that
the application software will
use to communicate with another
application software over the network.
An example is one chat client sending
a message to another chat client.
If both these clients use
the chatting protocol at XMPP,
it doesn't matter who designed the chat
client or what platform it is running on.
They will be able to send and
receive messages.
Here, the application
layer protocol is XMPP.
The layer beneath the application
layer is the transport layer.
Its purpose is to establish host-to-host
communication from one device to another.
It receives data from the application
layer, it doesn't care what this data is,
and transmits the data to another
process on another host computer.
Imagine you have three browsers,
Chrome, Firefox, and Internet Explorer.
And on the first one you entered Google,
on the second one you entered Yahoo,
and Bing on the third one.
In this case, you send three HTTP requests
from three separate applications.
HTTP is an application layer protocol.
The responses for
these requests are appropriately
provided to each application.
Chrome gets the Google page,
Firefox gets the Yahoo page, and
Internet Explorer gets the Bing page.
Now, all of them send similar requests,
but the data didn't get mixed up.
Why?
The transport layer, which provides
the data to the application layer,
is responsible for ensuring that each
process receives what was intended for it.
Moreover, this layer is responsible for
reliability, congestion control,
and multiplexing.
At the internet layer, which is
the next lower layer, the source and
destination addresses are attached to
packets coming from the higher layers.
This layer is responsible for
addressing and routing.
Also, when a packet is received,
it is the internet layer's
responsibility to forward it to
the appropriate transport layer protocol.
The link layer at the bottom of the
protocol stack specifies the standards and
methods that handle the physical link.
These protocols reside on the local link,
meaning that they are limited to
the scope of the local network.
For example, ARP, or
address resolution protocol, is
used to figure out the physical address,
that is the media access control or
MAC address against an Internet
protocol or IP address.
This is how your computer knows
which local device an IP packet
should be forwarded to.
A distinction to make here is that you
need a MAC address to send data in
a local network and an IP address
to send data across networks.
Sending data across networks is
an internet layer operation,
and sending data within local
network is a blink layer operation.
The TCP/IP link layer
doesn't assume anything about
the type of the physical medium and
its issues.
It just assumes that an underlying
physical link exists.
Therefore, the link layer represents
any media access protocol,
including wireless protocols such
as Wi-Fi, GSM, and bluetooth.
Here are some example protocols for
each layer.
As a recap, in this lesson, we looked
at the internet, the World Wide Web,
and the basics of the TCP/IP model.
In later videos, we will have a more
detailed look at the different layers and
their respective protocols.
[MUSIC]