Welcome to this course,
introduction to MongoDB.
This course is part of our
specialization, MongoDB
Analytics, which has been
designed to provide you
with a broader understanding
of how to fully utilize
MongoDB from a data science
and analytics perspective.
Obviously, we need to
start from the beginning
and provide you with
the knowledge foundation
on how MongoDB works, how
to operate with MongoDB,
and where it fits
your development
practices before starting a
full fledged MongoDB journey.
In this course, you will learn
the fundamentals of MongoDB
that are needed to fully
understand how to leverage
its power to perform analytics.
These fundamentals will include
topics like MongoDB's document
model, importing data
into a MongoDB cluster,
or working with the
MongoDB CRUD API,
alongside with an introduction
to B's Aggregation framework.
These topics will
be explained to you
by the means of a demo
application, Mflix,
which is a video
streaming application
similar to popular online
streaming services.
This will give you a
great first encounter
of how simple and practical it
can be to build applications
with MongoDB.
In addition to these
essential topics,
you will also learn and work
with useful MongoDB tools
and services.
Especially, you will
work with MongoDB Atlas,
our database as a
service, MongoDB Compass,
our schema visualization
tool, as well as
many other useful
command line utilities.
This course is for newcomers
to the MongoDB family,
so no prior MongoDB
expertise is expected.
That said, we do have some
technical requirements
that you should be aware of.
We will be expecting you
to know about Python,
the most beautiful
language in the world.
This is the language of choice
throughout this specialization.
We will ask you to have
Python 3 environments set up
in your workstation.
Finally, I just want
to welcome you again
to this first course on MongoDB.
We hope that you enjoy the
material we prepared for you,
and we wish you
the best of luck.
And I'll see you in class.