One advantage of using MongoDB for data
science is that it is trivial to get data
into MongoDB, and easy to change your
data model as needed to support analysis.
With our data in MongoDB,
we can take advantage of indexes,
the MongoDB query language, and
the aggregation framework to manipulate
and explore data efficiently,
as we work to better understand and
refine our requirements.
MongoDB provides a free tier option
in Atlas, which is perfect for
getting started.
Atlas is a MongoDB hosting service
provided by the people who built MongoDB.
It's easy to migrate data from the free
tier to production scale databases
when you're ready.
To get started, please sign up for
MongoDB Atlas, visiting the link provided
in the lecture notes for this lesson.
We'll be loading some initial data
sets that we will clean up and
begin analyzing as soon as we're
done creating an Atlas cluster.
Please create an account and
save your credentials somewhere.
Once you've submitted
an account creation form,
you'll be prompted to create a group.
Atlas uses groups to enable you to
control who has access to your data.
As is often the case, you can grant
full read write access to some users
such as the data scientists on your
team and read only access to others.
Please enter analytics as the group name.
Throughout this course, we'll give you
pretty specific instructions on set up
tasks such as this so that if you have
trouble, it's easy to diagnose the issue.
Once you've created a group,
you'll be taken to a screen like this.
Please note that as with all websites,
Atlas is actively developed.
The user interface you see may look
a little different from what we see here.
Note also, that Atlas uses Intercom, and
you might see a welcome message
when you first create an account.
Now, don't be nervous about the fact
that you see a cost here under pricing.
Just select M0 here, under instance size,
and you'll see the price go to zero.
Also, let's name this cluster mflix.
This is the name of the app we'll be
building as we move through this course.
Once you've named the cluster and
selected M0 as the instance size,
please scroll to the bottom of this modal.
And create an administrative user
with the username analytics,
and the password, analytics-password.
We'll use these credentials to connect to
this MongoDB cluster from Python scripts
and applications later in this course.
Now, if the term cluster is
unfamiliar to you, don't worry.
All you need to know at this point is
that a cluster provides redundancy.
The cluster we are creating is actually
three MongoDB database servers.
This a safeguard to make sure your
data is always available to you.
While the probability is small on
something going wrong on any given day,
computers crash, network connections
break, and other problems emerge.
Having a cluster rather than
just a stand alone instance
ensures that you'll be
able to access your data
even if something bad happens to
one of the servers in our cluster.
The client libraries we will use from
Python will automatically switch
to one of the other servers if for
some reason it could
no longer communicate with the one
it was reading from and writing to.
This is called automatic failover.
All nodes in the cluster
maintain copies of your data, so
it really doesn't matter which
one your application uses.
All this is handled for you automatically.
You probably won't even
notice of a failover happens.
Okay, with that little bit of
context about what a cluster is,
click Confirm & Deploy to
initiate the creation process.
You might see a captcha pop up.
Simply do what it asks you to do, verify.
It will take a minute or two for
your clusters to be created.
While we wait,
let's ensure we can access our cluster
once we begin to write
a little Python code.
Click the Security tab,
then click the IP-Whitelist tab.
Click the Add IP Address button And then
the Allow Access from Anywhere button.
And finally, Confirm.
Atlas allows us to restrict access to a
cluster to specific IP address ranges to,
for example, ensure only computers
in a specific corporate network
can connect to the cluster.
Allowing access from anywhere
will make it easy for
you to access MongoDB from wherever you
are and simplifies access for this course.
You will still need to supply a username
and password to access the cluster.
Now, click the Clusters tab and wait for
your cluster to finish initializing.