Compass doesn't yet
fully support the MongoDB query language.
So in order to explore all
CRUD operations in MongoDB,
we're going to need to
install the Mongo Shell.
The Mongo Shell is a text based client
that we'll be using by means of
whatever command line interface you
have available to you on your system.
In this lesson,
we'll take a look at how to install
the Mongo Shell on a Mac OS X system.
If you're on Windows,
please see the video for
installing the Mongo Shell
on Windows systems.
Now to install the Mongo Shell,
we're actually going to go ahead and
just install all of
MongoDB Enterprise Server.
Enterprise Server is bundled
with a number of executables
that are part of the MongoDB ecosystem,
including the Mongo Shell.
So please visit the MongoDB
download center,
you can get there with
a single Google query.
Click the Enterprise Server tab, and
then select your operating system.
In this case, we want to select OS X 64.
Now please follow these
installation instructions,
even if you already have
a version of MongoDB installed.
Earlier versions of the Mongo Shell
did not support SSL, and
we need SSL support in order
to connect to Atlas clusters.
Once you've selected your
operating system, click download.
Now you might see a contact form pop up.
If you do see a contact form,
please complete it, and
then download Enterprise Server.
Once the download completes, we can open
the Finder and navigate to Downloads.
Here's the file we just downloaded,
I'm going to move it to my home directory.
Now if I navigate to my home directory,
we can see the file right here.
I'm going to double-click it,
and unpack the archive file.
Then if I look inside this
folder I can see that there is,
in addition to some licensing information,
a bin directory that contains
a number of executable files.
The executable file we are interested
in is this one, mongo.
This is executable for the Mongo Shell.
Please don't confuse this with mongod,
mongod is the executable for
the MongoDB server itself.
So when we say that we have
a MongoDB deployment running,
it's running one or more mongods.
Again, we're interested in
the Mongo Shell or the mongo executable.
Please place the download that you've
unpacked into your home directory,
as I've done here.
That will make following these
instructions a little simpler.
Now in order to conveniently
run the Mongo Shell,
we're going to have to update
our PATH environment variable.
The PATH tells OS X where to look for
programs that we'd like to run.
You can set your PATH in a hidden
file called .bash_profile.
If I open up Sublime Text and
select Open, I can see hidden files
on my Mac by typing Cmd+Shift+Dot.
Then if I navigate to my home directory,
I can see that there is,
in fact, a .bash_profile.
Now on your system,
you might not have a .bash_profile.
If you haven't created one previously,
you probably don't.
Don't be alarmed if you don't see one.
You can easily create
one by simply creating
a new file in your favorite text editor,
and then saving it as .bash_profile.
Make sure that you save it
in your home directory.
Don't save it on the desktop,
don't save it anywhere else.
Make sure you save it
in your home directory.
You can simply click Save, and
a .bash_profile file will be created for
you.
I already have one, so I'm simply
going to open the one that I have.
Again, it's Cmd+Shift+Dot
to see hidden files.
And there's my .bash_profile,
again, in my home directory.
If I open this, we can see that
there is one bash command in here.
This command sets the prompt for
my terminal application.
Now in order to use the Mongo Shell,
we're going to run it from
a command line interface.
The terminal application
ships with Mac OS X, so
that's the one that I'm going to use.
And one thing I'll point out here is
that you can see my prompt is dollar and
then a space.
That's because my bash profile
specifies that the prompt for
terminal, or for any bash shells,
should be dollar followed by a space.
A dive into bash,
a dive into using command line interfaces
other than the Mongo Shell is a little
bit outside the scope of this course.
So if you'd like to dive deeper on this,
there are any number of tutorials on
bash and the terminal application.
Or, if you're on Windows,
the Command shell or PowerShell.
Any number of tutorials available
online that I would encourage you
to take a look at.
So in order to run
the Mongo Shell conveniently,
we want to setup our PATH
environment variable.
When you have a Terminal application open,
at any point you can look at environment
variables that have been set.
For example,
if I'd like to see what PS1 is,
I can do that simply by typing echo $PS1.
You must use the $ character in order
to stipulate that you want to see
the value of that environment
variable that's defined.
I can do the same thing with
the PATH environment variable.
And here I can see that it is setup to
some standard system directories where
executable files or programs are found.
This is so that I can run a number of
commands from the terminal, including
a number of system programs that make the
command line interface really work for me.
What I'd like to do is
update our PATH to include
the location where we just put MongoDB.
As a reminder, that's in my home
directory under this folder and
inside the bin subdirectory.
Now I've got an existing PATH,
that's all of this,
and I don't want to blow that away.
So I need to make sure
that in updating my PATH,
I maintain all of those directories
as well, as part of the PATH.
The way we do that is
through a command like this.
So here I'm saying, as the value
of the PATH environment variable,
use this sequence of directories.
So this simply means my home directory,
and
then with in my home directory,
that long download name for MongoDB.
And just as a convenience,
don't try to type it,
because you'll probably
screw something up.
Just right-click and select Copy,
and that will copy the name of
that directory for you, and
then you can easily paste it in.
So my home directory,
the name of the download/bin, okay?
And then,
you'll see that I have a colon here.
That colon says everything
that follows is another
directory in which to look for
executable programs.
So what this is saying is anytime
a user requests to run a program,
look for that program first
in Shannon's home directory,
mongodb-osx-x86_64-3.4.6/bin.
So look here first, and then,
if you don't find it there,
continue on looking in other directories.
Now by specifying $PATH here,
don't forget the $,
what we're saying is take
all of these directories,
note that they're all separated
themselves by colons, and put them here.
The PATH is always searched in order,
so this will be searched first, and
then each of the directories that
are listed following this directory,
following this colon,
will be searched in sequence afterward.
I'm asking you to put the directory we
just downloaded first in your PATH so
that if you happen to have
a prior installation of MongoDB,
when attempting to run the Mongo Shell
Because the first place the system will
look is in that directory we just
downloaded, that is the version of
the Mongo Shell that will be run, not some
version that you installed previously.
So if we save this, then our bash
profile is updated with the new PATH.
The last thing that I need to point
out about this is that your PATH in
the terminal won't be updated until
the next time you launch a terminal,
or unless you run a special command.
So if I echo $PATH again, we'll see that
it's exactly the same as it was before.
However, it I type source ~/.bash_profile,
what that does is reads my bash
profile that I just updated..
And then, if I echo $PATH,
now we see that that new directory
we added is included in the path.
What this does for
us is ensures that all of these executable
files can be found if we type
their name here in the shell.
So now if I type mongo, and
I'm going to add the --nodb command
line option, and you see that?
What happened is exactly what
I cautioned you against.
And that is that I haven't correctly
specified that folder in which our
downloaded version of MongoDB exists.
So I'm going to go back into the Finder,
and
I'm going to select Copy.
And then I'm going to go
back into Sublime, and
I'm going to update my PATH
with the correct value.
I'm going to save it, and then I'm
going to source bash profile again.
And now if I check my PATH, we can
see that it's been updated correctly.
And now if I run Mongo, I can see
that it does in fact start up for me.
What we've walked through here is how
to download MongoDB Enterprise package.
We've talked about the fact that the Mongo
Shell is bundled with the Mongo server and
a number of other executables.
We've walked through how to setup
our PATH environment variable so
that we can run
the Mongo Shell from anywhere.
And I've cautioned you against
a couple of things that can go
wrong when we're trying
to set up the PATH.
So it turns out that, given the steps
we followed, we actually have
both the correct version and
the incorrect version here in our PATH.
Because we were simply concatenating
whatever was here onto the front
of what was already the PATH.
But don't worry because if I
simply start up a new shell,
you'll see that just
the correct one is there.
So on new invocations of
the Terminal application,
I'll pick up exactly what I want from
my PATH, and I'll be able to run nodb.
We look at a few more tips about how
to use the Terminal application and
go a lot deeper into how to use
the Mongo Shell in other lessons.
One last thing before we close this lesson
is that if you have any trouble at all
installing MongoDB on your OS X
environment, please visit the MongoDB
documentation for detailed instructions
on installing MongoDB Enterprise.
In addition to OS X, there are detailed
instructions for installing
MongoDB Enterprise on Linux and all the
various flavors of Linux, and on Windows.
And again, the Windows installation
is covered in another lesson.