It's easy to load data in to MongoDB.
In part, this is because MongoDB
supports a very flexible data model.
Meaning, you do not need to define
a schema in advance or set up any tables.
Tables, by the way are called
collections in MongoDB.
In addition,
MongoDB is flexible about the shape of
individual documents within a collection.
The number of fields,
specific names of keys, and
value types can vary from one document
to another within the same collection.
In general, you should develop and
use a consistent data model but
MongoDB makes it easy.
To use an exploratory iterative
approach to developing the data model.
This is important in nearly all
use cases for data science.
Requirements evolve and
the availability of new data sources
imposes changes on our data models.
So let's get started with an example
of loading, cleaning, and
iterating on a data model using MongoDB.
First, we're going to load some data
into your free tier cluster, for
this we're going to use
the Mongo import program and
import the csv file of the data for
a little more than 46,000 movies.
First, download the file
movies_initial.csv
from the handouts, then we will import
the data, using the mongoimport command.
Mongoimport is distributed with MongoDB.
Since you have already downloaded and
installed MongoDB,
you have access to it from the command
line interface of your choice.
On a Mac or Linux machine, you'll
probably use a Bash shell of some kind.
On Windows, you'll probably use
the Command Prompt, or PowerShell.
For this example, we're going to use
some movies data from the open movie
database also known as OMDB.
This data set is nice because
it is large enough and
requires enough data
cleaning to be realistic.
In addition, there are a number of other
publicly available data sets that we can
work to integrate with the OMDB data.
In a manner that effectively simulates the
types of challenges we face in developing
and maintaining data resources to support
enterprise analytic applications.
To import our initial data
set you'll use mongoimport,
specifying several command line options.
Here's the template for
the command you'll use.
You simply need to fill in
the command with the cluster name and
seed list for your free tier cluster.
To get this string,
go into Atlas and from the cluster view,
click the CONNECT button.
In the model that pops up,
select Connect with the Mongo Shell.
Mongoimport has a slightly
different API than the Mongo shell.
So, we just need to copy a couple
portions of this connection URI.
First, we'll copy the cluster name.
The cluster name for your replica
set should appear as the value for
the URI parameter replica set.
Go ahead and copy and
paste it into our mongoimport command.
Replacing the cluster place holder
with the actual cluster name.
Next, we need to select
the seed list from this URI.
The seed list begins immediately
after the :// in this URI and
ends just before /test.
The seed list is nothing more than a list
of the fully qualified domain names, plus
the port on which MongoDB is running, for
all the servers in your MongoDB cluster.
Replace the seed list placeholder with
the seed list you've just copied.
See the lecture notes for this lesson for
a mongoimport template command
you can copy and paste.
And for
a written version of these instructions.
Once you have correctly added your seed
list to the mongoimport command go ahead
and run it.
But before you do, make sure that
the movies_initial.csv file is located in
the same directory from which you're
running the mongoimport command.
I can run exactly the same command,
in Windows,
from the Command Prompt or
the Windows Shell.
Mongoimport has the same API,
regardless of which operating
system you're running on.
Once mongoimport finishes running,
you should see a message indicating
how many documents were imported.