There are a number of ways we
can work with data in MongoDB.
As we've just seen,
one way is through Compass.
In addition to simply viewing
a collection, we can also filter and
perform a number of other operations.
Here, our filter for the movie,
The Big Short Note that just two documents
from this collection match this filter.
In fact, this is actually evidence
of some dirty data because
one of these is a duplicate.
So we can delete the dupe.
We can also update an individual
document by editing its fields.
Here, I'll update this
doc with the runtime.
From a google search,
I happen to know that it's 130 minutes.
So compass provides a convenient means
of exploring data and it's visual.
So that helps immensely in investigating
many types of questions you might have
about a data set.
Especially as you first
begin to work with it.
But the bulk of the work will be in
manipulating and analyzing data.
For that, we want to use a combination
of the Mongodb aggregation framework and
query language.
In this chapter, I'll provide you with
an introduction to both, as we work to
reshape and clean up the movies data set,
and integrate it with other data sources
that will set us up to build an
application and analytics infrastructure.
We'll do all of this from Python,
using the MongoDB driver, PyMongo.
The same principles would apply
across Java, Node, C Sharp, R or
any of the other programming
languages MongoDB supports.
First however, it's valuable to discuss
how all the pieces work together.
And I wouldn't be doing my job as an
instructor if I didn't throw at least one
architectural diagram your way.
As you know, your MongoDB free
tier cluster is running in Atlas.
Atlas is a convenient platform for running
MongoDB which is why we're using it for
this class.
You could just as easily run MongoDB from
your local computer but Atlas requires
very little set up on your part and
all the administration is managed for you.
Depending on where you are in the world,
your cluster is probably running on
servers physically located in
an Amazon AWS data center.
This means its in the cloud.
I've drawn your MongoDB cluster as three
servers because that's what it is.
It's a replica set, meaning that three
servers are working together to remain in
sync, each maintaining
a redundant copy of your data.
One member of your replica set is always
primary, meaning that it's the one that
you were communicating with when writing
data, and usually when reading data.
If the primary stops functioning or
loses it's internet connection,
another member of the replica set
will step in to serve as primary.
Since it holds a complete
copy of your data,
you probably won't even
notice if this happens.
By default, both Compass and PyMongo
are designed to direct the request to
whichever node in a replica set is
primary, even if the primary changes.
For a course like this,
it's less important but
in production environments this type
of high availability is essential.
The free tier option in Atlas supports
this because a three member replica set is
the default minimum deployment for
all clusters in this platform.
Now, you downloaded Compass to your local
computer, so it's running there and
connecting to your Atlas cluster
through an internet connection.
We will also be developing scripts and
applications written in Python that
will use your free tier cluster.
In order to connect to MongoDB and
make use of the aggregation framework and
the MongoDB query language,
we need to use PyMongo.
PyMongo is available in PyPi.
And, you can install it using Pip or
easy install.
PyMongo is just a Python, library like
many of the other you are constantly
using, such as namPy, Sci fi, or pandas.
We'll also be making extensive use of
python Jupiter notebooks in this class,
to enable you to work through
exercises right in your web browser.
This will also make use of PyMongo.
But that will all be handled behind
the scenes in the Coursera platform.
And that about wraps it up for
the big moving parts of the scripts and
applications we'll be using in this class.