You can get a clearer picture of
this data if we sort the results.
Sort is just another pipeline stage.
As with group we identify
the stage by its name $sort.
The expression used to define
the sort is a dictionary.
This document specify the field or
fields we want to sort on.
Use 1 to indicate you want
to sort in ascending order.
Use minus 1 for descending.
In this pipeline,
the dollar group stage emits
documents that contain just two fields,
_id and count.
We are sorting on the count field.
Let's run this.
Now in scanning through these results,
we can get a sense for the variety and
relative frequency of
language combinations used.
So, what we've done here is
grouped in order to count and
then sorted on the count.
This is a very common
sequence of operations.
So common that the aggregation
framework actually
includes a single stage
that supports this idiom.
It's called "sort by count".
So, we can simplify this
pipeline to just this.
The thing I love about this is that we're
able to perform an important operation
with very little effort.
There are a number of examples
with this type of power throughout
the aggregation framework.