The problem with this output
is that it doesn't provide
a very good summary of what
values the language fields holds.
Using this movies data might require
a deeper understanding of say,
how the languages are distributed.
In general understanding
the distribution of data in a field is
valuable as part of any ETL process.
This is one example of an ETL problem and
my objective is really just
to give you a taste for
whats possible with the aggregation
framework as we begin this specialization.
We have quite a few fundamentals to get
through in the is course as you ramp
up on the MongoDB ecosystem and
In the second course,
we'll do a deep dive on
the aggregation framework.
Returning to this example,
let's generate a better summary of
the distribution values this field.
Essentially, I want to see
specifically what language
combinations are heavily used and
just get a sense For
how man unique language
combinations we're dealing with.
I want two different types
of summary information.
One has details on specific
language combinations,
the other just provides some raw counts.
I can do this in Python.
But it would require me to write
a couple dozen lines of code and
would be a little slow because I'd need
to process all the documents in my script
rather than in the database server.
The challenge doing these two types of
analysis simultaneously presents to
the aggregation framework, is that with
the pipeline I can really only process,
the documents to one outcome.
Again, this type of situation frequently
arises, so the aggregation framework
actually does support running
multiple pipelines in parallel,
with the use of the dollar facet stage.
Let's use a dollar facet stage to provide
both types of summary information I want.
Again remember, I want details on
specific language combinations and
just some raw counts on
unusual accommodations.
$facet enables you to define multiple
pipelines through which to process
the same input documents.
The output for
each pipeline is omitted as the value of
the key you specify in
the facet stage definition.
Here, I'm using $facet
to define two pipelines.
Note that I'm defining two fields,
each has as its value,
an array here and here.
Each one of these arrays defines
a separate pipeline that will be
processed in parallel.
And the result of running each
pipeline will be stored as
the value of these keys in
the output from this $facet stage.
These pipelines function just
like a top level pipeline.
In this case both pipelines will
receive as input the stream of
documents admitted by the sort by
count stage in the main pipeline.
I've defined one pipeline and
labeled it top language combinations.
The output of this pipeline would
be admitted as the value for
a key with the same name,
top language combinations.
This pipeline will simply take the input
it receives from the sort by count
stage and
limit it to the first 100 documents.
To do this, I'm using a pipeline
stage you've not seen yet
but it's pretty straight forward.
Just specify an integer as the value and
the $limit stage will take it's input and
pass those documents along as output until
it reaches the limit you've specified.
Once the limit is reached, it stops.
The second pipeline uses two stages,
$skip and $buckatAuto.
Skip, like limit,
is defined by specifying an integer.
And I see that I've actually
got a mistake in my code here.
Because what I really want to do is skip
all of those top language combinations
in this pipeline, because I'm considering
all of those to be unusual combinations.
So I don't want 25 here, I want 100,
because I'm considering the first 100 to
be top language combinations, and for
those, I'm simply calculating counts.
So let me go ahead and fix this.
And then, what I'm doing here
will again take that output
from the SortByCount stage,
skip the first 100, and
then pass the remainder documents
through to the second stage
in the pipeline I'm defining here for
unusual combinations.
Now $skip like $limit,
Is defined by specifying an integer.
It simply ignores the number of input
documents you specified that it
should skip.
Once a number of documents equal to
the skip value has passed through a skip
stage, it will pass any additional
documents on as output.
$bucketAuto is the second stage.
It's very similar to
the group stage except,
it automatically defines a list of buckets
into which it will group input documents.
The buckets are defined by the value
you specify for the groupBy key.
Here we're using a value of $count
as our value around which to group.
However, rather than create
groups based on the single value,
bucket auto will automatically
define ranges of values, and
group all documents that fall
within that range into the bucket.
We specify a cap on the number
of buckets that will be created
using the buckets key for
the $bucketAuto stage.
Here we're asking bucketAuto to
create five or fewer buckets.
For each bucket, it will output the value
we specified for the output key.
Here I'm saying that I want the value
of each bucket to be a document
containing a single field.
The name of the field should
be language combinations, and
its value should be the count of the
number of documents added to this bucket.
As we did with $group earlier we're
simply using the $sum operator
to add one to a running count for
every document added to this bucket.
Since the output of the sortByCount stage
in the main pipeline is a stream of
documents that captures the number of
movies that use a particular combination
of languages.
The output of the unusual combinations
shared by pipeline will be a count of
the number of movies that share their
particular language combinations
with only a relatively small
number of other movies.
Those that share their
combination with only two or
three other movies might be
grouped together, for example,
depending on the distribution bucketAuto
sees and what buckets it creates.
So let's go ahead and run this.
In the output, we see that, indeed, for
top language combinations we have a list
of documents that specify the most
frequently used language combinations as
the number of movies in our
collection that use that combination.
So 25,000 for
English down to 16 movies that use
a combination of English,
Italian, and Spanish.
A couple of other things to note here, are
that not surprisingly a small number of
language combinations dominate
the dataset here at the top.
One other thing to note here,
is that it's significant number of
documents in this collection do not
specify a value for language at all.
That's why we see this empty string
as one of the keys in our output,
more than 1,000 documents
have no value for language.
As we scroll down and look at the output
for unusual combinations shared by,
first let me explain that bucketAuto
specifies ranges such that
the minimum value is included in the range
but the maximum value is excluded.
So for the second bucket, for example,
we'll have all movies for
which at least two but
no more than five movies use
the same language combination.
In this first bucket here, we see that
there's a large number of movies.
The use of language combination
that no other movie does.
Nearly 1900 that use a unique
language combination.
So as $facet, we can see how we
can perform two types of analysis
simultaneously with
an aggregation pipeline.
And we've really just seen
the tip of the iceberg.
But this at least gives you a glimpse of
how easy it is to perform some pretty
complex exploratory analysis of data
sets using the aggregation framework.
Again, we'll dive into
some deep data science,
using the aggregation framework in
a second course in the specialization.