Now that we've explored the data set
a bit, at least for one field, let's take
a look at how to filter to get just those
movies that match a particular criterion.
There are several ways we can do this.
Compass supports
the MongoDB query language,
there is a $match stage in
the aggregation framework for
filtering, and
there's a collection method called find.
Which we can use from
a Python application.
All of these support the same
filter syntax and set of operators.
The one exception is Compass,
which at this time supports only
a subset of the MongoDB query language.
Though, it is a very large subset.
Let's do some simple queries in
the aggregation framework first.
The syntax for writing filters in
MongoDB is based on documents.
You specify one or more keys on which
you would like to filter and then for
each key provide an expression
that defines the criteria
that matching documents must meet for
that field.
As a simple example, lets search for
movies that use both Korean and English.
To do that,
we'll use a $match aggregation stage.
Have a look at the syntax here, there is
an equality match on the language key.
If you're building a Python
application such as a web app,
it's more likely that you'll use a query
language method to filter documents.
For filtering you will most commonly
use the find collection method.
Let's take a look at an example.
Here we define a filter,
note that it's just the filter portion
of the match stage we just looked at.
Both the MongoDB query language, and
the aggregation framework use exactly
the same syntax and
operators for expressing queries.
To apply this filter,
we simply pass it to the find method.
Remember that find is a method
on the collection class.
So here, we're calling find on
our movies_initial collection
that we been working with all along.
find returns a cursor that enables
us to iterate the results.
A cursor is simply a pointer to where
we are in a list of query results.
Calling list here causes Python to iterate
through the cursor and create a list.
pprint prints the output that
we'll see when we run this script.
And we can see here that what
we get is in fact a list or
array, and
that everyone of the results in this list
does express a combination of Korean and
English for the language field.
We can do this same thing in Compass, and
it uses the same syntax, or very nearly.
The only difference is that Compass likes
double quotes rather than single quotes.
And applying that filter, we can see that
the result set is reduced to 27 documents.
And again, if we scroll through these
results, we see that the combination of
Korean and English is what's used
throughout for the language filed.
This type of query is
called an equality filter,
because we're matching on exact values for
a key.
As I mentioned earlier,
we can filter on multiple fields.
So to provide an example
of that lets go ahead and
add an additional selector to this filter.
And applying that filter we can see
that our result set is reduced from 27,
to just 2.
Because now we're requiring that all
documents returned in our result set have
a combination of Korean and English as
their language, and a rating of unrated.
Now, one last thing I'll point out
about the MongoDB query language,
as expressed in Compass, is that for
keys, it is not necessary to use quotes.
Compass will correctly
interpret these as keys.
And we get a slightly cleaner
looking filter as a result.
Of course in Python,
when constructing filters it is
necessary that you use quotes.
Because you're really just
building a dictionary
that is passed to find as a filter.
Now, I'd love to go further and
show you how to do range queries
on fields like runtime, and
maybe even look at interesting
combinations of genre, for example.
But the fact is,
that this data set is a bit of a mess.
Values like runtime should be integers and
languages, genre and
several other fields should be arrays.
So that we have maximum flexibility with
respect to filtering this collection.
For the types of analysis,
we need to run and for
when we build a map,
a little later in this course.
So let's take a look at
cleaning up this dataset.