[MUSIC].
We're often trying to pick the best of
something.
We're trying to optimize our lives.
Right?
We're given a bunch of choices, and we've
got to make the best choice.
But how do we do this?
How do we do optimization?
Well, if I've only got 17 choices, I can
just try all 17 choices.
But what if the optimization problem is
more complicated.
What if I've got infinitely many choices.
What if I've got a function.
It takes a real input, and produces some
real output.
And I want to figure out which thing can I
plug into this function, to give me the
biggest possible output?
There's lots of problems in the real
world,
where this is basically the situation that
you're in.
You know?
You get to choose how many hours that you
work today, and that's really a, a real
number.
Alright?
You can choose any number between zero and
24.
And then you've got some sort of
happiness, right?
There's some sort of effect on your life
once you've made that choice.
And you're trying to figure out how many
hours should
you work today, to make yourself as happy
as possible, say.
And that's really this kind of problem.
It's a problem where you've got a
function,
which takes a real input, produces a real
output, and you've got to figure out which
input, makes the output as big as
possible.
Well, unlike a situation where you've only
got
finitely many choices, you just try them
all.
When you've got infinitely many choices.
When your choice could be any real number
between 0 and 24, how can you choose?
You know?
You can't just try them all.
And it turns out that calculus comes into
play.
We can use calculus to solve these kinds
of optimization problems.
[MUSIC]