[MUSIC] So here's a great function to
look at.
The function is going to be defined by
f(x) = sine x / x.
My question is what's the limit of this
function, as x approaches zero.
Let's try to guess the limit by looking
at a table of function values.
So here's a bunch of input values that
are getting closer and closer to zero,
right.1, .01, .001.
It's getting closer and closer to zero.
Then looking at my output values from my
function,
right?
So f(1) is sine of 1 / 1.
It's the sine of 1.
f(.1), that's sign of 1. over 1,. it's
99..
A little bit more.
f(.01) is 9999. a little bit more.
And you keep looking down here and these
numbers seem to be getting close to
something, alright. 999999. this is
really, really close to one.
So based on this table of values your
tempted to guess that the limit of f(x)
as x approaches 0 is 1.
Another way to gain some insight about
this limit will be to look at the graph.
Here's the graph.
This is the graph of sign x over x.
And you can see that when x equals zero,
functions not defined there because I
can't divide by zero, so I got this
little hole in the graph.
Nevertheless, I'm claiming that the limit
as x approaches 0 is equal to 1 which
actually means that I can make the output
as close to 1 as you like, if you're
willing to have the input be close enough
to 0.
Instead of talking about closeness, push
this red button and turn on this red
interval.
So when I say close to one, what I really
mean is the output is inside this, this
red interval.
And that red interval might be really big
or it might be really small.
But to be close to one is going to mean
inside the red interval.
The point is that, can turn on this blue
interval.
And as close as you want the output to be
the one, I can promise you that the
output is within the red interval if the
input is within this blue interval.
When the red interval is really big, well
that's not much of a challenge.
I can have a really wide blue interval
and anything inside the blue interval has
output landing inside the red interval.
But even when the red interval is very,
very small there's still some tiny blue
interval so that whenever x is within the
blue interval, the output is within the
tiny red interval.
In other words, even if you want the
output to be really close to one.
I can promise you that the output is that
close to one, if you're willing to have
the input be close enough to zero.
So, we've looked at the function values,
we've looked at the graph.
We've got this idea that the limit of
sine x over x as x approaches zero is
equal to one.
But it's just that, it's just an idea.
We don't yet have a rigorous argument
that this limit is equal to one.
Here's a sketch of a more rigorous
argument that the limit of sine x / x, as
x approaches 0 is equal to one.
It turns out that for values of x which
are close to but not equal to zero, this
is true.
Cosine of x is less than sine x over x,
and sine x over x is less than one.
Now why would you care about this?
Note, the limit of cosine x as x
approaches zero is one and the limit of 1
is 1 because the limit of a constant
function is just that constant.
So I know that the limit of this side is
one and the limit of this side is one and
what I'm trying to conclude is that the
limit of the thing in between is also
one.
And it turns out there's a way to do
this.
Let's take a look.
Here's what we're going to use, the
squeeze theorum.
Suppose you've got three functions, I'm
calling them GF and H.
G(x) is less than equal to f(x) and f(x)
is less than equal to H(x).
For values of x that are near A, but
maybe these inner qualities don't hold at
the point A.
Also, suppose that the limit of G(x) as x
approaches A, is equal to the limit of
H(x) as x approach A, is equal to sum L.
So the limit of G(x), the limit of H of X
are the same value, L.
The, you get to conclude the limit of f
as x approaches a exists and it equals l.
Why is this thing called the Squeeze
Theorem or some people call it the
Sandwich Theorem or the Pinching Theorem?
Let's take a look.
Just pictorially, why is this called the
squeeze theorem?
I've got an example here.
Three functions.
G, F, and H.
And again, G(x) is less than F(x), F(x)
less than H(x).
Now, note, the limit of G(x) as x
approaches A is L.
And the limit of H(x) as x approaches A
is L.
F is squeezed, or sandwiched, between H
and G.
And consequently, the limit of f as x
approaches A is also equal to L.
Now, we're going to use the squeeze
theorem to try to understand the limit of
sin x over x.
So we've got the Squeeze Theorem.
And what do I know?
I know that cosine X is less than sine x
/ x is less than 1 for values of x that
are close to but not equal to 0.
And the limit of cosine x as x approaches
0 is equal to 1.
If you like, because cosines continuous
and cosine of 0 is 1.
Also the limit of 1 as x approaches 0 is
equal to 1 because the limit of a
constant function is that constant.
So the limit of this function is one, the
limit of this function is one as x
approaches zero.
And that means by the Squeeze Theorem,
the limit of sine x / x is also equal to
1 [MUSIC]