[MUSIC]
This course is going to give you a global
overview of modern subatomic physics.
In order to follow it easily, it would
be good if you had basic notion of
classical mechanics and
classical electrodynamics.
You must also be able to understand and
appreciate a simple mathematical formula,
including simple differential and
integral equations.
>> If you have the educational
level of a third-year student of
any scientific discipline, then you have
the right level to follow this course.
>> It would also be good if you had basic
notion on the restricted relativity and
quantum mechanics.
But in any case, it will give you
a quick reminder of this notion and
the specific vocabulary.
>> We will cover the atomic nucleus,
its structure and its properties, and
how they are put to practical use.
>> We will guide you through
techniques to create, accelerate,
and detect particles and
measure their properties.
>> The fundamental particles,
namely the quarks and leptons,
will be discussed in a lot of detail.
With the same amount of detail,
the fundamental forces will also be
discussed, as well as their properties.
>> We will complete our tour of what is
called the Standard Model of particle
physics by discussing the Higgs boson.
Which prevents the particles from
moving at the speed of light.
>> We will go beyond and
discuss how we search for
new physics beyond what is
already well understood.
That way you will understand
the use of the formidable machine,
such as the LHC of CERN,
and it's experiments.
>> But those experiments are using
the particles like cosmic rays,
which are not manmade.
>> And
you will understand how dark matter and
dark energy contribute to
forming the universe we live in.
At the end of this course,
you will be able to answer questions from
your friends about the subatomic world.
And you will be well prepared
to continue your studies.
So once again, welcome to the course,
Particle Physics, An Introduction.
[MUSIC]