[MUSIC]
In this module we will be conveying
the essential aspects of archiving
digital data.
It's important that we cover
the topic in detail because simply
storing data on a CD, or even in the
cloud, is not the same as archiving data.
To ensure that data are accessible and
usable over the long-term,
data requires specific strategies
to preserve their authenticity and
integrity, something a trustworthy
repository can provide.
At the end of this lesson, you will be
able to understand the preservation needs
of research data, distinguish
between concepts of authenticity and
integrity, and recognize
the different types of metadata and
their roles in data discovery and reuse.
Preservation of digital data is
especially important because data
is a valuable resource and
can be at risk if not properly preserved.
A key aspect of both
successfully managing and
sharing data is ensuring the data
will be available for future use.
However, data present real challenges for
several reasons
due to the nature of digital objects and
the heterogeneity of data.
Some of the major risks associated with
losing digital data include benign
neglect, bit rot, obsolescence,
and insufficient documentation.
Data loss due to benign
neglect is the result of not
having an active strategy in place for
long-term preservation.
Without an active preservation strategy,
there are no guarantees that your data
will be usable years later,
or when others need it.
The ability to use data in digital form
is contingent upon layers of technology,
to access, read, and render the data
from physical storage media.
Without you knowing it,
data over time are subject to degradation.
This brings us to bit rot.
Digital data are represented as bits, or
units of machine-readable information.
These bits may degrade or become corrupted
over time, which we refer to as bit rot.
This perceived rot may cause decreased,
delayed, or faulty rendering of the data.
In addition, the physical media
on which the data are stored,
may also gradually decay.
Even if the data or the physical
storage media have not experienced any
deterioration, there is still a risk
to data loss due to obsolescence.
With perpetual advancements in technology,
software and
hardware eventually become
obsolete as time progresses.
Consider the researcher who has his or
her research saved on a 5.5" floppy disk.
Because this storage medium
is rarely supported today,
if at all, the data could be lost,
effectively trapped on a floppy disk.
Likewise, if she saved these data
in a proprietary file format,
then the software company that developed
it decided to discontinue its support for
that file format,
her data may have become unreadable.
An act of preservation strategy would
include approaches to avoid obsolescence,
such as constant monitoring of changes
in technology, migration of files
to current formats, and normalization
of files to non-proprietary formats.
Still, if the data are sound and
the technology is current, there is yet
another potential cause of data loss.
Insufficient documentation presents
a risk to long-term data preservation.
A lack of complete and
appropriate documentation and
metadata can make it impossible to
interpret the data in the future.
Without a codebook,
that contains variable and value labels,
we're left with data that are essentially
meaningless and unusable.
The addition of questionnaires,
methodology reports,
codebooks, and descriptive metadata,
alongside the data,
are essential for ensuring the data
continue to be useful in the future.
[MUSIC]