[MUSIC] Up until now, we've been
considering the functions that you can
get by starting with variables and
numbers, and combining them using sums,
products, quotients, and differences.
So we can write down, you know, functions
like f(x)=x2+x/(x+1^)^10+x, all of this,
-1/x.
But there's more things in heaven and
earth that are dreamt of in your rational
functions.
For instance, can you imagine a function
f, which is its own derivative? I'm
looking for a functions, that if I
differentiate it, I get back itself.
Now, if you're thinking cleverly, you
might be able to cook up such a function
very quickly.
What if f is just the zero function? Or
if I differentiate the zero function,
differentiate a constant function, that's
zero.
So this would be an example of function
in its own deriviative.
But, that's not a very exciting example.
[SOUND] So let's try to think of a
nonzero function, which is its own
derivative.
How might we try to find such a function?
So to make this concrete, I'm looking for
a function f, so if I differentiate it, I
get itself and just make sure that it's
not the zero function. Let's have this
function output one if I plug in zero.
Now, how could I rig this function to
have the correct derivative at zero?
If the derivative of this function
itself, the derivative of this function
at zero should also be one.
Can you think of a function whose value
at zero is one and whose derivative at
zero is one?
Yes.
Here is a function, f(x)=1+x.
This function's value with zero is one,
and this function's derivative at zero is
also one.
But if the derivative of f is f, then the
derivative of the derivative of f is also
the derivative of f, which is also f.
So, the second derivative must be f as
well.
So, if this function is its own
derivative, the second derivative of f
would also be equal to f.
Now, specifically, at the point zero,
that means the second derivative of the
function at the point zero would be the
function's value with zero which should
be equal to one.
is this function's second derivative at
zero equal to one?
No.
If I differentiate this function twice, I
just get the zero function,
but I can fix this at least to the point
zero. If I add on x^/2,
now, this function's derivative at zero
is one and this function's second
derivative at zero is one.
Since f is its own derivative, the third
derivative of f must also be f.
No worries.
If the thid derivative of f is also equal
to f, which is a consequence of the
derivative of f being equal to f.
That means the third derivative of f at
zero is equal to one, but this thing's
third derivative is just zero.
But if I add on x^3/6, now, if I take the
third derivative of this function and
plug in zero, I get out one.
The fourth derivative of f must also be
f.
Okay, yeah. I gotta deal with the fourth
derivative.
I'm out of space here, but no worries,
I'll just get more paper.
Here, I've written down a function whose
value at zero is one, whose derivative at
zero is one, whose second derivative at
zero is one, whose third derivative at
zero is one, whose fourth derivative at
zero is one.
And you can see, this is sort of building
me closer and closer to a function which
is its own derivative.
If I try to differentiate this function,
what do I get? Well, the derivative of
one is zero, but the derivative of x is
one, and the derivative of x^2/2 is x,
and the derivative of x^3/6, well, that's
x^2/2, and the derivative of x^4/24,
well, that's x^3/6.
And yeah,
I mean, this function isn't its own
derivative,
but things are looking better and better.
But the fifth derivative of f must also
be equal to f.
Okay, yeah.
The fifth derivative.
I'll just add on another term,
x^5/120.
And if you check, take the fifth
derivative now of this function,
its value at zero is one.
I've written down a function,
so that if I take its fifth derivative at
zero,
I get one.
The sixth derivative of f must be equal
to f.
The sixth derivative I am out of room,
but here we, go.
Here is a polynomial whose value first,
second, third, fourth, fifth and sixth
derivative at the point zero are all one.
And you can see how this is edging us a
little bit closer still to a function
which is its own derivative,
because if I differentiate this function,
yeah, the one goes away, but the x gives
me the one back, and the x^2/2, when I
differentiate that, gives me the x.
X^3/6, when I differentiate that, gives
me x^2/2.
X^4/24, when I differentiate that gives
me x^3/6.
x^5/120, when I differentiate that, gives
me x^4/24. X^6/720, when I differentiate
that, I've got x^5/120. And now, of
course, these aren't the same, but I'm
doing better.
The seventh derivative must be equal to
f.
To get the seventh derivative at zero to
be correct, I'll add on x^7/5040.
The eighth derivative, I'll add on
x^8/40,320.
The ninth derivative, I'll add on
x^9/362,880.
Okay, okay.
This is, isn't working out.
We're not really succeeding in writing
down a function which is its own
derivative.
Let's introduce a new friend, the number
e to help us.
Here is how we're going to get to the
number e.
This limit,
the limit of 2^h-1/h as h approaches zero
is about 0.69, a little bit more.
On the other hand, this limit,
the limit of three to the h minus one
over h as h approaches zero is a little
bit more than one,
it's about 1.099.
If you think of this as a function that
depends not on two or three, you could
define a function g(x), right?
The limit as h approaches zero of x to
the h minus one over h. In that case,
this first statement, the statement about
the limit of two to the h minus one over
h, that's really saying that g(2) is a
bit less than one.
And, this statement over here, and if you
think of this as a function g, this
statement is really saying that g(3) is a
bit more than 1.
Now, if you're also willing to concede
that this function g is continuous, which
is a huge assumption to make,
but let's suppose that's the case.
If that's the case, I've got a continuous
function, let's say, and if I plug in
two, I get a value that's a little bit
less than one,
and if I plug in three, I get a value
that's a little bit more than one.
Well, by the intermediate value theorem,
that would tell me there must be some
input so that the output is exactly one.
I'm going to call that input e.
In other words, e is the number, so that
the limit of e^h-1/h as h approaches zero
is equal to one,
and this number is about 2.7183 blah,
blah, blah.
Now lets consider the function f(x)=e^x.
So let's think about this function
f(x)=e^x.
Now, what's the derivative of this
function? Well, from the definition,
that's the limit as h approaches zero of
f of x plus h minus f of x over h.
Now, in this case f is just e^x,
so this is the limit as h approaches zero
of e to the x plus h minus e to the x
over h.
And this is e to the x plus h minus e to
the x over h,
so I can write this as e to the x times e
to the h.
This is the limit then as h goes to zero
of e to the x, e to the h minus e to the
x over h,
Now I've got a common factor of e to the
x.
So I'll pull out that common factor and
I've got the limit as h approaches zero
of e to the x times e to the h minus one
over h.
Now, as far as h is concerned, e to the x
is a constant,
and this is the limit of a constant times
something,
so I can pull that constant out.
This is e to the x time the limit as h
goes to zero of e to the h minus one over
h.
But I picked the number e precisely, so
that this limit was eqal to one.
And consequently, this is e to the x
times one, this is just e to the x.
Look,
I've got a function whose derivative is
the same function.
We've done it.
We've found a function which is its own
derivative.
The derivative of e^x is e^x.
E^x is honestly different from this
polynomials and rational functions.
We couldn't have produced that number e
without using a limit.
E^x is the function that only calculus
could provide us with.