[MUSIC]
Welcome.
It is good to see you back for
this lesson.
In the previous module,
we explored the Contiki operating system.
Now, we will take a look at
Contiki's kernel architecture and
explore the details of
its characteristics.
By the end of the lesson,
you should understand the benefits and
challenges faced when developing
applications in Contiki.
Let's start with Contiki's
kernel architecture.
As we know from previous videos, Contiki
is based on a modular kernel architecture.
Therefore, the kernel is minimal.
Due to this reason,
the kernel comprises only a few lines
of code that perform vital functions.
For example,
the kernel consists of an event scheduler,
which is light in terms of code size.
In Contiki,
all program execution is triggered
either through the polling mechanism or
by events which are sent by the kernel.
In Contiki, the kernel supports two types
of events, synchronous and asynchronous.
Asynchronous events are not
delivered to the receiving process
immediately after being posted.
Instead, they are stored
in an event queue.
The events in the queue are delivered
to the receiving process by the kernel.
The kernel delivers an event from
the event queue by looping through it.
The receiver of an asynchronous event
can be either a specific process or
all running processes.
When the receiver is a specific process,
the kernel invokes this
process to deliver the event.
When the receiver of an event is
set to be processes in the system,
the kernel delivers the same event
to all processes sequentially.
This is one after another.
The process post function is used for
posting an asynchronous event.
Actually this function is very simple.
First, the size of the event queue is
evaluated and if there is room for
the new event,
then the event is added to the queue.
Otherwise, the function will return zero.
Synchronous events work differently
from asynchronous events.
In the sense that when
a synchronous event is dispatched,
it is delivered to the receiving
process immediately.
Another difference
between asynchronous and
synchronous events is
the type of receiver.
While asynchronous events can be received
either by a specific process or all
running processes, a synchronous event can
only be received by a specific process.
The mechanism for invoking a synchronous
receiver is similar to calling a function.
A synchronous receiver is called,
so it performs it's task,
after which it returns control
to the posting process.
Besides events,
the kernel supports a polling mechanism.
In short, the polling mechanism
behaves as high priority events
that are scheduled between
asynchronous events.
Typically, processes operating close
to the hardware level use polling for
evaluating hardware status.
When a poll is scheduled, all processes
that implement a poll handler
are called sequentially
according to their priority.
In a similar way to
event posting functions,
Contiki also provides a process
poll function for posting a poll.
Posting a poll has a similar
effect as an interrupt.
It causes the receiving process to
be scheduled as soon as possible.
Contiki's kernel uses a single shared
stack for all process execution.
The use of asynchronous
events reduce a stack's space
requirements as the stack is rewound
between each invocation of event handlers.
At this point,
you may have questions regarding
events such as is an event unique?
Or how are we best identify it?
To answer these questions,
let's talk about event identifiers.
An event identifier is an 8-bit number
used as a unique identifier for an event.
When a process receives an event
It uses the event identifier to
determine the actions to perform.
There are several event identifiers
reserved by the Contiki kernel
to handle process control, inter-process
communication, and peripheral access.
To get better acquainted with
the available identifiers,
I suggest you go through
the suggested materials.
Now, let's take a look at the way
Contiki implements the scheduling.
Contiki schedules all events using
a single level hierarchy, and
events cannot be preempted
by other events.
The only way to preempt
an event is using interrupts.
It is important to notice
the interrupt must be supported
by an underlying real-time executive.
Correspondingly, interrupt
handlers cannot post any event.
The reason behind this policy is
to avoid possible race conditions
in the event handler.
Instead, a polling flag is
used to request a poll event.
This flag provides interrupt handlers
with a way to request immediate polling.
Next, we are going to discuss about
loadable programs in Contiki.
To implement loadable programs,
Contiki uses a binary format that includes
relocation information and
a run-time relocation function.
But, how does a loadable program work?
When a program is loaded,
the loader uses the relocation information
provided by the binary
format to allocate memory.
In case that there is not enough memory,
the loading is aborted.
In case of successful loading,
the function for
initialization is called for
starting or replacing other processes.
Finally, we're going to look
at power saving in Contiki.
In general, power can be saved by
putting inactive nodes to sleep.
In some cases,
choosing appropriate level protocols
may also reduce power consumption.
Contiki also provides a mechanism for
reducing power consumption even though
there is no explicit abstraction for it.
The mechanism works by checking
the size of the systems event queue.
If the event queue is empty,
the micro-controller goes into a sleep
mode until it's woken up by an interrupt.
This is all for the lesson about
Contiki kernel architecture.
I hope now you have a better insight on
how Contiki's kernel is structured and
how it works.
Thanks for watching and
see you in the next video.
[MUSIC]