[MUSIC]
Hello, I am glad to see you back for
this lesson.
In previous lessons,
we explored Contiki's kernel architecture.
Now we will look into the details of
Contiki's services and libraries.
By the end of the lesson,
you should understand the benefits and
challenges of using and developing
services and libraries in Contiki.
First of all,
I will go directly to a question.
What is a service in Contiki?
As we mentioned before,
services are implemented as modules.
So when a particular service is required
the corresponding module is loaded
thus making Contiki run efficiently.
From a certain point of view, a service is
different from other application programs
since a service can be used by
several application programs
In other words,
a service is a type of shared library.
One of the benefits of Contiki Services
is that they can be
dynamically replaced at random.
As mentioned before, with this strategy
Contiki minimizes the number of modules
to be loaded during booting time.
As a result, memory researches
can be used more efficiently.
As an example, some popular and
hag intensive use services in Kentucky
are communication stacks and
sensor device drivers.
These kind of services will be
discussed in depth in coming videos.
After this short introduction,
I assume that you already have
a basic idea of Contiki Services.
Now, we are going to take a look under
the skin of Contiki Services and
other components related to Services.
In every operating system, each service
should have a unique identifier,
defined by the system or users.
The format of the identifier
can write depending
on a particular operating system.
In Contiki, a service identifier
is a textual string that describes
the functionality of the service
Identifiers are used when application
programs invoke a service.
When a service is requested, the service
layer uses ordinary string matching for
querying the installed services.
You may now be wondering,
what is a service layer?
The surface layer is a component located
between the kernel and services.
When a process wants to call a service,
it posts an event to the colonial,
which in turn sends a command and
information related to their requested
service to the service leader.
This layer uses this data for
querying a matching services.
Instead of searching
services in the kernel,
the searching job will be
doing by the service layer.
Everything we have discussed so
far does not unveiled the actual
structure of a service in Contiki.
Therefore, now we are going to
explore the structure of a service.
A service includes a service interface and
a process.
A service interface
provides an entry point
that an application uses to access
the functionality exposed by the service.
The service interface
includes a version number and
a list of functions with pointers to the
functions that implement the interface.
Services and application programs
use a stub library to communicate.
How does a stub library work?
A stub library that has been linked
with an application utilizes
the service layer for the purpose of
finding the corresponding service process.
After a service has been located,
the service is stopped,
gets the process identifier,
which will be used for later requests.
By using a stub library an application
does not need to know the exact
location in memory of the service, or
the implementation details of the service.
When a service is called for
the first time the stub library queries
the service layer for searching for
the necessary service.
As a result, if there is an instance
of the service in the system,
the service layer will return
a pointer to the service interface.
After this, the version number
in the service interface
will be compared to the stub
interface's number.
If they are identical,
the implementation of the requested
service will be delivered.
Next, I am going to explain
about service replacement.
What is service replacement in Contiki?
As we know, services in Contiki can
be dynamically loaded and replaced.
However, it would become unmanageable if
the process identifier would be changed.
Therefore, in order to avoid this issue,
the service identifier must remain
the same even if the process is replaced.
A reasonable question would be,
why is the process replaced but
the process identifier is still kept?
To answer this question,
we are going to explore the mechanism
that performs this task in Contiki.
When a service is about to be replaced,
a special event is sent from the kernel to
the service process to inform the running
version of the service about the changes.
Accordingly, the service is
automatically removed from the system.
However, there are some
cases that many services
have internal stage that may need to
be transferred to the new process.
In order to deal with those cases,
a pointer and
a stage description are used for
passing to the new service process.
In short, this stage description,
which is stored as a shared memory,
is a tag with the motion
number of the service.
The reason for
this is to avoid that an incorrect
version of this same service is loaded.
Now let's talk about libraries in Contiki.
As we know, the kernel in Contiki
is minimal and only performs
vital functions such as event handling
features and CPU multipliers.
The rest of the system
is build as a library.
When the program needs to use
a function provided by a library
It can link with a library that
implements the required function.
There are three types of linking
between an application and a library.
The first one is a static link
between an application and
libraries which are part of the core.
The second one Is a static link
between an application and
libraries which are part
of loadable program.
The last one is the application can
call the service that
implements a specific library.
As a result of the last method,
the library implemented as services
can be replaced at random.
What is the difference
between these linking types?
Libraries are part of the core.
This means that when the system
is booted or rebooted,
these libraries are always automatically
loaded along with the system.
Other type of libraries are loadable
program libraries, these
libraries are only loaded when a program
application requires their functions.
These libraries are rarely used, or
are very application-specific libraries.
The last term is runtime libraries,
which are implemented as services.
This runtime libraries can be replaced
when the system is running and
these libraries are frequently used.
To give you a more
comprehensive understanding
of different types of libraries,
I will discuss some examples.
Let's discuss two functions commonly used
in Contiki applications memcpy and atoi.
The memcpy function is used for
copying data between two memory regions,
while atoi function is used for
converting strings into integers.
Memcpy is frequently used in Contiki,
therefor it is considered
as a part of the core.
Whereas atoi is less frequently used, and
therefore it is not included
in the system core.
It is implemented in
loadable program libraries.
This is all for
the lesson about Contiki service,
service replacement, and libraries.
I hope by now you have a good idea
about how these Contiki features work.
Thanks for watching.
[MUSIC]