[SOUND].
Welcome, I am glad to see you back for
this lesson.
In this video we will discuss
the details of how Contiki implements
network communication.
By the end of the lesson you should
understand the structure and
functioning of Contiki's
communications stack.
But perhaps the best question
to start this lecture with is,
what is communication in Contiki.
Before answering this question,
we are going to talk about communication
in wireless sensor networks.
Communication plays an essential role
in any wireless sensor network system.
Basically, communication in a wireless
sensor network architecture
includes three parts.
Sensor nodes, a gateway,
and the backend system.
Sensors collect data and
send it to the gateway wirelessly.
Depending on the network characteristics,
a particular communication
protocol is used.
For example, Wi-Fi or
Bluetooth can be used for
sending data from sensor
nodes to a getaway.
Then the data is forward via
the internet and reach the cloud.
Finally end-users can access data or
use services offered by the cloud.
In this lecture,
we will focus on communication
between sensor nodes and the gateway.
In other words, the communication
between devices using Contiki.
In Contiki,
communication is implemented as a service.
Therefore it has all the features
of Contiki services,
such as run time replacement.
As a result, it allows to simultaneously
load multiple communication stacks.
This helps to reduce the latency
of loading modules one by one.
In addition, this feature can be used for
comparing different
communication protocols.
To have a better understanding
of such protocols,
we will explore them in
depth later in this video.
But now, we are going to focus on
the loosely coupled communication
stack in Contiki.
Communication in Contiki may be
divided into different services.
The communication stack
uses synchronous events
to communicate with a program application.
Here, an interesting question is,
why using synchronous events instead
of asynchronous events, or polling?
The answer is that it is possible
to use a single buffer for
all communication processing,
since it is necessary that synchronous
event handlers run to completion.
This approach ensures that there is no
need to copy data to intermediate buffers.
The bias drivers operate between
the communication stack and the hardware.
Device drivers would in come in packets,
place them into
the communication buffer and then call
the upper layer's communication service.
When the communication service is awaken,
it inspects the packet in the buffer.
Based on the content of the packet header,
the service searches for
the application which is
the destination of the packet.
When it finds the exact application,
it posts a synchronous event
to that application program.
After receiving the event generated
by the communication stack,
the application program
proceeds to process the packet.
In some cases, it is necessary for
the application program to replay
by posting some data to the communication
stack before returning the control to it.
Then, when the communication stack
takes control, it places the reply
in the communication buffer and
appends its header to the outgoing packet.
Finally, it gives control
to the device driver, so
that the packet can be transmitted.
After understanding the big picture
of Contiki's communication stack,
let's examine its
structure with more detail.
There are two types of communication
stacks in Contiki, Micro IP and Rime.
In this lesson, we will only discuss Rime
and leave micro IP for the next video.
What is the Rime communication stack?
Rime is a lightweight communication
stack with a layered design
where the more complex communication
protocols can reuse the simpler ones.
When using Rime there is no rule
that compels an application
to go through all the layers of
the stack in order to communicate.
Instead it can use any primitive or
protocol that it requires.
Both single hop and
multi-hop communication primitives
are fully supported in
Contiki's Rime communication stack.
However there is no packet routing in
the multihub communication primitives.
This task is specified by the application
or the upper layer protocol.
One of the benefits of Rime stack is that
users can implement all their protocols,
which do not belong to
Rime on the top of it.
So now let's take a look at some of
the primitives available in the set of
communication abstractions in glide.
First is single-hop broadcast.
Where the sender's address is
added to the outgoing packet
before sending it to all
local area neighbors.
Then we have single-hop unicast,
which is used to send packets
to a specific destination.
The reliable unicast is another
type of single-hop unicast that
repeatedly sends a packet to a particular
destination while waiting for
an acknowledgement packet
from the receiver.
Finally, the multi-hop unicast
primitive is used for sending packets
to an identified node in the network
which is located several hops away.
In this case, a rooting function must
be provided by the application or
protocol to choose
the next hop destination.
This is the end for
the lesson about Contiki communication and
ground communication stack.
By now, I hope you have a deeper
understanding on the way Contiki's
communication is structured and
how it works.
See you in the next video.
[SOUND]