[MUSIC].
Let's think about the fundamental theorem
of calculus physically.
Let's define the function v by the rule
that v of t is my velocity at time t.
Physically, what does the accumulation
function of velocity mean?
Well that accumulation function,
remember, is say, the integral from 0 to
b, of v of t dt.
And this is really the distance, that
I've traveled from time 0 to time b.
This also makes sense when we think back
to Riemann sums.
But what would the Riemann sum say?
if I think about how far I traveled over
a short time period, say, between time
zero and time h for some small number h,
right?
How far did I travel during that time
period?
Well, I traveled for that small time
period h and I was traveling at a speed
of, I mean, you know, a velocity at time
zero, say, is a good approximation.
And I imagine my velocity didn't change
very much during this time period.
So, that's a pretty good approximation
for how much I traveled during the first
h moments of my journey.
What about between time h and time 2h,
right?
How far did I travel there?
Well, the time that elapsed was h units
of time.
And how fast was I going?
Well, I could use v of h.
My velocity of time h as a good
approximation for my velocity over that
time period, right?
My velocity is not necessarily constant.
But this is standing in for a reasonable
approximation and my velocity is not
changing too rapidly.
All right.
This is how far I traveled, right?
Time times velocity is distance.
All right?
Now how far did I travel between, say
time 2h and time 3h.
Well, again, how long was I traveling for
h units of time?
And how fast was I going?
v 2h is a reasonable approximation for my
velocity during that time period.
And of course this keeps on going, right?
But what do I get if I add all of these
things up?
Right?
What I'm getting is a Riemann sum.
And if I keep on adding these things up
until I get, you know, all the way to, to
b, right?
What I'm writing down is the
approximation for this interval of a
particular Riemann sum which approximates
this integral and in the limit as h goes
to zero, that Riemann sum will compute
this integral.
So, summarizing that, the accumulation
function of velocity, is displacement.
And what's the derivative of
displacement?
It's velocity, right?
The derivative of my accumulation
function in this specific case where the
accumulation function is the accumulation
function for velocity, right, the
derivative of that accumulation function
is the thing that I'm integrating,
velocity.
That's the fundamental theorem of
calculus.
Or in symbols, you know, the accumulation
function, which is[INAUDIBLE]
displacement, is the interval from zero
to b of my velocity.
And what I'm asking is, how is that
changing, right?
If that's my displacement when I travel
from times 0 to times b, right?
What is the derivative with respect to
the time that I've been traveling?
The derivative of displacement is
velocity.
So physically, differentiating the
accumulation function of velocity is to
differentiate displacement.
It's to ask for the rate of change in my
position, which is velocity, which is the
integrand.
It's the fundamental theorem of calculus
just wrapped up in physical clothing.