We've seen what happens when we
differentiate the accumulation function.
That's the fundamental theorem of
calculus.
If I take the derivative of the integral
from a to b of f of x dx, well what do I
get?
Well, it's just f.
Of b, right?
The rate of the change of the
accumulation function is the functions
value.
But, what would happen if I were to
differentiate with respect to the left
hand end point instead of with respect to
the right hand end point?
By which I mean.
What's the derivative with respect to a
of the integral from a to b of f of x dx.
Right.
What happens if instead of diferentiating
with respect to the top end point, I'm
diferentiating with respect to the bottom
end point?
I'm asking how is this function as a
function of a changing?
Let's think about the graph.
Let's draw my coordinate axes.
And I'll draw some random looking
function.
And I'll pick some points a and b.
And the integral from a to b calculates
the area in here.
And I want to know how does that integral
change when I wiggle a?
I'm asking to differentiate the integral
with respect to this.
Left-hand endpoint.
So let's wiggle the left-hand endpoint.
Let's move it over a little bit to a plus
h.
I'm imagining h is very small.
Alright, and I want to know, how does the
integral change?
Well the quantity that calculates the
absolute change in the integral is this.
What's this thing here?
This is the integral from a plus h to b.
And this thing here is the integral from
a to b, so this difference is telling me
how the integral changes when I replace a
by a plus h.
Now if you think about it, what this is
really calculating is, you know, related
to the integral from just a plus h,
right.
This integral is calculating this area,
and subtracting this larger area.
So the difference is really just this
area in here between A and A+H but it
comes with a negative sign because I'm
subtracting this smaller area and I'm
subtracting now this larger area.
So I've got this negative sign here.
Now this region, if h is small enough, is
practically a rectangle, and it's
practically a rectangle of width h and
height let's say f of a.
So, that means that this difference is at
least approximately just h times the
function's value at a.
Now how does that help?
Remember what I'm trying to calculate.
I, I'm trying to differentiate the
interval from a to be with respect to a.
That means I'm trying to take the limit
of this difference quotient.
But the numerator here, we just saw, is
approximately, negative h times f of a.
And that means in the limit I expect to
get an answer of just negative f of a,
alright, these hs will cancel in the
limit, and that's exactly what I hope
for, right?
The derivitive of the integral from a to
b with respect to the left hand endpoint
a is negative f of a.
So I can summarize this.
The derivative with respect to a of the
integral from a to b of f of x dx is
negative f of a.
This fact coheres with a certain
convention about integration.
The convention that we use is that if we
integrate from a to b.
the function f of x dx that's negative
the interval from b to a of f of x dx.
So if you integrate the wrong way, so to
speak, we want to count that as negative
area.
>> Now in light of this convention, what do
we know?
>> So d da of the integral from a to b of f
of x dx is d da of this, negative the
integral from b to a of f of x dx.
But now this is the derivative of the top
end point which is just the usual
fundamental theorem of calculus.
So this is negative f of a.
So the upshot here is that
differentiating the integral from a to b,
with respect to the left hand or bottom
end point, Is negative the function's
value.
And that make sense because if you
increase the left hand endpoint that
decreases the area.
Alright, so it seems reasonable that a
negative sign should be popping up there.
And the cool thing is that, that fact is
cohering with a convention about
integration.
That compared to integrating the usual
way, if you integrate the wrong way you
introduce a negative sign.