[SOUND] Welcome to our course on
Interactive Computer Graphics.
In this course we will learn design and
implementation of interactive tools for
visual problem solving.
Visual problem solving appears
everyday in our daily life.
Medical doctors plan surgical operations.
Coaches teach how to play sports.
Engineers and
architects design products and buildings.
And fashion designers design garments.
Scientists try to understand nature.
All these activities involve
intensive visual problem solving.
And our goal is to have these
activities with computation tools.
And they have.
First, computers can help you
understand incoming visual information.
And the second,
computers can help you come up with new
solutions based on this information.
And finally, computers can help you
communicate these results to other people.
In this course, we will introduce various
tools we developed in our groups.
As example cases, topics include,
graphical user interfaces,
[SOUND] 2D Drawings, and [SOUND] 3D
modeling, and [SOUND] Fabrication,
and Computer-Aided Design, and
[SOUND] Real world interactions.
And then we'll show five demonstrations
on described implementation details.
Stay tuned.
I'm looking forward to seeing you.
Thank you.
[MUSIC]