[MUSIC]
Here is an ancient saying,
it is easier to destroy than to create.
Through mathematical instances
of this too like multiplying
as compared to antimultiplying.
What is antimultiplying?
Normal people wouldn't talk
about antimultiplying.
They'd talk about factoring.
Here's an example.
Suppose somebody gives you a number
like 247 to antimultiply that number,
which is just my crazy way of
saying factoring this number.
Means I want to write this as
something times something else.
And yeah, you can sort of play
around with this and try diving
this by various numbers, and you'll
eventually hit on 247 being 13 times 19.
Well, that seemed to
have come out of nowhere.
How did I figure that out?
Well, basically I just have to
keep trying to divide, right?
So to figure this out,
maybe I'd first see is 247 divisible by 3?
Well, 3 goes into 247 82 times,
but there's a remainder of 1.
So 82 time three isn't 247,
I've got that pesky remainder.
Maybe I'll try five,
does five go into 247?
Well clearly not, because the last
digit's not a zero or a five, right?
How many times does five
go into this thing?
I guess 49 times, and I get 245 and
that gives me a remainder of 2.
Does seven go into 247?
That's a lot harder to see
if 7 divides this number.
7 goes into this thing 35 times but
35 times 7 is 245 so
again there's a remainder of 2.
Does 11 go into this thing?
Does 11 go into 247?
It goes in there 22 times,
but 22 times 11 is 242.
Which again leaves me with a remainder,
in this case a remainder of 5.
And finally, I get to 13.
Does 13 go into 247?
Yes, 13 goes into this thing 19 times,
right?
And that's exactly what I'm looking for.
But the easy way here to antimultiply, or
to factor,
is just to try a bunch of stuff.
And hopefully,
you'll land on a product of numbers
that multiplies to your given number.
Why is factoring so difficult?
Yeah, so what we just saw is
that it was hard to factor 247.
It's hard to write this number as
a product of two other numbers.
But if somebody comes up to you and asks
you to check that 19 x 13 is equal to 247,
well that's super easy, right?
I can do this multiplication problem,
right?
9 times 3 is 27, 3 times 1 plus 2,
1 times 19, right, and I add.
And yeah, I mean, I get 247, right?
So it's easy to verify if I'm told the
answer that these numbers multiply to 247.
But it took some guessing, really, to
figure out that 247 factored in this way.
Well this is an example where undoing
an operation is much harder than just
performing that operation.
All right, here's a piece of paper.
It's very easy for
me to rip the piece of paper.
It's harder for
me to unrip the piece of paper.
And honestly, 247's not even that bad.
Take a look at this number, 311,512,699.
It turns out right that this number is
the product of two other whole numbers.
It turns out this is 17,551 times 17,749,
but how would you ever have known that?
It would have been a real
pain to do a bunch of tests
to see which numbers divide this number.
And since these two numbers are prime,
there's no other smaller numbers
that go into this number evenly.
So it would have been a ton of work.
And yet, if somebody tells you,
do these two numbers multiplied to this,
that is easy to verify, because you can
just multiply these two numbers and
check that they really
give you this number.
But undoing that multiplication,
starting with this number and
trying to find these two numbers,
would really be a pain.
Now, in that situation, a computer could
just search for the factorization.
But what if I gave you a number
that was much, much bigger?
Well, here's a 240 digit
number that I've cooked up.
I got this number by taking two prime
numbers and multiplying them together.
Probably I'm the only person on Earth who
knows the factorization of that number.
I got that number by taking
two big prime numbers and
multiplying them together, but nobody else
but me knows what those prime numbers are.
For someone else to come along and
find those two factors
would be really difficult.
The cool consequence is that if I were
to reveal to you the factorization
of that large number, well that would be
evidence that I'm really who I say I am.
Because who else in the world knows
the factorization of that enormous number.