[MUSIC]
Well now, it's time to do some calculus.
Calculus is all about relationships.
All throughout the world,
there's these quantities.
And some of those quantities
are connected together.
Well how so?
Maybe one of those quantities is
the input to some sort of machine,
or some sort of mathematical expression
that transforms that quantity in
to a new quantity, an output quantity.
Maybe two of those quantities are forced
to vary together for some reason.
Maybe you've just got a table
of numbers that tell you
how to take certain input values
to certain output values.
Maybe you've got a graph that
you're reading that tells you
how to take an x coordinate and
output a y coordinate.
But regardless of how you
conceptualize this idea,
there's relationships between different
quantities in the real world and
we're often encoding those
relationships through functions.
The other big idea I wanna
think about now are limits.
Sometimes I'm not just interested in
a function's value at a single point.
Sometimes I wanna know what happens
if I evaluated that function
at nearby points as well.
And try to make sense of that precisely,
that's what limits are gonna do for us.
So to begin our quest in calculus,
we're gonna look at two big ideas.
We're gonna look at functions and
we're gonna look at limits.
[MUSIC]