[MUSIC].
The basic idea of integration by parts is
that it lets you differentiate part of
the integrand, but only if you're willing
to pay a price.
And that price is anti-differentiating
the other part of the integrand.
Well, let's try it.
For example, let's find an
anti-derivative of x times e to the x.
If we're going to attack this integrand
by parts, then I've got to pick a u and a
dv.
I'd be willing to differentiate x.
That'll make x just go away.
And the price I'd have to pay is to
anti-differentiate what remains.
But anti-differentiating e to the x is
not much of a price to pay because e to
the x is its own anti-derivative.
So let's set that down.
Let's set u to the x, because I'd like to
differentiate that part.
And I'm willing to anti-differentiate
what remains.
Now, let's figure out du and v.
Now if u is x, then du is dx.
And then, I've got to pick an
anti-derivative for dv.
Now, in principle, there's a ton of
anti-derivatives I could pick, right?
e to the x plus 17 differentiates the e
to the x.
But I'll just pick the nice one.
I'll pick e to the x.
Now I've got u, dv, v, and du.
We can put it all together.
Parts tells me that an anti-derivative u
dv is uv minus anti-derivative v du.
So, in this case, the anti-derivative of
u dv is u times v, x times e to the x
minus anti-derivative of v du, which is
just dx.
But, I know how to integrate e to the x.
Anti-derivative of e to the x is just
itself.
So, the anti-derivative of x, e to the x
is x, e to the x minus e to the x plus
some constant.
We did it, and we can check our answer.
So we have to differentiate this and make
sure I get x, e to the x.
Let's try it.
So, if I differentiate xe to the x minus
e to the x, I don't need to add the plus
C because if I differentiate a constant,
I just get 0.
All right, this is a derivative of a
difference so it's the difference of the
derivatives.
But now this is a derivative of a
product, so I'm going to use the product
rule.
I'm going to take the derivative of the
first, so the derivative of x, times the
second, plus the first times the
derivative of a second, right?
That's the product rule.
And then I subtract, well, the derivative
of e to the x is just itself.
And I've got the derivative of x, which
is 1 times e to the x plus x times the
derivative of e to the x e to the x minus
e to the x.
And here's the slightly exciting part,
right?
This and this cancel, and all I'm left
with is just x times e to the x.
So, in fact, we have found an
anti-derivative for x e to the x.
Here it is.
And of course, that makes sense because
integration by parts is just a product
rule in reverse.
Now, we can use the same trick to attack
similar integration problems.
For example, let's say you want to
anti-differentiate some polynomial in x
times e to te x.
You could do this with parts.
Well, how?
Well, I've made this be u and I make this
be dv.
And why is that such a great choice?
Well, think about what parts lets you do.
Parts lets you differentiate part of the
integrand if you're willing to
anti-differentiate the rest.
But anti-differentiating e to the x is
paying no price at all because it's its
own anti-derivative.
And, if you differentiate the polynomial,
then you reduce its degree.
So, by doing parts enough times,
eventually you're just
anti-differentiating e to the x by
itself, which you can definitely do.