[MUSIC] Integrating requires patience.
Sometimes you can start attacking the
monster, but it might take a little bit
of time before you start to see success.
Prepare to persevere.
Let's attack the indefinite integral of
cosx times e to the x dx.
There's a metaphor here.
There's really different ways to win the
battle.
Suppose this is you, and this is the
integral that you're trying to attack.
One way, is you know, to try and do it by
hand, right.
To take your shield and to take your
sword, and just to evaluate that integral
directly by, say going back to the
definition of Riemann sum.
But we almost never attack integrals in
this way.
Instead of using, you know, swords and
shields, we're really using, you know,
magic.
Right?
We're putting on our wizard hat.
And instead of trying to kill the
intregral, right?
We use something like u substitution to
transform that integration problem into a
friendly integration problem that we can
actually deal with, right?
We're never attacking integrals directly
we're just transforming integrals by
doing u substitutions or parts.
So let's try to transform the integration
that we're attacking here.
Let's tranform e to the x cosx to
something else.
So I'll use what u, I'll make u be e to
the x.
because I don't really mind
differentiating that.
And I'll make dv cosx dx.
Now in that case, the derivative of e to
the x is just e to the x.
And what's an anti-derivative of cosine?
An anti-derivative of cosine is sine.
Now what is integration by parts say.
So then anti-derivative of cosx e to the
x dx is U times V, so e to the x sinx
minus the intergral of V du So, sinx, e
to the x dx.
Well that didn't really help matters.
But the word of the day is persevere.
So let's persevere, and transform that
integral into yet another monster.
So the monster in this case is this thing
here.
let's try the same trick on that new
integral.
So U will be e to the x again and dv
here, will be just what's left over, sine
x dx.
And in that case, if U is e to the x,
then du is e to the x dx.
And, if dv is sin x dx, well, I've got
other choices for more anti-derivative,
but I'll have v be minus cosx.
Now, I've put this into the integration
by parts formula.
So the antiderivative of sinx e to the x
dx is uv, so minus e to the x cosx minus
vdu.
So my-, the integral of vdu, so v is
cosx, and du is e to the x dx.
Now what's happened thus far in the
battle?
I'm attacking this integral.
I used integration by parts to transform
the monster into something else.
It didn't help, so I used that magical
weapon again.
I used integration by parts again to
transform the integration problem into
yet another integration problem and it
didn't help.
Or did it?
What happens if I put these two
integration facts together?
Well, and then I've got here, the
integral of cosx, e to the x dx, is equal
to e to the x sin x minus the integral of
sinx, e to the x, dx, which is down here.
So minus negative e to x cos x plus the
integral of cosine x e to the dx.
Lets persevere, lets keep going.
So this is saying the integral of cos x e
to the x dx is e to the x sin x plus e to
the x, cosine x, minus the integral of
cosine x, e to the x, dx.
Now I'm going to add the integral of cos
x e to the x, dx to both sides.
And what I'll then get is 2 times the
integral of cos x e to the x, dx is equal
to, well what's left on the righthand
side, e to the x sin x plus e to the x,
cos x.
And then I'll divide both sides by 2, and
if I divide this side by 2 and this side
by 2 well then these 2's cancel, and I
find out that an antiderivative of cosine
x e to the x Is e to the x sin x plus z
to the x cos x all over 2.
What we did here is one of my favorite
applications of integration by parts.
We didn't use integration by parts to
solve, to evaluate the integral directly.
Instead, I applied parts twice and ended
up with a clone of the original monster.
So how did that go?
Well, here you are, right, and you're a
wizard, so here's your wizard hat, and
here's the integral that we wanted to
attack.
But we didn't attack this integral
directly.
We didn't' even transform this integral
by using U substitution.
Instead, we used parts twice and it
seemed like that was a terrible idea
because when I applied parts twice, I
ended up with a clone of the original
monster.
The same integral ended up appearing.
But, that other integral came with a
minus sign.
And, consequently that monster ends up
defeating itself and we're able to
evaluate the integral without actually
integrating at all.
If anything suggests that there's
creativity in the battles ahead of us, I
think integration by parts is telling us,
to be prepared to be amazed.