[MUSIC]
In this fifth module we are discussing
the internal structure of hadrons and
strong interactions.
This fifth video will
examine the consequences
of the fact that strong interactions
become stronger with distance.
After having watched this video, you will
understand why one cannot observe free
quarks, and what happens when the quark,
antiquark pair is created in vacuo.
Because of the enormous amount of
energy stored in a color field at large
distances, separated color charges will
create additional particles instead
of becoming free quarks or gluons.
A dynamic separation occurs, for
example, in the e+ e- annihilation
into quark antiquark pairs at
high energy far above threshold.
The left figure shows the Feynman diagram,
the right figure,
the kinematics in
the center-of-mass frame.
The central figure is an example of
an event of this kind showing multiple
hadrons in the final state.
Again, there are two approaches
to qualitatively understand
the process of hadron
formation in the final state.
a chromostatic one and
a more chromodynamic approach.
In a chromostatic approach,
the quark-antiquark pair
creates further quark antiquark
pairs as soon as the original pair is
separated by of the order of 1 fm.
At this distance, the stored field
energy is large enough to do this.
This process continues until
the relative momentum of the quarks is
sufficiently moderated to permit
the formation of bound states.
Hadron formation occurs along strings,
a kind of elastic
band connecting two color charges thus
with limited transverse momentum.
The hadrons thus form jets which
approximately follow the initial direction
of the quark and the antiquark.
In a more chromodynamic approach,
the process can be visualized
in terms of a quark-gluon cascade.
It starts with the emission
of a gluon by the quark, or
the antiquark as shown
in this Feynman diagram.
This gluon can produce either
a quark antiquark pair, or
a pair of gluons, according to
the elementary vertices of QCD.
Because there are more gluons than quarks,
splitting into gluons is more probable,
and is thus shown in this Feynman graph.
The strong coupling
will become the larger,
the more the invariant mass q^2 of
the virtual particles involved diminishes.
At the end of the cascade, the quarks
will form colorless bound states.
It is clear that this
approach cannot be used
up to the end of
the hadronization process.
At small q squared, the coupling constant
becomes so large that a perturbative
expansion in powers of the coupling
constant will no longer converge.
In this domain,
collective effects take over which end up
by the formation of mesons and baryons.
They must be described by
more phenomenological models.
The hadrons are formed in vacuo at
the end of the quark gluon cascade.
Their transverse momenta with respect
to the original quark direction are thus
limited by Heisenberg's
principle to some 300 MeV.
Hadrons are thus concentrated around
the initial quark direction and form jets.
Their transverse momentum is small,
and independent of the quark momentum.
Thus, jets become more and more
collimated as the quark energy increases.
If the first gluon emitted in
the cascade has sufficient
transverse momentum with respect
to the natural width of a jet,
a third hadron jet will become
visible along the gluon direction.
One thus observes an event with
three jets as shown in this example.
These events can be attributed to
the reaction e+ e- -> q qbar gluon.
The cross section for this process
e+ e- -> q qbar gluon
is calculated using the Feynman
diagrams as shown on the left.
The gluon emission from a quark
has all the characteristics of
a Bremsstrahlung process.
Its amplitude has two divergences,
becomes very large for
the emission of a low-energy gluon,
which is an infrared divergence.
It also blows up for a very forward
emission by a collinear divergence.
In both cases, the quark and
gluon jets will merge.
Two as well as three jet events are
counted among the hadronic final states.
In the calculation we must thus add their
cross section to obtain the total hadronic
cross section introduced in video 4.5.
One thus obtains a better approximation
for the ratio R at high energies in better
agreement with the experimental data
as shown on the right of this graph.
Jets appear without exception
whenever a high energy quark or
gluon converts into hadrons.
This means, first of all,
that the probability for
the hadronization process is 1.
It is an inevitable process.
Second, the conservation
of energy-momentum and
the limitation of transverse momentum
by Heisenberg's principle means that
jets follow the direction and represent
the energy of the initial quark or gluon.
And this with the more and more narrow
collimation as the energy increases.
This event shows a final
state with two energetic jets
produced in a proton-proton
collision at the LHC.
On the top you see a zoom of the inner
detector and the calorimeters.
On the left, you see multiple vertices.
The high luminosity of the collider
causes multiple reactions at the same
bunch crossing.
The two reactions with most of the
deposited energy, which are colored in red
and green, show back to back jets
which are strongly collimated.
The bottom image on the right shows
a histogram of the directional
distribution of energy.
The two narrow peaks correspond to the
direction and the energy of the two jets.
This concludes our short
discussion of strong interactions.
In the next module, we will deal with weak
interactions and the Higgs mechanism.
[MUSIC]