>> Welcome to the last module of this
entire course.
In this module, Module 7, I will be
putting all of the pieces that we have
developed together into one neat unified
package.
And what we're going to have to do in this
module is, connect the robotics piece that
we discussed early on differential drive,
mobile robots, odometry sensors to the
control theoretic developments that we've
gone through.
And in particular, we need to see how we
can take the navigation algorithms we have
developed, and actually make them fit onto
the actual robotic platforms that we're
interested in.
And the first lecture is really going to
be a little bit of a high level
discussions of what are the things that we
need to be aware of when we start putting
things together.
I've call it approximations and
abstractions and the reason for that is
whenever we try to design control systems
or navigation algorithms, we're using
models.
And we need to understand when these
models are indeed relevant or useful, or
applicable.
So, recall our rather messy, yet exciting
hybrid automoton.
When we developed this, we assumed that we
had perfect sensing.
We even assumed that x dot was equal to u,
meaning that we directly could control the
velocities of, of the robot.
But then, as we saw at the end of the last
module, we ran it on a differential drive
mobile robot.
And these two robot, or systems, the
actual differential drive mobile robot and
x dot equal to u, it's very unclear what
they even have in common.
How do we make our models fit the reality,
or more importantly, when are the models
relevant to the real world?
Well, I like to think of models as fables.
Let's return to our old friend, the hare
and the tortoise.
So, when we discuss the Zeno phenomenon,
we had the hare race the tortoise.
Well, I don't exactly know where all of
you live but chances are that where you
live, very rarely do you see hares and
tortoises actually racing.
So, here's a story or a fable that never
applies, but somehow, we still gain some
kind of insight into the real world from
this story.
Like, slow and steady wins the race if the
tortoise wins.
Or, in the Zeno case, the hare is going to
win.
Well, what we should take away from that
is, well, don't rush it when you're doing
the quizzes for this course.
So now, the hare and the tortoise actually
had something to say about how we should
approach the course.
And similarly, the models are fables.
They have some relevance, but they're not
exactly telling the full story.
So, let's take a step back and see what
assumptions did we actually make and what
kind of models did we actually use when we
were talking about the robots.
Well, we really had two main classes of
assumptions.
One was the dynamics.
And when we developed our control
algorithms, we made the assumption that we
had this particle located at x, where we
immediately controlled the velocity, x dot
is equal to u.
Well, that may or may not be reasonable.
We also made this assumption that the
robot has a sensor suite.
It's actually one of these sensor skirts
that allows the robot to see roughly, a
disk around it that's not exactly true,
because as we saw in the last module, we
only see certain parts of this disk.
But from, in assumption point of view, we
still kind of made the assumption that, we
cannot, we can see everything around us up
to a point and we can measure where
obstacles are and the angle to that
obstacle.
When it turns out that the sensing
assumption is more or less okay.
As the robot moves around, you can
actually build up rather accurate models
or, or maps of what's going on in the
world.
The problem is with the dynamics.
This is not even close to being
reasonable.
The Khepera [inaudible] that we've used a
lot, it's not, at all, looking like x dot
is equal to u.
So, in order for our fable, or our model,
or our navigation algorithm to be relevant
to the actual robot, we somehow need to
remedy this lack of reasonability.
So, the problem, of course, is that we
have the point mass.
And then we're using the unicycle model
for actually describing the robot, where x
dot is v cosine phi, where v is the speed
and phi is the heading, y dot was v sine
phi, and phi dot was equal to omega, where
omega was the angular velocity.
Well, this robot, this model, doesn't act
like x dot is equal to u and somehow for
what we've done during the last couple of
modules to be relevant, we need to make
these two models actually co-exist
peacefully.
So, what we're going to spend the next two
lectures on is a very, very simple problem
which is, how do we make a unicycle robot
or a differential drive model robot act
like x dot is equal to u?