We saw that the one remaining challenge
is, how do we actually make our real
robot or a model of the real robot, which
was the unicyle model, behave or act like
the simpler model x dot is equal to u,
that we used when we designed our
navigation architecture.
And we really have a problem because we
used the simplest possible model,
x dot equal to u, as the basis for our
control design.
And then, we started switching between go
to goal, follow wall, follow wall
counterclockwise avoid obstacles and so
forth. And the navigation architecture we
ended up with is this, as we've seen a
couple of times now, rather messy-looking
hybrid system.
Now, what we need to do is somehow come
up with a way of making the real robot
relevant or this model relevant to the
real robot.
And
we would like also to do this in such a
way that we don't have to worry too much
about what kind of robot is it that we're
using? We want this navigation
architecture to be relevant for
differential drive robots or 4-wheel
robots or snake robots or flying
quadrotors.
So, the question is, how do we do this?
And the standard way of approaching this
problem is to produce a layered
architecture, where you have different
levels of abstraction. So, in today's
lecture, I'm going to talk about the
standard layers that people think of when
they build architectures high-level
architectures for robotic systems.
Well, the standard and most canonical way
in which people approach this is to have
three levels and borrowing terms from the
military tactical literature people
typically talk about a strategic level
and operational level and a tactical
level.
So, the strategic level is high level.
Where do we go? Recall, for instance,
that we have go to golal behaviors,
we have a goal point, well, where did
that goal point come from? Who decided
that that's reasonable?
Well, that happens at the strategic
level, where the high level decisions are
being made.
And then at the operational level, you're
trying to figure out, okay, I know that
there is a goal point somewhere out
there, where do I go now? Meaning, this
is a short term, low-level planning
problem. And in many ways, we can think
of our x dot equal to u model to live at
the operational level.
But then, we have the lowest level, the
tactical level, which asks, well, okay, I
know that I want to go this way but how
do I actually do that?
I am snake robot, how does a snake go in
this direction or I am a differential
drive mobile robot,
a unicycle, how do I actually go in this
direction? So, the question of mapping x
dot equal to u onto the real robot is a
question of moving in between these two
levels or layers in the architecture.
While, if you want to be slightly less
militaristic,
which, maybe we do we can call the
highest level a high-level planning
level.
We want to plan where the intermediary
goal points should really be.
And then, the low-level planning that's
the question of which direction to move
in-between these goal points.
And then at the execution level that we
previously called the tactical level,
it's just a matter of how do we actually
execute this? How do we make the robot do
what it is that we want it to do? And I
should point out that the highest level,
we haven't touched at all in this course.
In fact, we have assumed that someone
very clever has designed a, an AI,
artificial intelligence algorithm for
somehow producing the correct goal
points.
And then, at the low-level, well, that's
where our navigation architecture sits.
That's where we're assuming that x dot is
equal to u, which really tells the robot,
if I'm here, this is x, then u is really
going to be, this is the direction in
which I would like to move.
So, the navigation architecture we've
seen really sits squarely at the
low-level planning layer.
And then, of course the execution level.
Well, one thing we can do is simply say,
here is our actual system.
Let's say x dot is, oh, let's, let's say,
it's a complicated nonlinear system.
This is a slithering robot, that every
now and then, can fly.
I don't know how to build that, but if I
did, that's what this system would be.
And now, I would like it to follow, let's
say, this reference.
And this reference is generated as if x
dot is equal to u.
Well, this is simply r, right, a
reference signal.
And we have seen repeatedly how to design
controllers for making systems, general
systems, track reference signals.
So, the execution problem be, really
becomes a question of how do you track
reference signals? Well, we kind of know
how to do this, at least for linear
systems, so that seems rather promising,
as far as I can,
I can tell.
Okay, let's discuss these levels a little
bit more.
at the high-level, like I said, it's
really not part of the, the course, there
are many, many different ways in which
people think about how to produce these
high-level plans.
Typically, you somehow discretize the
world into a graph structure or somehow,
a kind of grid structure and then you can
use Dijkstra's algorithm for searching
through graphs, something called Dynamic
Programming.
There are more specialized robotic
planning algorithms, something called A*,
a version of A* called D*, which is a
dynamic version of A*, or something
called RRTs, Rapidly Exploring Randomized
Trees.
These are all methods for generating
these intermediary waypoints.
And this big picture here, you're seeing
underneath it is, this is the kind of
maps that we produce at the high-level
kind of plans and maps we produce at the
high-level at, when we're building this
autonomous self-driving car.
So, this map clearly doesn't tell us how
the car should drive but it tells us
where do we want to go and how are the
things that we want to go to connect it.
So,
all I want to say about this is if your'e
interested in probing further when it
comes to high-level methods this six
different methods are good places to
start if you want to to learn more about
these high-level methods.
Okay, low-level, well, ta-da, we already
know how to do this.
The simplest thing is to assume a very
simple model, in our case, we've said x
dot is equal to u, and then we simply go
to work.
Again, if I do that, my model, x dot is
equal u model,
is going to produce a trajectory that we
would like the actual robot to follow.
So, this trajectory becomes the plan, the
low-level plan that will take us, let's
say, that here is a, a goal point and
here was an obstacle.
Well, this low-level plan will tell us
how we should go about avoiding the
obstacle and going to goal, but it
doesn't at all tell us how to achieve it,
which leaves us with the execution level.
as you can see, this is the video that
I've shown before of our self-driving car
that is trying to to drive around in the
world.
Well, the car, it's not a unicycle, but
it's almost a unicycle.
but, if we're trying to build a
navigation system explicitly for a
unicycle, it's not going to work, it's
going to be too complex.
So, what we had to do in order to make
this car actually drive, was well, plan
at a high-level, then a low-level, and
then make the car execute the trajectory.
So, for instance here, you're seeing the
car overtaking an obstacle and what's
going on here is that we have a low-level
planner that's telling it roughly how to
do it.
And as you can see, the car overshoots a
little bit and this is due to the fact
that the execution level reference
trajectory isn't perfect.
Okay, so, what we've now arrived at is a
layered architecture where at the highest
level, we're generating sequences of
intermediary waypoints.
Well, those waypoints are fed into the
plan level or the low-level plan level
where our navigation architecture
generates reference trajectories.
Well, these reference trajectories are
then fed into our actual nonlinear
systems.
The actual dynamics were u now, well,
it's going to be function of this state,
and r, where r is the reference and then
out of the trajectory comes the actual
trajectory, the actual control signals
that will be running on the robot.
So, what I want to do in the next lecture
is take this high-level view of a layered
architecture for robots and apply it to
the [UNKNOWN] or 2-differential drive
mobile robots, in general.
So that's it.