The outcome of the last handful of
lectures was that we can really use a
layered architecture to make our robots
act like a simpler system.
Like x dot = u, in our case.
And they key idea was to plan using the
simple dynamics.
And then track using some clever
controller.
And what we saw last time was we could
use a PID regulator, for instance for,
controlling the heading of the robot, and
then simply set the velocity of the robot
equal to the magnitude of the planned
velocity, u.
Well, today, I want to discuss another
twist to this theme.
In fact, I want to be even more clever.
And there is a particularly eloquent and
cute way you can think about unicycles.
And in general I'm not a big fan of
clever tricks for the sake of clever
tricks, but because differential drive
mobile robots are so common.
And we know that unicycles model them
well, then this trick becomes more than
just a piece of mathematical curiosity,
becomes an effective way of thinking
about a large, a large and rich class of
mobile robots.
So, instead of doing tracking, we're
going to transform the unicycle dynamics.
So recall that we have the position xy,
we have the heading phi, and we have the
dynamics as seen here.
Well, typically, what we've seen so far
is, we want the robot not to slam into
things, we want the robot to end up on
top of goal points we want the robot to
folow walls.
We don't particularly care which way it's
pointing, so the first thing we're going
to do is say, you know what let's just
pretend that we don't worry about
orientation whatsoever.
Well, we still have a rather awkward
looking nonlinear differential equation
but let, now, pick another point.
Let's not pick x, y, which as you
remember, was really the point right in
between the wheels of the
differential-drive mobile robot.
What if we picked another point, instead?
Let's pick this point.
The red point here.
And let's say, that the distance between,
the red point and the black point.
That's, that's some distance l, where l
is some small number.
What would happen if we looked at this
new point, instead? Well, let's place the
new point at x tilde y tilde The next
tilde is simply x + l cosine phi.
Simple geometry.
And y tilde is y + l sine phi.
Where, again, l is the distance removing
our point along the heading of, of the
robot.
Well, let's see what the dynamics of this
new point.
The tilde point actually looks like.
Well, this is our old dynamics this how X
and Y and phata actually behaves.
This is our new point and now, what we
need to do is put dots over the tildes to
see.
What do the time derivatives actually
look like? Well, it's not so complicated.
X till the dot, well, it's x dot + the
time derivative of this thing, and, the
time derivative of cosine phi, and
remember phi is a function of t, if I
take ddt of this thing, then.
What I get, is, I get - phi dot * sin
phi.
Well, that's what we have here, x tilde
dot, is x dot - l phi dot sin phi, and
similarly for y, tilde dot.
Alright, this still doesn't seem all that
helpful, to be completely honest, so lets
simplify this a little bit.
Well, first of all, I know what x dot is.
It's this thing here, so instead of that,
I'm just plugging in v cosine phi.
I also know what phi dot is.
It's, it's omega.
So, now I end up with a slightly, less
scary-looking expression.
And, then we do the same thing for y
tilde dot.
Well okay, where does this lead us? Well,
let's assume for a second that we can
control this new point directly.
That this new point is indeed, the point
that we before have called x dot = to u,
as a way of generating reference
velocities.
Let's assume that we can actually
immediately control this new point.
What would that tell us? Well, x tilde
dot as you recall, was given by this
mouthful of an expression.
Well, let's set this equal to u1 which is
our desired velocity in the x direction.
And similarly, we set y tilde dot = u2.
Now, all we need to do at least, well I
can say all we need to do, I don't know
if we can do it.
But, all we would like to do is actually
solve this equation with respect to V and
omega.
Because, if we did that, we would relate
the actual velocities of the unicycle to
these u1 and u2 velocities, which are The
planned velocities.
So let's see if we can do that.
Well the first thing we do is we pull out
the cosine and the sine terms.
So we get that cosine * v - sine * l
omega well that's that thing, that's
equal to u1.
And similarly for the y tilde dot, or the
u2 dot, sorry, the u2 equation.
I don't know, this equation still looks a
little hairy but, as you hopefully
recall, this matrix right here is a
rather nice matrix.
It is, in fact, a rotation matrix.
All it's doing is it's taking a vector
and rotating it theta degrees.
Actually, it's rotating it phi degrees,
but it is a very well behaved and well
understood matrix,
okay?
I don't particularly like l there,
because l is not part of what I would
like.
I would like v and omega and, no l.
So, what I can do, is I can rewrite this
thing as, a matrix, a diagonal matrix,
with one on the first diagonal, and l on
the second diagonal, simply times v, and
omega.
And if I do that,
I get the following expression.
Rotation matrix phi, sorry, yeah, phi, *
this matrix, v omega.
Well, these are all invertable.
What is the inverse of the rotation
matrix? Well, the rotation matrix rotates
something phi degrees.
Well, the inverse would be to rotate it
back, right? Then you're back where you
started.
That's -5.
So, R inverse phi always exists and it
corresponds to rotating it back five
degrees.
So, we can invert this matrix easily.
Well, this is a diagonal matrix, and the
inverse of this thing is simply the
inverse of the diagonal, 1 / 1 00 1 / l.
So the inverse of this thing is also
trivial.
That means that I can actually solve
directly for V and omega, no problem.
No questions asked, no tracking, no
approximation, just bam, I get the right
velocities out.
So if I have my low level plan producing
U1 and U2, then I can transform that into
V and omega directly.
And this seems almost too good to be
true, and it is too good to be true,
because remember We're actually not
making x y behave perfectly, we're making
this new point that we call x tilde y
tilde, we're making that point behave
perfectly.
And then we have l, that tells us how far
away we are, and by making l small, we're
getting closer to x and y, so you
practice.
You pick l tiny and then you go to work.
So what does this mean, it means that
before we had a planner we used our
complicated navigation algorithm to spid
out u1 and u2 all right and then we had a
tracker and in our case we use the PID
tracker for the heading and simply set
the velocity equal to the magnitude of u
and from that we got v and omega out.
Well now, we don't have to deal with
trackers.
We've actually replaced second part with
a transformation of the unicycle where
we're simply saying that V and omega, or
these 2 matrices * u1, u2.
And again, these matrices are, not
particularly complicated to compute.
This, is simply the rotation matrix and
phi of course we have.
This is one, easy to compute, it's just
one.
And ;; is something that we decide, so
what we put here, this is 1 / l, l should
be small so 1 / l should be some large
number, right? And the larger this number
becomes the closer the tilde the point
and the actual point approach each other.
I should put out a little warning though
that if you make this number too large,
then you get a behavior where the robot
starts turning quite a bit, because this
going to hit omega directly.
Okay but, this gives us a direct
transformation, instead of a tracker, to
produce the desired velocities.
And the reason why I like this trick, and
why this trick shouldn't be thought of as
simply, an interesting little curiosity
because it is kind of interesting is that
so many robots are differential drive
robots, and this transformation applies
to all of them, because all of them can
be mapped onto the unicycle dynamics.
So, that takes care of, how do we
actually go from low-level plans.
To executable, desired velocities for
differential drive mobile robots.