The punch line with last lecture was that
we can, in fact, make the unicycle model
or a differential drive mobile robot, act
like a simple x dot equal to u.
What this means is that if we have some
desired direction we want to go in,
direction and magnitude, we can come up
with v's and omega's, speeds and angular
velocities that make the differential
drive robot execute this controller.
And we did it in two ways.
First, we saw that we can actually use
some kind of tracking controller to
follow this.
But then, in last lecture, we came up
with a rather clever transformation that
allowed us to, to actually track this u
vector more or less perfectly.
And when I say more or less, what I mean
is that we really ignored orientation.
So, we only cared about where the robot
actually was,
not particularly which direction it was
pointing.
And we couldn't track or used the
original point, we had to accept this
small offset error.
But it was rather elegant, because no
longer did we have to design trackers.
the question one should ask then, of
course, is does this apply to other types
of robots? Meaning, this idea of starting
with a unicycle and then somehow making
it behave well,
how, how relevant is that to other kinds
of robots? So, we have dealt with the
differential drive robots.
We know that it's super important in
relevance to that but you know what, what
if you have flying things? What if you
have snake bots? What if you have, this
is called a snake board, what if you have
fixed-wing aircrafts or blimps or
underwater robots? Does this even apply?
Well,
what I want to do today is basically see
that it does supply but, it does supply
if you squint your eyes a little bit and
focus on what these types of robots have
in common as opposed to what they don't
have in common.
So, what I want to do today is simply go
through a smorgasbord of different robot
classes and see how they actually are
like unicycles or maybe not.
We'll see.
Okay.
Here's the unicycle,
right? We have, as always, position, x y,
and it's pointing in some direction,
phi, this is the standard robot model.
So, the states are position and
orientation.
The inputs to this model, this
abstraction, are angular and
transalational velocitiies.
Meaning, how quickly do you turn and how
fast do you go.
Well, let's start expanding this model to
encompass slightly more elaborate
systems.
So, let's start with what's called a
car-like robot.
A car-like robot is not a unicycle
because all of a sudden, we have more
states.
We have our old friends which is x and y,
which is the position.
We have phi which is the orientation, but
then we also have a new angle known as
the steering angle.
So, here is the picture we should have in
mind.
Here's a car, here are the rear wheels.
Well, the front wheels are going to be
turned because we're turning the steering
wheel.
So, if I call this point here, x and y,
as always, then this, of course, is, as
before, the heading.
And now, we also have this angle here,
which is psi, known as the steering
angle,
how much are we actually steering it. And
all I wanted to show here is that we have
almost the same equation for x and y, the
only difference is that we are now going
in this direction, which is phi plus psi.
and then, the orientation has its own
dynamics that's a function of the
velocity and the steering angle.
And then, what we can do is we can
control how quickly we're steering.
So, psi dot is equal to u.
So, this is the next level up in
complexity where we no longer have a
unicycle but a car-like robot, four
wheels we can turn the front wheels.
Well we've already seen the Segway robot.
So, the Segway robot is really a unicycle
or a differential drive robot at the
base.
And then, you know, this, this mess here.
I drew it like this because it actually
didn't fit in the box if I didn't make it
small and sideways.
The point is that, we had a rather
complicated equation describing the
pendulum part or the part that's sitting
on top of the unicycle.
So, we had a bunch of states, position,
orientation, tilt, angle, and here, we
actually had to deal with the tilt
velocities and other kinds of velocities
because we actually need to get into
dynamics.
Many accelerations of what's happening
for this thing not to fall over and the
inputs were the wheel torques to this
model.
The point now is that this still has a
unicycle underneath and then this mass
sitting on top of it.
So, that would, would be the Segway robot
that we actually already seen.
Well, what about flying things? Well, a
standard model for a fixed-wing aircraft
is ta-da, a unicycle, right? Which means,
it's moving.
And then, it can change altitude.
So now, no one in their right mind would
actually say that this is what a,
an aircraft is actually doing but from a
high level obstruction point of view,
it's not a bad idea.
An aircraft can't go sideways but it can
kind of move like a unicyle in, in the
plane.
And then, you can change altitude.
now, you would actually have to couple
this to the real dynamics of the aircraft
if you wanted to do it for real.
the one thing to note though is that
there is something slightly fishy about
this and that's the fact that the fixed
wing aircraft cannot hover.
When you can't have v=0, but there's
really no constraint or no way of
capturing this in, this model, we see
later how to do it, but the point here is
that there are ways of thinking about
flying things as unicycles plus an
altitude component.
Now, let's look at another model.
This is the standard model of an
underwater glider,
and, well, let's go back a slide.
Aircraft, underwater glider, nothing
changed, right?
So, an underwater glider, people
typically model as a unicycle.
And then, you can go up and down.
So, you can go down to a lower depth or
you could climb up towards the surface.
So, again, unicycle plus an altitude or a
vertical component that describes how
high up or high down the, the robot
actually is.
Well,
all of these robots have some notion of
where it is at least in the plane and
where it's pointing.
And if I call position plus heading for
POSE, the punchline, at least based on
the models I showed you, cars, segways,
flying things, things on the water, and
as we know, differential drive robots,
they have this key thing to it known as
POSE.
And POSE is x, y, and phi.
You know, that's just, that's just what's
going on, where is it and which way is it
pointing.
It's pointing in the phi direction
instead of the x and y.
Well, you know what, if you ignore the
dynamics, the actual dynamics and say at
the certain high level abstraction, we
already know how we should think about
this,
the unicycle. So, almost everything
involves a POSE.
And almost everything with POSE is almost
a unicycle and I will make this more
precise.
But the point here is that whenever you
start dealing with postion and heading,
the unicycle model is applicable, maybe
not perfectly, but fairly well.
So, this model is still very, very rich.
So, the punchline then becomes that we
can almost use everything that we've
already done and then possibly add
another layer to to what's going on.
So, what you have, is you have, let's
say, your, your u plan, right, that comes
into your unit cycle, and out of that
comes our old friends, v and omega, and
then, whatever actual robot you have is
going to move like this.
[SOUND] And the point is that, in here,
we may be forced to somehow make the
actual robot look like a unicycle a
little bit.
But it's just another layer to our
already elegant and well-layered
architecture that we've discussed.
And, in fact, next time, what I want to
do is exactly this for the car robot, to
see how do you make a car act like a
unicycle and this is something I had to
do when I was dealing with the autonomous
self-driving cars.
We were reasoning about them at the level
of position and orientation and speeds
and angular velocities but then we have
to map it back onto the, onto the, the
car robot.
Before we do that though, I need to talk
a little bit about constraints.
What I mean, mean by that is if you're
flying, for instance,
you can't hover.
You're going to have a certain minimum
velocity or a lot of times, it's
convenient to assume a fixed velocity and
then you can turn.
But here's an aircraft.
It can't immediately or very quickly just
spin either.
So, there are caps on how quickly you can
actually turn.
Well, the most famous of all constrained
unicycle type models is known as Dubins
vehicle. And all it is is a unicycle with
the added caveat that we can only fly
with v=1 or drive with v=1, meaning we're
going to go with a constant velocity and
we have a max and a minimum angular
velocity.
If you want, you can say, you know, v0
there and omega v max or omega max plus
omega max instead of -1 and 1, but the
point is that we're constraining the
velocities.
This means, that Dubins vehicle can
basically execute straight lines, it can
go along paths like this so, so it can go
along angles, I mean, along circular
arcs.
Or it can go anything in between,
right? But basically, you have, you
cannot go arbitrarily tight with a Dubins
vehicle.
So, this is one way in which people
incorporate constraints.
And this makes the planning part
significantly harder.
We're not going to cover it, but I
encourage you to look up Dubins vehicles,
for instance, to see how people think
about curvature constrained versions of
unicycles, for instance.
Well, another version or another standard
constraint that people deal with is
what's known as the Reeds-Shepp model,
where omega again, is between -1 and 1,
or negative omega max and omega max, and
v can now be, well, the absolute value of
v is 1, which means that v is either +1
or -1, meaning it's a Dubins vehicle that
can also go backwards.
That's all that this means.
You can go forward along these arcs or
you can actually pull back in in reverse.
And Reeds-Shepp is also a standard type
of model that people like to deal with
when they're dealing with mobile robots.
Now, aircrafts typically can't back so
it's not a par, all that relevant of a
model for fixed wind aircraft, for
instance.
But there are, for instance, robots,
at the end of the day, we have a top
speed, for instance,
so we can't go faster than v=vmax, so,
but we can indeed go backwards.
So, the Reeds-Shepp model would not be a
bad model if you actually want to take
max velocities into account.
So, remember that this may or may not
come into play.
The last thing I want to say though is
that there are, of course, robots where
POSE is not a reasonable way of
describing them.
You know, you have a humanoid, well,
people will have maybe a position and
orientation but there is so much more
going on in a humanoid.
A snake, you know, which way is the snake
pointing, well, you know, if the snake
looks like this, what's, what's the
orientation of the snake? It's very
unclear.
What's the position of the snake? Who
knows? It's not clear what we mean by
that.
same thing, we would like mobile
manipulators like this robots that we
have here at Georgia Tech, where, well,
the base is a unicycle.
So, if you only care about the base,
fine.
But if you want to do more things like
carry things around or opening doors and
so forth, we have to care about more than
the just the POSE,
more than just position and orientation.
So, there are situations where we have to
worry about more things, but in a
surprising amount of situations, POSE is
indeed the way to go.
And like I said, the next lecture will be
about cars and how to actually make a car
behave like a unicycle.