The punchline with the previous lecture
was the POS, meaning position and
heading, is central in a lot of different
situations. and we made the claim that,
other POS-based models, like cars or
underwater gliders, or other kinds of
autonomous vehicles, can be made to look
like a unicycle.
Today, I want to make this observation
precise and concrete by looking at the
car-like robots.
So, for instance, there's a picture of
our autonomous car out of Georgia Tech.
And the question is,
how do we make this thing look like a
unicycle? Well, the first thing we need
is a model.
And the standard car kinematics is to add
another state to the system, which is the
steering handle.
So here is the picture that we have in
mind.
The, the rear wheel wheels are just
pointing in whatever direction the car is
going which it or the car is facing,
which is the orientation phi.
The position of the car, well, we're
going to take this point which is in the
middle in between the front wheels.
And this distance here is going to be l.
So, the rear wheels are l away from the
front wheels.
And then, we have this angle which we're
going to call psi.
So, what we're actually going to end up
doing is moving the car in this
direction.
And the direction then is psi+phi.
So, if we make this observation into a
model,
we first see that the states are x, y,
phi, and psi steering angle.
The inputs now that we're going to have
are,
as before, the speed.
How quickly is the car going? And, how
fast are we turning the steering wheel?
I'm going to call this sigma.
Angular steering velocity, or steering
angle velocity.
The model then becomes,
well, x-dot and v-dot is as before v
cosin and then the direction we're going
in.
But the direction we're going in is now
psi+phi.
Then, we have an equation that relates
the steering angle and the velocity to
the heading of the car.
And then, the last component is that we
can immediately influence the velocity of
the steering angle, so how quickly are we
turning the, the wheel.
Okay, good.
Now, what we're going to do is pick sigma
and v in a clever enough way to make this
thing become a unicycle.
Well, let's start then with the unicycle
itself.
So, this is our car model. Well, let's
start with our unicycle model and do
something called curvature control.
So, what this means is that if I want to
drive along a particular circular arc,
let's say that the radius of the arc is
raw.
And here's the car, it's going, sorry,
the unicycle it's going, do, do, do, do,
do, right? This is the direction in which
it's going so the orientation in the
unicycle, this angle is just phi.
Well, here's alpha and simple geometry
tells me that alpha is just phi minus pi
over 2.
Okay.
If I'm describing how this thing is
evolving along a circular arc,
then I get, for instance, that the x
position is simply,
let's say that the center of the circle
is x0, y0.
Then, x is simply x0 + rho cosine alpha.
But because alpha is phi minus pi over 2,
I can write this is x dot plus rho sine
alpha,
thanls to one of my favorite
trigonometric identities.
Well, if I take the derivative of this
with respect to time, I get that, well,
this thing the derivative of that is
zero.
The time derivative of this,
phi dot is equal to omega.
So, my x dot becomes omega rho cosine
phi.
But, wait a second.
I know what x dot is,
it's v cosine phi because it's a
unicycle.
So now, these two expressions have to be
the same.
Which means that the radius of the circle
is v over omega.
Now, a lot of times, we care about what's
called curvature.
And curvature is 1 over the radius.
So, the curvature is simply 1 over rho.
Which means that the curvature I would
get if I have omega and v,
well, it's omega over v.
So, the bigger the omega is, the tighter
the circle, meaning the higher the
curvature.
If omega is zero, I'm going at a, in a
straight line and the curvature is zero.
So, this is the curvature of a unicycle.
Okay. Let's figure what the curvature is
when we have a car.
The only difference now is that the you,
the car is actually pointing in this
direction but it's going in this
direction because of the fact we have a
steering angle.
So, as before, alpha, this angle where we
wanted to say where the car is, is,
well, it's phi plus psi minus pi over 2.
So, we're doing exactly what we did
before.
x is x0 plus rho where rho is the radius
of the circle,
sine phi plus psi.
Taking the derivative, we get x dot is
rho phi plus psi cosine phi plus psi.
Now, let's assume that we're driving on a
circle.
This means that we're going to hold the
steering wheel fixed.
Which means that this term is going to be
equal to zero because we're not changing
the steering angel,
right? So, we know that psi dot is zero.
Well, we also have the equation for phi
dot, it looks like v/l sine phi, sorry,
psi, v/l sine psi.
And, we also know that x dot should be
equal to this expression.
So, what do we do?
Well, we simply now line up v here and
rho phi dot there to get the curvature.
Sorry,
to get the radius of the circle.
So, this becomes l divided by sine psi.
And now, we invert this to get the
curvature.
So, the curvature becomes sine psi over l
where psi is this fixed steering angle
we're driving.
Okay.
Then, we have curvature for the unicycle,
this thing.
Curvature for the car,
that thing.
Well, we just put them equal, right? Why
not? If we put them equal, then we
immediately get that sine psi should be
equal to omega l/v.
So this is the steering angle we, if I
have a unicycle that's driving at omega
and v, then this is what the steering
angle should be to get the same behavior
out. Which also means that my psi then
should be arcsin of, well, omega l/v.
Well, I can't set psi directly.
So, what I need to do is say that this is
my desired steering angle.
And then, I somehow need to make my
actual steering angle become close to my
desired steering angle.
That's the name of the game here,
right?
So when we get these arcsin, or arcsine
sorry.
psi d is arc sinus of omega l/v.
Okay.
Now, arcsin is a little bit of an
annoying thing to have to do.
So instead, we're not going to do that.
So, let's say that I have this thing and
I would like d to be close to it.
Well, one thing I can do is a simple
P-Regulator, which is something you've
seen.
But
this thing involves this arcsin and one
thing to note is what happen if actually
keep sinus in there while we would get
something kind of cleaner,
right?
So, let's get rid of it and simply say
that instead of psi here, I'm going to do
sine of psi.
And instead of omega d then, I'm going to
do sine omega d.
So, I keep saying omega, I mean psi, sin
psi d, which we know is omega l over v,
which goes in there,
right?
So, we keep the sinuses in there instead
of taking arcsin.
And the reason for that is that for small
enough angles this is, this is roughly
equal to the angle itself.
So, sinus is, is not a bad thing to do.
well, let's see if this works.
So over on the left there, you see the
unicycle, and over on the right you see
the car.
And the unicycle has some omega and v,
and the car is running the sinus version
of P-Regulator.
And, as you can see, they're pretty
close, which means that we can basically
do the same kind of curvature control on
the car as we can do on the unicycle.
So, the moral of the story with this is,
you know what? We're planning.
We're getting some direction we want to
move in.
Here is my direction I want to move in.
Well, we know the clever trick. The
trick, right? The trick gives us v and
omega, which is what are the speeds and
angular velocities we would like.
We now also know that the curvature is
omega over v. So, if you give me v and
omega, I can tell you what the curvature
is going to look like.
Well, let's use this curvature idea to
make the car track the unicycle which
gives us v and sigma.
And, of course, this v is the same as
that v.
So, we don't have to do anything about
it.
The only thing we have to do, is to add
what sigma should actually be.
And this, ladies and gentlemen, allows us
to make the car act like a unicycle
simply by using this curvature idea.
And this generalizes to other types of
unicycle like systems where POS, again,
is really important.