We are now extremely close to the end of
this entire course and I'm actually done,
believe it or not, with the technical
part.
The grand finale was really this idea
that we could even make complicated
systems like cars act like unicycles that
we now know how to control and navigate
around in complex environments as we've
seen both in theory In simulation, and
actually in real experiments.
What I want to do in this sub-lecture is
basically probe further.
There are lot's of things, believe it or
not, that are actually not in this
course, pretaining to other control
robots.
Here I have a picture of a praying mantis
and the reason for that is that, we have
not covered praying mantises.
So I'm going to let this be a proxy for
all the things we haven't talked about.
Well one thing that we haven't talked
about is, what happens when your system
is generally non-linear instead of
linear.
So we are now really, really good at
dealing with linear control system.
Well, what if it is linear, non-linear?
Well we have dealt with some, we've dealt
with the unicycle quite a bit, but there
we were kind of lucky that we had a lot
of intuition.
What if this is not the unicycle? What if
this is massively non-linear, and
strange, and complicated? What do we
actually do? Well, that's called nominal
control and it's not in this course but I
encourage you to keep educating yourself
and probing further along these lines.
another thing that we didn't deal with is
what is called optimal control.
So for us, the name of the game was
stability.
Stability, it was performance in the
sense of tracking, right, so we want it
to track reference signals, and then we
had robustness, but what we didn't have,
explicitly, were things like this.
So this is a general, type of cost, where
we're saying, well we want to minimize
some cost involving x and u.
This could be, you know, the fuel
consumed, or the time it takes to get
there, plus possibly some cost on the
final point as well.
This is known as optimal control, and
this was also not, in the course.
So this was one grasshopper that we
didn't see.
There is another branch of decision
theory known as Machine Learning that we
didn't touch upon.
The reason why I am putting this as a
another thing that you might want to
probe further along is it's useful in
robotics and it's highly related to
control in general and optimal control in
particular.
So the idea is that.
I'm going to have some costs V and I'm
going to have some policy pie which says
what are you going to do when you're at
the certain state?
And the cost is just going to be a cost
of the different, where I am at time k
and what I'm doing at time k.
So this is really U sub k, right? And now
I'm going to sum up this entire cost and
if you do that you can write down.
Something known as Bellman's Optimality
Equation or Bellman's equation, that
basically characterizes what is the
smallest you can make this cost while it
satisfies this kind of weird looking
expression.
And the point here is not the math, the
point is that we have this equation, and
machine learning is all about finding
this V* by exploring.
If I'm at this position, let's try doing
u4. if I'm in another position, let's try
doing u9.
And while doing this, you're building up
this a, this V* cost function.
And when you're done building it up, you
all of the sudden have a complete map or
guide to what should you do.
If you encounter a certain state, and
that's in a nutshell what machine
learning is about.
Another thing that we didn't do much with
is perception and mapping.
We had infrared or ultrasonic range
sensors, but a lot of times.
We have those.
We have laser scanners.
We have cameras.
We did not deal with complicated sensing
modalities and we did also not deal with,
okay what do we do with all these sensor
data.
How do we actually produce maps of the
world? Our world was, here is the, the
robot.
Here is an obstacle.
It's a point.
Let's just avoid it.
But you know what.
This obstacle may not be a point it may
be part of, I don't know, a corridor, and
we would like to go in the corridor.
Well then it's good to actually describe
what the world looks like.
This is known as mapping.
And again, this is a perfect opportunity
for you to probe further, trying to build
maps of the world.
There are lots of different methods for
doing it.
And finally, the thing that we didn't do
at all either is really talk about the
high level artificial intelligence.
So, how do you actually decide in the
first place where you should be going.
We said, given a goal point, how do we go
there? But where did the goal coin, point
come from? Somehow, somewhere, someone is
going to have to make decisions about
what at the very high-level the robot
should be doing.
And this falls Squarely under the domain
of artificial intelligence.
Not covered in this course, I encourage
you to probe further.
So, to conclude, there are things that we
haven't done in this class.
There are lots of praying mantises that
we didn't cover.
And those are good things for you to
probe further.
And learn more about.
If you know all of it, you can build an
awesome robotic system.
But, beyond that, there are also lots of
things we don't know.
So here, Not only praying mantises, but
other green creatures.
We have no idea what they look like.
We don't know if they exist, we don't
know what they are.
It's the same with robotics.
There's a lot of stuff going on that we
as a community don't know how to do yet.
So the last thing I want to do is give
you the impression that this is a closed
and complete case.
We know everything about robotics.
We don't.
So, not only in this course are there
praying mantises, but outside of the
course there are potential aliens that we
still have not discovered.