Hello and welcome to the seventh and final
programming and simulation lecture.
This week, the programming assignment
comes to its grand finale, and we
will have an ro, quickbot navigate to the
most complicated environment yet.
And what makes this different From our
navigation,
from from week five, is that we need to
answer three new questions
this week.
And the first one is, we need to keep
track of the progress that the robot is
making.
Last in week five, I talked about this
problem
that the robot can get trapped inside of
an obstacle.
And if it does, it doesn't, it doesn't
know that it's not making progress.
It's just going to try to keep going to
the, to the goal, and then it'll
avoid the obstacle, try to get back to the
goal, and it'll go on and on.
It'll never make any progress to the,
towards the goal.
So this week, we'll actually think about,
is the robot making any progress?
And If robot is not making any progress,
maybe
we should, you know, use the controller
from week six.
And follow the wall either to the right or
to the left.
So we're all have to make a decision not
only, do we now
start following the wall but in which
direction, right or, or to the left?
And
finally.
We also need to again revisit our final
[INAUDIBLE] finite state machine from week
five because that one will no longer cut
it for, for this week's obstacle course.
We're going to have to, to really think
about if
we're in a certain state and certain event
becomes true.
To which other states should we switch in
order to have the rogo,
robot progress towards its ultimate goal,
which is to reach the goal location.
And of course, don't collide with any
obstacles,
because that would be bad for our
quickbot.
So, all of the implementation this week
will happen in the
supervisor, so we're only going to be
worrying about one file this week.
And that's mainly because for the past
seven weeks or six weeks we've written
all of the necessary controllers that,
that we need to, to solve this problem.
And unlike the previous weeks I'm actually
going to start off with the demo this
week.
To show you what it looks like when it
works.
So Let's see it in action.
I'm going to go ahead and launch the
simulator and
hit Play.
And we're going to click on the robot
and try to get it, oop, there we go.
And what you see
here is first of all the robot has Is
navigating out of this obstacle that it's
trapped inside of and it's following the
wall
nicely, or the boundary of the obstacle
nicely,
and it's going to stick to the wall until
it decides, hey, I'm going to peel off
and go towards the goal location, because
the
goal location is somewhere up around this
area.
And you'll see the robot has made it.
And eh, in the next couple slides, I'll go
over exactly what decisions have made
to get to this point and what all of these
beautiful colored lines actually mean.
And one more thing, here in the map land
command window, you
can see that I have a few f, f statements
and these are.
The robot switching between a state, so I
can actually see that I was in ao and
go to goal, and then I switched to avoid
obstacles, and then back ao to ao and
go to goal, and then to avoid obstacles,
and eventually, there's also a follow wall
in here.
And so on and so forth.
But let's get back to the slides.
So.
I talked about progression.
And we need progression because if we were
just to
use the controller from week five I said
we were going to
get stuck and that's for the, the, the
reason for that is
that the robot is first of all trying to
go to the goal.
So.
Right here I have the goal to goal vector.
And that was ugtg and that's pointing me
towards this goal.
So you can just imagine this extends to
here.
So is our goal to goal vector we're
already familiar with that one.
And I also
have the obstacle avoidance vector.
And perhaps I'm either going truly, go to
goal, or perhaps I'm doing something in
between.
So, but the point is that I'm trying, that
the robot is
really trying to drive itself in this
direction, or in this general direction.
So it's wants to go to this, to this goal
but it's a blocked
off by, by, by this obstacle and it has to
somehow navigate around it.
Now,
[BLANK_AUDIO]
With respect to progression, what I
want to do is I want
to keep track of how close the robot gets
to the goal.
So, first, in the previous slide the robot
was at this
location, and now in this slide has
progressed to this location.
And it's actually gotten closer to the
goal.
And.
Because the reason it's gotten closer to
goes
goal, because this distance to the goal is
larger than this distance to the goal.
And the way that we update
our progress is by calling the function,
set_progress_point right here.
So this function we'll call and we'll
make, we'll
say, well, you know, the robot has made
some progress,
and we're going to save its progress but
we're always going to
store the closest it's ever gotten to the
goal location.
And the reason that we do this is because
we want to
check a certain event, and this event is
called progress made.
And progress made to checks whether the
current location the current distance of
the robot to the goal location is shorter
than the last set_progress point.
And if so, it returns true otherwise it
returns
false and we're going to use this to check
whether you
know our robot has made progress towards
the goal or not.
So, what
we saw in the what we saw in the
simulation, was that the robots started
somewhere over here,
and then it drove in this direction and it
started avoiding goals and now it's gotten
to this point.
So it's kind of follow this general
trajectory,
because it's gone here, it's probably
going.
Go to goal, and then here, it's doing
avoid obstacle, and
then here, it gets to the point where it
says well,
no progress made.
So, the robot's not made any, not made any
more progress.
So, time to make a decision.
And, the decision that the robot makes is
that when it's no
longer progressing, it's going to try to
switch into the Follow Wall behavior.
But an important question is, what should
the direction should be?
Should we follow the obstacle at our left
or the obstacle on our right side?
And we're going to make this decision
based on three vectors.
based on
the goal to goal vector which points
towards the goal.
So this is pointing me towards the goal
location.
The obstacle avoidance vector, which is
pointing the robot away from the
obstacles.
And we're going to inspect both the follow
wall vector.
That we computed last week.
In the, on the right side and on the left
side of the robots.
So we're going to look at these four
vectors and make our decision
whether we need, we should follow an
obstacle to the left or
to the right.
And that's, and that's how we determine
the follow wall direction of the robot.
And the way we're going to do this is
we're going to
ask the questions, is this vector, right
here, follow wall, and
this is L again denotes that it's, it's
with respect to
the left, is this between the vector's
obstacle of ordnance and [INAUDIBLE].
We're going to ask that question.
And we're also, at the same time we're
going to ask.
Is this vector.
U Follow Wall comma R.
Between U _ao and ugtg.
And of course you can argue
in this picture, well they're both, right?
Because this is one, this is between
[BLANK_AUDIO]
This one right here is, this vector is
between the two vectors
on this side of things, whereas this
vector right here is
between these two.
On these thought-side of things.
And really, the requirement is going to be
for, is it between these two vectors?
If the A is, we're going to look
at the side where the angle between U go
to goal
and U A O, so this angle between them is
less than Pi.
So less than 180 degrees, so when we say
is a vector between these two vectors.
It has to be between them on the side
where it's
less than, probably where these two are
less than pi apart.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And the reason I'm setting it up in this
way is because
that allows us to just do a little bit of
linear algebra.
And the little bit of linear algebra that
we're going to do is, is this following
equation.
So what I have here is I have the go to
goal vector.
I have the obstacle avoidance vector.
I have some scalar parameters.
Sigma one and
sigma two.
And on this side I have the follow wall
vector that I care about.
In this case, I pick the left side, but
this might as well be the right side.
And the condition is that we're going to
solve this linear equation for these two
parameters.
So.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
What is this vector equal to and oh, I'm
so sorry.
What is this scalar equal to?
And what does this second scaler do?
And we can compute this we're you know,
you just have to rearrange this a little
bit.
And What we're going to do is, say, the,
the
condition that we're going to come up with
is, as follows.
If
sigma1 is greater than 0, and.
Sigma 2 is greater than 0.
So if they're both
positive, that implies that if we
have the two vectors, ugtg and uao,
then.
This vector ufw,of L is
between those two.
So it's not on the other side.
It's, it's on this side between the two,
because this, because this angle right
here is less than Pi, that's going to be
our condition.
And I have
posted 2 PDF's online, and in and
announcement that go over why this exactly
works.
Why this linear algebra works, and why it
makes sense.
And I'll have and, and then, those notes,
I
have some more diagrams and a lot more
detailed
math, and you'll be able to follow along
exactly
what this little piece of linear algebra
does for you.
Now,
at some point the robot is, the robot you
know follows the,
follows the, the wall, the obstacle, so
Originally it was over here.
Over here and then it drove around and
drove around.
And this was the, this was the best
progress
we had made at any point, so right here.
And it follows it around, follows it
around all the way until it gets to this
point right here.
And at this point, it says look This
distance here,
from here to the goal, is less than the
distance from here to here to the goal.
And if that's the case, and I no longer
need to slide, and sliding refers to that
condition that I just talked about in the
previous slide and we have one for either
sliding
left or one for sliding right, but in this
case, it's sliding left.
And so if this condition is no longer
true, which
it isn't because the, because as you can
see right
here these vectors are no longer between
the [INAUDIBLE] goal
and the obstacle points vector, and
progress has been made.
If those two conditions hold.
Then we can go switch
back to go to goal and our robot can go
ahead and make its way
to the goal location and it doesn't, it
no, no longer has to follow this obstacle
right here.
Now, like I said, the.
State machine, the finite state machine
from week five is no longer sufficient
for this particular problem so you're
going to have to design a new one.
And the design is up to you, but here are
a few pointers of what you should probably
think about in your finite state machine.
The first is, as usual.
If the robot is at the goal, then you
stop.
And it's useful for that as the first
thing that you check in the finite
state machine, because you don't want to
execute anything else once you're at the
goal.
Once you're at the goal the robot is done
with
its task and it's just going to stay in
the stopped state.
Also, if the robot get into an unsafe
distance
to the obstacle, we immediately want to
switch to avoid obstacles,
because avoid obstacles really is our last
ditch effort to
make sure that a robot doesn't crash with,
with obstacle.
So it's usually a good idea to have that
in there, to make sure that there are no
collisions.
Then
Also, you want to have the condition that
if are you going to goal or maybe
you're doing obstacle [INAUDIBLE] and
[INAUDIBLE] goal
together, but both of these goal seeking
behaviors.
And you're no longer making progress then
you
want to switch to either to follow wall
and you
want to do that based on the condition
whether you're
sliding, you're suppose to slide left or
slide right.
And I talked about it in the previous
slides but make sure you have that in
there.
And the fourth one is if you do get around
the obstacle there will be a point where
you're going
to start making progress again toward the
goal location and
you Will probably no lee, no longer need
to slide
along the wall in order to make progress,
so if
those both tho, both of those conditions
are, end up
being true, then you can go ahead and
switch back
to your goal-seeking behavior, so which is
either go to goal,
or what I usually like do to is if, if I'm
close to an obstacle, which I typically am
because of the
follow all behavior I first switch into
avoid obstacles and go
to goal before I switch into pure go to
goal behavior.
Now, my tips for week seven are.
Again, read the manual.
It has more details.
And also read the handouts, the, the
additional handouts that
I'm going to be posting that explains the
Linear Algebra.
And do that.
And then really the more, even more
important one is
when you design this finite state machine,
it's fairly complicated.
And what I like to do
is I like to get out a piece of paper and
a pen and I like to draw the finite state
machine.
Really think about...
What are all the states that the robot can
be in, and what are the events that can
take it from state to state, and then
construct
it on paper before you even start coding
it.
Because then you, what you can do is you
can take your piece of paper, and you can
pretend you're the robot and you can go
step
through and, and see if you can make it.
All the way around the obstacle to the
goal location.
And then
after that, you can implement it and you
can test it.
And then you'll always, always have this
piece of paper
to go back and forth and make sure, hey is
the robot actually doing what I designed
the funded state
machine What I'd de, how I'd design the
finite state machine.
Is it doing that, is it not, and that
really makes debugging this week's
programming assignment much easier.
And usually I would end the video lecture
here,
but I have one extra special slide for you
this week.
And that's the What's Next?
Well, it is the last one, but the
simulator and it's
documentation will be available outside of
this course at the following URL.
So the project continues to lives on after
this course, and
at any time if you want to get new updates
to the simulator.
If you want to check in.
Have their new robots been added to the
simulator has there, have
there, are there new sensors, if there's
now maybe a camera sensors, or,
whatever it may be, you go to this URL,
and
you'll be sent to a webpage where there'll
be updates.
And there also will be links to a GitHub
repository.
And the point of this GitHub repository is
for everybody to have access to share
improvement.
And using improvements can be either, hey,
this is a way better way of
for example, limiting the error between
minus pi and pi.
I want to add that to the simulator.
You can go ahead and do that there.
You can also add new robots, so if you
wanted to have, for example, a robot
that's more like
a car you can add that to the simulator
and then have that become part of the
official project.
And the same thing with sensors and
anything else that you think
of, so I would really like to encourage
you to consider if
you're making any improvements or adding
anything to the simulator,
contribute back to the project because
it'll just make everything better.
And future students and future users of
the
simulator will really, really benefit from
your improvements.
And the last thing is just, thank you very
much
for your hard work and your participation
in programming assignments.
I've seen some really exciting discussions
on the forums, it makes
me really, really happy And privileged to
witness everybody grow into
seasoned robotics experts during the
course of this of these seven weeks.
And with that, thank you very much and
goodbye.
[BLANK_AUDIO]