Hi and welcome to the third
segment of Spacecraft Kinetics.
Here, we're going to be studying in
detail the gravity gradient, torque and
forces that happen on a rigid spacecraft.
So with the spacecraft, every part of the
mass distribution is a different distance
away from the center of the Earth.
That means it's experiencing
a different gravitational force.
Now, we have to sum it
up over a whole body.
So in particular of interest to us is if
you have the gravity gradient that you've
computed, which orientations of a craft
caused the gravity gradient to be zero.
And when we're moving in a rotating frame,
which one of these are now relative
equilibrious will be
developing all of those and
then there's some interesting examples.
You can look at which
one of those is stable.
Look at a tall slender object,
the lower object weighs more has a
stronger gravity force than the top part.
So if you disturb the attitude,
this would help stabilize it.
We'll begin to study such
configuration for full 3D.
This is a very useful topic.
There's many satellites of
gravity being stabilized or
there are big things
like the space station.
Gravity gradients definitely
impact the attitude motion.
So, this section gives you a good
handle on how to predict that torque.