So good.
This is the vector form,
the coordinate independent form.
Let's now actually apply
some particular frames and
there's different answers
that we get out of this.
It's always the same answer,
but it's different expressions,
different formulations
of that same answer.
So if I'm using an orbit frame, and
here I've used an aircraft-like frame,
where if an airplane is flying you have
your nose pointing in the one direction,
your wings may be to the left or right.
I have yaw axis up,
aircraft probably would have had it down.
But with orbits we tend
to have our third axis or
one of the axis up in
the radial direction.
So, 01 is my long track,
02 is my cross track orbit normal, and
03 is my orbit radius direction vector.
They're all unit direction vectors.
That means Rc by definition is always
going to be 7,000 kilometers in that
direction, all right?
And that direction is defined here by 03.
So, in the O frame, your position vector
on a circular orbit in particular,
is just going to be constant.
It's just going to be 0, 0, Rc,
all right, which is kind of nice.
So we can write that.
But we've seen the spacecraft part,
the inertia tensor,
we tend to write in the body frame.
So while the orbit positions could
be written in very simple manners,
we tend to need it in the body frame.
And now, so if this is your position
vector pointing up to your satellite, and
you've got a coordinate frame on your
satellite, depending on your orientation,
you can have an infinity of different
variations, and most generally,
you're going to have to account for
three different vector components, for
your Rc inertial position vector, always.
So, Rc 1, 2, 3, nothing but
B frame components of my position vector,
different ways to look at it.
So we have that.
Now we plug this in,
I added these this morning.
Everything's in the body frame
just to make it explicit.
So we had Rc, cross I Rc.
I've picked a principal coordinate
frame here just to make,
I can always do that for
a rigid body, all right.
It exists, it makes your
analysis a little bit easier.
Now you can do this math,
this multiplication is what talking about.
You get a little bit of scaling,
then the cross product, and
this is going to be your answer.
So this box, the answer's the same
as the earlier one after it's
expressed everything now
in body frame components.
But we can again look at
more conditions now and
try to figure out when will the gravity
gradient torque go to zero?
Why do I care about it going to zero?
For equilibrious that
we're about to study,
that's thing if you have these conditions
and this is the one disturbance you're
modeling, if that disturbance acts on it,
you won't be at an equilibrious.
This is like gravity gradients
we talked about last time.
This would be a gravity
gradient equilibria.
If you disturb it, then,
this one weigh more than this
point makes it restore itself.
So what orientations or
what shapes give us that?
And as you guys mentioned earlier,
one way to make these things go to zero
is simply these differences
all have to vanish.
And that means, as you guys already
identified, is that all the principal
inertias must be equal which is either
a sphere or a cube, those kinds of shapes.
So, there are particular shapes that
can make your attitude go to 0.
That's not or so
your gravity gradient torque go to 0.
And that's important, there was a
satellite that we built here called Dandy.
Anybody know that one?
Heard about it a little bit, right?
It was a sphere for reason like that so
we could do this stuff, and
didn't have any other gravity gradient
torques disturbing because I really wanted
to measure atmospheric force effects, and
I didn't need all the disturbances
acting on it very much.
So that was really leading to this
decision, all right, that gave us zero
gravity gradient torques,
also how the atmospheric drag effects so
you didn't have weird panels sticking out,
there were other reasons too.
So the other way we can make it go to
zero is we can look at these components.
Are there particular orientations?
Remember, Rc one and two and three,
the position vector always
points to straight outward but
then depending on my attitude, I will
have different Rc 1, 2, 3 components.
Are there different orientations that
will force this LG to go to zero?
And the answer I'm showing you
is Rc is equal to Rc times bi.
So, is it David?
What does that mean for your orientation,
if Rc is equal to Rc bi hat?
>> Does it mean you're aligning your body
axis with the O frame that you created?
>> Be more specific,
what part of the O frame?
>> The radius vector.
>> Right, because if you say you're adding
a body axis relative to the O frame-
>> If they're principal inertia axis?
>> Then that implies all
my principal inertia axis
have to line up with the O frame,
and that's not true.
So your second argument is correct, and
it's what we really care about is
the Rc part here that we have, right?
That's in the O3 direction here, it's
basically the orbit to radium to axis.
And so that what it says is your
position vector on that direction has to
be a principal axis of your body.
And that could be B1, B2, or B3.
But it's just locking
one of your R axis in.
I'm going to use these to have
three distinct axis, right?
So we have, this is a principal axis,
this is a principal axis, and
this is a principal axis.
It just says that if I line up one
of those things as a principal axis.
Let's do the simple example, right?
Here I have my skinny axis
in the vertical direction.
That satisfies that condition.
If I rotate about that axis,
this is still in equilibrium, because
of the symmetry of the stuff, right?
So you can see,
that orientation doesn't matter.
It just matters that one of
the principal axes is lined up.
This is another one that we identified,
where right now the gravity gradients
are even and they cancelled each other.
But I can rotate about that
about the gravity direction.
And I still have a zero gravity
gradient torque, right?
That's what this condition means.
So it only locks one of my body axis to be
aligned with the orbit direction vector.
That's it.
But it still leaves an infinity of
orientations because you can rotate about
that local vertical axis.
Okay, good, yes?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Thinking more like J2 and that stuff?
>> They're pretty small.
J2 is about a thousand times
smaller than the regular stuff.
So if you care about those accuracies, you
could do that and you'd have to account
for that then in these developments,
that would be actual terms.
I don't typically see those because
this is already a pretty small torque.
Many simulations don't even include this,
but if you do include it, great,
and J2 is much, much smaller.
If you're going around asteroids,
that's a whole different problem.
If you're looking at
an asteroid binary system,
I know some of you this year
might be looking at those.
That's a full on thing.
Then you do these expansions
like I've done but
on two bodies not just treating the Earth
as a big point mass, as a big thing.
But for Earth, it is very spherical
as far as that goes, right?
But yep, no, great question.
So, this would be modified.
The process is the same, but you might
have extra conditions to line it up with
the local area, and what does that mean?