After all that math and
linearization and everything,
it really boils down to a pretty simple.
This is how you fly an equilibrium which
we've identified all three axis line up,
all three orbit axis have to be
principle axis of the body so
you line that dictates
particular orientations.
And then, to be stable, you have to
make sure this condition is satisfied.
And it's not just one, if this is stable,
flying sideways, you know?
And so is this one, right?
You could fly nose up and nose down.
Do you care if you're flying nose up or
nose down?
>> But it depends on the application.
If the shuttle does not want to use fuel,
it doesn't care.
This spacecraft did care.
This is a famous one,
the Polar Bear Mission,
it has, you can see these gravity
grating stabilized, all need.
[LAUGH] they need the three
axis to be the skinnier one, so
they put the small mass and to save weight
on a very thin boom all the way out.
And so now the inertias about any
other axis are going to be big,
because of the big moment arm between
this mass and this honking mass.
But along the axis,
that's the least inertia.
That's what we needed for
stability, right?
And they go through this stuff, and
I2, bigger than I1, bigger than I3.
Life is good, what could go wrong?
This craft does care that this
point is looking at the earth.
Why?
That's why they put all the sensors.
It didn't put them on this side.
So this was launched to gravity
gradiants stabilize the satellite,
reasonable mass, not huge but,
reasonable mass.
And it was supposed to point this way,
and what actually happened after
the first period in full sunlight,
the attitude degraded significantly.
Which basically means shit happened,
bad stuff happened.
Attitude degraded significantly,
essentially, means it inverted itself.
Instead of being here and a little bit
stable, this whole actually tumbled,
banded off to go there.
And then you go back through the shadow,
and everything is good.
And now we said, this is stable.
But so is this.
And in this case, we do care.
But the satellite doesn't,
it's just following physics.
And it goes, hey, I'm perfectly happy.
You can bump me all you want.
I'm stable, I'm going to stay here.
So it's like, great.
What on Earth does happened?
And it wasn't supposed to happen.
So, several attempts were made
to reinvent this thing and
finally they were able to get it.
They basically have to give it a kick.
And the way they can give it a kick
without using fuel is, despin or
spin off your wheel to crazy amounts
is going to apply this huge torque.
They needed something to move it pass
this linear local state stable regime.
And once the bigger motion happened
just basically give it a kick and
it tumbled and then recovered and
this other one.
And then use the wheel to clean
up the mess and get it close and
hopefully stay stable again.
So, good news is they
were able to recover,
bad news is why does it even happen?
Jordan, you got a question.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> What did we miss here then?
What assumption do you think was
violated with the space craft?
And there's a clue.
After the first period
of fully sunlit orbit.
What happens with sunlight
put in a space craft?
>> A radiation pressure.
>> Could be radiation pressure,
they don't think that was the cause but
definitely something I would look at, is
the [INAUDIBLE] do you have a craft which
this huge solar sails basically
attached that would cause significant.
They don't think that was the cause here,
but definitely related.
Spencer?
>> Outgassing?
>> I think outgassing you've always have,
or
what causes more outgassing in
the sunlight condition do you think?
>> I figured in the first fully
sunlit orbit that it would
have out-gassed most of what it
was going to out-gassed initially.
>> You think because it's a first orbit,
not because it's sunlit.
>> Yeah.
>> Maybe.
Again, I don't have the details of this,
but these are all good ideas.
Right now, you start to wonder,
what did we miss?
What's going on here?
What happens with sunlight, though?
>> Heating up.
>> You heat up.
This is a very lightweight structure.
What heats up, is one side of it.
What happens to the other side?
Or what happens to the heated breath?
I can see some-
>> That side will expand [INAUDIBLE] so
[INAUDIBLE].
>> And if we're curving,
what do we violate?
Rigid?
It's not rigid, this was a really,
really lightweight structure,
they had to get this tucker way out there.
There's not much stiffness to this and
they didn't really
model well the thermal deformations that
can happen on these kinds of an orbit.
So there was flexing going on.
Now flexing doesn't necessarily
immediately make it go crazy.
But this was just an unlucky mission
that flexing happened to be happening in
such a way.
That it was able to give it
the right kick at the right time,
to get out of one equilibrium and
in the end once it all settled,
it settle into the other equilibrium.
Perfectly stable, that's the trickiness.
Gravity gradiants do stabilize.
But it really doesn't care if
it's positive or negative.
Every one of those equilibriums has
a flip that's still like an equilibrium.
And if you do care,
then you have to have a mean to put
it into the right equilibrium, right?
And then locally it's there.
And so here's a case a lesson's learned,
where the thermal deformations
really did matter.
And so flex endure, that's what
I heard was the primary culprit.
All these other ideas are fantastic ideas,
and I'm sure they tested every one of
those as well, just make notice
another bounding case assumption.
With these even cause this effect right?
To model and simulate that.
So, it gets tricky.