[MUSIC]
[MUSIC] >> In this module,
we are discussing the properties
of electroweak interactions.
And in this video we will
visit the ATLAS experiment,
whose visitor center is behind me.
ATLAS is an experiment installed
at the Large Hadron Collider LHC of CERN.
In video 3.2a
we have already introduced the full
range of CERN’s accelerators.
And in video 3.10a, we have discussed the
properties of the ATLAS detector.
Today we will talk with
one of the active participants
in the discovery of the Higgs boson,
who is Sandrine Laplace.
Follow me please.
>> I will quickly present to you our
interview partner of today,
who is Sandrine Laplace.
Sandrine obtained her PhD in 2003
at the Laboratoire d’Accélérateur Linéaire LAL
in Orsay, close to Paris.
on a subject of CP violation.
Then she joined the Laboratoire d’Annecy de la
physique des particules, LAPP,
close to here, about 50 km from Geneva,
to join the ATLAS experiment,
to which LAPP contributes in a major way.
Then in 2011, if I remember correctly,
she joined the Laboratoire de physique
nucléaire et des hautes énergies,
LPNHE in Paris, where she still works today,
always on the ATLAS experiment,
which is our subject today.
So, Sandrine, do you still remember
when you first heard about
the Higgs mechanism and
the Higgs boson?
>> Yes, I do remember.
It was at the university, during a course.
>> I imagine, and I hope so!
>> Well, a course with was called
DEA at the time,
in the fifth year in France.
Indeed in a field theory course,
that is where I think I first
heard about the Higgs mechanism
and the Higgs boson.
>> And what did you
think at that time
about this somewhat complex mechanism?
>> Indeed, at the time, it seemed
complex to me.
As a student, one has a
sort of intuition of what
for example the mass
of a particle could be.
And then one day, someone explains that
it is more complicated than that.
>> In fact, that mass does not exist.
>> Yes, so I remember that I found
this pretty complicated
for a property that seemed
simple to me.
And in addition, it was very
theoretical at the time,
since it was in the context of a course.
It became somewhat more concrete,
when during my PhD,
while I worked on a totally different subject,
in the year 2000…
>> Indeed.
>> at LAPP there was some excitement
about a possible signal.
>> Yes, a possible indirect signal
of the Higgs mechanism.
In fact it was very indirectly,
through radiative corrections,
that one found that the existence
of this effect was not totally excluded,
that it was even relatively probable,
but not directly accessible to
that generation of experiments.
>> And that was one reason
why we built the LHC.
Did this also count among your
motivations to join the ATLAS
experiment at LHC, at the time?
>> Yes, absolutely.
I did not, at that time
consciously tell myself that
I will join ATLAS for this
very reason.
But, once I arrived in the
ATLAS collaboration,
it appeared perfectly natural to
work on this subject, indeed.
>> So what was your role
during the construction of ATLAS?
>> So I joined ATLAS in 2003.
In 2003, the detector was almost
completely constructed.
So, I arrived at LAPP Annecy,
which was involved in the construction
of a sub-detector, which is called the
electromagnetic calorimeter,
and which serves to measure the energy
of electrons and photons.
So, quite naturally, I joined
this activity, but at that moment
the detector construction
was already finished.
We exposed modules
to particle beams at CERN
to test the final modules,
determine their performance.
So, I participated in that,
it was in 2004-2005.
And then the calorimeter was lowered
down into the cavern,
and the electronics was pugged in,
I think this was in 2005-2006.
And from then on,
until the start of the LHC,
in 2009, we were able to study the
electromagnetic calorimeter, to make sure
that it worked well in the cavern, that it
was ready for the first collisions.
So, I have participated a lot in this
commissioning of the detector, as we call it.
>> And this detector has evidently
played a major role
throughout the history of
this discovery.
So when did you decide to get involved
in the data analysis
which led to the discovery of this particle?
>> Well, early on, because
working on the electromagnetic
calorimeter, it was natural to
look at a physics reaction that
involved this detector.
So, I got interested quickly in the
search for the Higgs boson in the channel
where it decays into two photons.
And which was actually one of the two
channels where we first saw
the Higgs boson.
One of the discovery channels.
>> But evidently, this discovery
did not happen in one day.
It was a long sequence of events.
Can you recall for us how
you lived this race for the discovery?
>> Indeed, this happened progressively.
We started to take data
in 2010.
But very little.
It became interesting in 2011,
when we really arrived at an energy
of 7 TeV in the center-of-mass frame.
That is when we started to accumulate data.
The way we worked was
that we regularly watched,
every few weeks,
the distribution of photon pairs
we were able to reconstruct.
>> The invariant mass distribution.
>> Yes, the invariant mass distribution, indeed,
of photon pairs.
And then, we waited to see if
photons could come from the Higgs boson,
that their mass starts to
peak around the
Higgs boson mass.
And that started to be
the case very gently.
That is to say, it really happened
gradually.
At the beginning,
we did not have much data,
we saw fluctuations everywhere.
So, we did not know too much.
And then, at a certain moment, there
was one of these fluctuations, which started
to somehow deepen.
>> And which stayed always in the same place.
>> Indeed, week after week, it
was always there, larger and larger,
in a regular manner.
And then, at a certain moment, we learned
that our colleagues from the same experiment,
who worked on another Higgs decay channel,
the one into leptons,
saw a fluctuation, which started to
grow at the same place like ours.
So, at this moment, we started to…
>> You started to believe it.
>> …yes, to believe it.
Exactly. And in December 2011,
there has been a seminar.
>> Here.
>> Yes, here at CERN,
where for the first time
we announced that we started to see
the premise of the Higgs boson.
The evidence was too weak at the time
to really announce a discovery.
But there was serious premise,
which was confirmed on July 4, 2012
when we really announced the discovery,
because then it was…
>> Time to celebrate.
>> Yes, right.
>> Above all here at CERN,
where there was a grandiose meeting
with the forthcoming Nobel laureates
for this mechanism, with Peter Higgs and
François Englert.
>> François.
François who?
>> Englert.
Yes, Englert, that’s it.
So with the data
accumulated until today,
we are relatively sure that we really
deal with a Higgs boson, aren’t we?
How do we know that it is really a Higgs boson
and not something else?
>> Well, we study its properties.
The Higgs boson
was predicted by the
Standard Model since 1964.
>> Yes, right.
>> And we knew…
>> So,
everything was known except its mass, wasn’t it?
>> Exactly, we knew everything
about it, except its mass.
And the fact that it existed.
So, once we found that it exists and that its mass was measured…
>> …125 Gigaelectronvolts,
just to quote it…
>> 125 yes. So, from the moment when
one knew the mass, everything
was predicted, like all its couplings
with other particles.
So, by measuring the number of times
when it decays into
two photons, into four leptons,
or into other final states,
one verifies if this corresponds exactly
to the prediction of the Standard Model.
So, today this is the case,
but still with a large
experimental uncertainty.
That is to say that we measure these
couplings to roughly 15% accuracy.
>> OK.
>> So, there is still some margin.
>> But at this precision, it is
compatible with this hypothesis
that it is a Higgs boson.
>> Yes exactly.
We have also verified the quantum numbers
of the Higgs boson, its spin, its charge,
its parity, etc.
>> With charge zero and spin zero.
>> Right.
>> Very probably spin 0,
I believe that spin 1 is
practically excluded, isn’t it?
>> Spin 1 is already excluded
by the simple fact that we observe
that the Higgs decays into
two photons.
>> Yes!
In fact, that’s true.
>> And afterwards we have excluded spin 2,
which is really exotic.
That way we have excluded that it could be
a graviton, instead of a Higgs boson.
Here we are.
Rather easily too.
>> OK.
So what does it change.
There has been a lot of noise made
around the discovery.
What does it change for a
physicist like you?
Did this, the proof that this
effect exists,
did this change your paradigms?
>> Well yes.
This means that what has been explained to me
at university, that the mass of elementary
particles, that it is not an intrinsic
property, but that
particles are massless, but they
acquire a sort of effective mass,
because when moving, they are
sort of slowed down
by the Higgs field,
which fills the vacuum,
this is something completely counterintuitive,
you learn it at university,
but the day that you really see
this mechanism at work
that is when the revolution, for me
at least, really happened in my brain.
It is at the moment when we
discovered the Higgs
that I told myself: but, this is
thus really the mechanism?!
And it was really then that I thought
a bit more intensively
that this was a revolution.
>> We all shared the same thought.
To abandon this well rooted notion, that
mass is an intrinsic property,
that particles are born with,
and replace it by a coupling constant
to an ubiquitous field, that is a big step.
>> That is a big step.
Yeah yeah, it really is an interior revolution.
>> So, what does this have to do with the
mass of the trolley which one pushes?
>> Well, nothing! Haha, nothing at all!
>> That is where our world
decouples a bit
from everyday’s world, yeah, yeah.
>> Yes, as I already explained
in the previous module
the mass of ordinary matter,
the gravitational mass
and the inertial mass are given
essentially by the mass of the nucleus,
which has nothing to do with the mass
of electrons and quarks.
So, what will follow now?
Why does one continue
when one has already completed
the Standard Model?
One could stop there, no?
Why does one continue
experiments like ATLAS?
>> There are plenty of good reasons to continue!
>> Give us some, please.
>> So.
We have there this Higgs mechanism,
which is a complicated mechanism,
to answer the question: what is the mass
of elementary particles?
We have answered this question, but at
the same time, we have opened lots of new questions.
So, the existence of this field in the
vacuum poses lots of questions.
It poses a lot of problems.
It is in fact funny, because one shifts the problem:
one poses a
first question, one answers it, but in
answering it, one puts a new question.
>> One has shifted the intrinsic mass to
a coupling constant,
that one must now predict or explain.
>> Exactly.
And then the mere existence of the
field is problematic.
Because this field is fluctuating,
it receives all kinds of
radiative corrections, and thus,
it should not be the way it is.
That is already a first reason for us
to think that we have not understood everything,
and that we must continue to
make collisions
to understand this mechanism a little better.
So this, by the way,
is really a question linked to
particle physics.
But there are plenty of other observations,
which are more linked to the Universe,
like the existence of dark matter
and dark energy
which correspond to no less than 95%
of the contents of the Universe,
and of which we do not know the origin,
and which are not at all explained
by all the particles we have seen to
date at accelerators.
So we know from the start
that we must still find things
that we do not know yet.
Thus, we continue to search.
>> To stay with the Higgs
just a little more, we do not even know,
as far as I understand, if it is the only
particle with these properties, do we?
There could be several.
>> Absolutely.
In particular, to relieve the
problems which the Higgs boson brings
to the Standard Model, which predicts only one,
one has invented, for example,
a solution to these problems
which is called Supersymmetry.
This is one of the solutions, there are several,
but in this framwork
>> It is not my favorite one, but be it.
>> It was my favourite one, I think,
before the LHC started,
but by now it is in bad shape,
because we have still not seen it,
but OK.
So this is one extension
of the Standard Model, where
one effectively predicts
other Higgs bosons.
Where there are even five,
neutral ones and charged ones.
At minimum.
So yes, we continue to search for
other Higgs bosons.
>> It is for that reason that one has now increased
the energy by practically a factor of 2,
where one is now.
During the whole year,
you have experimented at a total energy
of 13 teraelectronvolts.
Is there still more margin,
concerning either the luminosity
or the energy of the accelerator?
>> So,
with the LHC energy one is practically
at the maximum.
The theoretical maximum, the energy
for which the LHC has been constructed
was 14 TeV,
and we are now at 13 TeV, I believe
it is quite complicated to arrive at 14.
>> And I believe it would not make
a big difference,
it is just 10% more.
>> Right,
it will not make a large difference,
we have thus arrived at the maximum
of the LHC as far as energy is concerned.
In terms of luminosity, clearly,
there are improvements and there is
already what we call
upgrades, foreseen in the future,
to strongly increase the luminosity,
so as to accumulate 100 times more
statistics, which is what will happen.
And then afterwards, to go to higher energies,
means really to construct
a new accelerator
and that is for the longer term,
we talk about several decades here.
There are projects on the table
to do that.
>> We will  certainly dedicate
another MOOC to this great project,
which has a nickname,
it is called FCC for the moment.
>> Yes.
>> So, thank you, Sandrine,
for this interview.
It was very interesting
to see how someone who has had
a rather important role in
this discovery has lived it.
Thank you very much.