Enough of blobs, let's get rigid.
All right, so now we're going to deal with
everything on, things are going to freeze.
Instead of just general continuum, but
I think this is a good classic thing.
Earlier stuff, definitely things
that I will put on the exam.
Something like that's going to
be on there guaranteed.
But now we're going to freeze it.
How do we do that?
How does that change my definitions?
How does it change momentum, energy,
all this kind of stuff and
we want to look at this.
So now angular momentum about a point O,
this is an inertial origin.
I've picked that already.
I can write that as my position vector or
cross or with dots.
That goes to each DM.
I didn't draw the the DMs here anymore.
But this is now a rigid boby.
So if it's rigid, every point in
the body has the same angular velocity.
If I'm spinning, then the speed of
my right hand is different than
the speed of my left hand,
the velocity, right?
because one's moving forward, that's
a different vector than a velocity vector
moving backwards relative to me,
opposite for you guys, all right.
But the angular velocity,
if we're spinning,
everybody needs to be rotating
at one degree per second.
Otherwise if the panel number two is
rotating at two degrees per second,
panel number one is only rotating
at one degree per second,
those panels are going to
catch up at some point, right?
It's deforming, that's not a rigid body.
So as before when we argued, RC was common
with the body integrals here we would have
tricks where we can say omega is constant
on a rigid body or blog the jello.
That's not true because everybody could
be spinning in different ways right
in that case.
So that's one thing.
Another one, this is the basic definition.
You've seen now how we break this up.
We write r as big R as Rc plus little r.
And then same thing here, with thoughts,
do the cross products on your own.
Make sure you can derive this.
And then you come there.
There will be terms that vanish, but again
the angular momentum about point O can be
written as, this is the angular
momentum of the center of mass
plus the angular momentum
about the center of mass.
Kind of what we did with energy as well.
So I'm leaving this up to you
to practice and go through and
make sure you can go from here to here.
Now this part, that's your Orbits class.
You've all taken some type
of Orbits class probably.
And you hang momentum on orbit and
how it's conserved and
from that you get all of the different
chronic intersections and trajectories.
And that comes from here.
That's cool, but
we don't care about that part.
This class is all about
attitude of spacecraft, right?
The translational side, as you see through
the super particle theorem, you can really
handle separately and track what happens
to the center of mass of a spacecraft.
I care about what happens about
the center of mass in this class.
So I have wheels, I have gyroscopics,
all the stuff, that's what I care about.
That's what the attitude dynamics is.
So instead of HO, I'm just going to keep
this part which I'm going to write as HC.
That's the angular momentum
about the center of mass and
that will simply be r cross r dots dm.
Same definitions we had before right?
So that's good.
So now if this is rigid.
People, if this is rigid,
what happens to this derivative?
>> r dot, it goes to zero doesn't it?
>> Okay, who agrees with that?
Who disagrees with that?
And the rest of you are asleep,
okay, or just confused, that's fair.
I'm also confused sometimes.
So, you agree that it would go to zero?
Sorry, what was your name again?
>> Ansel.
>> Ansel, thank you.
Why do you think it would go to zero?
>> I thought that's how
a rigid body was defined,
that the points don't move
relative to the center of mass.
>> What does this dot mean?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> So this is your body.
And to track this point, this little
knob at the end of the pen, right?
It's inertial, I mean it's an inertially
fixed spin axis, it's a rigid body.
Is the velocity as seen by you,
an inertial observer, zero?
Right, the position vector would be center
of mass to this little knob, right?
And that vector is clearly
rotating as seen by you guys.
So as seen by what frame would this time
derivative go to zero if it is rigid?
>> Body frame.
>> The body frame.
That's the key.
So I'm glad you guys mentioned inertia
because this an easy stumbling block.
Everybody starts out with, it's rigid.
All the dots go to zero.
No.
This is the inertial
derivative of the velocity.
If it's rigid,
it just means as I'm rotating,
my right hand is always to my right.
It's not moving up, down,
otherwise I'm not being a rigid body.
So only as seen by the body are these
time derivatives zero for a rigid body.
That's the key thing that
everybody always misses otherwise.
So good, so now if we do that, we know
how to do this transport theorem, right?
Kinematics comes back and
we take the body frame derivative, why?
Because we know it's going to go to zero,
we love zero.
And what you're left
with is omega cross r.
Okay, good.
We do that so r dot is nothing but omega
crossed r and I can plug that in here.
So I get an r cross omega cross r.
This form is not very convenient.
I said omega is constant
as seen by the body itself.
If it's rigid, every point in that body
needs to be tumbling at the same rate or
it's deforming.
But in a cross product like this, I can't
just pull the middle term out, all right.
So I want to make it either at the left
hand side, or the right hand side.
Then I can take it outside of the body
integral, and that's what I'm doing here.
On A cross B is a same
thing as minus B cross A.
So I flipped it, and then I have r cross
r cross omega with the minus sign.
And in matrix form, this r cross r
cross is nothing but r tilde r tilde.
Again, that's where
the minus sign comes from.
And then now I can take the omega
outside of that interval because it is
rigid, right, that is the key assumption.
Anybody recognize what this
term is going to become?
Angular momentum turns to
be something times rates.
>> Inertia.
>> Inertia, yeah,
moment of inertia, exactly.
So these can become our inertia tensor
that you've seen from your statics and
mechanics classes.
So we're just going to derive this now.