If you pick vector components, this is
just written in a very corner frame,
independent way.
I'm just taking the cross product operator
and representing it in a matrix form.
Now to actually numerically compute it,
you'd have to take r1, r2, r3.
And then your first rule becomes 0 minus
r3 plus r2, right, and you break it down.
That means you've picked
a particular body frame.
So if you do that and that matrix with the
minus sign, it gives you this definition.
If you replace r1, r2, r3 with just x,
y, and z this should look very familiar.
And now you would have your y squared
plus z squared, x squared plus z squared,
x squared plus y squared.
Those are your different
moments of inertia definitions.
And then we have our off diagonal
terms that appear as well.
So generally, to have a rigid body your
inertia tensor, which is what I'm showing
here, will be a three by three matrix
when you numerically evaluate it.
But to do so, there's two conditions.
One, we've picked about which
point we're taking moments.
These r's are defined relative
to the center of mass.
And then when you numerically evaluate it,
you pick a particular coordinate frame and
say, okay, my one access point is forward.
The second one is to the left and
then the third one is up.
If you pick a different coordinate frame,
you would have different components.
And you get a different inertia matrix
representation of the inertia tensor.
The inertia tensor is really an invariant,
that's it for
this space craft has one inertia tensor.
But then how we numerically express it.
There's an infinity of answers, because
I could pick a infinity of body frames
to break out these vectors and
do the tildes and compute this.
Now this body integral is not very fun.
It gets tedious.
Cat programs love this.
They know where every nut and
bolt and panel and fuel tank is, and
everything that goes on the spacecraft.
So it simply has to sum them up, know
the location, do this math, times dn and
sum everything up, and
it spits it out in a heartbeat.
Doing it analytically
a little bit tedious, so
we will look at tricks that we don't
have to redo this integral every time.
What if I am not taking moments about this
point, but I am putting this at the end of
a robot arm and
I need movement about this other point.
Do I have to redo all this math?
So angular momentum expression,
as we said, was just hc.
You already identified that term as
being nothing but the inertia tensor.
I am writing it as Ic times Omega.
There is now some
notational subtlety here.
Here I picked a particular bonding frame.
Here I am not specifying body.
So I'm really equating matrix math is
equivalent to this tensor vector math.
The inertia tensor, think of it as
a two-dimensional vector, right?
I can write these quantities in a general
way, but then when I evaluate any vector I
have to have a coordinate frame to
break down the components and add and
subtract them.
But you can write them in
a very coordinate agnostic way.
And that's what I'm having here.
I'm not saying, if this is the b frame,
this better be in the b frame.
Otherwise, you're adding apples and
oranges.
But, this can also both be in the q
frame or the r frame, it doesn't matter.
In the vectorial way, we can just
write the tensor operator like this.
So that's the Inertia Tensor.