So now there's two aspects.
Either we need to have a different point
about which we're taking moments or
we're taking a different corner frame.
And hopefully you've
seen some of this before.
Just going to go through
this pretty quickly.
The book derives this,
if you want to look at this steps, but
I'm just going to give you the answer.
So if you have the inertia tensor
about the center of mass and
that's typically what a statics
mechanics book gives you.
And now you have this block, or
this cone, or this panel, right.
And then it gives you X, Y, and
Z coordinates, and assumes that things
are lined up with symmetry, it gives you
this answer, basically, in that form.
For some reason this panel,
you don't need the inertia, the moments.
About its center of mass, but
it's going to be attached to a spacecraft.
The arm is the panel.
The panel center of mass is here, but
the spacecraft center of mass
might be somewhere else.
How do I get these moments about here?
You could redo all these integrals.
Or this parallel axis theorem basically
allows you to take moments about other
points.
And the way this is written is you need
the inertia tenser about the center of
mass, that's always going to be
the smallest inertia you'll have,
any further away and
it's going to get bigger.
And you get mass times distance squared,
that's probably how you remember
parallaxes theorem for
fixed axis rotation.
If this is the inertia about center and
all of a sudden I'm spinning
about the end-point.
You would have that distance squared times
mass that you have to add to the inertia.
This is a 3D version of that.
Total mass,
I need to know what is that shift.
So I'm taking moments about O.
There's a vector going from
O to the center of mass.
And I'm calling that one RC again.
And I've got a tilde form
to avoid a minus sign so
it's plus mass times distance squared
essentially but in a tilde formulation.
So that's how we can,
we don't have to reevaluate
the inertia tenser every time we
have a different moment point.
You just use this theorem.
Here's the one subtlety
people often trip over.
In here again, we mention these tensers
when you numerically value a three pathway
matrices.
You have to pick a coordinate frame.
Make sure you're adding these things
up in the same coordinate frame.
That includes this.
So these RC tildes better
be broken down in the same
N frame if this is given in the N frame.
Or if this is given in the B frame,
you have to write RC in the B frame.
RC's often given in the other frame.
You have a, your cube set,
it goes on to the space station.
You probably have your cube set inertia
about at the center of mass but
then it's in the space, and
that's in the cube set frame.
But where, it is in the space station its
typically expressed to you in a space
station coordinate frame.
All right, relative to the space station
you put that cube set at this launch
location.
Well, then you have to of course
use a DCM to map vectors from
a space station frame to body
frame before you apply this stuff.
That's the one step I often see missed.
Right, so just make sure if you do this
math everything's taken with respect to
the same frame.