Kinetic energy, let's start here.
Now we did this for blobs in space.
And for blobs in space we were able to
show kinetic energy was nothing but
the kinetic energy off the center
of mass plus kinetic energy
about the center of mass.
But this second term contains
both deformational energy,
if panels are flexing and
doing or fuel is sloshing.
And the rotational part, right?
Now let's use the same assumption.
r dot for a rigid body,
it doesn't go to zero, but
the r dot just became omega crossed r,
the body relative derivative of zero.
So we're also just going to
focus on the rotational side.
This is basically your translational
energy which comes out of
your orbits class.
We're not going to focus on orbits in
here, just the rotational dynamics, so
we're not going to cover that.
And this is where I plugged
in r dot is omega cross r.
So you get a bunch of cross products,
dot product.
And you know right away there
must be some magic trick identity
that we can rearrange this.
That's kind of what I'm doing here,
almost actually.
First, and I'm using trig here, this omega
is a constant as seen of the integration.
If it's rigid, every point has
to be rotating at the same rate.
So this omega I can just take outside.
There's a dot product.
Okay I did use a vector identity
already to rewrite this into this form,
and now I could take your omega
outside to the dot product.
Here I'm still left with
omega in the middle but
we have the trick that
a cross b is minus b cross a.
That puts it on the right hand side.
And you can take that one out as well.
In fact if you go back and look at Hc,
this whole definition is nothing but Hc.
In fact this term becomes nothing but
your inertia tense times omega.
And the inertia tense times
omega was nothing but
angular momentum about that point c.
So it's nice, we now have, rotational
energy can simply be written as one half
omega dotted with angular momentum.
Those are two vectors dotted together.
When you dot them,
mathematically make sure they're
taken with respect to the same frame.
But here is written in
a frame agnostic way.
So angle rotation, so
that's the same thing, H is I omega,
you might remember as rotational energy
being inertia over 2 times angular
rate squared for fixed axis rotation.
This is the 3D version of that.
You would have one-half
omega transpose I omega.
And that's basically inertia omega squared
over 2, essentially that's what it is.
Power.
We had earlier,
if the time derivative from a blob,
the first part translation was just force
times the inertial velocity, again,
that's the translational sign.
What we do care about here is T dot.
So if you differentiate this term,
you will end up with this.
Now to get this form, you need to have
the rotational equations of motion,
which we haven't derived yet.
But I will let you, this is something
you should make a note in exam,
definitely go back and make sure you can
go from here to here, but it simplifies.
But the beauty of this is,
for translation,
we have force started with
translational velocity.
With rotation, you have torque
dotted with angular velocity.
It's really the same type of
term that we're going to have.
And that's what makes,
this is what gives you your power rate.
To the system.
When is T-dot going to be zero?
Let's ignore translation,
we'll just focus on this.
When is my power equation
going to be zero?
Sheila, what do you think?
Without reading more,
I want to hear you think.
>> The angular velocity is zero or-
>> You could, if you're not spinning.
>> Center of mass is acceleration is zero,
the Rc.
>> Well we're going in
translation right now.
>> Okay.
>> Just focus on this one,
the rotational side.
What makes this second term go to zero?
Omega could be zero, yes.
It's kind of a trivial
dynamical system then, yes,
if the energy is zero then
the energy rate is going to be zero.
But that works, yep.
What else could you do?
>> [INAUDIBLE] Make Lc zero.
>> So what is Lc here?
[INAUDIBLE].
>> No?
What is LC here?
>> Torque.
>> It's a torque.
So this is a torque about point c.
And in fact when we get this torque,
this torque is due to external forces
when we derived all this stuff.
So for this dynamical system,
if your external torque on that
rigid body is zero,
you won't dissipate energy.
This makes a great integration check.
So as you guys are writing numerical code,
you've got something that's spinning and
there's no external torque on this system.
I know energy has to be preserved.
If we had H dot equal to L,
that was the same thing.
The angle momentum as seen
by the inertial observer,
that's what that dot meant right,
inertial derivative.
As seen by inertial observer,
H has to be a constant vector if no
external torque is acting on it.
These things become fantastic
integration checks.
This is for a single rigid body.
But even if you do multi-body,
complex panels flapping, reaction wheels,
gyros spinning, twisting, this stuff
still has to hold, which is really nice.
And now if there is a torque
acting on that system.
I can actually predict very quickly
how my kinetic energy needs to change.
And this becomes a nice integration check,
because I can compute kinetic energy from
the simulation numerically and
then differentiate it to get T dot.
And compare,
I know I applied this gravity gradient
torque, this is my spin rate at the time.
Energy should have changed by this
many joules per second, right?
So these tools becomes very,
very useful validation tools, but also for
analysis you will see.
So torque-free motion is when
momentum is inertially preserved and
kinetic energy is preserved,
because this is zero.
The third option actually could exist,
in that the dot product goes to zero.
Maybe you have very particular torques
being applied, such that no matter what
your spin rate is, right now
the torques are orthogonal to that.
In that case you have
a non-working force acting on it.
That's what they call
it because it doesn't,
not doing work means it doesn't
change my energy state.
So there's three ways,
either omega zero, Lc zero, or
those two things are orthogonal.
Then T dot goes to zero.
And again over, if you have to work down
between points and time, you can do this
with a time integral or you could
also do it in the spatial integral.