Let's derive the equations
of motion of a rigid body.
We know how to describe
the orientation of a rigid body.
We have Euler angles, we have DCMs.
We've got and CRPs, MIPs.
All these things and
we always have differential equations and
how they relate back to omega.
If the omega is not just prescribed or
measured, if you really
have a free tumbling body.
You kick off the satellite
from the rocket.
What happens as it gets released?
I need to be able to mathematically
predict how omega will evolve, and
that means I need to find
differential equations for omega.
And what we're going to use always,
for translation,
we use f equals ma essentially.
That's what it boils down to,
that's one of the forms.
Here, for rotation,
we always go back to H dot equal to L.
And so, here,
H is taken about the center of mass.
So, we know H dot equal to L holds.
And L is the torque.
About of all the extra influences about
the center of mass of the system.
So okay if we know it's the inertia
derivative of H that is equal to
this equal to this torque.
So we have to be now a little bit
careful in how we derive this.
I've chosen to take a body relative
derivative of this plus now,
I have two omega b, relative to n,
crossed with that h vector again, right.
The transport theorem isn't just for
positions and velocities and so forth.
It's true for any vectorial quantity
that you're differentiating,
as seen by a rotating frame.
Angular momentum counts as also a vector.
So this is true.
Now why did we choose to do
the body frame derivative of this?
If we do this, and I just use chain rule,
we know h we defined as being
the inertia about point c times omega.
So that's two terms.
And taking the time derivative
of this chain rule, right?
You get the derivative
of the first term plus
the derivative of the second term
with the right multiplications.
That's good, now it says this is
going to become equal to i omega dot.
There's two steps in this
one little equal sign.
What happens to this part?
What happens to body frame
derivative of the inertia tenser?
Jordan.
>> Finishes.
>> Why?
>> Constant in time.
>> So even if this thing is tumbling and
spinning and
going through space as seen
by you inertial observers.
The mass distribution keeps changing.
This point is here, it's up, it's left,
it's flat, it's all over the place right?
That's why doing this derivative on
any inertia tensers inertia frame
you can do it.
But it becomes a time varying quantity and
you have to track all this stuff.
And it gets harder.
Whereas the derivative of the inertia
tensor as seen by the body frame
is trivial if it's rigid.
Because in the mass distribution,
as seen by myself, if I'm rigid and
I'm rotating and doing stuff, that
mass distribution is exactly the same.
And this is going to vanish.
If you had a deployable mass,
you slowly having your solar panels
from your cube sat and doing something.
Then some servos that are moving them out.
Well then you would have body relative
derivatives and that's the point
where you include extra terms,
all of a sudden, into these equations.
That's what gives you those extra stuff.
So good, so that term vanished.
Now here, this dot, Lewis,
implies what type of derivative?
>> It implies an inertial derivative.
>> Here it's a body frame derivative.
So how did I go from a body frame
derivative to inertial derivative?
>> Make the vectors
consistent between the two.
>> Right,
this isn't omega of b relative to n.
So therefore, the b framed derivative and
the n framed derivative
have to be the same.
That's the one vector where
you find this kind of stuff,
where the derivatives between
the two frames is the same if it's
the angular velocity
between the two frames.
Because the omega cross
product term always goes to 0.
Exactly.
So, if you want to be careful,
show all these steps.
In an exam don't just go from here and
that's clearly this.
I'm, you can be missing points.
I want to see all these sub steps.
Argue every case as you understand,
this is why this goes to zero here.
And argue correctly why this
other one goes to this, right?
So, good.
So, the body around this derivative
is just going to be i*omega-dot.
Plus this cross-product term.
So, we're almost there.
Now, you put this together and
you get this differential equation.
I put this cross-product, H=Ic, so
I have omega cross is the same
thing as omega two the h.
That's essentially how we
got to this last step.
I took it over to the right hand side, so
I have i omega that is equal to minus
omega til the i omega plus l c.
That's the classic orders
rotational equations of motion.
This is what predicts now,
in your integration,
how does my omega evolve in time.
And for a rigid body,
tumbling like this, there's two aspects.
One is, this is a gyroscopic.
And you notice, it's omega and omega,
so it's omega squared, is essence.
And it's a second order term.
If you look at linearized departures, you
miss all of this stuff, it just vanishes.
So, this is the quadratic,
this is your gyroscopics and
you'll see different ways
this manifests itself.
The other part is our external torque,
and that's it and it looks really simple.
Why did this become so
hard so quickly sometimes?
Well, we'll talk about
different ways to write this.
This form, we have a nice, generic i.
So, we can have a principle coordinate
frame as we talked about earlier.
Or we can have any body fixed frame.
This can be a regular 3 by
3 matrix representation and
it will work, all right.
So, this is a very general format.
So in your integration, I would recommend
this is the equation you should implement
because that way you're solving
always the most general case and
the easier cases become
sub classes of that.
If you pick, sorry Jordan?
>> Quick notational question,
you have sub scripts on l and h but
you don't have them on i?
>> Yeah.
Is that purposeful?
Or wouldn't you [CROSSTALK].
>> Just lazy.
>> Same point?
>> I was just lazy.
>> Okay.
>> If you want to keep track,
I do recommend.
If you want to keep track of them,
this has to be the inertia
about point C in this case.
If you wanted to keep track of that.
For these kind of rigid body dynamics,
people very quickly drop them and
it's just implied.
But it's a subtlety.
If you have multi body stuff and you take
in moments and torques about you know,
there's a different body fix point,
there's a docking port point.
Definitely keep track of those suckers,
because it's easy to get it mixed
up when you're adding these things.
So here I just dropped
it out of convenience,
this is, you see this a lot
actually in the notations,
they don't declare themselves as
being lazy, but [SOUND] I don't care.
Okay, so we have this.
Now, let's say we have
a principal corded frame.
As we were hearing earlier,
that means all the matrix representation
of this tensor will just have diagonals.
Lots of off diagonals go to zero.
And the same thing here.
So, omega I omega will just become
i1 omega 1, i2 omega 2, i3 omega 3.
Really simple.
And then that 10 to the omega 2,
you carry out this math and
you up with these equations.
So, these are equivalent
to these equations,
this just assumes I've chosen
principal axes of the body.
Whereas this allows for
any body fixed axises.
So, yes integration wise
this is what you use.
But, in analysis we often find it
much easier to just look at this.
And in fact we will be using these
equations a lot here coming up.
The torque free motion and
discuss different things.
So, you can see the classic
kind of results and L, L 1 2 3,
is basically, this is all taken in
a body fixed frame that's principle.
So, these are the same vector components
with respect to that frame And then we go.
So, you can see now for example,
if you have a axis symmetric body,
we talked earlier about different shapes.
because if you have a cylinder, a rocket
body, a lot of things in space tend to be
barrels because everything
fits in a rocket.
Well the rocket itself is kind of a barrel
shape, it has an axis of symmetry.
In that case two principle
inertias will always be equal.
So since in here the gyroscopics are all
these differences of two principle
inertias you know right away [INAUDIBLE]
metric bodies one of these gyroscopic
terms is going to vanish right and
that's an insight to have.
I'll see this in a few
cases that we'll look at.
Now let's talk about how
to integrate these things.
One question I have for you is, does,
we've derived differential
nematic equation, just MRPs.
We know sigma odd is equal to one over
four b times is omega vector right.
So omega appears defiantly
going to need that.
Otherwise we just need sigma Here,
I need omega, omega, the inertia,
it's a rigid body so with relative to B
frame, this is a fixed inertia tensor.
And then, you have external torques.
Nowhere in here do you see sigmas, or
quaternions, or any attitude measure.
So if I have two differential equations,
the question then becomes can you
integrate just omegas first and
then do the attitude?
Or should you aways be integrating
omegas in attitudes simultaneously?
[SOUND], I see some wrinkles now,
okay, good.
Can we do it?
The sigma starts omega.
So, you know you can't do sigmas first,
but I could do omegas first,
integrate forward and then use that answer
and then separately integrate omegas.
What do you think?
Andre?
>> I'd say simultaneously.
>> Because?
But you delivered the question.
>> I know. [LAUGH] >> Hopefully you're
good enough at by now where you know
I'm asking you a trick question.
And B, the gut feeling probably is I know
simultaneous should definitely work.
Separating, now you need to argue
a defense why was that valid, right.
There's simple answers, definitely.
I would also do it simultaneously,
but why.
Is it ever okay to just integrate omegas?
And then do that.
Daniel.
>> Don't have torques.
>> Okay.
Torque free motion.
If I have torque free motion,
I don't have my that works only here.
If I don't have the torque, absolutely.
You could just integrate omega.
Now in my codes, let me just say upfront,
I always do it simultaneously.
Just, that's the most general answer,
right.
And I don't want to write code for
these cases when I have no torque or
here I have torque.
If I do them simultaneously,
it doesn't matter if I have torque or not.
But absolutely, you could do that but
let's say we do have torque.
I have some thrusters I'm firing.
There's two thrusters,
four thrusters, they're firing.
They're producing a torque.
Can you still integrate the omegas first
and then apply them to the sigma dots?
Need to have a situation where your
angular rates aren't coupled to
your actual angle, itself, right?
>> Well, yes, the angular
accelerations we're worried about.
It's omega dot.
Does omega dot couple with the angles?
This will never make
it couple with angles.
This never makes it couple with angles.
The only term that could make us
couple with attitudes Is this.
My example with thrusters.
If I'm firing pairs of thrusters
that produce a torque and
spin it,
does that matter now on the altitude?
The thrusters are body fixed,
so I get this torque.
If I spun around, then I thrust again,
relative to the body,
you always get in the same torque,
it's actually just going to show up
a bunch of constants,
no attitude dependence that works.
Give me a torque that
is attitude dependant.
>> Gradient.
Spencer.
>> Solo radiation pressure.
Right.
Daniel,
talking about atmospheric drag,
those effects.
Gravity gradients.
There's all these kind of disturbances,
often environmental.
All of a sudden, you need the attitude.
And then, whoa, now it matters.
When we do another thing
[INAUDIBLE] as humans,
we will be developing feedback control,
and even the simplest form the torque,
we come up with a thruster control torque,
which is minus a gain times attitude error
minus a gain time rate error or something
very simplistic like that, right?
And all of a sudden, through our
algorithm, we're coupling in our attitude.
because we want to point here,
not just come to rest over here, right?
And the thruster firings will
be a function of attitude.
So yes, so when you look at these things
and it's a good PHD prelim oral questions.
There are ways we can one way decouple
them and solve omega separately and
doing that parallel as Andre was saying.
Absolutely your gut feeling is right.
That's probably the way
it always will work and
in fact that's how you should program it.
And the way attitude couples into it,
thought, is only through this part,
which could be environmental effects
like drag, SRP, gravity gradient or
also we could external torques.
That's our control solution, all right?
That's what's producing these things.
And that's where attitude
couples in as well.