So, we want to integrate in a coupled way.
So, let's talk about this as you
can be writing code like that.
Let's just use sigmas.
I'm using my attitude being
explicit here all right?
The other set of stakes that I
have to integrate now are omegas.
So, we're going to put in
an omega B relative to N.
So, your code you've written earlier to
integrate just the attitude rates can
even omega.
It all works, it's just instead of omega
being looked up in a separate sine and
cosines or some function,
it's now computed every time step and
updated as well.
So you have to do
everything simultaneously.
Your x dot equals to F function.
F is basically the first part
is nothing but sigma dot.
And the second part is omega dot.
That's what you have to find.
In your code, you already have this part.
So you know that and it's based on
the current omega, the integration,
that's fine.
And now this one,
also depends on the current omega but
it also needs the inertia
tensor representation.
And it needs to know what the external
torques are and that's it.
So you can see once you have those
nice clean writings set up for
dynamical systems,
we can then easily expand.
Later on if we have reaction wheels,
we have to keep track,
those are extra states,
CMGs, extra states.
You just start expanding the state vector.
But you can build on your prior work,
and that makes life much easier, okay.
Any questions on this?
So, these are basic equations of motion.
H dot equal to L you saw.
It's like two lines with
the right arguments, and
you get the equations of motion
in a very general tensor form.