Last time, we derived the equations
of motion of a rigid body.
I got little cube with me here,
it's somewhat rigid right now.
How do we find the equations of
motion of a rigid body, Spencer?
Before you read too much.
>> You use super particle theorem on this
center of mass because it's rigid, so
the center of mass shouldn't
be changing position.
>> True,
if you worry about the translational part.
At this stage of the class, really
as we're talking about rigid bodies,
we're going to start just dropping
the translational, for most of it.
If not I will make it very explicit.
So if I'm talking about
the equations of motion,
I'm really just talking about
the rotational side of it.
So how do we find the rotational
side of the equation?
What are we actually looking for?
What's the variable?
Yeah, we're actually looking for
omega dot, right?
That's the,
omega is already a rate information so
omega dot is the acceleration.
That's your angular acceleration.
Once we have it we can integrate it.
So whereas translation have f equals ma,
you go straight from forces to
acceleration of your position description,
in attitude we have this kinetics and
kinematics always broken up.
We have somehow added to coordinate rates
related to omega, and then an omega dot
relates to forces and torques and
everything acting on it, right.
So you have this clear
split that you have to do.
So here we're looking for
the second part, the kinetics.
What's the fundamental property,
Robert, that we use to drive this?
>> [COUGH]
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Which principle did we apply?
>> Conservation of angular momentum.
>> Why is it conserved?
Why is the rotational
motion of a rigid body,
why does it have a conserved
angular momentum?
>> because-
>> Ansel, can you help him?
>> It's torque-free?
>> If it's torque-free, but
I didn't mention torque-free motion.
So let's assume it has torque,
what do we need then?
How do we get to an omega dot?
Mariel, which principles do we
use to get equations of motion?
>> Like H equals the derivative of H time,
or plus, omega cross.
>> Okay, you've taken
the derivative of it already, but
what is the inertial derivative of
the angular momentum of the system?
>> The right hand side of-
>> Yeah, L.
>> L, there we go, right.
So like f equals ma, this is good for
a continuum if we have center of mass, or,
and here implied if I don't write a sub c,
it's always implied to be center
of mass in this notation, right?
So we can use H=L, the key features is,
this dot has to be an inertial derivative,
like f equals ma, those a's have
to be the inertial acceleration.
And this L is the net sum of all
the external ports acting on the system,
which right now we're just writing as L.
Later on, that could be gravity gradient
torques, it could be drag torques,
it could be control torques with
thrusters, or something like that.
Many ways to break it up, good.
So let's review quickly, this is going to
be a good, what is H of a rigid body?
All right, once we said this thing wasn't
blob and jello and flexing, it's solid,
what did H become?
Was it, Brett?
>> Not sure.
>> What is angular momentum?
Go back to your sophomore level class,
fixed axis rotation.
What is angular momentum?
>> Is it the inertia times-
>> Yes, inertia times what?
>> The regular rate?
>> Yes, and
this is the 3D version of that.
i omega, right?
Review this stuff, otherwise, hour and
15 minutes you're not going to have
time to remember such things, okay?
We're getting up to that exam point.
So if H is this, this is the inertia
tensor, right, we talked about that.
This is written as is in a coordinate
frame independent way, you just have to
make sure if this is in the B frame,
this needs to be also in the same B frame.
And this gives you the answer in
a rotating frame and the B frame but
you could pick any frame you wish.
Good, now we need to do H dot.
So Mariel actually already
got us on this track.
We need an inertial derivative and
we choose to take a body
frame derivative of H.
I won't go all the details,
we did that last time.
This is just a review.
Why do we choose to do
a body frame derivative?
Kevin?
Why is that going to make our life
easier dealing with this term?
Let's break it up,
you're going to have chain rule.
You're going to have
the body frame derivative
of this tensor times
omega plus the inertial
tensor times [COUGH]
the anglular velocity.
And that's not H dot,
let me just, scratch that.
We're just doing, we're choosing to
do the body frame derivative of H.
So Kevin, why do the body frame
derivative of I omega easier?
>> Because then the derivative of
the inertia matrix is going to be zero.
>> Exactly, and see by the body,
every point to here, if you just lock your
arms out and you start rotating, as you're
rotating that arm is always to your left.
The mass distribution,
all those moments you computed,
and you got the inertia tenser,
they're fixed, as seen by the body.
As seen by you guys as I tumble an object,
the mass distribution is clearly changing.
So if you did the inertial
derivative directly on this,
you'd have lots of extra terms.
You'd have to map it to
the inertial frame, DCN, DCN dots,
DCN dots r minus omega til DCs.
And it all looks much more complicated,
but it's the same simple answer.
This ends up being,
as seen by the body observer, it's 0.
So that's why we do this,
what happens to this derivative?
Anybody remember?
What happens to that, yes?
>> It's just omega dot,
because it's the same inertial frame.
>> Because this is really,
if I write omega, it's short for
omega B relative to N.
We're typically dealing with B and N for
the next several weeks so
this becomes much easier.
The B and the N frame derivative are the
same, the cross product always drops out.
Good, so if you do all this stuff,
then H dot as Mariel was pointing out,
really ends up giving you I omega dot plus
I have to do the transport theorem so
I have an omega crossed H and
H is I omega, and that's equal to L.
There we go.
Is this only true for
particular coordinate frames,
or is this true for any frame?
Daniel, what do you think?
>> An inertial frame?
That's two frames.
>> Yeah, this is really written in
a very frame agnostic way again.
We haven't picked anything, we just solved
it, like we did earlier with positions and
angular velocities.
They're just vectors, we can start adding,
subtracting them without ever
specifying where does EL really point.
Once you want to get a numerical answer,
well you have to resolve the geometry and
have all the right stuff.
And so this is kind of the same way,
this is a very, like a vector.
We have vectors and tensors but
they're written in a frame agnostic way.
And when you do the math, just make
sure everything's in the same frame.
Especially when we get to the control
side, we'll be doing this a lot.
This is how we'll be
deriving our controls, but
when you code it,
you have to go, wait a minute.
This will make a R, that's coming in,
that's in the R frame and
this stuff is in the B frame.
Well then implied, you're going to
have to do some translations.
Matt?
>> I was writing when you wrote it,
[COUGH] and
I don't remember from last time.
Where does the second term in
that L equation come from?
>> This one?
>> Yeah.
>> I need H dot equal to L.
And basically what we do is, we take
the body frame derivative of H, but
I need the inertial derivative, so
you need omega crossed H as well.
And omega cross, H is I omega,
and omega cross H is the same
thing as omega tilde I omega.
That's the form we typically see it.
>> Cool, thank you.
>> And then that's L.
So you can see, in exam this is something
that shouldn't take you more than three
minutes if you know what you're doing.
But there's lots of subtleties,
if you just jump to the answer,
the answer's in the equation
sheet you guys have.
Just giving me the answer will
give you zero points in the exam.
It's all about the path and the details.
So make sure every time we go
through this, hopefully more and
more will sink in.
Make sure you get this stuff.
So, good, now we have very specific frames
that make your inertia tensor diagonal.
Trevor, what do we call such frames?
>> Principle frames.
>> Was principle coordinate frames,
are there an infinity of
principle coordinate frames?
You say no.
And you slow down?
[LAUGH]
>> Well, for a particular application, for
a particular rigid body,
it'll be the same.
>> So, here's a nice rigid body,
are there infinity of
principal coordinate frames?
>> Mandara, you think so?
Why?
>> because we have one axis
as they symmetry axis,
we can have the other two in
the plane orthogonal too.
>> Okay but if it's a cube.
>> Then all of them are-
>> See, all of a sudden,
ooh, wait a minute.
>> [LAUGH]
>> If it's a cube what happens to
my principle inertias?
>> They're all the same?
>> Yeah, they're repeated.
Hm, right, all these easy
questions at 8:00 in the morning.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I need more coffee.
Okay, so if they're all the same, why does
it make you hesitate all of the sudden?
>> because the vectors, the uniqueness.
>> Yeah, then you have to kind of,
the eigenvectors form different
ways that you can map to there.
You have to take a closer look at it.
If it's a body,
let's go to a simpler body.
This one has three distinct inertias.
It's definitely rigid, right?
Are you going to have more than
one principle coordinate frame?
Bryan, you don't think so?
>> I think you probably, yeah,
I think you probably could.
It depends on the symmetry of the object.
>> This is it, I'm showing you the object,
there's no more depends, it is.
>> Right, but if you take the moment
of inertia around one of those
principal axis, negative moment
of inertia on the other one.
>> Right, for every body,
it doesn't actually depend on the shape,
every body has at least some principal
axis that will diagonalize it.
And maybe an infinity, if it's a cylinder,
that's kind of what you guys are thinking
of, if it's a cylinder, there's definitely
an infinity of ways that you have it.
But if you have even three discrete
ones like this, or it's something very
amorphous it will still have three
principal inertias, principal axis.
But when you pick those eigenvectors,
you remember wait a minute,
I can have a positive direction but
who says this isn't your principle axis?
Maybe you want a frame the points towards
the tail because that's where your docking
porter is or you want to port towards,
find the points towards the nose
because this is a flight frame and you
kind of worry about where you're flying.
There's immediately, well there's two
options and then there's another one and
so there's a kind of
permutation you can go through,
there's an infinity of principle
frames that a general body would have.
But there's definitely a finite set
because you can always rearrange what's
your first, what's your second,
what's your third.
And plus or minus,
just always keep it right-handed, right?
So yeah,
there are several that we can pick and
so if we look at that,
we went through that actually.
If this is diagonal, these simplify down
to those three scalar equations we saw,
and then we can do that.
Now, the last question we had
we covered was integration.
If you want to integrate the complete
motion we have something and
we give it a spin and it tumbles.
How do we now numerically solve this?
Tosh, help us out,
how do we now write an integrator for
a complete 3D attitude dynamics?
>> So you'd look at your omega dot and
[INAUDIBLE].
>> But besides omega dot,
what else do you need?
What describes the full
attitude state of a rigid body?
>> I guess, [INAUDIBLE] general forces.
>> Nope, I'm asking for
what describes, what coordinates
do you need to fully describe
the orientation of a rigid body?
>> There's no other answer but
MRPs, I would say.
>> Not MRPs,
it was a good answer, definitely.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Thanks for sucking up, I appreciate it.
>> So you need an attitude measure, right?
Just like if you have f equals ma,
spring mass to amperes system,
think back to that form.
Okay, we've got x double dots,
that's nice.
But I have, every integrator writes
these things back into first order form.
So you define that x1 is equal to x,
and x2 is equal to x dot.
And then x1 dot is equal, and
you just do that classic stuff.
We have to do the same thing for attitude,
it's just we have different equations.
So we still need the attitude measure,
that was the integrator you wrote
earlier in these classes, right?
So you had something for
MRPs or quaternion or
whatever you wish to,
some attitude measure.
So that means you have a state
vector that is going to be now a,
if it's an MRP it's six by one.
If it's a quaternion it's a seven by one,
right,
this is what we have to propagate forward.
Otherwise this is very much what you did
before, you have your current states.
Then you compute k1 is
equal to the derivative.
So if x dot is equal to an f function,
depending on these, all right.
Then the first order one would just give
me what's the derivative of these states.
And then xn + 1 is xn
+ k1 times delta t.
Or you can do a fourth
order on the cut out or
whatever you wish to integrate, right?
It's the same integration that
you're doing in those problems,
you're just expanding now, now we have
to keep track of attitude and rates.
Now there was some discussion that
we had regarding, could we integrate
attitude separately from our kinetics
equation, from our omega dot equation?
So, Nick, do you remember the arguments?
How does attitude actually couple
into this differential equation?
>> [COUGH] I guess you could
single out the omega dot term.
>> No, omega is the state.
It's not,
>> I guess I don't
understand the question.
>> How does attitude
couple into this equation?
Does this differential equation
depend on my instantaneous attitude?
>> No, well, I was confident.
>> It was very confident,
I give you kudos for that.
It was completely wrong, but
it was very confident, absolutely.
Why does attitude couple into this,
where, right?
because omega that's just another state,
that's not the coupling itself.
It's a derivative of some stuff.
The interia tensor, well,
that doesn't really,
I don't have different mass
because I point differently.
It's a rigid body,
it doesn't matter on the orientation.
The only thing left is L,
How does attitude couple into L?
What are some physical
examples of torques?
Daniel?
>> Some torques are added to it
independently.
>> Yes.
>> Drag, SRP.
>> Drag, SRP, gravity, gradience,
or even our feedback control,
you will see very much,
that's where it couples.
So while there's instances where you
could just solve for omega first and
then solve for
the attitude as you did kind of.
I just gave you the omegas essentially
in earlier homeworks, right?
When you code it,
I highly encourage just to avoid that,
just give the general answer,
it's simple enough to do.
And you want to solve your attitude and
your omegas all simultaneously.
Later on in class we can even add
other stuff like reaction wheels or,
that quickly moves to 6010,
the follow on class.
Matt?
>> [COUGH] Excuse me,
I have a question about that
equation on the last page.
So when you were just asking that
question I was thinking that
you were pointing towards the I's because
this is an inertial derivative and
the inertial frame I will change.
But are these is constant because
we derived it in the body frame?
>> These are just tensors.
I mean if you say constant I have to
ask constant as seen by what frame?
The inertia is not a matrix like a DCM,
where it's just a three by three grouping
of cosines that we picked, right?
We could have picked something else.
This is really fundamentally a tensor.
Which means just like a vector it,
when you numerically evaluate it you
have to pick a coordinate frame.
So I just said look this been a completely
vectorial thing I can take the body frames
derivative of this and
what happens then is,
well the body frame derivative of H,
and H is I omega.
You break it up into two parts, right?
Here, I can immediately say this part is
going to go to zero, which simplifies it.
And this derivative body frame is the same
thing as the inertial derivative,
as we discussed.
So this H B frame derivative becomes
nothing but I omega dot, that's this part.
Could then, to get the inertial
derivative, I have to add omega cross H,
which is equivalent to here.
So this gives me the answer but
I've never actually picked
a particular courting frame.
Remember when we're using
transport theorem and
we say we're taking the derivative
of vector as seen by this frame.
It doesn't mean you have to
write that vector in that frame.
Often we have,
that's why we've chosen that frame.
Here, we haven't chosen the B frame
derivative because we have a particular
coordinate frame, we've chosen a B frame
derivative because as seen by the B frame,
the mass distribution for a rigid body is
constant and that derivative goes to zero.
>> I think this was my confusion,
no matter was I is, it's constant.
>> It's constant, exactly.
For any shape with asymmetries and
whatever's going on,
this is always true, right?
The only thing is, it's rigid.
That's the single rigid body and
now we have this in a very general way.
You can see this looks suspiciously simple
in undergraduate stuff we go through this
very, very quickly.
But then all this, there's all these
layers of details that are on top of
this that take a little bit more
time to sink in, so, work with this.