Where we have a slender rod
that's falling to the ground.
So basically, think of this rod.
You sign in this up on
a frictionless surface.
Think of an ice rink, a very slick ice
rink and he's standing it up and for
some reason this is perturbed.
There's no friction force here
holding your lower end in place.
So once you slide off you're
just going to slide out.
So it's basically just going to
fall down and slide down like this.
That's what's going to happen.
And what we're going to try to find
here are our equations of motion.
And we're going to use these very
principles, super particle theorem,
HL equal to L.
The inertia tenser definitions and so
forth to derive all the right quantities.
So I'm giving you here from a material
statics book you can find easily
if you have a slender rod then the inertia
about it's center of mass is mass over 12.
L squared, L's length of the rod.
So slender means we're
ignoring the other dimensions.
It's just a homogeneous, very,
very thin mass distribution, right.
So that's what you get there.
So we're going, okay, so we have that.
Now let's look at the angular momentum.
If we want to write Hc, the angle
momentum above the center of mass,
we needed the inertia tensor times
the angular velocity of this stuff.
And you can see,
I've got a body fixed point,
a body fixed frame, E,
that I'm defining here.
So EL, E theta, where is E3 pointing?
Let me just make sure you're
looking at the picture, right.
Into the board or out of the board?
>> Into.
>> Into the board, right?
eL, e theta, e3,
third finger points into the board,
that's where it's pointing, okay?
So the angular velocity
as we're tilting in 1d,
it's going to be theta dot about e3,
right.
So that's what this part right here,
those two terms,
that's omega of e relative to n for
this body.
Now I need the inertia tensor about this
one, so let's just write that one out.
You've seen the matrix notations,
I want to make sure that you
get all this stuff right.
So if we have this in the E frame,
it's a principle frame,
you will have I1, I2, I3.
And, let's just ignore this.
E relative to N, theta dot e3.
What does theta dot e3 look
like as a 3 by 1 matrix?
0, 0, theta dot, right.
And yes, you have these other inertias.
We said, it's a slender rod so
there are some terms about that.
But in the end,
this matrix times this matrix is
just going to give me 0,
0, I3 theta dot, right?
In different components,
which is equivalent to
that I3 theta dot E3.
And in this problem I3 is
the N over 12 L squared.
That's the inertia about that,
the third axis that we have, in and
out of the board.
All right, we didn't need
the inertias about the long axis or
anything else like that.
That's where, so when you've,
this is something you want to practice.
Once it clicks,
you go how was this ever confusing?
But you want to be able to go from
the inertia stuff to this quick other
formulations especially
with the plane of rotation.
It should always give
you equivalent results.
So good, so that's how we get this part.
We have to angle momentum about C.
Now to get equations of motion,
one way we often do with rotational
side is we use Euler's equation,
which means H dot = L and taking moments
about center of mass, H dot = L holds.
And I need to have L
above the center of mass.
So let's see what do we have here?
What torch is being applied?
The only torch that's being
applied here is this normal force,
somethings holding that tip from
sliding beneath the I surface, right?
So the I is still pushing up.
It's just not pushing laterally.
So it's giving it lateral stability, but
it is holding that point in place,
all right?
Why does gravity's acting on this?
Why doesn't gravity cause any torques?
>> Ax on the center of mass.
>> Right, gravity ax on the center of
mass and therefore the moment on for
the gravity force.
That's when you apply it,
it would actually vanish.
Very good, okay.
So, we need the moment arm.
What is the point of force relative to the
center of mass then that's this vector.
So, this length is L, so
if going from here to here is minus
L over 2 in the eL direction, right?
Back to week one,
vectors are distances times direction.
The distance is eL over 2.
The direction is minus eL hat.
That's the moment arm
crossed with the force,
which is the normal force on the surface,
right?
And you now have an eL crossed in n2.
Well you're going to have to map one
into the other and that's what you get,
a sign term in here in terms of e3.
So we can write this out.
So good, we're looking for
equations of motion for theta, but
all of a sudden we have to
introduce an extra unknown.
We don't know what this
force is on the surface.
So we know right away H equal
to L is not going to be enough.
You can't have two
unknowns in one equation.
People try, they try really hard,
it just doesn't work.
So we'll need additional equations.
Let's first wrap this up,
we have H, we have L,
now the derivative of this H, inertial
derivative has to be equal to this L.
Well e3, this is a rotating frame but
what can you say about e3?
Is that a rotating axis or
a fixed heading axis?
It's fixed, actually, right.
It's the other two that are rotating.
So e3 is actually N1,
it's the same thing as minus N3.
And N3's definitely an inertial frame so
that's why taken the intertial
derivative of this, I don't have
to treat e3 as a rotating axis.
It's actually a fixed axis.
So this inertia is fixed.
I'm not changing the mass
distribution of the rod.
The only thing that varies is theta.
So you very quickly get the inertia
times theta double dot.
And here I've dropped e3.
Because in the end,
everything's along the e3 axis.
So it gives me my one thing.
So H dot equal to L.
I brought L over to the left hand side.
And that's how that comes in.
So this is one equation.
I'm looking for always second
order differential equations for
equations of motion.
And so acceleration, that's my theta
double dot acceleration equation.
But it have an extra unknown.
So H dot equal to L was not enough,
what else do we have?
People.
>> Super particle theorem or energy?
Energy here is pretty smart
because there's no friction.
>> Yeah, energy doesn't typically
help quite in these equations of
motion typically.
The principles we use is either H = L,
there's different points we could use.
We've used for now the point c.
What was the other point
we could have used?
An inertia point that
was another approach.
And you can try H equal to L about center
of mass or about the inertial point and
they can give you different information.
And that might be a way
to get a second equation.
But what we're going to do here is
actually use Newton's equation.
Basically, super particle theorem, right?
That said, well whatever the sum
of the external forces is,
mass times the inertial
acceleration to center of mass,
has to be equal to that force, right?
So if we do that,
the center of mass location,
I'm just going to call this coordinate y,
you can see here.
So Y doubled up in two because its own
center of mass is only moving in N2
direction.
That makes it easy,
it's an inertial direction.
Take it twice derivative it's just
Y doubly NY doubled up in two.
That's my big M times rc
double dot that we have to
review the particle theorem, right.
Now that has to be equal to the sum of
the forces acting on the system, and
this system only has two forces.
There is a force on the surface that's
pushing back against the pen tip,
keeping it just in place.
And there's gravity acting on the slot and
that's why we're falling.
Otherwise, if you have slippery
surface on the space station and
without any other human slip.
So with gravity +N it's
in the N2 direction and
NG is in the -N2 direction so
this gives you your differential equation.
But you look at this and go, I can see
Brian already going wait a minute.
We get an end that's good but
now we introduce a y.
We just seem to be chasing our tail here.
Every time we have an equation
we have an extra unknown.
So now we have two equations and three
unknowns we're not making any progress.
And Brian's absolutely right,
so what are we missing?
We need an extra equation.
Are y and theta independent?
Spencer, are those two independent
coordinates of the dynamical system?
Or another question is, this dynamical
system has how many degrees of freedom?
>> One.
>> One, right,
there's only one degree of freedom.
There's only one angle, right.
Now with that angle, we can prescribe
what that height has to be.
So there must be a geometric relationship
between the y coordinate and
the theta coordinates, right.
Because you have y and theta, this didn't
turn it into a two degree freedom problem.
It's still a one degree
of freedom problem.
So what is the relationship?
And that's what we do here.
It's very simple, this line would be L
over 2 cosine, that gets you to heighth y.
That's what I have here, all right.
So if I have theta, I know y.
And now here, I need theta double dot,
that means you simply take 2 times
derivative of this y expression,
chain rule of this cosine, so you get
some sines and cosines and other stuff.
But that's how your y double
dots relate to your thetas.
Theta dots and theta double dots, right.
So those are not, we had two kinematic
variables that was convenient.
This y was very convenient
when writing f = ma.
But in the end,
we have to pick one of them and
write everything in terms
of one of the coordinates.
So if you do this, you plug this in here.
You can now,
actually this depends on y and
n, this depends on y and theta,
I can now write n in terms of theta.
So I get rid of one of the variables, y.
And now the last step is this,
this has to go back up in here and
now we can write our
equations of motion for
this slender rod falling in place,
slipping down like this.
Looks a little bit more complicated.
It's amazing how life gets complicated
quickly, even with simple examples.
Now with this differential equation,
is this a linear differential equation or
a non-linear differential equation?
Non-linear.
There's sines,
cosines of the states, right?
There's even theta dot squares, sine
squared of stuff, definitely not linear.
So who thinks they can quickly
solve this differential equation?
Darn, I always hope somebody raises their
hand because then I want to talk to you
about a PhD program.
because I can't solve this.
Maybe a mathematician can solve this.
But it's tricky, right?
So how do we solve this?
Well, we go back to integration, right?
You put this in state space form.
x1 is equal to theta.
x2 is equal to theta dot.
Then you get your sets of equations.
You can integrate.
So numerically, no problem.
But analytically, this can be a challenge.
And very often in these problems
we want to have at least
integration of one time.
That means, I'm looking for the
relationship between positions and rates.
And it happens, you've done this,
high school physics problems.
Bouncing balls,
perfectly elastic bouncing ball, right?
The total energy has to be preserved.
It's a conservative system.
So therefore, we have our
potential energy of the ball, and
we have the kinetic energy.
And as you're up,
you have a lot of potential energy.
No kinetic energy.
Let go, it trades potential energy for
kinetic energies, but
the sum has to be the same.
Potential energy always
depends on position.
Never rates.
Kinetic energy, you see the definition.
It's always ex dots, theta dots,
it's all the rate of the coordinates.
So if you're looking for a relationship,
and one of the homeworks asks you for
this in part B in particularly,
what's the relationship
between some states and rates?
Your first step shouldn't necessarily be
to try to integrate this equation once.
That might be quite hard.
The trick is you're going to look for
is the system conservative, and
if yes,
now we can look at the energy balance.
So people was talking
earlier about energy,
this is typically where I use energy
systems and I can come up with directly
in analytic, at this angle what
is my rate going to have to be?
It's good conservative.
Now in this system there's
no lateral friction.
There's nothing doing work on the system
it's just a conservative one.
And this point here is not doing work
because this point is not moving
up and down.
Work is typically force
times distance moved and
this point is not moving
in this direction.
So this force end also.
This system is conservative.
And we can use conservation.
So this part should hopefully be boring.
Very simple, mgh, right?
Or this case, y,
we have it as in terms of the angle theta.
I know what the potential
energy is of this rod.
I need the total mass of this rod,
the moment arm,
the height of the surface, I've got that.
The kinetic energy,
now remember how do I get this?
Kinetic energy, like momentum, I can break
up as the kinetic energy of the center of
mass plus the kinetic energy
about the center of mass.
For weird complicated tumbling things like
this I really recommend that approach.
Sometimes there are shortcuts with
other stuff that you can quickly do but
this is a way that's very rigorous, you
won't double count terms all of a sudden.
So the kinetic energy,
all the center of mass is mass
over 2 times the only
velocity we'll have is y dot.
And we know how to relate
y dot to theta dot right,
by using that earlier geometry
expression and differentiating.
And then here is the moment
over 2 times theta dot squared.
That's the one-half omega
transpose i omega but
put back into everything's about E3.
And it all simplifies down to
the simple scalar equation.
So we've got that.
So you plug in that kinematic
relation between y dot and
theta theta dot simplify.
This is what you end up with.
So you do something very similar
in the homework to this.
So now we have kinetic energy and
potential energy and
if you sum the two up, I'm seeing
initially this rod is standing up,
and yes, something has to disturb it but
the disturb it's been
treating us infinitesimal.
So the total energy is basically
just the initial potential.
And then something turns it ever so
slightly and it will start to slip, right?
And so the initial one is this.
And then we want to look at what is
the relationship at a later time so now
we know at a later time we plug in this
plus this has to always be equal to this.
This is the total energy system.
So no matter how far you slipped
of whatever angle you're at,
I can come up with a relationship.
And in fact, solve for the theta
dot which we do here analytically.
So energy's become very powerful
expressions that we can use in these
systems to actually predict some great
relationships to states as well.
If you looked at the prior
differential equations,
I would challenge anybody
to just glance at this.
And then predict that this is how
states and rates have to relate.
It's not intuitive,
that's why we have these principles,
these mathematical processes
in there in place, to do that.
So anyway that kind of wraps that one up.
Any questions on this example?
So when you solve this equations,
and there's a few in the homework,
if you want to look for h dot equal to l,
but apply it about points that make sense.
Either center of mass,
that's often a very good place to start.
Or you might find that
inertial point as well.
And that might,
both of those equations might give
you all the information you need.
The other one that we have is
F = m a of the center of mass,
that's the super particle theorem.
Between the combinations of that you
should always get all the states,
everything that you need.
If you have multiple kinematic states,
it's only one degree of freedom look for
the geometric relationship.
How does theta relate to y or z or
whatever you introduced, all right?
And if the statement is somehow
relates states to rates
immediately think energies.
Look for the system most likely
to system is conservative.
And that allows you to exploit
conservation of energy in some way and
come up with these relationships, okay?
Good, so that's good stop, not,
well for that topic that ends there.
We've got two minutes, that's good.
Well let's do a quick thought experiment.
So now what we'll move next
into is torque free motion.
Daniel already mentioned earlier that if
its torque free motion certain special
things happen.
And in fact,
spacecraft once deployed from a rocket,
the initial stage is always
tumbling in one way or a manner.
And then you have to recover,
maybe we use magnetic torque bars or
we use thrusters or
reaction wheels, or something.
And we want to go positive.
Or these all these different challenges.
And even otherwise, you don't have
a situation typically where you're
continuously controlling attitude
because you just run out of resources,
even with reaction that
only use electrical energy.
It's a lot of effort.
You try to exploit as much you
can the natural dynamics, and
the natural dynamics is no torque,
it's just there.
So can we come up with
spacecraft that spin?
And people do that quite often.
They spin stabilize a single rigid body.
Or we'll be looking at dual spinners that
means we have multiple parts that spin,
but without any feedback.
And then multiple parts that's basically
a stepping stone into reaction wheels,
momentum exchange devices,
which we'll derive afterwards and
stay up there as well.
So that's kind of the motivation for why
do we want to look at torque free motions?
Really a classic problem, even with three
axis control these days you still want to
understand the different modes.
Why are some motions stable?
Why are some motion unstable?
And one of the equilibria spin conditions.
And if I put it in a particular spin,
will it just stay there or
will it wobble out of that spin and
go and get in the way?
And one way we can investigate that
ends up being angular momentum.
The angular momentum vector H of a rigid
body, we know if it's torque-free, H dot
has to be equal to 0 which immediately
gives us a constraint equation.
But this first cut at it though
is very complicated because
if I do everything in the inertia frame,
I will get three components.
They all have to ce zero.
That's great but your momentum in
the body frame, if I have a principal
coordinate frame, is simply i 1 omega 1,
i 2 omega 2, i 3 omega 3, right?
We mentioned principal coordinate frame
that inertia tension that's just diagonal.
So it becomes a very simple product.
h is equal to i omega.
But then we have to map this
into the inertial frame.
And here I'm using [INAUDIBLE] in
terms of three to one Euler angles.
And immediately,
you get all these relationships.
But you can see there's tons of sines and
cosines and omegas and
everything varies with time.
And true, that's a constraint, but
it's very had to wrap your brain around
that and get some analytic insight.
So next time when we start off
we're going to start here and
I'm going to show you a different approach
which leads to the pole hold methods.
Those of you who have taken 3200 have
seen a little of this stuff already.
But it's a classic approach in
how we can discuss stability, but
we'll take it all a step
further then from that as well.