[music]
Where are we in the course?
Well we've seen some stuff about
anti-differentation, alright.
We learned how to start with a function,
and
find a function whose derivative is that
original function.
We've also had the sudden change of pace,
where we looked at integrals.
We looked at areas under the curves.
And now, I want to take those
two seemingly unrelated topics and connect
them together.
That's what the fundamental theorem of
calculus is, is going to do for us.
Alright, the fundamental theorem of
calculus, tells us
that evaluating integrals really amounts
to finding anti-derivatives.
These two seemingly unrelated concepts of
differentiation, and integration are
really related.
And this is really key insight of calculus
as a whole.
I mean think about it, in what sense did
Newton and Leibniz discover calculus.
Greek mathematics had these ideas right,
Greek mathematicians
were calculating areas of curved objects
by taking limits.
I have formulas for the areas of circles.
And the idea is of slope, okay, predate
Newton and Livenets.
So, what was the insight that, that means
that we credit Newton and Leibniz with
discovering calculus?
What really amounts to the fundamental
theorem of calculus?
It amounts to this idea that,
differentiation and integration are
somehow related.
By thinking systematically and precisely,
about
how a function changes when you wiggle
its input, and in particular, thinking
about a derivative of the accumulation
function.
Alright, we're able to see this, this
relationship between
evaluating a definite integral, and
finding an AI derivative.
And I want to do more now, than, than just
show
you how to calculate integrals, by using
the fundamental theorem of calculus.
That will be a big thing too, just the
process of computing.
But I hope, that you'll understand some of
the
reasons why, the fundamental theorem of
calculus is true.
So, I want to look at the fundamental
theorem
of calculus just from a lot of different
perspectives.
Alright, we should come on away from this,
not just with the ability to compute,
but also the ability to really communicate
sort
of an understanding, of this absolutely
amazing theorem.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]