[MUSIC].
We've seen that we can use either
horizontal strips or vertical strips when
using integrals to calculate area.
We end up computing the same number, the
area of this region, whether we use
vertical rectangles or horizontal
rectangles, we're getting the same
answer, the area of this region.
But if both work, which one should we
choose?
The best choice depends on the shape of
the region.
I like to think about how many different
kinds of edges my rectangles will touch.
Here is an example to demonstrate what I
mean.
I've drawn some region in here with three
edges, this curved edge, this curved
edge, and this straight edge along the x
axis.
Now, I could calculate the area of the
enclosed region.
Either by decomposing this into vertical
strips or horizontal strips.
The bad news about vertical strips is
that there's two different kinds of
vertical strips.
There's vertical strips over here, and
there's vertical strips over here.
The vertical strips over here touch the
orange and the purple edge, and the
vertical strips over here would touch the
orange and the blue edge.
Contrast that with the much better
situation that happens if I cut this up
into horizontal strips.
All of my horizontal strips have an
orange side and a blue side.
I only have one type of horizontal strip.
So I should calculate the area of a
region like this using horizontal strips.
Let's take this advice and apply it to
solve a specific problem.
So here's a bigger, specific version of
this problem.
Let's figure out the area of this region.
this orange curve is the curve y equals
the square root of x, and this blue curve
is y equals the square root of 2x minus
one.
And then here I've just got the purple
line along the x-axis.
I've really got a choice as to how to
approach this.
I could do this with vertical strips.
But then I'd have to do two different
integrals.
I'd have to handle the case over here
where rectangles are touching the orange
line and the purple line.
And I'd have to do an integral over here
where my rectangles are touching the
orange line and the blue line.
It's going to be better to use horizontal
strips.
In that case, all of the rectangles are
the same kind of rectangle, they're a
rectangle with one edge on this orange
curve, and one edge on this blue curve.
Let me just draw one of those thin
horizontal rectangles.
I have to figure out the size of that
rectangle.
Let's suppose this thin strip is at
height y.
I know how tall this strip is.
I'll call that dy.
But how wide is this green strip?
I should figure out what this point and
where this point is.
And if I think about it a little bit, if
this is y, I can solve this equation and
find out that in that case x.
Is y squared, and I can similarly solve
this equation and find out that if this
point has a y coordinate y, the x
coordinate will be y squared plus 1 over
2.
And that tells me the width of this green
rectangle, it's this minus this.
I'm going to write down the area of that
green rectangle.
So the width is y squared plus 1 over 2
minus y squared, that's how wide this
rectangle is.
And the height of that rectangle is dy,
so this product is the area of that green
rectangle.
But of course I don't care just about
that one rectangle, I want to integrate
so that I'm adding up the areas of all
kinds of thin rectangles.
And then in the limit I'm getting the
area of this region exactly.
So instead of just this single rectangle,
I'm going to integrate y goes from where
to where.
Well, I look at my picture here, y can be
as small as zero and as tall as this
point up here which is one.
So y goes from zero to one and this
interval calculates the area of that
region.
Let's do the calculation.
This integral is the integral from 0 to
1.
for I can simplify the integrand a bit.
It's 1 half minus y squared over 2 dy .
And now we can write an antiderivative
for that.
So I add a derivative of 1 half.
One half y and a derivative of y squared
over 2 is y cubed over 6.
I'm going to evaluate that at 0 and 1,
take a difference.
But when I plug in 0 I just get 0.
So the answer is whatever I get when I
plug in 1.
And that's 1 half times 1, minus 1 cubed
over 6.
Could simplify that a bit, that's 1 half
minus a 6th, and 1 half, well, that's 3
6ths, so 3 6ths minus 1 6th, is 2 6ths,
which you might write as, 1 3rd.
So the area of that, shark fin shaped
region is a third of a square unit.
Often, it's not there are right ways or
wrong ways but there are better ways and
worse ways, right.
Ways that are better in that they are
quicker, safer, more elegant.
So don't just make good choices.
Make the best choices.