[MUSIC].
In a 27 kilometer long tunnel buried
deep underground at the CERN laboratory,
the seven story high ATLAS detector
is designed to enable scientists to
study the conditions
of the early universe.
In this episode,
we will see how ATLAS works.
The detector consists of many components.
These are needed to measure the different
types of particles produced in
the collision which then
pass through ATLAS.
[MUSIC]
The intersections measure
the tracks of charged particles,
which are bent by the magnetic field of
a thin superconducting solenoidal magnet.
Outside of all of these
are two calorimeter devices,
measuring the energies of particles.
[MUSIC]
Finally, the muon spectrometer
measures the tracks of muons,
which are bent in the field of
the superconducting toroidal magnets.
[MUSIC]
Here's how ATLAS detects
different types of particles.
An electron will plow through the inner
detector, leaving a track behind
before finally stopping in
the electromagnetic calorimeter.
A photon behaves in a similar way,
but leaves no track.
A proton leaves a track and interacts
primarily in the hadronic calorimeter.
[MUSIC]
A neutron behaves in a similar way,
but leaves no track.
[MUSIC]
A muon passes all the way through ATLAS,
leaving tracks behind.
[MUSIC]
Finally, a neutrino passes through
ATLAS without being detected at all.
[MUSIC]
Billions of subatomic particles called
protons advance towards each other from
opposite directions at
almost the speed of light.
[SOUND] As two protons collide,
hundreds of new
particles are formed from
the energy of the collision.
These collisions occur
a billion times a second.
[MUSIC]