[MUSIC] Here I've graphed some function.
Notice what happens if I zoom in on one
little piece of the graph,
right?
If I just focus on one part of the graph,
well, that little bit of graph sort of
looks like part of a straight line.
Another way to think about this is as a
limit of secant lines.
By secant line, I mean, I'm going to pick
two points on the graph and I'm going to
put a line, the secant line, through
those two points.
But, I can do better.
By taking this point and moving it closer
to a, this red line is going to be a
better approximation to the orange curve
near the point a.
So, instead of putting it through those
two points, let me put the secant line
through, say, these two points, this
point at a and this point that's nearby.
And now, the line segment through those
two points is a much better approximation
of the orange curve.
And I can do better and better by taking
a limit, by putting those two points
closer and closer together, I can get my
secant line to be a better and better
approximation to the orange curve near
the point a.
What we're really calculating here is a
limit.
So here, I've got an input a and an input
a+h, and here are the corresponding
points on the graph of the function.
I'm going to put a secant line through
those points.
What I want to know is what's the slope
of that secant line because I'm going to
take the limit as this a+h point is moved
closer to a as h goes to zero in other
words, and that'll make this secant line
move closer and closer to the tangent
line,
to the curve.
Okay, so what's the slope of the secant
line?
Well, the rise is f(a)+h-f(a).
The run is h.
So, the slope of that secant line is
this, f(a+h)-f(a)/h.
If I take the limit as h goes to 0, I get
this: the limit as h goes to 0 of this
slope.
We've seen this, this is the derivative
of the function at the point a.
Let's find the equation of the tangent
line in a concrete example.
Here's a graph of y=x^2.
Let's figure out the equation of the
tangent line to that graph at the point
(3,9).
So to do that, we're going to use the
derivative and I know that the derivative
of x^2 is 2x.
So, the slope of the tangent line at the
point 3 is 2*3=6,
and that's the slope of the tangent line.
I also know a point that the tangent line
passes through.
It should be passing through the point
(3,9), right? The point (3,9) is on the
tangent line.
So, if I know the slope of the tangent
line and I know a point on the line, I
can write down an equation for the line
using point slope form.
So, y minus the y coordinate on the line
is the slope time x minus the x
coordinate on the line.
So, this is an equation for this red
tangent line.
[MUSIC]