[MUSIC]
Now that we know what data management is,
and who the people involved are,
we will now show you where specific
data management practices fall within
the research lifecycle.
To do this, we're going to use
the research lifecycle from
the Data Documentation Initiative, or DDI.
During the initial phase of the research
lifecycle, that is the discovery and
planning phase, researchers will
need to determine what type and
format of data they are going to collect.
This may involve collecting new data,
combining existing data sets or
analyzing existing data.
If the project involves human subjects,
the researches will need to consider
privacy, confidentiality,
and other ethical issues.
In addition, researchers should consider
what types of documentation they will
create and the metadata standards
they will use to describe their data.
These are some of the details that should
be included in the data management plan.
Further, researchers will need to identify
the potential reusers of the project data.
Who will use this data?
What might they use it for?
Will the data, once stripped of any
potentially identifying information,
be useful for secondary reuse?
What access restrictions
will be placed on the data?
These are all questions that
the researchers need to answer
before the project even begins.
Contacting an information professional
early in the research life cycle can
assist researchers in
answering these questions.
As well as identifying appropriate data
repository, to archive their data.
Finally, during this phase,
it is important for
researchers to determine the possible
costs surrounding data management.
This will involve documenting the data,
formatting them,
storing them, cleaning and anonymizing
them, and finally archiving them.
During the data collection phase,
primary researchers make certain that
the research team follows data
management best practices.
At this point, this can include
file organization, backup and
storage strategies,
as well as quality assurance protocols.
Deciding on file organization schemes
including naming conventions and
file versioning policies
at the very beginning
will help make the data
collection process run smoothly.
This will decrease
the likelihood of duplicate or
out-of-sync versions of the data.
You will also make locating
specific documents and files
at the end of the project much easier and
decrease the risk of losing content.
Backup and
storage strategies will be implemented
through the data collection process.
As we know,
technology is not always a 100% reliable.
If a researcher has appropriate backup and
storage strategies in place,
this will help protect against data
loss from the beginning of the project.
It is best to discuss options for
secure backup and
storage with the institution's
IT department.
Quality assurance protocols outline and
document the steps and processes
necessary for checking and reviewing
the data during and after it is collected.
These protocols vary
across disciplines and
it is the responsibility of
the primary researcher and
the project team to implement these
protocols based on disciplinary standards.
It is also a good idea to
consider access controls and
data security during this
phase of the lifecycle.
While working with the IT department,
make sure to inform them of any
security concerns or needs.
If the data is sensitive then the
appropriate steps will need to be taken to
ensure that they are safely stored and
only accessible to authorized individuals.
Next is the preparation and
data analysis phase.
After collecting data, it may not be
in a form that can be readily analyzed.
Researchers may need to clean,
manipulate or process the raw data.
What is important at this point is
documenting the changes to the raw data
and creating a master version to be
analyzed and eventually archived.
A common tip here is to make the final
version of the data read-only.
So it can't be inadvertently altered.
Once the master version of the data has
been prepared, data analysis can begin.
Data analysis can take many
forms across disciplines.
The most important thing to consider in
this phase is making sure to document
analysis procedures such as additional
modifications to the data, the model used,
the code used to run the analysis, and
hardware and software specifications.
Having this detailed information will
help researchers write a better paper and
do better science.
During the publication and sharing phase,
a researcher will prepare their data
files and other research materials
necessary to interpret and
reuse the data in the future.
Data management best practices
dictate that data be stored and
made available to share in
a trustworthy data repository.
This phase is an opportunity to consult
with information professionals or
data repository staff.
Who can provide guidance as
you prepare data for sharing.
Researchers should make sure that their
data management meets all of the needs and
requirements of the repository.
This means that the data should be
in the appropriate file format,
should be cleaned to the specifications
of the repository, and
to comply with applicable privacy laws and
requirements.
Additionally, all documentation
should be reviewed
to ensure that the data can be reused and
standard metadata should be applied.
By working with a data repository,
researchers can ensure that data
will be properly preserved.
Discoverable, and usable in the future.
The end of the project can seem like
a bit of a blur and a time crunch.
But by following data management best
practices throughout the research life
cycle, you can rest assured that your
data will be available for the long term.
At this point your data are safely
stored in a data repository.
And you can begin planning for
your next project.
Some key repository functions got
ensure the long term management of data
include ensuring
the integrity of the data.
Protecting against data loss.
And providing access to data.
These and other functions
performed by trusted repositories
will be discussed in more
depth later in this course.
We covered a lot of data management
topics in this module, but
what is most important to take away
is that effective data management
takes places in all phases
of the research lifecycle.
From planning a project,
to collecting your data, to comparing and
analyzing your data, and then finally
publishing and sharing your data in
a repository that will see to their
long-term management and preservation.
[MUSIC]