[MUSIC]
In this video we will give you a few hints
on how to construct a Feynman diagram
for the two-body process a+b -> c+d.
We first have to decide wether this can be
an annihilation process in which the two initial state particles
annihilate into a gauge boson.
In that case the momentum transfer will be equal
to the total energy-momentum.
If they cannot annihilate, they have to
exchange a gauge boson in a scattering process.
In this case the q^2 is equal to the difference between
the final particle momentum and the initial particle momentum.
Now we must decide, which gauge boson can be exchanged.
First of all we have to remember that at each vertex
quantum numbers are strictly conserved.
First of all baryon and lepton numbers must be conserved,
and, if we are not talking about weak interactions,
also the particle flavor.
Then we must consider the charge at each vertex.
If the electric charge is not 0 and it does not change at the vertex,
we can exchange a photon.
If the particle’s weak isospin is not 0 and the charge does not change,
we can exchange a Z. If the charge does change
by ±1 unit, we can exchange a W±.
Finally, if the color is not 0 and it changes at the vertex,
we can exchange a gluon.
So here is a first example,
the process e+e- -> u ubar.
We clearly cannot couple the electron directly to a u quark
so this is an annihilation process in which the
e+ e- annihilate into a u bar pair.
This can proceed via the exchange of a photon
or a Z, since both the electron
and the u quark carry both electric
and weak isospin charge.
It cannot go via the exchange of a gluon or a W
because the e+ e- does not carry color
and the charge does not change
at the vertex.
A second example is the process e+ e- -> nu unbar.
Unless the neutrinos are electron-type neutrinos,
this is again an annihilation process.
It proceeds via the exchange of a Z boson.
It cannot proceed via photon exchange, because
the neutrino does not carry electric charge.
Neither the electron nor the neutrino are colored,
so gluons cannot be exchanged.
The electric charge is not changing at the vertex, so
W± exchange is also excluded. The third
example is the process e- u -> nu_e d.
In this case it must be a scattering process,
since the e- cannot directly couple to the u quark.
They must in fact exchange a W boson
since the charge changes by 1 unit at each vertex.
This is possible because both the e- and the u quark
carry weak isospin.
They cannot exchange a photon since the charge changes
neither can they exchange a Z. And since the e- and the nu do not
carry color, they cannot exchange a gluon either.
The next example is the decay of a d quark into a u
e- and an electron-antineutrino. To conserve baryon and lepton
number we must connect the d quark to the u quark and the
electron to the antineutrino.
This means that at each vertex, the charge changes by 1 unit
and we can exchange a W boson. We cannot exchange a photon
because the charge changes, likewise we cannot exchange a Z.
And since the e- and the nu don’t carry color
we cannot exchange a gluon.
The last example is a red d quark scattering off a blue d quark,
giving a blue u quark and a red d quark.
This is clearly a strong process since it involves color exchange.
Since strong interactions conserve flavor,
we must connect the two u quarks and also the two d quarks.
That means that the two
vertices are connected by a gluon
of red-antiblue color
such that the color is conserved at each vertex.
We cannot exchange a photon since
the color changes, neither a Z or a W bosons
since all of these cannot change the color of a particle.
[MUSIC]