[SOUND].
Hi, welcome to Lesson 1 of Creative
Programming for Digital Media and Mobile
Apps.
I'm Mick, and this is Matt and Marco.
And we're going to take you through six
individual lessons starting with this
week, which is all about the basics of
drawing and the basics of sound.
So, first of all, we need to know how to
manipulate graphics and draw them to the
screen and we also need to know how
images are represented on the screen.
Marco is going to take you through that,
and he's also going to give you a
introduction on how to use processing for
making desktop applications.
Matt's going to take you through how to
control sound and how to find and play
back sounds from the internet.
He's also going to talk a little bit
about manipulating sound, and how sound
is represented in the computer.
In addition, he's going to show you a
little about how to run applications that
we develop on Android phones.
And then, I'm going to take you through
the basics of using Apple devices.
And after that, I'm going to show you how
to make a basic app with simple
interactions, like mouse and touch
interaction.
That plays back different sounds in
different ways.
And also changes the way that certain
types of images are drawn.
So, that's really what this lesson is
about.
It's kind of easing you in to the whole
idea of making creative applications.
And if you've got any questions, you can
check the forums.
We'll be looking out for any of you who
have particular issues.
It's always a bit difficult getting
started running software for the first
time.
So, we've got a whole load of examples
that you can download from the Coursera
website.
We're going to be referring to them
throughout the next six weeks starting
this week.
So, make sure that before you ask
questions, you have a look on the
documentation that we've put on the
website.
There's a lot there.
There are also people who are going to be
on the forums, expecting you to ask good,
relevant questions.
And hopefully, if you are stuck, then
we'll be able to sort that out.
So I think we're going to start off with
Marco.
I think he's going to do some graphics,
and then move on to Matt, and then I'll
be seeing you later on.
[MUSIC].