[MUSIC].
For this course, we'll be using a
programming environment called
Processing, developed at MIT.
It's a fantastic environment to learn to
program in, but in particular it's a
fantastic environment in which to create
a program in, because it makes it very
simple from the very beginning to do
highly graphical, audio-based, and
interactive software.
This is the Processing window in which
you run the Processing program.
The first thing you'll notice is there's
a nice Play button.
If we hit Play, we get a program.
It's not a very instant program, it's a
very small window and it doesn't really
do anything.
That's not surprising, we haven't written
anything to put in the code.
This main editor window is where we write
codes and I'm going to give an example of
some codes that you might want to write.
So I'm going to Set the size of the
screen with two numbers and set the
background color.
I'll come back later to exactly what
these things mean.
But for now we need to know that we've
changed the size of the screen, made it
bigger.
And we've gone and changed the background
to red.
Over the next couple of weeks, we'll be
looking at some much more complicated
programs that really use the full power
of processing, but for now, I wanted to
show you how to write a very simple
program.
An important part of this course is that
it's not just about writing processing
programs for the desktop, but processing
can be used on mobile devices, android
devices, iOS devices, and on the Web.
And in a minute, Mathew and Mick are
going to show you how to do that.
And Mick is going to go through a more
complex example that we're going to
explain throughout the course of this
weeks lecture.
The last thing I want to say is that if
you're used to programming and have had
some experience in Java you'll find
processing very familiar because it's
based on Java.
But even if you have programmed before in
say JavaScript or PHP it won't be too
hard to learn.
If you've never done any programming
before don't worry.
But have a look at some of the additional
lectures I've posted that will introduce
programming from the very beginning
[MUSIC].