[SOUND].
So today I'm going to introduce the
basics of how to write computer programs
that draw pictures and that you can
interact with.
The first thing you need to do when you
want to write, draw an image with a
computer program is turn your image into
a set of numbers.
Because at a certain level, numbers are
what computers understand.
If you think about a computer screen,
it's composed of millions of pixels.
These are picture elements.
These are tiny little squares, each of
which has their own color.
And you can think of the screen as a
large grid of pixels.
As you can see on my slides here.
The first thing you need to know when
you're drawing something to screen is
which particular pixel you're drawing to
or collection of pixels, and you need to
be able to express that as a number.
So, how do we do that?
The first thing we do is we have a number
that represents how many pixels across
you are.
That's the horizontal position or what we
call the x value.
We also need to know how many pixels down
you are.
The vertical position or y value.
These two numbers give us a position of a
pixel.
For example 8, 6 gives us this pixel here
shown in red.
So, with two numbers we can get a single
pixel value.
So let's have a look at that in practical
program.
So this is the program, I showed you
earlier.
We've got the size.
We've got the background, and we can draw
a point at a certain position.
Say 100, 100.
Now you probably cant even see the point,
it's actually here, if you see my mouse
position where I'm clicking.
Why cant you see it?
Because pixels are tiny, let's do
something else before we proceed and make
the point a little bit bigger.
We use this command called stroke weight.
Which gives you the width of lines you
draw or the size of the points.
Now set that to six and we're going to
get something a little bit bigger.
And there we go we can clearly see a
single point on the screen.
Now, creating images out of individual
points is going to be hard work.
So, let's look at how to make some more
basic shapes.
Okay, so here we have our pixel of
position 8, 6, with another point given
by another two numbers, say, 4, 3.
We can draw a line.
So, with four numbers, x and y at the
start position, and the x and y of the n
position, we can draw a line.
Similarly with another full numbers we
can go further and draw a rectangle, and
the only difference being that the first
two positions are the top left position
of the rectangle and the other two
numbers are not a position on the
rectangle, they are the height and width.
So let's have another look at trying to
draw more complex...
If, instead here, of point, we use the
command line, we can draw a line to 200,
300 and see what that looks like.
There we have a line.
Similarly, the rect command gives us a
rectangle.
And here instead of a, the end position
of the line for the second two points,
it's the height and width of the
rectangle.
So I'm making a square, which has equal
height and width.
So there we are.
Let's have a quick look at what I've just
done.
So here we are, these are two commands
I've written.
Size commands.
What is the size command?
I showed that in my introduction lecture
to processing, but I didn't really talk
about it.
Well, in size, you're passing in 2
numbers.
The first number is the x, is the width,
of the processing window you're creating.
The second number is the height, the y
value.
Similarly with a line The first number is
the x position, the horizontal position
is the start point.
Then the hot vertical position, the y
position is, is the start point, and then
the x and y positions of the end point of
the line.
So very simple, with four numbers, you
can draw a line.
And from there, you can get Many more
complex shapes.
The next thing you might want to look at
is colors.
So up to now we've been drawing black
lines.
How do we represent color as numbers?
Well, if we start with black and white.
The color coming off a computer monitor
is really the amount of light that is
being emitted by each pixel on the
screen.
So we can think of the brightness of the
of a particular pixel, as being a value
that we can measure.
and we can measure that brightness at
some maximum value, which is white and 0,
which is no color coming off, which is
black.
And if you look here, 0 is black.
And then we can use the value 255 as
why?.
Why 255?
Well, that happens to be the largest
value you can fit in 8 bits.
So 8 ones and 0s on, in computer memory.
Any value in between those two will give
you gray lighter, or darker gray.
So you can have shay, any shades or
variations of gray value between those
two values.
Fine, that's brightness, but what about
real color?
Well, when to talk about colors, we need
to think about primary colors, and if
you.
At a very young age at school, you will
have learned that you can make any color
by mixing three colors of paint together.
We're not actually working with paint.
We're working with light, and that's
slightly different.
The primary colors are different, but the
concept is same, and the primary colors
we have are green, blue and red.
And any color can be made up with these
three, three basic colors.
Why is that?
It's not a fundamental property of light,
but it's a fundamental property of our
eye.
we have three types of receptor in our
eye, that are sensitive to green, red,
and blue parts of the spectrum.
And, if the light comes between those
colors, it will trigger.
a mixture of say, the red and green
components receptors on our eye.
Therefore we can fool our eye by, instead
of having a color that's between green
and red, sending both green and red at
the same time will look like a mix of
green and red, which is yellow.
Similarly, green and blue is cyan Red and
blue is magenta, and any other color can
be mixed from those basic primary colors.
That's great from a computer graphics
point of view, because we only need three
numbers to represent any color, a red
value, a green value and a blue value.
So how do we use colors?
Well, there's a number of ways in which
you can use colors.
If we look here we've got a basic
rectangle and what can we change about
that rectangle?
Well, the first that we can change about
the rectangle is the border of the
rectangle and we use the stroke commands.
Stroke means the color of the line that
we use to draw lines on screen.
We can also change the center of the
rectangle using the fill command.
Fill is the color that is used to draw
the center of any shape, the middle of
any shape, that we're drawing on screen.
We've already seen the background
command, and I'll show you that again
which has the, changes the background
color of the screen.
The last command that I've already shown
you that is connected is stroke weight
that doesn't specify color, but it
specifies the width of any lines you're
drawing on the screen.
So let's have a look at that in code.
So we've already used background, and we
can see here that we've used backgrounds
25500, so that's 255 red, 0 green, 0
blue.
And as we see, that came out as a bright
red.
If we were to change that to 255 zero,
150, we would mix a little blue in and
we'd get a different colot.
Sort of more purpley color.
Let's try changing these, the colors of
this rectangle, so if we use stroke, we
can set the color of the border of the
rectangle, let's set it to a bright
green.
Sorry, just made a mistake there.
And we can use fill to set the sensor
color.
maybe we can use a light blue.
We mix in light blue by having quite a
lot of red and green.
So it's quite bright.
There's a lot of whiteness in there, but
more blue.
And there we go quite a light blue, we
could make it bluer by turning down the
red and green.
So that's, we've got some quite garish
colors here.
I wouldn't actually make an application
with these colors, but it shows you sort
of how you can mix, mix some basic
colors.
The one last thing I want to show you is
that once you'll called stroke and fill,
those values continue for everything else
you draw, so if I draw another rectangle
eh, then they will be the same colors.
So by putting in a second fill command, I
can change the color of my second vector.
Okay, there's one last thing I'd like to
say about color, which is to talk about
transparency.
Sometimes when you're specifying colors
as well as red, green, and blue, you'll
get a fourth number.
This is the opacity.
Often called alpha.
Opacity controls how transparent
something is.
It's actually the opposite of
transparency.
So when The opacity is 255, it means it's
not transparent at all, and when it's 0,
it's completely transparent.
So, to get colors which are partially
transparent, you need an alpha value
between 0 and 255.
So, for example, 255, 0, 0, 128 is half
transparent red.
And we can see this in code here, by
setting the alpha of this rectangle to
128, and move it slightly so that it
overlaps the original, the original
rectangle.
we don't want it to completely overlap.
And you can see it is partially
transparent.
Its color is affecting what's beneath it,
but not completely.
And Mick will show you some nice examples
of how you can use transparency to get
some really nice visual effects.
So, with what I've shown you so far, you
can make some nice drawings.
With computer codes, and that's cool as
far as it goes.
But it's not really a computer program
yet because all it's doing is drawing a
picture.
When you think of a computer program you
want to interact with it.
It has to do things independently.
So if we look at what our program is
doing up to now.
We're pressing play, it's running its
code.
And when it finish, it will draw a
picture and we can look at it.
But that's not how we, you complete a
program 1, we want to be able to interact
with that code.
so we can do this by splitting a code
into news and number bit.
First off, we we have some stuff that
should never change.
For example, the size of the screen, the
background color.
They should always stay.
[INAUDIBLE] And that's what we call the
setup part of our program.
And then there's stuff that should
change, so for example, the things that
we're drawing, like the lines, they
should move around based on what we're
doing.
That's the drawing part of our program.
And we put them in two different blocks
of code.
The first one we put in a block of code
called setup I won't get into full
details of what everything means here.
If you're familiar with Java, you will
understand it.
If not, look at some of my additional
lectures.
But void setup is what's called a
function, and that contains all the code
that we do at the beginning of the
program and it happens only once.
The important thing to note here are
these curly brackets.
They say they tell you where the start
and end of the setup code is.
Similarly, we can have functions which
happen times the response to certain
events.
So for example, I can have alpha function
mouseDragged.
What mouseDragged does is that it happens
every time you move the mouse while the
mouse button is held hold down.
A very useful function for interaction.
So what happens now is I move the mouse,
I give some input, mouse drag responds
and I play and then it paints a picture
and I can see that.
That's fine, but if you look at the code
as it is now, every time I call mouse
dragged, it's drawing the same line
because the numbers in there aren't
changing.
I need to put in different numbers to my
line in order to change the interaction
I'm getting and make it truly
interactive, to make it respond to my
mouse movements.
And this is how I can do it.
Rather than putting a number in there,
I'm putting in The value mouse x mouse y
pmouse x pmouse y.
Now what are these things.
Well these are variables their names
stand for numbers if you're not familiar
with the term variable.
But if you're not then you should look at
my additional lectures.
And mouse x and mouse y are automatically
set to the current position of the mouse.
So this is your mouse position as an x
and y value.
pmouse and X and pmouseY are useful
values.
They give you the previous position of
the mouse and that's what enables us to
do some, some smooth drawing.
I'll show you that in a minute.
So let's look at some code that does
this.
So this is about the most basic
interactive code you can get in
processing.
We have a setup function that sets the
size of the screen and the background
color, and a mouse drag function that
draws a point that the position is the
mouse.
So let's see what that does.
We've got a nice little drawing.
That's nice, but, when I draw, I'd like
to actually sort of draw continuous
lines, and we can do that with the code I
just showed you, because we can draw a
line from the previous mouse position to
the current mouse position.
[NOISE] And there we are, some nice
continuous lines drawn.
Now, we've got a nice bit of interaction
but it doesn't look great, there's a lot
we can do with this aesthetically to
make.
In a few minutes we'll talk to you about
that.
but for now, that's most of want to say,
what, what I'm going to say.
I just want to show you one little trick.
about the background function.
So at the moment it's not.
Every time I draw, it's drawing on top of
what I've already drawn.
And sometimes that's what we want.
Sometimes what, that's what we don't.
not what we want.
If I move the function background into
mouse dragged as well as setting the
background color what background does is
it clears the screen.
So if I move it into mouse dragged it's,
it's clearing the screen so I've no
longer accumulated all the drawings I've
ever done.
And I just get this tiny little try off
the mouse.
Maybe not exactly what we want now.
But there's lots of situations where it
is exactly what we want.
And next week we'll show you that in
detail.
So, so far what we've got is the ability
to draw some basic energies to screen.
Some basic shapes and interact with that
by responding to mouse position.
There's a lot more we, you can do while
you're drawing, and I would recommend
that you look at the the processing
website, processing.org.
There's a link to it from the from our
our call server site, and particularly
look at the processing reference and look
at some of the examples for shapes.
A good example is to look at the ellipse
command So far we've looked at lines, and
rectangles.
Ellipse shows you how to draw ellipses,
and circles, and, and with that, that's
already part of your repertoire, but it
will already, it will also start you
learning how to use the reference for,
for processing, and pick up, and use new
commands that will enable you to do more
complex drawing.
So I'll leave you here and Matthew will
talk a bit about how to do audio
processing in processing and then Mick
will show you more complex examples using
the basis, basic code that we've learned
here...
[MUSIC]