[SOUND].
Okay, so one of the first things we have
to learn how to do is to run applications
on mobile devices.
now Matt will have already shown you how
to run stuff on Android, and Marco will
have shown you how to run stuff off the
desktop.
I'm going to show you how you can run the
same application, using our code that
we've prepared for you, in the download
pack which is off, which is from
Coursera.
So that you can do exactly the same code,
write the same code, and have it run on
all three devices, specifically on, on
iOS device.
Now, crucially, the way we're doing this
as part of this program, is we're running
all of the iOS-specific code as
JavaScript.
So, when you finish making your
application, you press Go and it builds a
webpage specifically for our iOS mobile
device.
There's a couple of little tricky things
that we need to get right the first time
we do it, and I'm going to talk you
through those right now.
But firstly, we start with a
straightforward sketch.
Now, I'm going to use a sketch that
we're, we're going to talk about later on
in lesson one, called Sonic Painter.
And this is just a basic I'll sketch.
It also runs on the desktop, and it also
runs on Android in exactly the same way.
So, I'm going to start by creating a
running version on my desktop, so you can
see.
Just to give you a, a reminder of how
that works.
But we're using JavaScript.
So, I'm just hovering over with the
mouse, over the little bit that says
JavaScript.
When you click in the top right,
right-hand corner of the processing IDE,
you can see it says Java, Andriod,
Javascript, Experimental.
I don't really know what Experimental
means.
We're not going to try it out today.
But we're going to try the JavaScript
version.
When you run it, when you press this Play
icon as Mark already shown you, it
launches your web browser.
And I think we're recommending you use
Google Chrome for this.
Now, you should be able to hear, [SOUND].
And see the app.
And that's the app we're going to look at
later on in more detail.
But crucially, what we need to know is
what the web address is.
Now, before you start, you need to make
sure that you're on the same wireless
network as your desktop on your iOS
device.
Most people do this all the time.
When you're in your house, you've got one
wireless network.
And you connect your computer to that
wireless network and you also connect all
your devices to the same network.
But you really need to do that, because
if you don't do that, development can be
a bit tricky to get started with.
Okay?
So, I recommend you do that first.
If you haven't done that, do it now.
So, the next thing we need to know is,
what the IP address of this desktop is,
because the desktop is actually serving
the app at the moment.
Later on in the course, you'll be serving
the app from a web server, and even
storing it locally on your device.
I'll show you how to do that in a moment,
but for now, we really need to know the
IP address.
Now, on a Windows machine you can do this
by going to the command line terminal and
typing IP config, and it will give you
the IP address of your advice.
On a Macintosh device, we can do the same
thing.
We can go to a terminal.
If I type ifconfig, it gives me a list,
and you should be able to see that now,
it gives me a list of what looks like
ridiculous numbers.
But there's a number here, inet
192.168.0.108, that's the IP address of
this machine on this network.
I've got an iPad here.
I'm going to launch Safari.
And I'm going to go to the IP address.
Http://192.168.0.108.
Now, that's not enough, we also need a
colon, and the port number.
The port number here is 55523, I know
this all seems like crazy garbage, but
it, I promise you, is nearly over.
Here you go, and it's gone straight to
the Solid Painter app.
And once it's loaded in, [SOUND], there
you go.
It's running on my iOS device.
Simple as that.
It's running over the network.
Really simple.
And now, I can continue to edit that app
live and just refresh this page.
So, I can change an aspect of it, go back
to the code type something else in, and
then refresh the page and it will then
come up.
One final thing though which is useful to
know, if you want to embed this on your
home screen whilest you're developing,
you can hit this little sharing icon and
choose add to home screen.
And if you do that, it'll actually make
it a proper bundled app.
We'll be talking more about that later on
towards the end of the course.
But that, more or less, is how you get it
running on your iOS device.
And I just want to point out that our
template, which we've prepared for you,
is downloadable from the Coursera site.
And that should look identical on a iOS
device whether it's an iPad, an iPhone 5
or an iPhone 4.