[SOUND].
[MUSIC].
Okay.
So you've done some graphics.
And now you're ready to do some sound.
So I'm going to begin by showing you how
to obtain some sounds.
[INAUDIBLE] you get get sounds from
pretty much anywhere.
for example, you can record them yourself
or you can obtain them from a website.
Freesound.org is a really useful website
for obtaining sounds.
They have a wide selection of different
sound effects, ambient sounds, and music.
What I'm going to do is, I'm going to
quickly make a sound myself by recording
it.
I'm going to use the open source audio
editing software Audacity, which you can
see here.
So, I start with an empty page, I hit
Record.
[SOUND] I get my drumstick [NOISE]
[SOUND].
So this is the bit of the sound that I'm
interested in, so I copy that.
Paste it into a new sound.
Now because, because we're operating in
mono here, we're, we're trying to keep
the audio library as simple as possible.
So we operate in mono.
So I'm going to record my sound, like
this, in stereo, but then bounce it to
mono.
So I go into the track menu, stereo track
to mono.
Now I'm ready to export.
I'm going to store it into the data
folder of the sketch.
So you'll notice when you create a sketch
like this one and save it that it puts
data folder for you.
So my sketch is called Android Start, and
you can see I have a data folder in
there.
If it's not there, when you've just saved
your sketch, you can just create it.
The data folder is for additional files
that you want to use in your sketch.
In this case, audio files.
So I'm going to save this audio file I
just recorded into the data folder of the
sketch.
[SOUND] And I'm going to call it uh,
[SOUND] ping.wav.
[SOUND] Okay.
So we've recorded our own sound.
And now we're ready to see if we can get
it to play on the mobile device.
We're going to play a sound on the mobile
device.
In order to do this, we need to write in
some, some lines of code to initialize
the audio environment.
The audio environment in this case is
called Maxin/?.
This is our custom audio library.
[SOUND] So Maxim, so I created a variable
called Maxim, which has the type Maxim.
We'll worry more about the details of
types later on in the course.
Then, I need an audio player.
Audio player, so that's the type, and
I'll call it Player.
So I've two variables ready to store
these two object which I'm now going to
create.
So maxim equals new maxim, that creates a
new, a new audio environment.
You only ever need to create a single
audio environment for your whole sketch,
and everything operates within that
single environment.
Following that, I'm going to ask maxim to
create my audio platform, player equals
maxim .LoadFile, and I pass it the name
of the file I just saved, ping.wav.
Okay?
And so, remember, ping.wav is the name of
the file you just created, and it needs
to be saved in the Data folder, so that
the, so that Maxim can see it.
because otherwise it, you can only access
files in that Data folder.
Okay, and finally, [SOUND] I'm going to
set up an event, so that when they click
on the screen or tap on the screen, they
will be able to hear the sounds.
So I'll just say player.play in there.
So let's just try this out.
So I've written my really simple sketch
here.
Let's just [UNKNOWN] go through that code
again.
We've got these two variables, one of
which is the maxim, that's the audio
environment that all of the, that deals
with all of the audio processing.
Audio player represents a single player
which can play an audio file.
[SOUND] Maxim is being created there in
the setup function, and the player has
been created, too.
When they click the mouse, this function
gets called, mouse pressed during the
case of the touch screen device when they
tap on the screen, and it will trigger
play on the player object, which will
cause the sound to play.
I'm now going to run the sketch.
Okay the sketch has launched on the
device, so I tap the screen.
[SOUND].
Okay, so you can now hear me hitting the
table, playing from my Android device.
So to exit the sketch, you need only
press the Back button.
Like that, and now it's stopped.
Now, you noticed that it kept playing the
sound.
Because the default setting for the
player is to loop the sound.
So, for example, if you put a drum beat
in there, it will loop it.
And that's really useful for drum beats.
But for for a sound effect like this you
might not want it to loop.
But before we look at that, let's just
see what it sounds like when you play a
drum beat in there.
So I've already, I've already prepared a
drum beat called mybeat.wav.
Okay.
So let's just see if we can play that on
the, the device as well.
So mybeat.wav.
So I've just changed the, the file.
Now remember that file.
Oops, that, that file needs to be in the
data folder.
As you can see it's in the data folder of
my sketch there.
So I hit play again, and it will build
the sketch again and send it over to the
device.
And then, when I hit the mouse button,
you'll be able to hear the break beat.
Okay, the device is ready.
[MUSIC] So remember because it's looping,
it's going to keep playing until you tell
it to stop.
So what've we done here?
So we've created an audio file by
recording it, but you can also obtain
audio files from this FreeSound website.
And I didn't exactly show you that.
But if you don't want to freeze out, you
can see, so you want it to find a break
beat of your own.
You can type break beat into there, into
the search box, and you'll have to create
an account before you can search and, and
download files, but you can, it's pretty
easy to do.
You just do it by clicking on the account
creation button at the top.
Okay.
So I've searched for Break Beat, and I've
been given all of these files.
And when you go into the file, you'll see
that there's a download button.
So if you want to get your own Break Beat
into there, instead of using my one you
can, you can download there.
But you will need to load into Audacity,
and exporters of monoware, as I showed
you before, with my recorded sound.
[SOUND].
So, we've, we've obtained some sounds,
and we've learned about different types
of sounds.
And, we've set up the audio assistant to
play a sound.
And, we've had a little look of what,
what looping is about.
But you can actually control the looping
properties of the, the audio player like
this.
So if I go into here, back again, I can
tell it not to loop the files, so if I go
back to my ping thing, which we didn't
want to repeat, we just wanted it to play
once, then I just do player.set looping,
and set it to false, which says don't
loop.
Just play once.
The thing is, I now need, you'll see that
plays once, if I, if I do that.
But if I wanted to play it again, I'll
need to call Queue, because that will
rewind it, back again.
So once it's played, it's like a tape
that's played to the end.
You have to rewind it again to trigger it
again.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to
play it.
And, in fact, I'm going to put it the
other way around.
So I'll queue it up to zero, then I'll
play it.
So I'm just going to run this sketch, and
we'll see what it does.
[SOUND] So it's ready.
So we're going to hit the mouse button.
[SOUND] You can hear it plays at once.
If we hit it again.
[SOUND] Can you hear it plays again?
It's not looping because I told it not
to.
[SOUND].
Next week you're going to find out more
about the details of how audio is
represented in the computer's memory.
But for now that gives you the basic
tools that you need to create audio files
and play them and control that playback.
In your sketches.
[MUSIC]