Okay so, Lesson one has been all about
getting started understanding graphics
and sound and then try to make some very,
very basic program by manipulating them.
And I want to extend that idea so that
we've got to our first-stage application,
our Week 1 application.
And if you had a look at the intro video
for running an app on your iOS device
you've seen a little bit of this already.
So it's called Sonic Painter.
The application just allows you to draw
on the screen and it makes a series of
shapes and at the same time you can
manipulate some sounds using very, very
basic functions.
So it's quite a simple application.
Having said that, there are a number of
applications that are available on the
Web that people pay to use, that aren't
that much more complicated than this.
The key to making it look nice is about
having really, really good sound and
image integration, so that people really
feel that it's interactive.
And, also mapping information from one
domain to the other, we're going to talk
a little bit about how to do that.
So the basic idea is that we draw shapes
on the screen, and they slowly rub each
other around.
and we have different brushes as well,
which I'm going to talk about.
And as you make a gesture to draw a
shape, it plays back and manipulates a
sound.
And that's the idea behind Sonic Painter.
So how do we map information from the
mouse to control different aspects of
graphics?
Well, we need to think about graphics
parameters specifically.
The whole plan is to make something that
looks much better than just someone
wheeling around it with their mouse.
But essentially, it's someone just
wheeling around a mouse with their
finger.
It's up to the programmer to try and make
it look more interesting than that.
There are a couple of techniques which
you can use, which make that much easier.
The first one is mapping information.
So we start with the map command and
we're using it to adjust the color.
And you can see, the idea is we take the
mouseX position and we map it between 0,
which is x equals 0, which is right at
the leftmost part of the screen.
And the width, so the idea of that is
that the user moves their finger from
here to here, we get a number which is
representative of either 0 or the width.
And then we map that down to a scale
between 0 and 255, and as Marco's already
explained, that's the range, the
parameter range for a color.
Now, we're doing this by using this width
command, which always tells us how wide
the application is currently and then
we're mapping it in.
So let's have a look at that in action.
I'm going to make this really simple by
changing the brush to the most simple
brush, in fact, it's just going to be a
line.
Here's a line and I need to be sure that
I'm actually deleting the right line
there, okay, yeah.
Let me just try and run this again.
Now, what you'll find is, if I refresh
this, it will pick up the changes I've
just made without me having to mess with
it too much.
And we should find, yeah.
[MUSIC] There's a single line.
I'm just going to mute it for a second so
you can't hear, you can just see.
I'm just drawing with a single line and
you'll be able to see that on the desktop
version as well if I refresh this.
A single line is being drawn.
So let's go back to the code and see how
that works.
We're basically setting here, we're,
we're going to talk about the audio in a
bit more detail later on.
But as Matt's already explained we can
load a sound and we can play it back.
So playing back the sound, and then we're
getting the red channel from mouseX.
And we're mapping the, from 0 to the
width to a range of 0 to 255.
And then we're getting the blue, and
we're mapping mouseY, which is up and
down from 0 to width to a range of 0 and
255.
So that gives us our red and the blue.
We've also got a green.
Now, let's have a look at the green and
what it does.
So it's more green on the edges and less
green in the middle.
How do we do that?
Well, we can get the distance from the
center.
The dist function in processing allows us
to get the distance.
From any particular point to another
point, and it uses, quite fabulous to do
this basically just, it makes a triangle
and figures out what the hypotenuse of
the triangle is.
So the hypotenuse is, if you have a right
angle triangle, it's the bit that is the
longest item aside.
And that's the bit we want to work out,
with this being one point and this being
the other point.
Now, the dist function does that for us.
We just give it an xy coordinate as a
starting point and an xy coordinate as an
ending point.
It tells us what the distance is.
And we can use that to work out what the
green color ought to be.
So dist does this for us.
We get the mouseX and mouseY, which is
the, where the mouse or where the finger
is on the iPod or the iPad or iPhone.
And then we see how far that is from the
center which is width divided by 2,
height divided by 2.
So, let's just see again how that works.
So we have this, what we do is we're
using that to adjust the green.
And if we have a look at the app itself,
you can see we're greener as we get away
from the center, and likewise here.
Just the same here.
All right.
So we've got a nice mixture of red, green
and blue across the entire range, across
the entire screen.
We also want to know, well, let's see
what else we can do.
We can get the speed.
If we get the speed, we can use the
distance between the previous last
position and the current last position,
and that's a good measure of speed,
because it's halfway traveled, right,
with the finger.
So we get that distance, and that tells
us how fast we're moving.
Simple as that.
We can also change the alpha.
We can use the speed value that we've got
to set how bright the alpha is, so how
transparent the drawing is.
So the faster we go, the more
transparent, sorry, the less transparent
it is, and the slower we go, the more
transparent it is.
We can also set another variable called
line width, and we can use the speed to
do that.
You can see on the screen here.
That if I go very slowly, it's a fat
line, and if I go fast, it's a thin line.
Also, I might want to constrain the line
width so that it doesn't go over a
certain width.
Otherwise, I can end up with a really
big, fat lines, when I don't want them,
simply because I'm going very, very
slowly.
So here, what we're doing is using a
function called constrain, and we're
saying that we want to constrain the line
width, which is this variable here to
between this value and this value.
Between 0 and 10, so the maximum line
width is always going to be 10.
Okay.
So, using these techniques, we can map
parameters from mouse interaction to
color.
We can get distances from the mouse
pointer to different different parts of
the screen and use that to control other
aspects of the drawing.
we can also constrain certain elements
and certain variables that we've created
such as a speed variable, which tells us
how far we've traveled between two
frames.
And we can make sure that they don't
cause massive changes in our program.
So we can also have different brushes.
Now, I've included some brushes for you
to have a look at.
These are quite complicated.
It's up to you to spend more time looking
at them.
They're not too complicated.
In fact, sometimes, there'll be over, a
little bit over edge, but they're all
right and they're just to get you
started.
But what makes a really good visual app
is really, really good brushes.
You'll know that when you use Photoshop,
it's one thing just to be drawing a line
on the screen.
It's another thing to be able to draw a
very, very pretty pattern.
So your brush can even be an image which
you load.
Well, in this case what I'm doing is I'm
just using the, the basic shapes, because
it's lesson one.
The basic shapes that comes with
processing, circles and rectangles and
lines.
Just to give you an indication of some
cool things you can do with very, very
limited material, and it's up to you to
expand on that, really.
We've done the color, this is about
shape.
So, let me show you some of these
brushes.
And I'll quickly demonstrate a few of
them.
So brush1 here, all I have to do is make
it is on comment brush1, and then refresh
my apps.
So I can just refresh.
Wait for it to finish loading.
You can see on an iPad or an iPhone,
there's a little icon.
There you go.
So this is drawing a circle.
And you'll notice that the faster I go,
if you can see that, the faster I go, the
bigger the circle.
And that's a very simple idea of a brush,
so now, I'm going quite slowly and I've
got very small circles but the lines are
still quite thick.
And the curls are more or less the same.
I've also got this one, which draws
squares instead, so it's the same thing,
but it's using rectangles.
It's just loading up here, you can see
there's a little icon spinning around.
There you go.
And this one produces a, not just one
square, but a whole bunch of squares.
I think that's something which is really
important to understand, just because
you've only got one input, doesn't mean
you should only have those one inputs.
You can have more.
So you can take one input and map it to
lots of others.
I'll show you how we do that in a minute
and then I'll expand on that.
brush3 is a random selection of lines.
So, when I draw on the iPad screen, we
can see, we have what looks like, I guess
it looks like kind of very bad tinsel.
As I say these are just examples to get
you started.
And they get varied with thickness
depending on the speed and you get the
color variation.
There's a few more of these.
You should have a look at them.
But, this one is a bit more interesting.
And this introduces another idea.
Symmetry.
Now, you can use symmetry to easily
create order out of something which
doesn't necessarily look like ordered.
And in this example, all I'm doing is I'm
getting the mouse position and drawing
the line the same way that I did in the
very, very first approach that I showed
you.
But I'm also drawing a line on the
opposite side in the x-axis.
So anything I do is mirrored, and when
you do that, it gives the illusion that
it's somehow intentional or more
intentional than it was.
So if you have a look, I can just do this
and it looks like I have a symmetrical
pattern, and I do.
But that's because my single, my single
interaction is now two interactions that
mirror each other, I've got in sort of
lateral symmetry.
And this symmetry is one of the methods
that you can start to make stuff that
looks very random, look very ordered.
Symmetry is a cheap way of getting
something beautiful.
And the more layers of symmetry that you
add, often, the more attractive people
find things.
Not always, because it depends on their
personal taste, but it's one of those
things you should explore if you're
interested in making, for example,
concentric patterns or any kind of
abstract patterns or flower type shapes
and arrangements.
It's used all the time in lots of
different forms of art and it's a very
important aspect to computer graphics.
It's a very important way of taking
something very simple and making it very
complicated.
So I want to show you a more advanced
version of that symmetry sample with
perhaps eight order of symmetry.
That's with circles, let me just make
sure that it's right.
That's, no it's it was actually the next
one.
I should have known.
Yeah, so this is the same, but it has
eight borders of symmetry.
And you'll notice now, we get something
that looks, that has a kind of religious
appeal.
And if I turn the audio up, we can see
how this is going to work.
[MUSIC] And I'm randomly drawing, it
doesn't matter where I draw, I get
symmetrical patterns.
I'm literally, I'm paying no attention to
what I'm doing.
But it's, it's just coming up with
interesting stuff.
That's because I've got so many different
reflections.
As if I'm looking into mirrors upon
mirrors upon mirrors upon mirrors.
Cheap trick, but powerful.
Okay.
The last thing I want to talk about is
sound.
I'll do this as quick as I can, because I
know you want to get on.
It's really easy to have more than one
sound, you can hear, we've got two.
We've got the bells and we've also got
the ambient wash.
So I'm loading two sounds in exactly the
same way that Matt was showing you.
[MUSIC] Let me mute this while I quickly
show you.
What we have is a separate AudioPlayer,
AudioPlayer 2.
And player2 loads the following exactly
the same way.
So we have one maxim context, but we have
two players.
player2 is loaded here.
We set the new ping to true, and we're
also balancing the first time I'm
loading, which is what I must warn is a
lot louder than the bells.
So I'm using the volume command to turn
the volume down for the first one.
And then, I'm playing them both in this
mouse drag method.
So when I, when the mouse is dragged, it
starts to play the sounds before that
it's silent.
I'm also doing a couple of other cool
things, which I'm going to talk about in
more detail in the next lesson, and
that's sound manipulation.
And this is just a taste of [UNKNOWN].
The two things I'm doing to make it more
interesting is I'm altering the speed, as
you can see here, but I'm also altering
the filter.
Now, the speed Is a really simple
equation which I'm going to quickly show
you now.
player2 speed here is the mouseX divided
by the width divided by 2.
So wherever that I am, from x, so from 0
to width x divided by width times 2, that
is how fast I want it to go.
And that's why we get these lovely
sounds, these lovely sounds.
[MUSIC] There we go.
So I can slow that right down.
Also, I've got a filter on the ambient
wash, which means the further down the
screen I am, the brighter the ambient
wash is.
[MUSIC] And I'm going to explain that in
more detail next week.
So, I think it'll be a great idea for you
to take this example and pick it apart,
add your own sounds, add your own
brushes.
Try and make something which just helps
you understand the different aspects of
graphics and sound to give you a better
indication of how you might move forward
and create an application of this type
for your uses.
[MUSIC].