Okay, so that's the end of Week one.
And a little kind of easy way in.
And yeah, that was okay.
It seemed to it seemed to all work.
But if you've got any questions, we've
actually got a forum which you can use.
And they should use the forum.
Right?
Because, there's a lot of our students on
the forum.
Aren't there?
>> Yes, so students here at DOLSMITH
have been doing several years of this
kind of work.
And we'll also be on there from time to
time, if there are some important
questions we'll be answering them.
>> Yeah, so they, they're a creative
bunch as well.
Aren't they?
We got sta, people from our creative
computing program, and also from people
we know work with you know, our
colleagues in the art department, and
also on our Masters program too.
So it's worth you checking out the forums
and asking questions.
But what are kind of things can we
encourage people to do in the coming
week, before week two?
What's a good thing to do?
>> You might have a look at some of the
pr-, the capabilities of processing.
Look at the processing reference.
I got a link, a link up there on the
Coursera website.
>> What about sound-wise, what's a good
thing?
>> Well, you just gotta get out there,
and record some sounds.
Get out, get out, get out away from the
computer.
Go out and, and record some sounds.
>> Yeah.
>> And load them in, and just play
around with those parameters we've
already shown you.
We've shown you how to slow things down,
and speed things up.
>> Yeah.
>> You can, there's so much detail in,
in the recorded sound, that you can
really have a lot of fun just exploring
that.
>> Yeah, and if you start filtering and
stuff like that, it kind of really comes
alive.
>> Exactly.
>> And there's loads of different ways
you can do some interaction, and stuff
like that.
So okay, that sounds good.
So that's what we're going to do.
there's some stuff that you can do, you
have to do, and there's some assessment
type behavior and things you can look out
for.
But we're going to see you next week.
Next week we're going to be doing a DJ/VJ
type app.
And there's a lot more sound and a lot
more graphic and direction and
specifically video.
So we'll see you there.
[BLANK_AUDIO]