[MUSIC].
Hi, and welcome to week 2 of Creative
Programming for Digital Media and Mobile
Applications.
I'm Mick.
This is Matt and Marco.
Say hello.
So last week, we learned how to do the
basics of graphics and sound.
This week, we're going to be a little bit
more advanced.
We're going to create an application
called DJ Tube.
it's really basic, but it does run on all
your mobile devices.
So, it runs on your iphone and an on your
ipad and it runs on your android device
as well.
But, we're going to make these a bit more
advanced.
We're going to learn how to play more
than one sound at once, and manipulate
the sound by changing the pitch and the
speed, and also by maybe doing a bit of
filtering.
We're also going to learn how to create
image sequences.
So, for example, making editable videos
for live VJ interaction.
And also image sequences for doing basic
animations.
Mark is going to take you through all the
graphic stuff as usual.
Matt's going to take you through the
basics of the audio.
And then I'm going to pull it together
and show you the final thing.
And in the final piece, the DJ tube app,
there's a lot of mouse interaction, and
you can start and stop different tracks
and synch them up together.
so you'll be learning how to synchronize
different audio tracks as well, and play
them back so they're all tightly
synchronized and connected to the vision.
so yeah, okay, we'll start with Marco
[SOUND] [MUSIC].