[MUSIC].
Right in this weeks audio class we're
going to learn about how we can get more
control over the audio.
You've already had a bit of a preview of
that last week where towards the end of
the exercises you would have got into the
depths of controlling audio and using the
various functions.
What we're going to do this week is look
at a bit more detail about how audio is
represented in the computer's memory
Wha-what's this thing we're telling it to
play?
Wha-what's in there and what's it, what's
happening?
So we're trying to, pick a few of those
details.
And then we'll look at some more, control
methods, for, for controlling audio
playback using RAPI.
So here's a, here's a starter slide
showing you how Computers represent
sound.
So what have we got?
We've got this, two blocks here.
So, the, the block, the, the has the
number zero through seven.
So imagine that's a short snippet of
sound.
Only seven, seven little snapshots of
that would last a very, very short time.
Because sound in a, in a machine is
typically represented with a lot of
numbers.
So it's, it's very similar to, something
that you might be more familiar with,
which is the idea of, of a video, and,
and film being chopped into frames.
We do the same thing with sound in a
computer.
We slice it into frames, called samples,
and then we just play those out through
the sound card in sequence.
Now, if we, if we look at those frames,
what's actually in them, it's slightly
different from the video.
So in the, in the case of audio, there
are a lot of frames, there could be up
to, well, a typical sample, right say,
for a good quality audio, would be 44,100
of these frames, of these samples per
second, which is a lot of data.
So this is, this is way compressed audio
formats exists like mp3 because it makes
it possible to reduce the amount of data
required to store the audio but maintain
the quality.
But in this example we're going to be
working with uncompressed data, which is
just the raw numbers that represent that
audio signal.
So let's have a look.
So in the first box here, you can see,
I've illustrated what the real contents
of a, of a single sample might be in the
computer's memory.
So I've represented it with the binary
number, which, which converts to 27 in
base ten.
Those of you, in, in the numbers you'll
be more familiar with.
So you don't need to worry too much about
that conversion.
But it's just to show you that the
computer's memory is taking up 16 of
these zeros and ones to represent one of
those samples.
Sometimes it might take 24 if it's a
higher quality audio.
But in the examples we're working with
here, typically it's going to be 16.
So we use 16 zeros and ones to represent
one single snapshot of sand.
And, we use say, 44,100 of those
snapshots to represent one second of
sound.
Okay, so what I've, I've, I've shown you
here is that, that chunk of memory which
is represented by those boxes can extend
to you know, many thousands of, of spaces
in the memory So we talk about the sample
rate which is the number of those samples
that are used to represent the signal per
second.
The higher the sample rate the more
accurate the representation of the sound,
the wider range of sounds we can
represent.
the bit depth is another property which
is as I said earlier the number of 0s and
1s that I use to represent each of those.
Snapshots.
So if we have a very low bit depth, what
happens is the samples are very
inaccurate.
Because they don't have enough range to
represent all the possible values that
sample might have.
But if you have a higher bit depth.
then you can, you can store a much more
accurate representation of sound.
Now I've got a, an animation which shows
that.
Perhaps more clearly.
So the first animation I'm going to show
illustrates what happens if you increase
the sample rate.
So we'll start with a very low sample
rate and we'll see what a typical smooth
signal looks like.
Now, it will start off very blocky and
then get much smoother as it goes.
So let's have a look at the animation
now.
So, as the, as the pointer moves across
the screen, the sample rate increases.
So, you can see the signal is, kind of,
getting smoother and smoother.
And the smoother the signal, the more
accurate It is in, as a representation of
the original sound.
So remember, earlier, I was recording
myself hitting something.
And and when I play that back, I want to
hear an accurate recording of that.
I don't just want to hear a really rough
inaccurate recording of it.
So, having a high sample rate allows
that.
So, on the next slide, we're going to see
what the, what the representation looks
like, as we increase the bit depth, is a
kind of similar effect, in that it
becomes less blocky as you increase the
bit depth, but it's totally different.
Okay.
What we might say is that increasing the
bit depth increases the vertical
resolution, the resolution from top to
bottom on the y axis, which represents
how loud the signal was at any given
time.
Whereas increasing the sample rate
changes the horizontal resolution, which
is, if you like, how precise it is in
time.
So the sample rate represents the, the
precision in time.
Whereas the bit depth represents the
precision in, in the actual measurements
that we're taking.
Okay.
So that's the end of the theory section.
We're now going to look at how we can get
more control over this, this sound.
And, and, and to, to understand what,
what we're doing when we're changing
those controls.
So the first thing we're going to try and
do It's to create an interactive speed
slider which allows us to vary the speed
of the playback.
So you can see in this code here that I'm
first calculating a ratio.
So now I'm going to demonstrate how you
can vary the speed of the sample
playback.
So remember the speed, relates to the
sample rate if you like.
So it's the speed of playback is how
quickly we're flinging those numbers at
the sound card.
So, if you increase the speed, it's
going to zip through that, that, that
section of memory that, that's storing
the sound faster.
So if we double the speed, it should get
through twice as fast.
So let's just remind ourselves by playing
it at normal speed.
So player, speed, one.
Let's just run this app and see how it
sounds.
So I'm running it now.
So it's now building for the Android
device.
[SOUND] So that's, that's speed one,
that's, that sounds very similar to how
it did when I actually played it in the
real world.
What happens if I double the speed?
Speed [NOISE] It's the 2.
[MUSIC] So that you can see that it
sounds higher.
[MUSIC] So what's doing it, it's scanning
through those [UNKNOWN] twice as fast as
sending them out to the sound card.
Obviously, it's really boring, having to
continue, edit, and then run it on the
device.
It'd be much nicer if we could experiment
with the speed in an interactive way.
So what we're going to do is make a
simple, if you like, slider that allows
us to slide the mouse pointer across the
screen, or a finger across the screen,
and.
Increase the speed.
Now speed is, is useful so in the range
zero to two.
So that gives us an interesting range.
'Kay, we just heard what it sounds like
if you play at speed two?
Speed zero, it doesn't play at all, and
then and so on, up to two.
So let, let's just listen to that by
making interactive slider.
So what I'm going to do Is, in the draw
function I'm going to continually
calculate a new speed for the player.
So I'm going to calculate, first of all,
the ratio of the position of the mouse to
the width of the screen.
And you'll see all this, these float,
things there.
I'll explain what they are, they're for.
So, I do float ratio.
Now remember, float is a number that
is not a whole number, it's a
real number, so we can have
say, 0.5 or 0.6. And in this case
we want to, because we've only got the
range 0 to 2 for the speed in this example
we want to be able to specify that very precisely.
So I'm going to take the floating point
version of the mouse position and
floating point version of the width,and
that, that would cause it to do the
calculation with these accurate numbers.
If I didn't do this, it would do it in
whole numbers and I wouldn't get my
accurate ratio.
So that's the ratio of the MouseX to the
width.
What that means is, when they're on the
far left of the screen it'll be zero and
when they're on the far right it'll be
one.
Now I'm just going to scale that up by
two, so that's in the range zero to two.
And then, I'll just call it player.speed
with that value.
Okay.
So that should mean I can now, change the
speed dynamically.
What I might do, when I tap it should
queue it back to the beginning again.
We'll set it to loop.
We'll set looping to true so that it's
kind of You can continue to hear what's
going on.
So let's play this sketch now, let's just
review that before we do it actually.
So I'm just going to review what I just
typed.
Player set looping is set to true, so
that it continually plays the sound.
I've calculated the ratio of the position
of the mouse or the, or the finger tap on
the screen.
Across the screen, scout it by two, and
then sent into, for the speed, so I will
be setting a speed to a range from zero
to two, so the idea is that when it's on
the far left of the screen you should
play it slowly, when it's on the far
right of the screen it should play
quickly.
Let's see what it does...
[SOUND] Okay, so what you heard there was
me moving my finger around and varying
the speed of the playback, as, as it was
playing the sample.
Now if you do that with, with the break
beat, just as, by comparison, you'll see
that it has a slightly different effect.
[MUSIC] Okay, so then you're getting
towards more of a musical deejaying
experience where you can slow the sound
down and then speed it back up again.
And it has a more performance feel to it
rather than playing with the sound.
[MUSIC].