[SOUND].
[MUSIC].
Okay so we've created a slider which
allows us to vary the speed of the
playback, and you saw that there's
immediately some quite pleasing creative
effects you can achieve with that.
What we want to do now is add another
control which is to play and stop the
sound, so we can completely switch it
off...
And switch it back on again.
It's a little bit more complicated,
you're going to do it with a button.
So we'll basically make the top part of
the screen into a button which can switch
the play back on and off.
And then we'll make the bottom part of
the screen into the slider that we used
earlier.
Here's the sketch with the slider.
So first of all I'm going to go to
trigger this code.
If the mouse Y position is greater than
the height of 2.
Okay so if we're in the bottom half of
the screen, we'e in the bottom half of
the screen it'll operate the speed
slider.
Now what I'm also going to do to make it
obvious That that's, that's what we're
doing there.
I'm going to draw a rectangle in the
bottom half of the screen, which has the
color of the current speed.
Let's leave grayscale for now, because
I'm not working too much on the graphics
in this session.
So we'll just do a grayscale color.
So you remember, color is in the range 0
to 255 We've got this ratio, which isn't
0 to 2.
So, we can just do something like, ratio
times, 128.
Now approximately, give us, a gray scale
based on, on the, the range of the
slider.
So the rectangle needs to be at position
It takes up half of the, the bottom half
of the screen.
So we go zero zero and height over two,
so it starts at the far left of the
screen, halfway down, and it goes to the
far right of the screen.
Therefore the size of it is the width of
the screen and the height is the height
of the screen over two.
So remember that's the x and y position.
That's the width of the square, and
that's the height.
So let's just double check that, that's
working before we carry on.
Okay, so I've got, cannot find symbol.
Let's see if we can debug that.
So I'm referring to a variable called
ratio.
Where did ratio get defined?
Well, it's inside the if statement.
So that means that ratio, because I've
declared it there with float ratio, that
that variable is local to the if
function.
So it's not okay for me to then use it
outside the if function.
So what I can do is take it out like that
and, so now I'm declaring it above the if
statement, and I am then using it outside
the if statement that's fine.
Okay, so now I have a problem here, where
I've forgotten to put a t there.
Okay, See that, see that it's
highlighting the line that has the
problem.
It's quite communicative about the, the
errors in your code.
[MUSIC] SSS Okay.
So now you can see the slide is now
displaying a color, which represents the
speed.
So I now need to quickly add a bottom and
top of the screen, which deals with,
which deals with the stopping and
starting.
First of all, I am going to draw the
button.
So I will do, and I'll choose whether to
draw it red or green, based on the state
of a boolean.
So we create a boolean called buttonOn,
and we start off with buttonOn equals
false.
So the button starts off being off.
Now if button on, so we'll represent my
button as having a state of being on or
off.
It's just a switch so I use a Boolean
which can be a true or a false.
and Boolean's are used quite extensively
in controlling the state of programs.
Way things can either be on or off.
So it the button is on, I'll set the fill
color to.
Red.
Otherwise, I'll set it to.
Green.
Can you guess?
Okay.
So, then I draw my rectangle.
this one starts at 0.
This one starts at 0,0 and goes to, and
the size is the same size as the other
one so it's width, height over 2.
Okay, then I need to manage it.
If they press mouse, if the mouse is
pressed, I need to now update this data
that button.
So I need to check where it is if Mouse Y
is less than the height over 2.
In other words if they're in the top half
of the screen, which is where about I'm
going to be, then I set, I toggle value
to bottom button on equals.
And this is how to toggle a Boolean
[SOUND], I'll use this operator here, the
exclamation mark.
That'll switch button on to whatever the
opposite state is.
So if it's true it'll switch it to false.
If it's false it'll switch it to true.
And then, I'm going to change the state
of the player.
So if the button is on I want the player
to play.
Remove that line.
Otherwise, I want the player to stop.
Okay, let's just clean that up a bit.
Remember, you can always do the Also
format.
Ctrl+T, Apple+T, depending on what you're
using.
Okay?
So, basically, if they are in the region
of the button, which is the top half of
the screen, then we switch the state of
the button, and then we look at what the
current state of the button is now, and
update the player to either stop or, or
play, based on that.
And then we draw the button with either
red or green depending on the states in
the draw function.
So let's roll that.
Okay, I can't spell button.
It's bu.
So again it highlighted the line a little
examination of that line showed that I
mistyped the name of the variable.
[MUSIC] There's my button, switching it
on and off.
[MUSIC] So even a DJ could operate this
interface.
[MUSIC] [MUSIC] I'm not a DJ, as you can
tell.
There you go.
So there's a simple interface which
allows you to control the speed and the
playback state of an audio player.
[MUSIC] [MUSIC]