[SOUND].
[MUSIC].
Well, that's the end of week two.
and I hope that was interesting, and
useful.
A bit more complicated than last week,
don't you think?
>> Yeah, for sure.
so we're really trying to combine these
different elements, and, and work with a
lot of different data here.
So you, so you figured out how to work
with sequences, and images, and how to
play two sounds at the same time.
>> Mm.
>> So you're really making, these,
these applications more complex.
And also I hope a lot more fun to, to
interact with.
So what can you do?
I'll put these apps in, in your friend's
hands and get them to play with them.
>> Whacka, whacka.
Yeah, yeah, and maybe make some YouTube
videos and stuff.
That's always fun.
make a video with some terrible techno o
VJ behavior.
What about, yeah maybe try to play more
than one sound at once, as well.
[CROSSTALK].
>> Work with images.
>> Yeah.
>> Work with images because, ye, well
now you've got images in there, you've
got a much richer visual feel, much more
varied than you can.
>> Mm.
>> I mean, the Drawing command's
impressing and really powerful, but once
you've got images, there's the, it's the
richness of the real world that you can
bring into it.
>> And you can get loads of images,
can't you?
>> Yeah.
>> Off stuff like the internet archive,
and things like that.
And again you should use the forums if
you want, if you got any questions.
We have our students on there.
Students who are on degree programs in
creative computing, students who, you
know, doing various kind of ghost less
type stuff, you know, very creative, very
energetic, good engineers as well, good
programmers.
>> Technically they know their stuff.
>> Yeah.
>> Also they've got lots of experience
in audio visual work so they, they know,
a lot about exact kind of things.
>> We're doing this course.
>> That's right, so if you get and, if
you get stuck, post some questions, and
if anything gets really tough field to us
to and we'll be there as well.
So we'll see you next week for week three
where we'll be making audio
visualizations.
So, stuff to make your music players look
better.
So, I'll see you then.
[MUSIC] [MUSIC]