[MUSIC]
We've been spending a ton of time on
derivatives.
And at this point, you might be asking
yourself, is there
anything more to do with derivatives, and
the good news is, yes.
There's a lot more to see.
Right now I want to look at the chain
rule.
The chain rule tells us how to
differentiate a composition of two
differentiable functions and because lots
and lots of functions in the real
world are written as compositions of
differentiable functions, we'll then be
able
to differentiate just a ton more functions
by using the chain rule.
Now, looking ahead a bit further to see
what else might be coming up on the
horizon.
Well, after the chain rule we're going to
learn
how to differentiate functions like e to
the x, natural
logarithm and then even further out we're
going to
learn how to differentiate trig functions
like sine and cosine.
And once we have all of that, and once
we've got the chain rule, we'll
be in a position to just differentiate
anything
you could write down by combining those
functions.
And then, even further out, as we look
even further
ahead in the course, we can see some
applications of differentiation.
Once we learn the mechanics of
differentiating, then
we'll be able to get to these
applications.
Things like, solving optimization
problems.
All right, well.
Hang in there.
We think that the chain rule, but
computations are going to get harder.
But, I know you can do it.
Good
luck.