[MUSIC]
At this point, you have a good
understanding of what is required to
effectively manage data as you move
through the research life cycle.
As you know, data management
can seem quite the undertaking,
when you consider all the aspects
of data management best practice.
But data management does not
have to be overwhelming,
if you have a data management plan.
A data management plan or a DMP for
short is a formal document
that describes the data produced in
the course of a research project.
And outlines the data management
strategies that will be implemented both
during the active phase of the research
project and after the project ends.
If you have been involved in a research
project supported by a major funding
agency, you probably have a good idea
of what should be included in a DMP.
Many funding agencies,
particularly federal agencies, now require
grantees to submit a data management
plan as part of the proposal package.
If you think you or your clients
may be applying for a grant from
the National Science Foundation,
the National Institutes of Health,
the Alfred P Sloan Foundation, NASA, the
Institute of Museum and Library Services.
The National Endowment for
the Humanities, the Gordon and
Betty Moore Foundation,
the Institute of Education Sciences and
the Economic and
Social Research Council, the Science and
Technology Facilities Council,
the Wellcome Trust, and
while the list goes on you will need to
know how to write a comprehensive DMP.
Even if you won't be
participating in funded research,
writing a DMP will encourage you
to think carefully about the data
management needs of your research data and
plan accordingly.
Remember, like planning for
your taxes, planning for
data management will save you time and
headaches in the long run.
By the end of this lesson, you will
be able to identify the components
of a good DMP, understand
the importance and purpose of DMPs, and
be familiar with the DMP policies
of several funding agencies.
Also, you will add to tour toolkit
some great resources and tools for
data management planning.
Let's go ahead and get started.
Just as I mentioned, many funding
agencies now require grantees to submit
a data management plan as part of
the proposal package submission.
This gives assurances to
the funding agency the project data
will be accessible and
usable over the long term.
They want to see that you have
established a strategy for
managing your data throughout
the research lifecycle.
Making plans for how you will collect,
document, organize,
and preserve your data are all part
of the data management strategy.
This is important for funding agencies,
for two primary reasons.
The first reason is transparency and
openness.
It is an expectation that publicly
funded research data will
be discoverable, accessible,
and reusable to the public.
Since they underwrite federally
funded grants, it is a government
responsibility to ensure citizens can see
where their tax dollars are spent and
allow them to capitalize on
the products of these grants.
A data management plan that illustrates
how data will be made discoverable,
accessible and
reusable supports this responsibility.
The second reason is return on investment.
Making data discoverable,
accessible and reusable,
maximizes the research
potential of the data and
provides greater returns on
public investments and research.
Well-managed data allows for
verification or
refinement of published research results,
reduces the potential for
scientific fraud, promotes new research
through the use of existing data,
provides resources for
training new researchers and
discourages unintentional
redundancy in research.
By planning for data management, these
benefits are more likely to be realized.
[MUSIC]