[MUSIC]
Let's take a look at the data
management policies from a few of
the major US funding agencies.
The National Science Foundation
data management plan
policy requires that proposals
include a supplementary
Data Management Plan document
of no more than two pages.
That includes information on five
key aspects of data management.
The types of data to be produced for
the project, data and metadata format and
content, policies for access and
sharing, including security provisions,
policies and provisions for
dissemination and reuse.
And plans for archiving, preserving,
and providing access to the data.
The National Institutes of Health
requires applicants seeking $500,000 or
more in direct costs to
provide a description of
how project data will be made
available in a data sharing plan.
This document should describe final
dataset formats, documentation,
analytic tools necessary to use the data,
data sharing agreements,
and how and when the data will
be made accessible to others.
The National Endowment for the Humanities
summarizes the content of data
management plans they require with two
questions that should be addressed.
What data are generated by your research?
And what is your plan for
managing these data?
To answer these questions,
NEH requires that the DMP describe
the data to be produced,
how the data will be managed and
maintained during the active
phase of the project,
any factors that might impact the
researcher's ability to manage the data,
types of information that
need to be managed and
maintained alongside the data, how data
will be shared in a timely manner,
and the facilities used
to preserve the data.
[MUSIC]