[MUSIC]
In all of these three data management
policies, DMP should describe in detail
all major aspects of data management
throughout the research life cycle.
Here is a checklist for a data management
plan from the Digital Curation Center
that list questions that should
be addressed in the DMP.
What data will you collect or create?
To answer this question, you should
provide a description of the data,
including the type, format, and volume,
with a justification of the format choice.
If there are any storage implications
due to the format or volume of the data.
You should include these as well.
How will the data be collected or created?
Describe the data collection
methods to be used,
including the standards
that dictate these methods.
You should also discuss your plans for
organizing data files and
applying version control,
as well as how quality assurance
protocols will be implemented during and
after data collection.
What documentation of metadata
will accompany the data?
It is important to determine what
information will be required to ensure
that the data be understandable to
secondary users of the data, or
for you and your team in the future.
In other words, you should
describe the type of documentation
that will be needed to accompany the data
in order to interpret and use them.
These documents might include
a description of the methodologies,
a codebook that provides variable and
value definitions, questionnaires or
instruments, or analysis procedures.
How will you manage any ethical issues?
The DMP should demonstrate
that you have considered critical
issues related to laws and guidelines.
Regarding the protection
of human subjects.
If your project will conduct research
involving human participants,
you need to describe provisions for
protecting their confidentiality.
This should include strategies for
handling and
storing sensitive data,
restricting access to sensitive data, and
preparing de-indentified datasets for
sharing.
How will you manage copyright and
intellectual property rights issues?
This is where legal issues of data
ownership need to be addressed.
You need to identify the owner of the data
and their conditions for using the data.
If you are reusing third-party
data particularly property data.
You should discuss permissions
with the data producer.
How will the data be stored and
backed up during research?
To answer this question, you should
describe provisions for storage.
And the degree to which they are adequate
for the type and size of your data.
Provisions for
storage should include plans for
systematic back ups of the data files.
How will you manage access and security.
If the data are sensitive or
should otherwise be restricted.
To authorize project personnel.
You should describe in
detail security measures
that will be in place to protect the data.
You also need to describe the standards
with which those security measures comply.
Which data should be retained,
shared, and/or preserved?
In thinking about how the data will
be used by others or by your team in
the future, you should make note of the
potential value of the data and the effort
that will be required to prepare
the datasets for preservation and access.
What is the long-term preservation
plan for the dataset?
Answering this question requires you
to identify the repository you will
use to archive the data and your plans
to prepare and document the data
to ensure that they will be preserved and
usable into the foreseeable future.
How will you share the data?
Here you should identify the mechanism
you will use to share your data.
Describe how others might find your data
and how data files will be delivered.
You should also specify how you would like
others to acknowledge or sight your data.
Are any restrictions on
data sharing required?
Again, if privacy concerns affect
your ability to share project data,
you will need to discuss them and
how you will overcome these concerns
to enable data sharing whether by
providing anonymized versions of the data.
Requiring a data use agreement or
other mechanisms.
You may also choose to place
an embargo on the data,
to ensure you have exclusive use
of the data for a period of time.
If this is the case,
you should explain why this is necessary.
Who will be responsible for
data management?
Quite simply, you need to identify,
by name if possible,
who will oversee the implementation
of the data management plan.
What resources will you require
to implement your plan?
For some projects with complex data,
whether due to type, size, or the fact
that project activities are geographically
distributed among different institutions,
data management might require specialized
expertise or special equipment.
You may also consider costs
associated with performing ongoing
data management tasks,
as well as the resources required for
long-term preservation of
the data in a repository.
[MUSIC]