If this check list seems overwhelming,
don't worry.
There are multiple data management plan
tools available to use online for free.
Two of these are the DMPTool produced
by the University of California,
Curation Center of
the California Digital Library
and DMPOnline developed by
the Digital Curation Centre.
The DMPTool allows researchers to
create customized data management plans
via a step-by-step wizard based on
each funding agency's requirements.
This wizard office resources,
help text and suggested answers
based on templates developed and
reviewed by information professionals
from the researches institution in
the California Digital Library.
When funding agency policies change,
the DMPTool is updated.
This ensures that the information
is up to date and
all new requirements are listed
in the DMPTool templates.
DMPOnline like the DMPTool is the DCC's
data management planning tool.
It offers guidance for researchers writing
DMPs and includes templates specific
to the requirements of UK funding agencies
and funding agencies outside the UK.
Institutions can also customize
templates via DMPOnline.
For more information, check out the videos
for these tools on the resources page.
Writing a data management plan gets you
to think through data management issues
early on in the research life cycle.
By considering all of these issues,
you will not only be in compliance
with data management requirements,
you will also be better prepared to
implement data management strategies.
Even if you aren't required to
write a data management plan,
this is a helpful process
to do better research.
[MUSIC]