,, . I can cook up some really nasty
functions, give them to you. And then ask
you to differentiate them. For instance, I
could ask you to differentiate this
function. 1 plus x squared to the 5th
power, 1 plus x cubed to the 8th power,
all divided by 1 plus x to the fourth,
this to the seventh power. In principle,
there's nothing stopping you from plowing
ahead and computing the derivative. You
can totally differentiate this function.
Right? What's the derivative of this
function? Well, this function's a quotient
so he needs the quotient rule. The
denominator of the quotient rule is the
original denominator squared. So it's
going to be the original denominator now
to the 14th power And the quotient rule,
the numerator starts off with the
derivative of the original numerator. Now,
the original numerator is a product. So
I'll be able to do this derivative by
using the, product rule and chain rule. So
it's the derivative of the numerator imes
the denominator. And it keeps going,
right? Then I gotta subtract the,
derivative of the denominator times the
numerator. But, look, you can do this
derivative just by careful application of
the quotient rule, the product rule, the
power rule, and the chain rule. There is
one thing stopping you, your sense of
human decency. It's just an awful
calculation. Nobody would want to do that.
So instead, I propose a trick. But maybe
it's not a trick, because it's a trick
that fits into a general theme. It's
logarithms. Logarithms turn exponentiation
into multiplication, and multiplication
into addition. Let's see how this helps
us. So here we go. Instead of calling this
function f of x. I'm jut going to call it
y, because I'm getting ready to do a sort
of implicit differentiation. I'm going to
first apply log to both sides of this. And
I'll get log y. And what's log of the
other side? Well it 's log of a quotient,
which is a difference of logs, and logs of
things to powers, which is that power
times log of the base. So this works out
to 5 times log of 1 plus x squared plus
This log turns multiplication into
addition. 8 times log of 1 plus X cubed
and this quotient becomes a difference,
so, minus 7. The 7 in the exponent, log 1
plus x. Now, we differentiate. All right,
so differentiating now, what's the
derivative of log y? Remember, y is
secretly a function of x, so I
differentiate log y. It's the derivative
of the outside, which is 1 over y, times
the derivative of the inside, which, I'll
write dy dx. This is really an example if
you like the implicit differentiation.
Alright, now I differentiate the other
side, 5, I just multiply it by 5 the
derivative of log is 1 over, so 1 over the
inside function and 1 plus x squared times
the derivative of the inside function
which is 2x. The derivative of 1 plus x
squared is 2x. All right, plus 8, and its
derivative log is 1 over at the inside
function, 1 plus x cubed, times the
derivative of this inside function, which
is 3 times x squared, minus 7 over, the
derivative of log is one over at the
inside function, one plus x to the fourth,
and the derivative of one plus x to the
fourth is four x cubed. We're almost
there. So now, I just multiply both sides
by y. And I get that the derivative is
this thing calculated x y, y is this
quantity. I can write this a little bit
more nicely alright here's this 5 times 2x
is 10x, 8 times 3 is 24, 7 times 4 is 28,
and then I multiply by y. So I found the
derivative, here it is. In general, this
trick logarithmic differentiation as it's
called, works fantastically well for
functions like these. Rational functions
that involve a lot of high powers.