[MUSIC]
Hello and welcome to this course on
embedded hardware and operating systems.
My name is Marco Ramirez and
I will be your lecturer during the course.
Welcome to the University of Turku.
Well, let's get started.
[SOUND]
[MUSIC]
Cyber physical systems operate at the edge
between the cyber and the real world and
compromise of computational networking and
physical components.
The importance of such systems
is difficult to overestimate.
They are literally everywhere from
the smartphone to space station.
Hardware is an integral component
of a cyber physical system.
This is figuratively speaking,
a foundation of the system.
Therefore, it is important to
choose the hardware correctly.
This choice should be system oriented.
Meaning that the hardware should
fulfill the requirements of the cyber
physical system.
At the same time, the resources
provided by the chosen hardware
should not be excessive for the system.
Unlike hardware design for
a specific purpose,
embedded systems require software to
function and accomplish their work goal.
However, writing this software
from the ground up for
every type of hardware is not practical.
The most common approach
is to use operating systems
to handle the basic task of
managing the hardware resources and
provide great services for
user applications.
In this course, we will talk
about two components of a cyber
physical system namely,
hardware and operating systems.
We will give you hints on how to make
a proper choice of those components.
I hope this knowledge will boost your
interest in cyber physical systems and
help you to implement
your ideas more quickly.
Good luck.
[MUSIC]