[MUSIC]
Hello and welcome back.
By now hopefully, you have a general
picture of what an embedded system is.
However, in order to give
you a better insight,
in this video we're going to talk about
the characteristics of an embedded system.
We will also discuss the challenges you
may face when developing embedded systems
as well as possible design flows
to tackle those challenges.
Any embedded system is built for
a certain application,
thus the system should fulfill
the requirements of the application.
These requirements dictate the
characteristics of the embedded system.
In general,
we can distinguish several of them that
can be applied to any embedded system.
In the video,
we will highlight some of them.
We will talk about dependability,
efficiency, and real-time constraints.
These characteristics are crucial since
they influence the way the system works.
A lot of embedded systems are safety
critical and so they must be dependable.
A good example of a system which
everyone would agree should be
dependable is nuclear power plants.
They are of course many other
examples such as airplanes or cars.
Why should these systems be dependable?
The main reason is they are directly
connected to the environment and
if something goes wrong they will
have an immediate impact on it.
Dependability can be split into
several sub-characteristics.
The system is considered dependable if
all those characteristics are fulfilled.
An important issue is that
initially the developers
should not focus only on
the functionality of the system
assuming that the dependability
can be brought in on later stages.
In fact, this approach does not work,
because design decisions might not allow
achieving dependability afterwards.
For example, if the wrong components
are chosen for an application,
let's say there is not enough
computational performance to execute
critical tasks on time, It will be very
difficult to deal with it in later stages.
So dependability should be considered
during the initial stages of
the system design.
Efficiency is another issue.
The importance of this
characteristic comes from the fact
that the amount of resources
is always limited.
Resources can be represented
in the form of energy or
memory space if it's an embedded system or
as money if it's a customer.
Nowadays, small resource constrained
devices such as wearables or
Internet of Things nodes
are becoming more and more popular.
These devices do not have
constant power supply.
However, they should last longer to
provide costumers with proper services.
Therefore, energy efficiency is
much relevant to embedded systems.
How can these characteristics
be estimated?
In general, Energy Efficiency can be
estimated based on the amount of work done
by the system considering
the amount of spent energy.
For example, for
processors energy efficiency can be
estimated based on the number
of instructions per joule.
It is probably obvious that the number
of operations per joule is increasing as
technology advances.
If we make a quick comparison
of the current technologies,
we can conclude that the more
application specific
the components are that the more
efficient the application is.
According to that, processors offer
the least energy efficient solutions.
Whereas, application specific
integrated-circuits are the most
efficient ones.
In an embedded system, hardware and
software play equally important roles.
If the running software does not
exclude the underlying hardware
at its full potential Then
run-time efficiency will be poor.
Inefficiencies cost by poor mapping
of the application to platforms
should be avoided.
For instance, compilers should
not bring in overhead which
will eventually leave
two of wasted energy.
Code size is another issue that needs to
be addressed when it comes to efficiency.
Devices capable of loading additional
code dynamically are still rare.
Usually an embedded systems code
is stored within the device.
Therefore, it should occupy
as less space as possible.
The physical appearance of
the system is not less important.
Portable devices should be lightweight so
to be more attractive to customers.
The last but not the last parameter that
influences the overall efficiency is cost.
The system should be built using
as little components as possible
to implement the required functionality.
Embedded systems should
meet real-time constraints.
If computations are not finished in time,
the quality of the solution
might decrease.
Sometimes, violating real-time
constraints may actually lead to more
serious consequences, which will
make the system less dependable.
Of course, not all embedded systems
share the mentioned characteristics, but
the majority still do.
However, since embedded systems lie in
the intersection of different fields of
a study.
There is some haziness in the definition
of what these systems are,
and therefore,
the set of characteristics may vary.
Considering the above listed
characteristics of embedded systems,
we can think of challenges
that developers might face.
The dependability level of embedded
systems goes beyond the level for
PC-like systems.
A real life example of the effects
an undependable system can have is what
happened in Southern California
back in 2004.
When due to technical problems,
the air traffic control center
could not operate and
many airliners were held to the ground.
This s the kind of situations that
obviously everybody would like to avoid.
To make a system efficient,
software can not be developed
independently of the underlying hardware.
This means that during the initial
design steps, both software and
hardware should be taken into account.
This actually requires
collaboration between the fields of
electrical engineering and
computer science.
The best energy efficiency can be achieved
by building application specific hardware.
However, there are downsides
to hardware implementation,
it doesn't provide high flexibility.
It is also expensive and
requires long design times.
Embedded systems development is about
finding the right balance between
efficiency and flexibility.
Embedded systems interact
with the physical world.
This fact has additional implications.
For instance, developers must check
if real-time constraints are met.
It should be also considered,
that real systems are concurrent.
Managing concurrency is
another important challenge.
Embedded systems may consist of many
components, such as processing elements,
input-output devices, and
communications units.
This means that the impact of combining
these components should be studied and
considered.
For instance,
it is desirable to know how one component
might influence the other components.
In order to make
the design process easier,
it should be broken into
several soft tests.
These self tests should be
performed sequentially and
some of them can be repeated.
Also, it is important that all solutions
and methods are reused whenever possible.
Designing starts from an idea which should
be converted into a design specification.
Special repository should be created
where the relevant designing
formation will be stored.
The repository will lead the developer's
to keep tract of the design.
It is also good if the repository provides
version control to make it possible
to roll back to previous version
of the design at each iteration,
the repository should be updated.
During the design process, applications
are mapped to the platform iteratively.
In each iteration,
new design information is generated.
The information comprises the mapping
of operations to hardware or software.
Computation and
scaling in each step the design should be
evaluated considering perimeters
such as dependability, performance,
energy consumption and others.
During the intermediate steps there is no
warranty that the design will be correct
that's why the design should
be validated in each step.
As it was mentioned before,
the system should be efficient,
that's why optimization is important.
To ease the design process, you might be
interested in different design models.
These models clearly show the different
steps that must be performed.
For example, the waterfall model
is a sequential design process
where development proceeds
from the top to the bottom
from obtaining the requirements
to the maintenance.
In order to use this model, the design
process should be thought through
very well because after the fact
changes are very costly.
The iterative model doesn't have
dimension drawback since before
deployment the design goes
through testing, evolution,
implementation every as many times
as needed to meet the requirements.
Well, this is all for this video.
We discussed the main characteristics and
challenges of embedded systems.
In the next videos,
we will go into interesting details and
we will discuss more
about embedded systems.
[MUSIC]