[NOISE].
Hi and welcome to the final week of
Creative Programming for Digital Media
and Mobile Applications.
This week's a bit special because it's
the last week, but also we're going to do
something that's a bit more fun and for
our specialist audience and our
specialist market.
We are going to build a synthesizor and a
drum machine that works on mobile devices
and on desktop devices entirely using
browser technology.
So yeah, we've been working quite hard to
get this together for you.
Although, it's very, very simple for you
to interact with and you should be able
to, from this example that we're going to
show you, go ahead and build a lot of
your own music synthesizers and
sequences.
And I think this is a nice way to end
because it shows you how we can use a GUI
and quite complex audio ideas, sound
ideas, and music ideas to put something
together that's very usable for people
who don't necessarily have a lot of
musical skills.
But then allows the to produce something
which does sound musical...
Although, having said that, it's me
that's playing it so, you know, my goal
whenever I try and write music software
is to make something which I can play
when I'm really drunk.
so that's been my vision for this week.
we've got Marco, who's going to be
telling you a little bit of how to set up
sliders.
Particularly, sliders so you can change
the parameters for the synthesizer.
And then we've got Matt.
And Matt is going to tell you that some
of the specifics about creating a
sequencer using processing.
Now, it's gotta be said, processing is
not the best language to be doing sound
in of any kind.
So the fact that this works at all is you
know, is I think very useful for a lot of
people that are interested in making
music.
So, we'll take you through step by step
as always, and this week we're going to
start with Matt, and he's going to talk
you through basic, building a basic drum
machine.
So Matt, how does it work?