[SOUND].
Wow, what's this?
It's a drum machine.
So what, what, how does a drum machine
work?
Well, let's figure it out.
So, a drum machine has a pattern, pattern
which specifies what rhythm it's going to
play.
And the way that you, you, you input that
pattern is using these colored buttons at
the bottom, okay, so this is, this is a
tra2a, it's the classic drum machine.
And you can see, you've got 16 buttons on
the bottom there.
So if you, if you press a button, and a
light comes on, and that means that on
that beat you're going to trigger a
sound.
And then, a clock will step it through
the beats, and if it sees that the button
is on, it will play a sound.
So, what we're going to try and do is
emulate that kind of behavior.
What we call step sequencing inside
processing.
So, we're going to have to figure out how
we're going to represent that sequence
int he memory, we're going to have to
figure out how to do the clock and
various other things.
but it's really nice because if you do it
at this low level you have complete
control over how the sequencer works.
And that means you have a much wider
range of possibilities to get creative.
So, let's get into some code.
So, I've got a basic starter code here.
And you can see I've got the usual maxim
object.
And I've got an audio player, which I'm
calling snare.
Which will be obvious why shortly.
And then, so I create my maxim.
And I create my snare.
So, I'm loading in wav files.
So, this is I believe it's a sample from
the Roland TR-909 drum machine.
but you can obviously use any samples
you'd like.
But certainly for a drum machine you
probably want to be using short samples.
So, that's my snare sample.
And then, my frame rate, I'm setting to
30.
that could be, that could be set to
anything.
But I'm just setting it to 30, so it's
really explicit how the timing is
working.
Okay.
Then, I've got this variable called
playHead, which I'm setting to 0.
And playHead is, is how I'm going to
figure out when, when to trigger events.
Okay?
So, when draw gets called, which happens
repeatedly.
Remember, draw is just being called all
the time.
The playHead is going to go up by one.
And then, I'm going to check if the
playHead, how far the playhead has gone,
and if it's gone up to 30, in other words
if I, if I take the remainder of the
playHead in 30 then, and it's 0, that
means that it must have got through three
calls to draw, sorry, 30 calls to draw.
So, that means because it's 30 frames a
second that means one second has passed.
So, this little if statement here, checks
if a second has passed, okay.
And so, when one second passes, I queue
up the snare drum sound and I play it.
So, the, the sound we expect to hear from
this is a snare drum being triggered once
a second.
[SOUND].
Okay, there you have it.
Now, that's not really the best rhythm
I've ever heard.
so, I think quite a few songs aren't that
far from that rhythmically, but we can,
we can do better.
So, what we need to do now is, is address
that problem I mentioned earlier which is
how to represent a sequence in the
memory.
So, the way I'm going to do it is I'm
going to take a Boolean array and call it
snare, snSeq, like that, so I'm giving it
a kind of short variable name so I don't
have to keep typing it in, okay.
So, snare sequence.
Now yes just to reiterate it's a Boolean,
so that's going to contain trues and
false values.
Because the idea is that it, remember
with the buttons on that drum machine we
saw at the beginning they're either on or
off.
So, Boolean is fine.
And it's an array so that means you can
install several Booleans in one place,
which makes it more convenient.
So, let's initialize it.
snare sequence equals new boolean.
And I'm going to put four slots in it,
and then I'm going to put a rhythm in.
Equals true.
So, it's going to play a snare on the
first beat, let's put four beats in, one,
two, three, and this, they're going to
miss it on the second beat and it's
going to trigger it on the and then two,
it's going to do two.
So, the idea with this rhythm, it's true
false true true.
So, it's going to be like this.
[SOUND].
Okay?
So, we get three in a row, and then a,
and then a gap.
Right, so let's, so the problem is I now,
I now need to look into that array as my,
as my, my ticking clock, you know, my
playHead.
Every time playHead gets to zero, I need
to figure out where I am in the array.
So, I'm going to need another variable
which is it's going to be called
snSeqPos, okay?
So, snSeqPos is going to start off at 0,
okay?
Now I'm going to, want to do is every
time the the playHead tells me it's time
to, to, to play a sound, I'm going to
increase my, my sequence of position by
one.
Right, and then, I'm going to check if
its gone too fast, snSeqPos.
So, I'll do a check.
If, snSeqPos is equivalent to
snSeq.length, so in other words, if I've
got up to four which is a remember from
Marco's lectures about arrays that arrays
are zero index.
So, we don't want our index to go up over
four and this is our index.
so, so we check if it's gone that far.
If it's gone that far then we reset it.
Okay, so that, that code there is, if you
like, a simple thing which steps through
from zero to three then goes back to zero
again.
So, we can just check that code by, by
testing, so let's print line position.
And let's print it out, snSeqPos.
Okay, so we should see it going zero,
one, two, three, zero, one, two, three.
So, let's run that.
Save and run.
[SOUND].
Okay, so you can see that's going, that's
counting zero, one, two, three, and back
to zero again.
Okay.
So, we've got our in, so we can now use
that to index into the array.
So, we go snSeq.
And so, what we're going to do is
basically if there's a true value in the
in out sequence there, then we trigger
the sound.
So, snare sequence, seq snSeqPos.
this is equivalent to true, but we can
actually, we don't need the equivalent
true because we can just put it directly.
because remember in an if statement you
can put a Boolean directly in there.
But let's make it really explicit.
And there's different styles of coding,
some more explicit than others, so let's
be really explicit.
and just check if it's true, then we're
going to play the snare.
So, remember that beat I mentioned
earlier?
So, it was one, two, three, gap, one,
two, three, gap.
Okay.
So let's see if we can get that -- that
going now.
So, I'm going to run it.
[SOUND].
So, you can hear it's got that gap, but
it's too slow so I'm going to speed it
right up.
So, I'm actually going to just double my
frame rate and that should speed it up.
Okay, let's save.
[SOUND].
Okay, so the, the rhythm's a little bit
irregular.
That's because I'm doing a screen capture
at the same time.
So, if you're just running this in a
normal browser it should be fine.
And okay, so, so we defined a basic
sequencer which we can we can use to
trigger different sounds.
So sounds at different times.
Now so the programmer can edit the
sequence and make it longer and so on and
you can make a really elaborate rhythm
sequence.
And it's obvious that you can also add
another Boolean array.
And then you need another another
position counter, and then you an add
more and more tracks.
So, that will allow you to build a full
multitrack drum machine.
And I'll leave you to go and have a go at
doing that, and, and we'll show you a
kind of fully worked example later.
[MUSIC].