So last week we introduced user
interfaces, and I introduced you to the
user interface library that I have.
now this week we're going to continue
using that to make music machine, but
we're going to introduce one other
feature of that library, which is
sliders.
so, a slider looks like this.
It's a horizontal bar that you can click
on and it moves across the screen, and as
usual we can make that effect.
What's going out things in the program,
in this case you set the screen cover.
So, let's just see how that works.
Now a slider works pretty similar, in a
pretty similar way to the buttons that we
saw last week.
You can create a slider, give it a name.
And this is a new thing, you need to set
the minimum or maximum values of the
slider.
Those are the minimum and maximum values
that you can get out of a slider.
So, the slider will have a certain size,
just as any other user interface element.
And it will go from the, the left of that
slider to the right of that slider.
And left of that slider will give you a
minimum value, in this case zero.
And the right of that slider will give
you a maximum value.
These are the values we're using to
control color, which go between zero and
255.
If you were to control something else,
like audio volume, you would need another
range of, of values.
This is quite similar to the map examples
we used earlier.
And we have the initial value of the
slider.
So you might want to start it at 0, but
sometimes you want to start it at another
value.
Here I'm starting it at 20.
These other bits are pretty much the same
as the button.
You give it a position, X, Y, and a size,
width, and height.
And this last this last parameter is the
orientation of the slider, whether it's a
horizontal slider or a vertical slider.
You can see how we can change that.
sliders pretty much work as, in the same
way as buttons.
You need to draw them in the display
method, in the draw method, and you need
to do, you need to check whether they
have been clicked on in the mouse
released method, but I'll show you the
one other thing you need to do is get the
value of the slider.
So you need to know what, what the value
of that slider is, and we can use the
function get, the slider.get.
We'll return you a floating point value,
a number, between the minimum value and
the maximum value, and then you can use
that simple code.
So let's see an example of doing that.
So this is the program I ran earlier.
We've got a slider variable, just as we
had button variables.
This is where we creating the slider.
Can you remember these are the minimum
and maximum values, and that's the
initial value, we display it in the, in
the draw method, and we call, slide it up
mouse released.
In the mouse released method, and this is
where we actually make it interact with
the rest of our program.
We get the value of the slider and use
that as input to our background's color,
and let's just remind ourselves what that
does.
So we're getting the value of the slider,
it's a value between 0 and 255 because
that's what we set it to, and, and that's
changing the background color.
We can change your initial value.
We can change our minimum value so that
it's never going to get too dark, even
right at the bottom it's still quite
grey, our maximum value similarly so to
stop it whiting out as it does.
And the other thing we might want to
change is the orientation of it, so
currently it's drawn horizontally across
the screen, but we can draw it vertically
as well.
but, I need to remember to change these
values because.
it's going to be a very short, fat
vertical slider, if I draw the same size
as the, the horizontal slider.
So if I'm drawing a vertical slider, I
need to make it's it's thin but long, as
opposed to wide but short.
So I'm swapping the width and height and
there we have our vertical slider.
Now with a button it's fine just to
respond to clicks, but actually with a
slider it's quite satisfying to drag
around and you can't do it.
Input the code as it is now, but doing it
is very simple.
We just create a mouse drag method and
call s.mousedrag.
And then we can drag very smoothly and
smoothly change all the values so for you
can just call any of mouse press, mouse
release, mouse drags and our user
interface for each will have equivalents.
Now let's show you one last example of
how to use multiple sliders together.
Last week you saw how to create radio
buttons which is a combination of
different buttons, a series of buttons.
You can do something very similar with
sliders where you have a set of different
sliders that, that you can interact with,
and it looks something like this.
So I can now set each of the color
channels with my background individually
so I can make it less red.
And again, it works in a quite similar
way.
We have multi slider available.
We create the multi sliders.
Just like with radio buttons, we have to
give it the number of sliders you want.
In this case, we're taking it from the
length of this string of this array of
names, and again just like radio buttons
we can set the names.
and then we display it and then we do,
mouse release to capture events, and in
here we're getting there's no longer
single gets.
We can get the value of each individual
slider, and we pass in the number of that
slider, so it's get zero.
We'll get the first slider, get one,
second get two, we'll get third.
So, that's how it works.
So, get zero we'll get the value of this
slider as I click on it
[MUSIC].