[SOUND]
So
it's week six.
And as you know we're
doing audio applications.
The thing about music and
interactive music is it's much more
accessible than it's ever been.
And now it's really quite good fun making
interactive music applications that
run on your iPhone, your iPad or
your Android devices.
Because there's so
many people who want to use them.
And I thought as well as showing
you a really easy way of
making a very,very cool scent, which is
what we're going to do in a moment, and
incorporating some of the stuff that
Matt's been talking about I thought it'd
be really good if I got
want to my friends Martin.
So come and talk to you so
yeah basically this is Martin Roth, and
he's director of research
at a company called RJDJ.
So RJDJ specialize in interactive
audio applications on mobile devices.
So yeah Martin can you tell us a little
bit about some of the applications that
you guys have made.
>> Absolutely Mick thank you.
Well our first app was back in 2008 and
we started off with the original RJDJ app.
And that was really one of the first times
anyone on a mass scale had been able to
interact with their music.
You were able to download
what we call the seen.
It was basically an interactive
user track onto you iPhone.
And then interact with it either through
the microphone or by tilting the phone
around or the accelerometer would
influence what you were listening to.
Or perhaps, we can use the internet
to find out things about what,
what was going on around you for
instance what the was like.
>> Mm-hm
>> So, you can imagine that you
were walking down the street.
And the music that you were listening to,
would change tempo,
according to how fast you were moving.
So if you were moving slowly then the
music might be, you know might also have
a relatively low tempo, it might be
a little bit relaxed, little chill.
But then if you started running not
only would the tempo pick up, but
you could also change
the energy in the music and
it would become much more energetic,
much more exciting, much more thrilling.
>> So what kind of stuff did you do?
Because I've seen some of
the earlier apps as well.
>> Yeah.
>> But you've obviously done some
quite large scale apps
that have movie tie-ins.
>> Yeah, that's right.
One of the first movie tie-in apps that
we did was called Inception, and that
came out a the end of 2010, along with,
alongside the DVD release of the film.
The Inception app worked
extremely well with the film,
because the film is all about dreams, it
was about going to dreams within dreams,
and then losing yourself a bit in this,
in the dream environment.
And certainly one thing that the kinds of,
the kinds of music that we were
making at the time, one thing that it lent
itself very well to, was a kind of dream,
psychedelic experience.
Worked incredibly well.
Some people were in fact really worried
that if they went to sleep with
this thing on then they
would never wake up.
[LAUGH] It was a real customer complaint.
[COUGH].
>> Yeah, certainly.
But since then we have also done
other movie tie-ins such as with
the Dark Knight, and there are even some
new ones coming on down the pipe line.
>> That is really cool.
So, so that's what main stream that
interactive and reactive music there.
>> Yeah, absolutely and
I think it's something that will
become even more mainstream in,
in the coming years.
The philosophy behind RJDJ
is always been that for
the last year many decades
music has been frozen.
We record music,
we import it to some medium, whether it
be vinyl, cassette, cd or these days mp3.
But once you've made the recording
of that music, it's done,
it stays like that forever.
And every time that you go back and
listen to that piece of music,
it's exactly the same.
But with the technology that we have
in the palm of our hands today,
we can do so much more.
Not only can we allow the,
the musician to give their fans all of
the different variations that they
have in mind for a piece of music, but
we can allow the fans to explore all of
those different variations themselves.
>> Right.
>> For instance,
you can imagine as with video games,
where you can go and you are driving
the plot, you are driving what happens and
you can go and explore the scene of the.
The video game developers have created.
We would like to be able to give
the same opportunity to musicians.
>> Yeah right.
It's interesting as well because
the landscapes changing isn't it
a little bit from a development
Particularly in terms of audio.
Because of the web audio API, so we're
using it as part of this Coursera program
instead of doing native coding for
audio on the, on our devices.
When you think about it,
you think it's a good step forward?
>> Oh,
absolutely I love the web audio API.
In the past we've done
everything natively of course.
We needed the performance.
But now, that the web audio API's coming
along and it's been standardized to
some degree, and it certainly seen support
across not only desk top browsers but
also mobile browsers.
>> Mm-hm.
>> It gives it gives
the developer the opportunity to
develop their audio experience once.
And truly be able to deliver it to many
platforms without having to do a lot of
work in order to adapt your code
whether your experienced to
any one particular platform.
>> Yeah, and so I think we've found it
really useful for delivering this program.
>> Mm-hm.
>> But also I think we've gotta kind of
of there's an instinct about
what's going to happen.
Now that the web audio API is there.
You can just sense this huge
amount of music interactive music,
and reactive music and
music instruments on the web.
This huge kind of number of
applications just about to spill over
>> Oh for sure.
>> it's almost as if [INAUDIBLE] yeah.
>> I would say right now people
are really experimenting,
they're trying to figure out what's
possible like through this course.
>> Mm.
>> Once people become more
comfortable with the technology, once they
understand, what can they do with it?
What are the limits?
And then once they start pushing
those limits, I'm extremely excited.
>> Yeah.
>> Extremely excited.
>> Well, that's great.
I really appreciate you coming down and
talking to us.
I know that you're very busy,
and you got to shoot off now and
talk to some other music types.
But yeah.
We are going to go through some of our
some of our web audio API kind of
based synthesis stuff now, and,
and yeah, I just kind of of,
we're just going to give you
a quick burst of what it sounds like and
then kind of, you know.
Yeah, this is the one.
So this is the app that we're
going to be talking about.
[MUSIC]
So you get the picture.
So that's what we're working on today.
>> Mick, thank you very much for
inviting me.
>> That's great.
>> You're a true musician,
gentleman and scholar.
>> [LAUGH] Yeah, well,
that's what they all say.
[MUSIC]