[SOUND].
Okay.
So as you know, we were just talking to
Martin, and he was telling us a bit about
RJDJ.
We've heard from Marko.
Marko's been telling us about how to use
sliders.
and we've also done some stuff last week
on sliders and building them and stuff.
And, you know, Matt's been doing this
stuff with you about, playing back sounds
in rhythm to a sequence.
So, what I'm doing is I'm going to show
you an application that we developed, I
just briefly touched upon with Martin.
I'm just going to I'm going to set it
running again for you.
But I want you to just kind of pay
attention to the little things I do.
As I'm doing them, I'm going to briefly
explain what they are, then I'm going to
go through the whole application in
detail.
Explain how it works.
Then we're going to discuss it with me
and Marco and Matt at the end just so
that we can make sure we've got
everything covered.
This is like a fully fledged music
application.
It's sonically quite advanced.
It's just bare minimum on the user
interface, it just has the interaction,
so you could use quite a lot of the
techniques that are in this to make your
own thing.
But let's just see what it sounds like
again and see where we, we are with it.
[MUSIC] Okay, here we are.
So you can hear we've got a drum machine.
Let's just turn the two synths down, so
we can hear these these, these drums
here.
We've got a bass drum, we got a snare
drum and you can see, I'm pointing at a
snare drum hit.
[MUSIC] That one and that one.
And there's a blue line that tracks
across telling us where in a drum beat we
are.
The second line in the drum, in the drum
machine is this.
You hear that?
That's the
[INAUDIBLE]
the clap.
So the claps going on the in between
beats in between the base and the snares.
You got a classic techno feel.
And as Matt was saying all of the sounds
we're using come straight from your
standard kind of 808 or 909 drum machine
and thereof [MUSIC] So, what else can it
do?
Well, we've got two synthesizers.
We can play these [INAUDIBLE]
synthesizers individually, and we can
vary a whole range of parameters for
them.
They're fully fledged synthesizers.
We can write waveforms for them.
If you're interested in synthesis and you
know a little about it I think you'll
find this one interesting.
But if you don't, it's still really
usable and I need you to get your head
around it.
We can write waveforms, we can add a
filter, we can change the quality of the
filter.
Now let's just have a listen to the
filters, I'm want to turn one of them up.
[MUSIC] So here's one of the synths.
I'm going to change the filter.
[MUSIC] [MUSIC] I've also got this
resonance.
And this filter out.
We could also change the release and the
attack.
So we're giving it an envelope.
And it creates that kind of acid techno
feel.
If I change the attack actually with
something like this.
[MUSIC] Just makes it quieter.
We can transpose any of the channels.
So I'll change the key of the entire
sequence.
And then again.
And then if I want [MUSIC].
You just go back to where you were, more
or less.
and also, I can add some delay.
[MUSIC] And I've got a second one here as
well.
Now, the beat that I'm altering at the
moment is the actual [MUSIC] [INAUDIBLE]
sequence of notes that it plays.
Now, I can select a sequence of high
notes, like this, or a sequence of low
notes.
And just like in the example that Matt
was showing you [INAUDIBLE] [MUSIC] Drum
machine.
There's 16 steps, so I can change two of
the notes.
There you go.
I've got the fill trap as well and I'll
do this stuff.
[MUSIC].
That's quite pleasant.
We have resonance.
[MUSIC] That's distorting quite a lot.
I don't really mind.
I can add some more delay.
[MUSIC] Add a few claps.
[MUSIC] And some more snares.
Maybe a cymbal.
[MUSIC]
You gotta take,
So that's a basic music machine.
[MUSIC] It's a common thing that you can
easily sell on the upstart for, I don't
know, actually music apps.
Let's talk about this for a minute.
Music apps go for quite a lot more money
than other kind of apps.
You can sell an app like this for much
more than three quid on the [INAUDIBLE]
on the IOS app store.
You can probably sell it for five to six
pounds or more.
Or if you're in America, that would be
dollars.
I imagine that like $8 or $9 out of
[INAUDIBLE], what is, what are pounds and
dollars anyway?
Who cares?
Anyway, they're much more expensive and
they're much more specialist but they're
still they're still really useful.
And I think something like this, I mean
as something really famous, well, there's
a really famous [UNKNOWN] app which is
built on, based on a and old-fashioned TV
R3 synthesizer and a nice [INAUDIBLE]
drum machine in which still sells in it's
droves.
And all the people do is complain about
how unusable it is.
So I'm not that worried that ours is
knocked out quite quickly.
It is knocked out quite quickly, but it
is powerful, and you can build on it to
do more interesting things.
And you could use some of the other stuff
we've done to play some loops.
By there are some complexities to this
and I want to show that you know, what
they are, so I'm going to quit this
temporarily and just go back to the basic
version before I continue with that.
Just see you can see in the most simple
possible way what it is that we're doing.
So you go all this stuff for free as I
was describing before.
as I've said every week, you know, you
can just go to your lessons.
but this time we're in week six.
Week six has got a bunch of small tests
in it.
It's got a small drum machine, and t's
got this thing called synth test.
So, we're going to have a quick look at
this synth test.
Just because it's a easier code to, to
look at.
It's got the gooey code in it.
it doesn't have the drum machine it just
has one synthesizer.
and yeah.
There you go.
It's just one of the synths.
[MUSIC] [MUSIC] Now, [COUGH] so you can
see here it's the same, and it basically
allows me to set the pitch, change the
filter, change the resonance.
Same old same old.
Let's have a look at it.
So we start off as we normally start off
by declaring a maxim context.
If I can just make this a little bigger
so you can see.
so this is what's happening on the audio.
Behind it, as, you know when Martin was
here we were talking about the web audio
api.
So, behind this is all web audio.
And the maxim js, the maxim js file,
which is here has got all of this stuff
in the background.
Now, if you're interested in this sort of
stuff, and you want to learn more about
how we built Max and JS.
You can always post questions on the
forums.
And the TAs will manage those and any
really important questions where we feel
we've got some material we can really
help you with we can point you towards a
good answer.
And also there are lots of other places
like musicdsp.com and other sites like
that can help you understand what it is
that's gone into building this.
But you don't really need to if you just
want to get started.
We just have to have a context, and Maxim
provides the context.
Also, we've got an audio file player.
Actually, we're not using that here, so
that's not going to matter.
Instead of using the audio file player,
which is what we've been using most of
the time, we're using a synth.
So, Maxim can have a synth and I've
called this Synth waveform.
Now, the thing about a synth that makes
it different to an audio file player is
you can write in an array of values
between minus 1 and 1.
And that will define the texture of the
sound which you're creating.
Now, most synthesizers have a number of
different wave forms.
And there's lot of different approaches
to creating wave forms.
Um, [COUGH] and in one of the other
examples that we've got in this folder
there's a really easy way of gyrating
wave forms but essentially, you're just
writing numbers between minus 1 and 1
into an array which is of a particular
length.
So we'll be talking about how to do that
in a moment.
So we have our synth.
It's called waveform, and we're writing a
waveform into it, which is what makes the
sound.
we've got a play head.
Now, the play head, as Matt was
describing, is, it's literally the thing
which tells us how many, how many frames
there have been.
And we use that to work out whether we
should trigger a new beat.
Okay.
So we've also got, this array called
notes, which is an integer array.
And it holds MIDI notes.
If you know about music, then you'll know
what MIDI is.
If you don't really know about music and
music technology, you've probably never
heard of it.
It's called Musical Instrument Digital
Interface.
It's a specification.
For a numbering system that relates to
musical notes and musical information.
So these MIDI notes normally what they
represent are all the keys on the
keyboard.
they're 7-bit numbers, which means that
they go for a range of 0 to 127.
There's 128 independent values, the
lower, the number, the lower, The note.
So, I'm right down the bottom end of the
piano, as you can see.
With all these numbers, zero, zero, zero.
12, 12, 12, whatever.
okay.
So, then we've got some float variables.
Fc, which is filter cutoff, resonance,
attack, and release.
And these are variables which I'm using
to control the filter cutoff resonance,
attack and release of my synth.
This is my wave table.
Excuse me.
Its an array and of float variables.
Like I said its going to be between minus
one and one and its got four five hundred
and fourteen elements.
Now the reason its got 514 elements its
kind of complicated but its because of
something called interpolate.
Very briefly what we need to do when we
create that way-, when we create a
waveform, is we need to make sure that
that waveform can playback at various
different frequencies.
So it's sound is made up of lots and lots
of different frequencies and we measure
those frequencies in repetitions per
second.
Or cycles per second, and the measurement
value we use for that is Hertz.
So for example, if I take a sound, a very
small snippet of sound and I repeat it
more than 20 times a second we actually
hear it as a pitched note, because it's
repeating so fast.
And that's what we think of, we think of
music.
Most people just think about pitched
notes.
So, in order to be able to have a, a wav
form which can be played back at 20
hertz, or at the oth- -- at the other end
of the scale 20,000 hertz, which is about
the highest, frequency that we can hear;
in fact, I can't hear 20,000 hertz.
What -- who'm I tryin' to kid?
As you get older, you can't really hear
up there.
I probably can hear about 18,000 hertz
or, if I'm on a good day, with a good
wind.
So, in order to be able to do that, to go
between a very low frequency sound and a
very high frequency sound, we need to
interpolate.
To make the interpolation work, i.e.
to make up the numbers that we need.
because that's what interpolation means.
It means we're making up numbers that
aren't there.
What, because we changed the playback
rate or the waveform, to make up those
numbers, we need some spare numbers on
the end.
So it's, normally you have a 512 point
buffer, it's called a 512 point buffer
because it's, it's, that's the number of
points that you run through to make the
sound.
But where you've got a couple of extra
points on the end, and we're using those
for interpolation.
So that's the reason why it's 514.
Okay, so there are out setup options
sorry, they're not our setup options,
they, they are basically our
declarations.
We are declaring all the objects that we
need in order to make this program work.
and then what I'm doing is I'm going into
the setup function.
I'm just declaring a size.
I'm creating a, I'm calling new on my
maxim object, and that means I'm setting
up my context.
and then I've gone [COUGH] done, done the
same thing to my wave form objects.
I'm, I'm creating new synth.
So the synth is got a, a waveform in it,
which is waiting to be populated with
something with numbers.
And it's also got all the other stuff
that we need delays, filters and that
kind of malarkey.
Then we're setting up my sliders.
This is the same as the way Marko showed
you to do his.
I've got this, which is delayed time
that's dt, dg, which is delayed amount or
delayed game.
A, which is attack.
R, which is released.
F, which is the filter cut off.
And q, which is the filter q, which is
the resonance, which is what makes it
sound, sort of acidy.
so, there are the sliders that we need.
And then I have another multi-slider,
which I'm using to enter the notes.
So you can see here, Mark has explained
to you how the multi-slider works.
SEQ is also, that's a sequence.
It's a, basically it takes an array.
It takes the array notes.
And then it, it fills that array whenever
I interact with the multislider.
Okay.
So I then, I'm loading a file which I'm
not using.
So actually [SOUND] we don't need that.
Frame rate is 30.
the frame rate is roughly the speed of
the tick rate.
Just like Matt explained.
But instead of running through those
ticks, and using them to trigger drum
sounds, although we do that in the more
advanced example.
In this example, we're just going to use
it to select A note from our note array
and use it to set a frequency for our
waveform generator.
Okay.
So, before we do any of that, we're still
in Setup.
And you see the section here that I'm
highlighting?
This is me generating a waveform.
So we know that our buffer is 414 points
long so.
We want to fill the array, which is 414
elements long with a bunch of numbers
between minus one and one.
[COUGH] Now, I'm going for a sorptive
wave here so, I actually want the
waveform to be 512 points, as I've
explained, but with a couple of extra
points for good measure.
So, what I'm doing is I'm taking the
value, I, and I'm dividing it by 512 to
make a value between zero and one.
And then I'm subtracting 0.5 to make a
value between negative 0.5 and 0.5.
Now what actually happens when I do that
is I, I make a ramp, you know, it's as
if, if you imagine that's my array, the
ramp goes up like this, so it's kind of
an inverted sawtooth wave.
And as it repeats, it drops down, goes
back to the beginning, goes up again, and
this produces a nice harmonic spectrum
that we can filter.
It's a very simple waveform, but it
creates all these harmonics And, it
pretty much creates every harmonic that
we need.
And then, we filter those harmonics out,
and add the resonance for that acid
sound.
but the values, the actual amplitude is
only for minus, naught .5 to 5.
That's absolutely fine.
It's, it's absolutely fine.
We could double it, but then we'd get
more distortion.
And you can hear that You know I'd have
to do more work balancing this out so
it's just to keep the sound within a
reaonable range.
So then I make the, the waveform and then
I add it to my synth which is called
ironically enough or confusingly enough
waveform.
So I can set the wave table size I could
set it to any amount I like that we've
already discussed it's going to be 514.
And then I load my wave table.
In.
Wave form load wave table wave table.
And then it's wave form dot play.
So, that means I've initialized my
synthesiser.
I've loaded a wave form.
I can change that at any time, any way
that I like.
So you could have 10 different wave
forms.
You could have really long wave forms.
You could take a picture of your face,
analyze all the pixels, and then use that
as a The waveform it's entirely up to you
it's just an array of numbers.
So you know be creative and then I'm
pressing play what that really means is
it's on.
So ready to rock.
In the door method we're doing the same
stuff that Marco explained.
We are [COUGH] setting up our sliders
Then we get our slider information in the
draw method.
So, if f get, basically if we get
something from the frequency slider, we
set the filter that belongs to the wave
form object.
and if we get delay time, then we set the
delay time.
Yes unless I'm munging I'm dividing it by
fifty just to get it into a decent range.
The same thing to delay gang get and to
the huge get.
A get and R get.
Lot's of good gets.
Because we are in the draw method that's
a good place to set the display.
So we display everything.
And then we do the business end, which is
ticking through the array, which has the
notes in, and using that to set the
frequencies.
So, playhead ++, every time we enter the
draw loop, we iterate the playhead.
So the tick rate is different to the rate
of actual playback.
The tick rate Is quite fast, it's 30
frames a second.
We could have 60 or 120.
it can be quite fast.
And a tick rate's normally much much
higher than the rate of the rhythm.
So what I've done is I've just said,
okay.
Well, every four ticks.
We'll say that's a semi quaver, which is
a.
Small chunk of a beat, it's a quarter of
a beat, so f play had modular four equals
equals zero just the same way Matthews
already showed you.
Wave form.ramp, we ramped a [COUGH]
knot.5 which is going to be our volume
given the attack time...
Yet.
And what that does is it means that, if
the attack time's long, it'll be a slow
ramp.
And if the attack time, attack time is
fast, it will be a short ramp.
And then, following a ramp, we set the
frequency.
Wave form set frequency.
Now, we're using this thing, m2f.
Now what this does is it takes midi notes
and turns it into frequency information.
And this is just looking up an array,
which is a maxim j s here.
So it's saying okay, if I get a, a number
zero, that's going to be a midi note of
zero.
if I get a number one, a midi note of
one, that's going to be a frequency of
8.661957, which we'll never hear.
But I generated this with an algorithm.
And I just pasted it in, because it saves
you having to worry about it.
Okay?
Then we access notes.
We get the play head modulo 4.
Sorry, play head divided by 4, modulo 16.
That's basically saying, okay.
We've had ticks, that's fine.
But this is the note we actually want.
And then we're adding 30, which is a
constant, which is just, so if it was
zero, then it would actually be 30.
So finally what we do is the next ti,
tick we release.
So immediately we release before we then
Retriever.
So if player head module [INAUDIBLE]
equals equals one we trigger the release,
and then we're off.
There are better ways of doing this, but
not using processing.
Okay, so as you can see, we've triggered
our sound, we've set the note for this
particular tick and we've released it.
For the following notes, the following
tig.
So the next thing to do is to sort out
the interaction.
When mouse pressed, what we do is, we
just get the user interface stuff, and
that handles all our mouse pressed GUI.
Dt mouse pressed, dt mouse pressed, blah.
Same thing in mouse drags so that's
useful for mouse devices.
And in mouse release we we just check one
thing.
We check to see if the notes have changed
in the array that holds all the notes.
And if they have, then we just populate
the sequence sorry, we populate the notes
array with the new sequence that's in our
sequence similty slider.
And that's what this does, so notes I,
which is the current note from 0 to 15,
so there's 16 different steps, we flaw
this value basically.
So we get the sequencing value.
And then there's a bit of [UNKNOWN] to
make sure that it's the right value and
we stick it in there, make, we basically
convert it from the slider value to a
mini value.
We could have used the map function to do
that, which would have been easier to
read.
But instead of using map, I'm just doing
it with standard mathematical operators.
Right.
Now that actually is that, is that first
test.
So let's just go back and have a look.
[MUSIC].
Yeah, that's nice.
And here's the delay time again.
[MUSIC].
[SOUND] I wanted to just talk briefly
about the filter because the filter is
quite is, I don't know, it's nice to
think about what the filter actually
does.
I've already explained that we have a
wave form and it goes at a certain rate.
It give us lots of harmonics.
And then we use the filter to block them.
But how that process occurs is kind of
interesting.
Basically what the filter does [SOUND] is
it, it lets everything through [SOUND].
Let's just get a single note [SOUND].
It lets everything through when it's wide
open.
[MUSIC] And as we drop it, what it's
actually doing [MUSIC] Is this preventing
the weight form from moving very quickly?
The filter basically is averaging
smoothing out the weight form/g.
The weight form remember is like that.
And it's going really really fast.
Lets say it's going a thousand times a
second.
And it's producing all of these harmonics
which are.
Two thousand, three thousand, four
thousand, five thousand, six thousand,
seven thousand, eight thousand, et
cetera, times per second, with an
altitude drop-off.
And that's making a very bright sound.
That's making that buzz, that nice,
buzzing sound that we, we like.
Well, I'm assuming you like that.
If you don't like that [MUSIC].
That then tough, 'cuz that's the sound it
makes.
but the thing is that when we repeat it
over and over and over again., we're,
actually, when we get to the end of the
route, and we drop down again.
That's actually quite a fast move.
And that's what creates all the
harmonics.
If we smooth that, it prevents the
harmonics from being generated, and it
smoothes Filters out that sound, so what
we're actually doing is we're averaging
the signal as it goes up, kind of.
and that's fine because it's a slow
increase, but then when we get that
sudden drop, we smooth it in the same way
we might blur an image.
And that's more or less how we turn high
frequencies down.
So, it's really simple and if you're
interested in that process.
There's a number of filters that come
bundled with the course air package that
we've put together for you.
and they run nicely on Android as well,
so you want to have a look at those,
they're in the Android package and
there's 4 or 5 of them.
And you can actually see the algorithms
if you're interested, you can have a look
at them.
Alright, so that's how the synthesiser
works.
Now, finally, what I want to do is go
back to our,
A more complex example that combines all
the bits together and just talk about how
that tinal thing wor, works.
Just a few little things that make it a
bit more useable.
so I'm going to go back to our music
machine example which is here and I'm
going to run it and what's going to
happen is.
[MUSIC] It started up straight away
[COUGH] and it's distorting beautifully
really not bad.
There's very little I have to do now all
of it [MUSIC] Make music.
Let's have some bass drums.
I do like a bit of bass drum, can you
hear the bass drum?
You can just about, let me knock this one
out.
Okay, that's good.
It's quite hard to use that.
You could have a nicer keyboard setting
or something like that.
[MUSIC] So let's have a look at what
we've done to put the main application
together.
So, we've got two synthesizers.
now there's a clever way to do this and
there's a stupid way of doing this and
just to make your life easier, I've done
it the stupid way.
instead of creating an object or a class
which is a synth although I've already
done that behind the scenes anyway.
But instead of doing that, just so it's
clear and you can see how it's done, I've
just duplicated all of the codes.
There was actually two sets.
A brighter, cleverer, more engineering
savvy method is to make another class
that encapsulates all of the sliders.
And then just to create one of those
objects and to say where you want Where
to put it, so that's something we should
have a look at.
There's a good example in all of the
current examples that we've given you,
there are good examples of classes, and
you should have a look at that those.
But I didn't want to do that and find
that no-, that some of you didn't really
understand that whole process.
So I've just gone through and I've
duplicated all of that code.
So basic stuff is I thought well I want
it to look slightly better than it
currently looks so I've created a brushed
metal background.
I've positioned all the sliders on the
screen and then I've created this brushed
metal background and you see that this is
a good tip.
If you can avoid havong to draw
Non-animated information.
via algorithmic methods, i.e.
if you can avoid having to apply the
interface graphics, do avoid it.
Make a Photoshop image that has your
interface.
So I've got a slightly embossed area here
and here which these are the panels that
hold the information and if I spent more
time on that I can make them look really
nice and I've fake knobs and switches
that I copied and pasted of the Internet.
Or I could photograph my something from
my set connection and then put those on
them instead.
but I guess what I'm trying to say is you
can do an awful lot by preparing your
images in Photoshop just like we did last
week with the instaspan for the overlay.
It's the same sort of thing.
put the effort in there if it's not
going to animate.
Put the effort in in Photoshop, make it
look sweet, and then draw it.
I must admit I've not really put the
effort in here, but there's a back,
there's a basic starting point.
You can see where the panels are; they're
sort of lined up.
Another thing you can do is you can put
your interactive graphic elements Onto
your screen so that you do that
problematically then you screenshot it
the right size and move that into your
Photoshop application and then you can
draw on top of it.
I guess it's what I'm saying is do the
work in Photoshop is you're not going to
have to animate it make it look nice
there.
We did exactly did the same thing with
angry droids as well we just Do a bit of
support work there.
So that's the basic idea, and you can get
away with a lot there.
also it's nice to add custom graphics to
your sliders, and you can do that too.
So, we've done that.
And then we've loaded it in here.
And then we've done the same thing, exact
same thing that Matt did for the drum
track.
We created four Boolean arrays.
Track, 1, 2, 3, and 4.
These are for our four drum sounds that
were in our drum machine, which is a
kick, a snare, a handclap, and a cymbal.
Ideally, I'd have a hi hat.
There is a hi hat knocking around in one
of the, folders on the Coursera pack that
you've got.
And you can see here, exactly as I said,
I just duplicated everything.
So there's the floats that you've already
seen.
Except we've added another function,
filter attack, which is what gives it
that sort of TB 303 baseline sound.
[LAUGH] allegedly.
And then we've got, some transpose
functions as well, which allows us to
move it around.
We've got a second wave table for the
second object.
You can see we've got two syns waveform
and waveform two.
And now these are all basically
everything that has a two after it is for
the second waveform.
We create a bunch of secondary slide and
sliders and multi-sliders to hold all the
separate information and then we load in
some samples.
And then we set up a sliders, so we have
twice as many sliders.
But they have slightly different numbers
in to re, to represent the fact that
they're going to be drawn somewhere else.
Now as I said, you would draw them,
screen shot it, import it into Photoshop,
do your background, and then just load
the background.
Now so we load the background where do I
load the background.
Into the bottom of this.
that's the wavetable, exactly the same
way as I described in the first example.
Okay the background is loaded, there it
is, brushed metal, that's my brushed
metal background.
and then here, what I do is I set up the
drum tracks in the same way that Matt's
already explained.
I just create these boolean arrays,
they're either true or false.
And I set them all to false, so they're
all off.
Okay, and then we get all the information
in exactly the same way, as we did
before.
And then we use the same playHead
information to get the frequency content
for both synthesizers.
And then we use another variable, current
b, so we could use playHead if we're
using current b too.
It doesn't really matter, it's the same.
To find out whether it's if it's true
basically, then what we do is [COUGH] we
play that drum sound back.
the mass press stuff is exactly the same,
if you click there it sets it And, you've
set it to play.
in both mouse press and mouse drags.
And other than that, it's exactly the
same as the two examples you've seen.
The basic synth example, and the drum
example.
And that's how you end up with this.
[MUSIC].
[MUSIC]