[BLANK AUDIO].
[SOUND].
I have to say that sounds really good.
I'm the one here who isn't a musician, so
I can't say much about it, but Matt what
is it about that synth that makes it
sound well?
>> He doesn't care.
>> He doesn't care, he's playing.
I'm not going to, you know, I'm not
going to say anything.
>> I just love this mate, I think it's
amazing.
>> Cool.
>> so we've given you something great
here.
You, you really need to, to, to work on
this, and, and make it into something
individual to put your own sounds in
there.
To, to see if you can experiment with,
with the length of the sequences.
>> Yeah.
And you can stick your own waveforms in.
You can change all the sequence lengths.
You could do a proper GUI rather than
that bleak affair.
I quite like it bleak.
It's all post-nuclear TV 303.
>> You might, you might try and make it
like like a vintage drum machine.
You could get, get an image of a vintage
drum machine as you saw in my slides and
you could put that behind it, put the
buttons on top.
There's all kinds of stuff you can do,
you know, you can really get creative
with this.
>> Remember you can use images for the
buttons, so that's an easy thing to do.
>> Yeah, the I quite like the filter,
the thing about the web audio equalizer,
it has a really, really nice filter.
And I want us to get in.
>> Okay, come on then.
So, this is really taking me back.
I mean it's, you know.
>> [LAUGH].
It's that kind of where's it gone?
Where's the sound gone?
>> It's right here.
It's right here.
>> Oh, there we go.
Yeah.
[SOUND].
It's just that filter cut off thing, and
with the envelope.
Well, that's neat.
>> We can really, we can really dig
around and get into that kind of
[UNKOWN].
>> So, that's it for Digital Media and
Mobile Applications.
And we've been teaching you how to do
creative programming.
We've tried to make it as easy for you to
get started as possible, regardless of
your background.
And give you lots of opportunities to
develop your skills both creatively and
also technically.
You know, we've created a bunch of
programming, languages and libraries.
Well, not languages as such, just
libraries that make it easier for you to
do the things that you want to do.
and I think that's been quite good.
It's been successful.
They've got a physics engine, they've got
a music engine, they've got, what else
have they got?
They've got Facebook stuff.
All this different stuff.
And you can just go away.
And if you're interested in following
this up and doing some more, but you feel
like you want to do some if you, well,
let's say you want to be more creative,
at [UNKNOWN].
We run a digital loss computing program
which is a combination with the arts
department.
that's [UNKNOWN] art department so that
program is kicking off right now and you
apply for that more or less in the next
couple of months.
>> we also have a Master's program in
Computational Arts, and a Master's in
Fine Art and Computational Arts, if
you're more creative.
We also have a BSC in Creative Computing
as well, don't we, Marco?
>> Yeah.
That's running in London, but it's also
running internationally as part of the
University of London International
Programs.
>> Yes.
>> So, wherever you are, you can
actually take that program.
>> Yeah, and this is a good starting
off point plan.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> And that's really what it's been
about.
Thank you very much for still being here
through all of the coding help.
And but, actually, you know what?
It's exciting when it works and that's
what makes it worthwhile.
>> Yeah, and this is so much great
stuff, just combine together all of the
stuff we have shown you like mix it up,
figure out what new things you can do
with all the taught we have given you.
>> And then, send it to us, because we
want to see.
>> Yeah.
>> We really want to see what you're
doing.
>> We'd love to see what you're doing.
And we want to hear some more music.
Matt, do you got anything.
>> Yeah, music.
[MUSIC].
Matt's actually very, very good at synth
stuff.
I built this for you, it's true.
>> I just love this, it's brilliant,
brilliant work.
Have fun.
[MUSIC].