[MUSIC] So, I get a number like the
square root of two.
And square root of two is irrational.
So, how am I going to figure out what
it's approximately equal to?
Well, it turns out that it's
approximately, you know, 1.414 and a bit
more.
But how would ever figure that out?
How would I know that that's
approximately the value of the square
root of two?
Let's use the intermediate value theorem
to try to pull it.
I want to use the intermediate value
theorem to approximate the square root of
two.
To do that, I'm going to use this
function,
f(x) = x^2 - 2.
Notice something about this function.
This function is equal to zero when x is
the square root of 2.
And how is that?
f of the square root of 2 is the squared
of two squared, which is two, minus two,
which is zero.
So, if I'm trying to approximate the
square root of 2, what I'm going to think
about this, is that I'm going to look for
a positive value, that I can plug into
this function to make it a square root of
zero.
How am I going to find such a value?
You know, the other good thing about this
function is that it's continuous.
And then, I can plug in some values, like
f(1).
Now, what's f(1)?
It's one squared minus two and that's
minus one.
And I can plot that on my graph right
here, and it's this point right here.
And take a look at, say, f(2).
f(2) would be two squared minus two,
which is two.
And I can plot that on my graph, right
here.
It's 2,
2.
Now, f is a continuous function and at
one, it's negative.
And at two, it's positive.
So, it's a continuous function.
It's negative at one and it's positive at
two.
By the intermediate value theorem, there
must be a point in between when the
functions value is equal to zero.
And you can see that on the graph.
We're looking for that point.
That is the square root of two where this
graph crosses the x-axis,
the positive x-axis.
And that's the point that we're looking
for,
right?
The intermediate value theorem promises
me there's a value in between where the
functions value equals zero.
And I can see that there must be such a
point on the graph.
And now, I know that that value is
between one and two.
And I can do better.
I can cut this interval between one and
two in half and I get that f(1.5).
Well, 1.5 squared is 2.25 - 2 is 0.25.
[SOUND] Alright.
So, that's, say, this point on my graph.
Now, what do I know?
I know that the squared of two, which is
where this graph crosses the x-axis, is
between one, where the function is
negative and 1.5, where the function is
positive.
And I can do better,
alright?
I can pick some other point.
Let's be brave and pick 1.4.
And if I plug in 1.4, well, 14 squared is
196.
So, 1.4 squared is 1.96 - 2,
that makes this -0.4,
alright?
This is barely below the x-axis.
And I can plot that point here.
And now, I know that the square root of
two, the positive input to this function,
which is equal to zero,
well, it must be between 1.4 and 1.5.
Because the function's value at 1.4 is
negative and the function's value at 1.5
is positive.
So, this is not so bad.
I mean, we, we could do this with a few
calculations on the blackboard.
Let's, let's bring out some sort of
computation device so we can try to get
an even better approximation to the
square root of two.
So here, I've got a function.
The function is f(x) = x^2 - 2.
And you can see that if I plug zero into
the function, I get out -2 because 0^2 -
2 is -2.
Now, this is a physical function.
I've got this knob here. And as I spin
this knob, the function's input value
changes.
So, for example, if I spin it up to
f(05.), f(1/2), that's negative 1.75 and
that's right because if I take a half
squared, I get a quarter, and a quarter
minus two is -1.75.
Now, I could spin the input up to one.
f(1) is -1 = because 1^2 - 2 is -1 or
f(1.5), well, 1.5 squared is 2.25, 2.25 -
1 is 0.25.
Now, this is positive or I could wheel it
back down a little bit.
And I see that when I get to 1.41, the
function's output is negative again.
Then, I could increase the function's
input a bit.
Oh, now the function's output is positive
again, at f(1.145).
And then, I could decrease the value a
little bit.
Oh,
now, the function's output value is
negative again and that would increase
the output value a little bit.
Oh,
now, the function's output is positive
and I could decrease the input a bit.
Now, the function's output is negative,
could increase the input a little bit.
Now, it's positive, could decrease the
input a little bit.
Now, it's negative again.
Now, Look at what happened,
right?
What's going on?
I'm looking at the function f(x) = x^2 -
2 and I'm walking back and forth across
the point where this function is equal to
zero.
And as I walk to the left and to the
right, the function is positive and the
function is negative.
And I'm getting closer and closer to a,
to the actual place where the function is
equal to zero and what is 1.41421356?
It's awfully close to the square root of
two.
And if you think the square root of two
and square it and subtract two, you get
zero.
What we just saw with the knob that I was
turning is actually an incredibly general
technique for figuring out where a
continuous function crosses the x-axis.
And we can do it very efficiently.
Let's take a look at how we might do this
a little bit more carefully.
Here, I've drawn a graph with some random
looking continuous function and I've
labeled some points along the x-axis.
Imagine that we couldn't see this whole
graph.
Just imagine that the only thing you can
do is interrogate this function.
You can ask this function at some input
point, are you positive or negative?
We're trying to figure out where,
approximately, this continuous function
crosses the x-axis.
We're looking for a zero of this
continuous function.
How might the game begin?
I'll let it begin by asking the function,
are you positive or negative at zero?
And the function is positive at zero.
And then, maybe I'd ask at sixteen.
At sixteen, is this function positive or
negative?
And I'd see the function is negative.
The function's value is negative at
sixteen.
Because it's a continuous function and
the function's value at zero is positive
and the function's value at sixteen is
negative, I know that there's a zero in
between.
There's some point in between that if I
plug it into the function, I get zero
out.
Now, I could cut that interval in half.
I could plug in eight and I could ask the
function at f(8), are you positive or
negative?
And the function f(8), the value of the
function at eight is positive.
Now, look.
I know the function's value at eight is
positive, the function's value at sixteen
is negative.
So, by the Intermediate Value Theorem,
there must be a value in between, right
there, where the function's value is
zero.
And now, I could take that interval and
cut it in half again.
I could take a look at twelve, which is
exactly between eight and sixteen.
And I could ask the function, at
f(12),12), are you positive or negative?
And the function's value at twelve is
negative.
[SOUND] So now, I know by the
intermediate Value Theorem, the function
zero zero of this function must land
between eight and twelve and I could cut
that interval in half again.
I could look at ten, and I could ask the
function,
well, if I plug in ten, are you positive
or negative?
And the function's value with ten is
negative.
And now, I know that the zero must land
between eight and ten, because the
function's value at eight is positive and
the function's value at ten is negative,
so there must be a zero in between, a
point where the function's value is equal
to zero.
Now, I could cut that interval between
eight and ten in half again.
I could look at nine. And I could ask the
function, at nine, are you positive or
negative? And if I plug in nine, it looks
like the function is positive.
And that means that a value that I can
plug into the function to make the output
zero lies between nine and ten.
And this is really quite remarkable.
I, I, I could cut the interval between
nine and ten and half again and see if it
was between nine and 9.5 or 9.5 and ten.
And I could keep doing this every time
I'm getting a little bit more precision
as to the exact value of the input that
would make the function zero.
The other really neat thing about this is
that I could have just tried all of the
values between zero and sixteen.
I could have plugged all seventeen of
those numbers into the function to figure
this out. But by doing this clever
cutting in half method, this bisection
method, I managed to only ask six
questions,
right?
I asked the function's value at zero and
sixteen, at eight and twelve, at ten and
at nine, and by only asking six
questions, I was able to narrow down a
region where a zero resided.
Now, that's pretty quite efficient, much
better than asking seventeen questions.
So, this is a very general technique for
figuring out where zeroes of continuous
functions lie.
And I encourage you to pick your favorite
function and see if you can approximate a
root, a zero of that function.
[MUSIC]