[MUSIC]
Armed with the fundamental theorem of
calculus.
We can no evaluate definite integrals,
just, by taking antiderivatives.
[LAUGH] Of course, just, is really
overstating it a little bit.
It can be quite difficult to find an
antiderivative.
And the trouble is that it's hard to run
our differentiation rules in reverse.
And remember a long, long time ago, we
learned about the chain rule.
And if you take the chain rule, and you
run it in reverse, you get u substitution.
The difficulty though, is you know, when
you're doing u substitution, you
gotta make a choice for u, and that can be
pretty hard.
Well now, we want to do the same kind of
game with other differentiation rules.
I want to take the product rule, and run
the product rule in reverse.
We're going to call that integration by
parts and,
by being clever, we'll be able to evaluate
a
ton more integrals by doing them, by
parts,
by using the product rule in reverse on
them.
And one of those cool integrals that we'll
be able
to evaluate, our integrals of powers of
sines and cosines.
And I think maybe it sounds a little bit
dry.
But I think it's actually pretty fun to
see how we can do, these very fearsome
looking integrals, with just a little bit
of help from the product rule.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]