[MUSIC]
Now, where are we in this course?
Well, a long, long time ago, we were
looking at limits, right?
And we first studied the, the concept of
the
limit, and we learned how to compute with
limits.
And then went into application of limits,
which
was limits of difference quotients, which
was the derivative.
And we studied some of the concepts of the
derivative.
What is the derivative telling us about a
function?
And then we've been studying a turn of
techniques for computing derivatives.
And we learned about the product rule, the
quotient rule, the chain rule.
Derivatives of some special functions like
e to the x, log x, sines and cosines.
Where does that leave us?
We've studied the concepts we've studied
some of the computations.
Now we're going to study applications.
Why would anyone care about derivatives in
the first place?
Right, what's the real world pay off?
There's a couple applications I want to
look at now.
One of those applications is just back to
limits.
If you want to calculate limits.
Turns out, sometimes you can use
derivatives to calculate limits.
That's the story of lopital's rule.
But the second application this week is
much more exciting.
It's related rates.
All the time in the real world, you've got
equations between different quantities.
And maybe you know how one of those
quantities is changing, well, if you start
with that equation and you differentiate
it, that
gives you some relationship between the
rates, right?
The derivative of that equation will tell
you how one's things
rate of change is related to something
else's rate of change.
And by translating sort of story problems,
sort of real world scenarios.
Into equations, and then differentiating
those equations.
We can learn, about the relationships
between these different rates of change.
That's the story of related rates.
We're going to do a turn of the examples
of those, right now
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]