[SOUND] Hello, welcome back to the video
lectures on web connectivity and
security in cyber physical systems.
In this video lecture, we are going to
learn how two parties that don't know each
other previously can share a secret
through a public medium like the Internet.
The shared secret could be and
often is the encryption key of
a symmetric key cipher system.
The Diffie-Hellman key exchange algorithm
was published in 1976 as one of
the first public key protocols for
securely exchanging cryptographic
keys over public networks.
The algorithm is based on
the concept of discrete logarithms.
Diffie-Hellman is not an actual
encryption algorithm,
meaning that it's not used to protect
data transfer between two parties.
Let's explore how
the Diffie-Hellman protocol works.
Suppose that Alice and Bob don't know
each other and they would like to share
an encryption key of a symmetric cipher in
order to initiate secure communication.
To do this, first, Alice and
Bob have to agree on two numbers,
a sufficiently large prime number p and
a base generator g,
which is a primitive root modulo P.
Alice chooses a secret number or key a and
computes her public result, capital A,
as g to the power of a mod p and
sends it to Bob.
Bob also chooses a secret number or
key b and
computes his public results,
capital B, as g
to the power of b mod P and
sends it to Alice.
At this point,
a potential attacker may intercept
their communication and
get the public results A and B.
He might also capture p and g when Alice
and Bob are agreeing on these numbers.
Now, Alice computes a shared secret S1
with her secret key a as B
to the power of a mod p.
And, likewise,
Bob computes a shared secret S2 with
his secret key b as A to
the power of b mod p.
It can be mathematically proven that
S1 and S2 actually have the same value.
This shared number is Alice's and
Bob's shared secret and
can be used as an encryption
key of a symmetric cipher.
Because the attacker doesn't
know the secret keys a and b,
he will not be able to
compute the shared secret.
We just learned how Diffie-Hellman
is implemented mathematically.
Let's have a simpler example in order
to demonstrate how the protocol works.
Suppose Alice and
Bob know a common color yellow.
Alice chooses pink color and Bob chooses
green color as their secret colors.
Alice mixes her secret color with
the common color and produces a new color.
Bob also does the same.
They exchange the new colors.
Now they mix the new colors with
their secret colors and produce yet
another color.
Since the final color on each side is made
of the same combination of three colors,
yellow, pink and green,
it is identical on both sides.
So, Alice and Bob ended up with the same
final color without revealing their
own secret colors to each other.
As you can see on the screen,
the same thing happens mathematically.
The final values computed on each
side are actually identical.
Diffie-Hellman is one of the most
powerful security protocols and
is therefore still widely
used in many applications.
For resource constraint devices,
the Diffie-Hellman protocol can be
implemented using elliptic
curve cryptography.
If you are interested to learn more about
lightweight Diffie-Hellman protocols,
you can search on the web for
elliptic curve Diffie-Hellman.
You will find many useful
tutorials on this topic.
In this video lecture,
we saw how the Diffie-Hellman protocol
is used to share secret information.
In the next lesson, we will learn
how to establish a public key
crypto system to secure
digital communication.
[SOUND]