Welcome to module three of control of
mobile robots. what we're going to do in
this module is try to be a little more
systematic in how we think of our design
choices and how we actually Model the
systems that we're dealing with. So, so
far in module one we did some basic
control theory. We developed PID
regulators. we could do some rather
elegant things, but we really didn't know
Why anything worked. And in module 2 we
started talking about robots and some of
the more standard robot models we're going
to use, what abstractions are useful for
thinking about sensing modalities, and how
do the robots know where they are. so what
we're going to do in this module is
actually take a step back and start to
revisit some of the things we did. And
what we need to do first of all is develop
a Model class that is rich enough in the
sense that it's quiet general and it will
catch and capture a lot of different
robotic systems that we're interested in.
But it has to be simple enough so that we
can actually say things about it because,
you know, very complicated models don't
really give us anything because we have no
effective ways of interacting with them.
the model also needs to be expressive
enough and relevant enough, and what I
mean about With that is, it has to capture
the aspect of the systems that we're
interested in, in a way that matters and
actually translate into the actual systems
doing what they're supposed to be doing.
Because one thing to remember is that
models are always approximations, adn you
want to make suere that you, the things
that you don't fully model. Don't matter
so much. And what we're going to do is
we're going to go into the wonderful world
of linear systems. So, linear systems are
particularly effective and compact, and
well behaved system representations of
dynamical systems. So let's start with
what I want to call the world's easiest
and simplest robot. This is a point mass.
So what it is, is that it's just a mass.
On a line and I can immediately control
the acceleratio n. So if you start
controlling but p is the position of the
robot then acceleration which is the
second derivative of the position is just
p double dot is equal to u. Now we won't
actually like to write it in this way, we
don't want the double dots, we don't want
to have. P is for positions and then we're
controlling something else. We have new
variables. So, we want to come up with a
compact/general form that captures what we
want but somehow glosses over the, the,
the minor details of what separates a
point mass robot from a. Humanoid robot,
say. So the way to do this is to introduce
some new variables. And I'm going to
introduce in this case two variables. The
first one I'm going to call x1 and simply
say that that's the position. So x1 is the
position of the robot. And then I'm going
to say that x2 is the velocity of the
robot. And if I do that, I can actually
write down the derivatives. The dynamic's
of these new variables. So x1 dot, well,
we have x1 dot is equal to p dot but p dot
was equal to x2. So, x1 dot is simply
equal to x2. X2 dot is P double dot,
right? So X2 dot is P double dot, which we
have up here, which equal to U. So X2 dot
is simply equal to U. So this is a slight
reformulation that so far doesn't seem to
buy us anything. But what we can do is we
can actually We put now this system on
what's call state's based form. And the
state of the system is going to be our
excess. So I'm simply going to lump x1 and
x2 into a new variable that I'm going to
call x, and now note that this is actually
a 2-dimensional object. And then what I'm
going to do is I'm going to talk about the
dynamics of this 2-dimensional object. So
x dot is x1 dot, x2 dot and we know that
x1 dot was x2 and x2 dot was u. So I can
simply write x dot is this x2 u vector.
Well it gets even better because if I have
a matrix. If I have x1 x2 there and I
multiply this by 2 by 2 matrix, let's say
that I would like to get out x2, well what
do I have to multiply x1 and x2 with?
Well, this is zero times x1 so I'm going
to write 0 here and 1 times x2. Is going
to give me that, right. So what I am going
to do is simply write this as a matrix, so
x dot is zero times x1 and 1 times x2 and
x2 dot is simply u, so its zero times x1
and zero times x2 but we get one u out of
it so I am now rewritten my dynamics using
these matrices, which may or may not look
easier. But trust me, it actually will be
much easier. Moreover, the thing we care
about in this case would be x1. So, I'm
going to take the output of the system to
be x1. And, I can also write this as a
matrix. In this case it's a it's role
vector times x. This simply means that I
get one of x1, and zero of x2. So, I have
now re-writ them, everything in a much
more, I'm going to claim compact form,
using these matrices. So, to summarize, on
state space form x dot is this thing, And
x and y. Sorry.
The output is this thing. Now, if I
introduce some matrices. I'm going to call
this thing my a matrix. I'm going to call
this thing my b matrix. And this thing my
c matrix. Then, all of a sudden, I can
write everything like this. x dot is ax
plus bu, y is cx. And now we've hidden all
the particulars of the model inside this
a, b, and c matrices. But this is a very.
General way of writting systems so this in
fact clearly deserves one of these
sweethearts because what we have done is
to take a system that was really
particular and written it in a very
general form involving these system
matrisis and to make sure that we believe
this is in fact generally usefull let's
consider 2-dimensional point mass now.
Where, what I can do, is I can move in
both the x and y directions say. So, the
position is going to be the x and y
position, the input is my acceleration in
the x and y direction. And then the
dynamics of course is p double dot x is
ux, which means my acceleration, my
accelerating in the x direction with the
my ux input, and similarly for my, My y
direction. Well, now we need to do the
same thing. So I'm going to introduce a
bunch of new variabl es.
So x1 is px. x2 is p.x. As I said before.
But now I'm introducing 2 more. X3 is py,
and x4 is p.y. I have two inputs and two
outputs. So if I do this. I can actually
write this new system, also using a b and
c matrixes. So if you take a look at this
a matrix, up here in this corner is the
old a matrix that we had for a 1D
point-mass. Well this is just the x
component of the a matrix. And this would
be the y component. Similarly b, this is
my old b Now I have two copies of it. And
for C, this is my old C. Now I have a copy
of it. So with this choice of A, B and C
matrices, voila. I can write the same Or
that this system on exactly the same form
X dot is Ax + Bu. Y is Cx.
And one thing that I'm going to encourage
you to do is make sure that you go through
the matrix multiplications here and
convince yourself that this choice of a,
b, and c matrixes is actually corresponds
to the original dynamics that we had up
here. but the point that I really want to
make with all this is You know what, x dot
is Ax plus Bu, y is Cx, is a very general
way of writing down, the system dynamics
that you have. And in fact, this is what's
called an LTI system. Linear time
invariant system on state space form, and
we're going to see this a, b, and c.
triple quite a lot in this course, because
they will show up over and over again. And
they will allow us to be general about how
we reason about our systems. And then
we're going to hide the particulars of the
dynamics inside the a, b, and c matrices.
Before we move on to the next lecture
we're actually going to see a little bit
more where these models come from. Let's
say a few words though about the
dimensions of what we have here. If x is
an n dimensional vector so it's a Rn for
the point mass on the line x is
2-dimensional or a 2D point where we
control exploration x was 4-dimensional.
Anyway, x is in Rn, then A is an n by n
matrix. If U is in Rm, meaning we have an
m dimensional inputs, then V is going to
be an n by m matrix. And similarly if the
output is p dimensional, meaning we're
sucking out p different things from our
system, then the C matrix is a. P by n
matrix. And the reason this is right. you
can see that if you actually write down
the equation. X dot is Ax plus Bu. Well, x
dot has to have the same dimension as x.
So it has to be n by one. Now, I know that
a is n by n. And x is n by one. Whenever
you have matrix multiplication like that.
The first thing is that these numbers have
to be the same otherwise you cannot do
this multiplication. So you have to make
sure these are the same. And when you end
up with n at the end, it's an n by one or
n pieces here Which means that ax actually
becomes and n by one factor. Which is what
we need, right? Because x dot n by one.
Similarly with b, b is n by m And you u is
m by one, well these things cancel out
that they should and we end up with
something that's n by one. If you look at
y similarly, y is p by one, well is p bt n
and x is n by one. These guys cancel out,
and what we end up with is a P by one
vector. And, it's important that the
dimensions lineup. So, as a sanity check,
we're always going to be forced to insure
that the things that we build, have the
right dimensions. And, if they don't have
these dimensions, then what we write down
is actually nonsense, and we can't perform
these multiplications. Okay, that
concludes the first lecture on linear
systems. And in the next lecture, we're
going to see a little bit more where these
systems actually come from.