In this lecture, we're going to, dig a
little bit deeper into the original non
linear models. And see, how do we produce
linear models from them? And in fact, I
have a wonderful quote here. That says,
classifying systems as linear and non
linear is like classifying objects in the
universe. As bananas and non-bananas. What
this means is that if you're walking
around in the universe, let's say your'e
on Jupiter and you pick up something,
chances are it ain't going to be a banana.
Similarly, if you walk around and you pick
up a system or a robot, chances are it
ain't going to be linear. What that means
is that linear systems are really, really
rare. Yet, here I am, two lectures ago,
bragging about how useful they are. So
something's gotta give here. And what it
is, is that the non linear systems that
are everywhere. They act very much linear,
at least around operating points. So the
linearization is a way of producing linear
models from non linear models. Or
producing bananas from non-bananas, if you
want. So what we're going to do in this
lecture is. Produce Linearizations or
linear models from the non-linear models
that we start with. So, here is a general
non-linear model . So, x dot is now not a
x plus bu with some general function f of
x and u, and similarly y is not a simple
plus in cx, it's a non-linear function h
of x. Okay.
So now, what we would like to do, is we
would like to find some kind of local
description of what this system is doing.
And this local description needs to be
linear, and what I mean by local, is that
we have to pick an operating point. In the
pendulum we said, let's assume that the
pendulum is hanging very close to straight
down, so straight down is the operating
point and then what we do is we are going
to have to define a new variable. So,
let's say that this is my operating point.
This in the pendulum case would be, the
angle is zero, and I have no control
input. Well then, my actual state is going
to be the operating point, plus some small
deviation in this state. Similarly my
control input is going to be, well the
nominal operating Input point plus a small
deviation. And, what we would like to do
somehow is describe these small
variations. And in fact, the new equations
of motion that we care about well, we're
going to care about how Delta x. This
deviation from the operating point
behaves. Well, delta x is x minus x
operating point. Right? So delta x dot is
x dot minus xl dot. Well, this thing is
equal to zero, because it's a constant,
right? So this is just zero. So, here's my
zero. So, delta x dot is the same. As x
dot. Well, I know what x dot is, it's
this. So, now delta x dot becomes this.
Okay, let's see if we somehow can simplify
this. So this is my model, now luckily for
me there's is something known as a tail or
expansion that's allows me to write this
On a simpler form. So this thing can be
written as f evaluated at the operating
point, times this partial derivative of f
with respect to x, also evaluated at the
operating point, this is known as . And
then, you have the same partial
derivative, but now with respect to u,
evaluated at the operating points. And, we
multiply this with Delta u here, and delta
x here. And then I have something that I
call HOT, which stands for higher order
terms. So this is where, we're saying that
the higher order terms. Where, when delta
x and delta u become large, these matter.
But for small delta x and delta u, they
really don't matter. Well why is this
useful? Well, first of all lets assume
that we have picked operating points, so
that f of x0, u0 is zero which that we're
holding the state steady, x dot is zero at
this point which means that this thing
goes away. Now.
Let's call these guys A and B. Why is
that? Well, these are just matrices
because I'm plugging in some constant
value here. Similarly then I'm plugging in
a constant value. So, these partial
derivatives are just matrices. Well, let's
call them A and B. And now let's do the
same thing with Y. Y was the output. We
want to kn ow what it looks like around
this operating point. Well, we have the
same thing here, plus this term, plus high
order terms. So, let's assume that thing
is zero, so let's assume that we pick an
operating point that kills the output at
that operating point. So, the output is
zero at that point. Well, then, let's call
this thing c. Right? Now I have a, b, and
c. And in fact, let's summarize what we
just did. If I have this non-liner model,
and I pick an operating point, so that
these two assumptions are satisfied. And
then I look at small deviations from the
operating point. Then I can write delta x
dot. That's a delta x plus b delta u.
Which is linear. And y is c delta x, where
these a, b, and c matrices are given by
these partial derivatives, also known as
Jacobians. So this, ladies and gentlemen,
is how you obtain linear models from non
linear systems. Well, let's actually do
some computations here, just to know
what's going on. So let's assume that x is
in Rm. u is an Rm, y is an Rp and we have
f and a being given by these things, but
really what we have is f1 over x or is
actually a function of x1 to xn of u1 to
up right, no sorry Alright.
So when I just write f1, that's what's a
really mean. Okay.
Then, df, dx. This Jacobian that we talked
about. The first one we need. Well, it has
this form. First component is the
derivative of f1, with respect to x1. Then
it's f1 with respect to x2, and so forth.
And the reason why I'm writing this is not
because I enjoy producing complicated
PowerPoint slides. It's just, we need to
know what the different entries are. And
it's important to do this right because
otherwise your dimensions don't line up
when you produce your A, B, and C
matrices. So that's df dx or, as we now
know it, A. This is my A matrix. Well,
similarly, B is df du, right? And again,
the first component is df1 du1. This
component is the f1, the Here, we have the
f and the u1. All the way to the f and the
So this is a n by m matrix, which is what
we needed. And, in fact , this is the b
matrix, then. So it has the right
dimension. And not surprisingly, we do the
same thing for our c matrix. and the
reason again I wanted to show this is,
this is where the Jacobians come from. So
if I write dhdx, this is what I mean.
Good.
Let's do some examples. So let's start
with what's known as the inverted
pendulum, which is a slightly more
complicated pendulum where what I have is,
I have a moving base, my elbow in this
case. And then I have a pendulum pointing
straight up. Or with some angle, and by
moving the base, the pendulum is going to
swing, and in fact, it's going to fall if
I don't do anything very clever. But the
dynamics of this can be written like this,
where theta double dot is g over l sin
theta plus u cos theta. Okay.
Let's linearize this thing. the first
thing we do is we pick our stakes. In this
case it's going to be theta and theta dot.
And the reason I know that I have a
2-dimensional system is I have two dot's
up here. So, I have a 2-dimensional
system, x1 is theta and x2 is theta dot.
Let's say they're measuring the angles, so
y is x1. Well, then I get my f to be this
two vector. And I get my h of x to be x1.
Okay, fine.
Let's pick the operating point where the
pendulum is pointing straight up, and I'm
doing nothing. And in that case, well,
what is my a matrix? My a matrix becomes
df1, dx1. So now I have to take the
derivative of this thing here, with
respect to x1. There is no x1 there, so.
The first component is zero. Then I have
to take the derivative of this thing with
respect to x2, which is 1. So this
component is 1. Similarly, I have to take
the derivative of f2, with respect to x1.
So now, I have to take derivative of this
guy here with respect to x1. Well, the
derivative of this with respect to x1 is.
g over l times sine. The derivative of
that is going to be g over l times cosine
x1. While the derivative of this, with
respect to x1 is actually going to be
negative u, sine x1. But I didn't actually
write this here, even though I should
have. Arguably.
Because what I'm going to do is I'm going
to evaluate this at the operating point.
And you know what? U is zero. And in fact,
x1 is zero. So this term actually goes
away. So all I'm left with is this term,
evaluated at zero, zero. And cosine zero
is 1. So after all these pushups, I end up
with g over l here, as the known zero
term. Now, that's how you get the A
matrix. Again, I would encourage you to go
home, and thus your already home when you
are watching this and actually perform
these computations so you know where they
come from. Similarly B, you have to do the
same computation and in this case you have
no U up here, so you don't get a U in the
first component. Here you have U cosine
x1. Take a derivative of that with respect
to U. We get cosine x1. We plug in the
operating point, zero, zero. And wind up
with this elegant b vec-, b vector here. C
is particularly simple, right? Because h
of x is x1. Which means that c is simply
1, 0. So.
That was how we would go about getting
these a, b, and c matrices. Okay, lets go
to the unicycle the differental drive
robot that we have looked at that we saw
in the previous lecture that we had a
little bit of an issue with. first of all
lets figure out the state. Let's say that
x1 x now I'm having in the slight abuse of
n notation right because x is also the
full statement. But this is the x
component, x2 is y and x3 is theta and
then lets say that we're actually
measuring everything. So y is this. Okay
We can control the translational velocity,
or the speed and the angular velocity,
right? So my inputs would be u1 is v, and
u2 is omega. Okay.
Let's compute, now, the linearization
around x, operating point to zero. U,
operating point is zero. Okay.
If you do that, what you actually end up
with, and I'm not going to show the
different steps, you should do it
yourself, is first of all, an A matrix
that's 0, a B matrix that looks like this,
and a C matrix that's dead end to the
matrix, which is not surprising since we'
re measuring both the x y position and the
orientation of, of the robot. Now, this is
a little bit weird. Because if I write
down the, the dynamics for x2. Well, x2
dot it's going to be given by the second
row of everything. Well, first of all,
it's zero, right? Because my a matrix is
zero. Then I get zero, zero times u. So I
get plus zero, zero. I mean, times u, if
you want. But this means that x2. is
actually eqaul to zero. Well x2 was the y
direction, what this means is if I'm
pointing my robot straight in the x
direction, then apparently I cannot
actually make the car drive in the y
direction. That seems a little bit fishy
actually. what is going on here is that
the linearization That we performed didn't
quite capture all the nitty gritty
exciting things that were going on with
the non linear model. And this is an
example where the non-linearities are so
severe, that the linearization as applied
directly, doesn't entirely apply. Because
we lost control over the y direction. Even
though.
>> If I have a car, I can clearly turn it.
I can drive it and turn, and drive in the
Y directions. So, here's an example where
the linearization actually doesn't give us
just what we wanted. And, the punch line
here is that sometimes linearizations give
reasonable models, with inverted pendulum,
for instance. And, sometimes they do not,
with the unicycle. and with a unicycle we
have to be a little bit more care,
careful, but the fact that I want to point
out though is that when they work. When
the linear stations work they are
remarkably useful. Even though we're
finding them around the operating points
they seem to work Better than what we
really theoretically have reason to
believe, which is why we do a lot of
analysis of the linearizations rather than
the non-linear models. And then take what
we learned from the linearizations and
apply it to the, the non-linear models.
Thank you.