So the outcome of last lecture was on one
hand a little bit exciting because what we
did is we took the measurements that we
get and we try to use them as a, for as a
way of designing controllers to stabilize
the system. We actually know how to
stabilize systems. We need the real parts
of the eigen values are all strictly
negative.
On the other hand, the outcome of the last
lecture was wildly disappointing because
we couldn't actually do it. And the reason
for that was that we only looked at the
output and not at the full state
information. So today, we're going to look
at How do we design controllers when we
take all of x into account, and not just
y. so if you recall this picture. What
we're going to do today is simply say, you
know what? I don't care about y. In fact,
forget about measurements. What comes out
here is x itself. And then, what can we
actually do? Now, obviously. What we need
to which is the topic of the next modal is
create a way of actually sucking out x
from y but for now lets just pretend for a
moment that we do have access to the full
state information. Well if we have that
first off we dont have to worry about y
what so ever So x dot is Ax plus Bu,
forget about y. Then what we do is instead
of saying u is negative Ky, we're now
going to say u is negative Kx, where K is
the matrix of various gains in it. In the
previous example, it was just a scalar
with a 1 in it, but in general it could be
a matrix. Now, just like last time, we
plug this choice of u Back into the
equation for x., and then we get x., this
ax, plus bu, well u is negative kx. So
then we can put everything together in
this matrix, a minus bk.
And if we call this A hat, we all of a
sudden have a new system matrix and our
job is to make A hat as pretty as
possible. Well in particular A hat is
known as the closed loop dynamics because
now we have closed the loop of the system.
We're feeding back the state information.
Into the system and in that way we are
getting rid of the Ax's or x dot is Ax
plus Bu and we are getting x dot is A
minus BKx and they control the sign task
from a stability point of is simply pick
if possible K such that the closed-loop
system is stabilized and luckily for us we
now know. Exactly what this means. It
means that the real part of the
eigenvalues of the closed-loop dynamics, A
minus BK, has to be strictly negative. So,
let's go back again to our simple robot to
see how can we understand this in the
context of the simple robot. And arguably,
the entire next module, module 4, is going
to be devoted to this question. How do we
pick K such that we can stabilize this
system, get the eigen values we want? And
on top of that, how do we get around this
rather peculiar conundrum where we only
have y but we would like to have x and
we're going to pretend that we have X.
Well, that, we will have wait for. But for
now, let's go back to the robot. Let's
note, though, first of all, that u is in
r, and x is in r squared, or r2. And, in
fact, if u is negative kx. It's always
useful to write down this kind of
dimensional analysis. Where x is n by 1.
In this case, u is in general, let's say
that u is m x 1, in this case it's
actually 1 x 1, then, from a dimensional
point of view, K has to be m x n, because
otherwise it doesn't work out, so we have
to be able to cancel these things out, and
out comes soemthing that's m x 1. So in
general, K is a m x 1 Matrix where m is
the dimension of the output and the n is
the dimension of the state. Okay, in this
case m by 1 means 1 by 2, we pick k1 and
k2 here, those are our control gains, we
plug it to the A-Bk equation here. So this
is. This is a, this is b, and this is k,
right? So if we do that, we get this
system. And we perform the matrix
multiplication. I would encourage you to
make sure that I got the matrix
multiplication right by doing it
yourselves. But, for now, let's just
accept the fact that the close loop
dynamics becomes x dot, is 0, 1 minus k1
minus k2x. Okay, so now we have this 2
knobs that we can tweak, k1 and k2, and w
hen we tweak them, the eigen values of the
closed loop dynamics are going to move
around. So, in the next module we'll be
systematic in terms of how we actually
pick this case. For now.
Let's just put some case pull some case
out of a hat. Oh, and I'm a lazy man, so
I'm pull once out of the hat. So let's
just try k1 equals k2 equals to 1. Why
not? As a first, first attempt, at least.
Well, if I plug this in to my A mius BK
equation, I get the following closed-loop
system dynamics. And let's check the
eigenvalues of these things. So list write
eig in MATLAB or whatever system you want
to use. if you do that, you'll find out
that the eigenvalues are negative 0.5 -
plus minus something, something,
something, j. What are the real parts of
the eigenvalues? Well the real parts of
the eigenvalues. ,, . There, -0.5, so
there strictly negative, which of course
is what we needed for stability. So we
have asymptotic stability, so we have in
fact Achieved asymptotic stability. Now,
the other thing to note is that the fact
that we have a J hanging around there,
meaning we have an imaginary component to
our eigenvalues, that means that we can
expect oscillations in the way the system
behaves. So we have an asymptotically
stable system with some oscillations
floating around, and they are in fact
damped oscillations because, since the
system is stable, the oscillations are
going to become smaller and smaller in
amplitude, and as t goes to infinity, they
are going to in fact go away completely.
So if I do this, then here is what it
looks like. As you can see very quickly we
get close to the origin we overshot a
little bit and this because of these
osculations. So lets see if we can do
something about these osculations. Well
here is another attempt completely
arbitrary. I am going to make k1 smaller
which means k1 tells me how much I react
to position and k2 tells me how much I
react to volicity You can always think of,
almost think of this as a p parameter in a
PID regulator, and this is the d parameter
i n the PID regulator. Because p is the
position in this case, and d is the
derivative of position, which is velocity.
And that's what k2 is, is affecting. Okay.
If I do that, then my new system matrix
becomes this beast here. Well, let's check
its eigenvalues. In this case, the
eigenvalues end up being these 2 numbers.
And they're real, which means we cannot
expect, really, any oscillations. and even
better yet. The real and strictly
negatives. So this is an asymptotically
stable system with no oscillation.
Oscillations.
So, this seems like a pretty decent design
to me. Let's see what it would actually do
to the robot. So the robot, eh, well, it's
not oscillating but it's unbearably slow.
So, what we saw here is that we actually
got rid of the oscillations but we got
assistance that was much more or sluggish
in the sense that iti's slow and
borderline annoying from a performance
point of view. But for now asymptotic
stability is achieved and what we saw we
need to do is to be able to achieve
stability while doing other things at the
same time. But one thing that is
absolutely clear is that some eigenvalues
are better than others. And our design of
control gain, somehow, should be reflected
by, what are good eigenvalues. So, some
eigenvalues cause oscillation. Some
eigenvalues cause instability. Some
eigenvalues make the system Respond too
slowly and so forth. So what I want to
leave you with now is it seems like state
feedback is the way to go. Even though we
don't really know how to get to state yet.
But we will by the end of the next module.
And we have to be careful and creative and
clever in terms of how we select our
eigenvalues. And that's another topic for
the next module. which is how do we
actually Select the appropriate
eigenvalues to get the closed loop system
behavior that we want.