Welcome back to the second Programming &
Simulation lecture.
This week I will talk about Differential
Drive, Odometry and Infrared Sensors.
In fact, this week's programming
assignment is
focused on implementing the robot's
sensors and actuators.
Therefore, you will need to transform from
the unicycle dynamics in
the controllers to the differential drive
dynamics and the mobile robot.
You also need to use the wheel encoder
to keep track of the robot's position and
orientation.
This is called odometry.
And third, you'll need to use the infared
sensors to
measure distance to any obstacles that
might be around teh robot.
The simulator emulates the QuickBot, and
the
QuickBot is defined in the quickbot.m
file.
This is a class and it's located in the
robot package.
Packages in MatLab are denoted by a plus
in front of the folder name.
This robot has a two-wheel differential
drive, meaning that
each wheel is independently, controlled by
a single motor.
And, it also has a wheel encoder for each
one of the wheels.
And these wheel encoders are responsible
for
measuring the distance that each wheel
travels.
And they have a resolution of 32 ticks per
revolution.
And the robot also has five infrared
sensors and these infrared sensors can
detect any
obstacles, that are within a range of four
to thirty centimeters in their field of
view.
Following is a little diagram to explain
to you how the simulation actually works.
First of all, there is the simulator and
it has a timer object.
And this timer object calls at every
time step the execute function inside the
supervisor.
The supervisor is really the decision
maker and it's responsible
for, first of all, gathering the sensor
information from the robot.
It then selects a controller.
And passes the censor information along
with an estimate of the
robot's position and orientation to the
execute function in the controller.
This execute function in the controller,
then computes the
appropriate linear and angular velocity of
the robot which
is then, converted to the left and right
real
speeds of the robot and passed back to the
robot.
Supervisors also responsible for updating
the estimate
of the robots position in orientation and
this whole process is repeated at every
time step.
The supervisor itself was defined in the
QB supervisors.Mfile where
as all of the controllers are found in the
controller package.
The first part of this assignment is, to
convert the linear angle of velocity
in the controllers to the left and
right angular wheel velocities on the
mobile robot.
You'll do this in the unit diff
function which is defined in the
differentialdrive.m file.
This function takes in the linear and
angular velocity of
the robot and returns the left and right
wheel speeds.
The skeleton code show you how
to retrieve the radius of the reel r and
the distance between the two reels, l.
What you need to use to calculate the left
and right wheel speeds.
The second part of this assignment is
odometry.
What you need to do is to measure the
distance traveled by each
wheel and estimate the position and
orientation
of the robot using those measured
distances.
You will implement this in the update
odometry function, which is inside the
QBSupervisor.m file.
Let's take a look at the skeleton code for
this function.
Here you have the ske, skeleton code for
First you will retrieve wheel encoder
takes from the robot,
then you will recall the previous wheel
encoder takes; which is
used Which is achieved by retrieving the
previous text stored in
the pre, from the, in the previous
iteration of the code.
Then, you will use, then you will retrieve
the current state estimate,
meaning, what is the current estimated
position and orientation of the robot.
Then, you will retrieve the, the useful
constants such as
the radius of the wheel, the distance
between the wheel, and.
How many readers are there for each tic
of, each tic of the encoder.
Then your part comes, which is to
implement odometry
by computing the difference in the X
position, the difference
in the Y position, and the difference in
the orientation
between now and the last time the odometry
was updated.
You will then add these deltas to the
current estimate of
the pos, current estimate of the
orientation and position, and save, and
save that as the new estimate.
You will also need to save the
current number of ticks in the right and
left wheels for the next iteration.
[INAUDIBLE]
Part of these assignments is to make sense
of the IR distance sensors.
In particular, these sensors will return
votages in
the range from 0.4 to 2.75 and those
correspond to distances between four and
30 centimeters.
The relationship between distance and
voltage, is
shown in the graph on the left.
Now what, to make matters a little bit
more complicated, is that the
robot actually returns a integer value in
the range of 200 and 1,375.
What these values simply correspond to the
voltage divided by two then multiplied
by 1,000.
Since the graph on the, in the previous
slide is not linked is not linear.
We need to use the [UNKNOWN] polyfit to
find a fifth-order polynomial that will
fit the data.
We will then use the coefficients from
that function and the polyval
function to convert from the integers to
an actual distance in mirrors.
You will do this in the get IR Distances
function.
This function is defined in Quickbot.m.
And you need to implement two specific
parts.
First you need to properly convert from
the integers to the voltage, and then
you need to hard code the coefficients
that were output by the polyfit function.
To help you test the assignment, we've
included a go to angle controller.
This is a P regulator, which will simply
steer the robot to a specified angle.
If you wish to change the angle to which
this robot steers, you
need to go into the constructur and
QBSupervisor.m and change this variable,
right here.
Object.theta_d.
I have it set to pi divided by four, so
we'd expect that the robot
would drive off at a 45 degree angle with
respect to the x axis.
So let's see this in action.
I'm
going to hit play and what we should see
is the robot.
Drived at a 45 de, de, degree angle.
I'm
going to move the graph out of the way and
we're going to follow this robot.
And as you can see it's driving at 45
degrees with respect to the x axis.
It's going to just continue driving at
this angle all
the way until it's going to crash into the
thread wall.
There you go, we found a crash.
You'll see in the, in the command window,
that I've actually been spitting out the
estimated posts from the odometry at every
time step, and you can see that the values
that I'm getting for the angle are close
to pi divided by four.
So this controller successfully steers the
robot toward that angle.
My tips for this week are to, first of
all, make sure you read
the section on week two in the manual for
more
details than you find in the slide, in
these slides.
And also, to use the commented out fprintf
statements
that I've included in the comments in the
code.
Or into, maybe add some more, more of your
own and this is really
useful for debugging because for example,
when
you're dealing with implement in the
odometry,
you want to print out what you're
currently
estimating the position of the robot to
be.
You know for example you can easily see
that my robot drove at 45 degrees, but I
also needed to print that out to the
command
line to make sure that those values not
jump.
And that's it for this week.