[MUSIC]
Hello, I hope by now you have
a general idea about embedded systems,
the challenges that lie in this field,
and their main characteristics.
In this lecture,
we will go into details of what components
the embedded systems consist of.
We are going to start by
discussing on processing elements.
In the course,
we will cover embedded processors and
field program level gate arrays, FPGAs.
So in the end of the course,
you are capable of selecting
a proper processing element
to implement your own ideas.
So here, I would like to start
by giving you some ideas
on what embedded processors and
NetFPGAs are.
Well, we discuss embedded
processors first.
So what is a processor?
It is an electronic device
that works sequentially.
This means that a processor makes
computations in a serial manner,
one after another.
Any computation,
no matter how difficult it is,
can be split into simpler,
let's say sub-computations.
Those sub-computations might
be split even further.
An elementary piece of computation
that cannot be split anymore
is called an instruction.
Any piece of computation, given by let's
say by our programmer, in order to be
executed on a processor, should be
split into a sequence of instructions.
Different kinds of processors can
have different instruction sets.
They are different for example,
in the number of instructions or
let's say in how complex simple
instructions are in the sets.
So what is good about this approach?
And there should be oboisily something
good in it since nowadays processors
are widely used.
The good thing is it's flexibility.
Nearly, any piece of computation can be
represented as a sequence of instructions
and therefore executed on a processor.
That means we change the behavior
of an embedded system
just by changing the sequence of
instructions it's processor executes.
In other words,
we only change the software.
There is no need to change
the architecture of the processor.
The generality of such approach is the
reason why it is used massively nowadays.
Let's just think about the huge number
of applications that can be run on,
let's say, Cortex processors,
which are present in smartphones,
servers and many other devices.
One metric for processors, as mentioned
before, is the instruction set,
which actually defines the inner
structure of a processor.
If we compared reduced instruction set
computers and complex instruction set
computers, we will notice that
CISC instruction set is larger.
And it has more complex instructions, so
how does it influence
the complexity of hardware?
We are not going to go
deeply into the details, but
at least we can conclude
that the piece of hardware
that the codes instructions
should be more complex for CISC.
One of the most prominent representative
of Sisk is Intel's X86 processors.
Though in this course,
we are not targeting this kind
of big general processors.
I could not not mention a more kind
of embeddable processors are for
example RISC micro controllers.
If we look at Atmel's AVR family we
will find a large variety of options for
embedded applications.
Advanced RISC, arm processors,
as was mentioned before
are widely spread nowadays.
They've arrived from Cortex M to
Cortex A family which are meant for
different application domains in
terms of competition out performance,
energy efficiency and others.
In further lectures, we will give more
details about processors in general and
microcontrollers in particular.
So just how instructions are executed,
what peripherals are used,
what platforms exist, so stay in.
Now that you have an insight on what
the nature of an embedded processor
is we can move to the second
representative of processing elements.
Field-programmable gate arrays, or FPGAs.
Well, it is of course
an electronic device, but
unlike a processor it is meant for
more application specific designs.
So what does it mean?
First, let's have a quick
look at what an FPGA is.
FPGA has reconfigured a logic with them.
To make a simple example,
let's say we have two input and gates.
What kind of logic can we implement?
We can for example use only one gate and
implement a simple logic and function.
However, we can implement a more complex
circuit if we use both and gates and
connected the output of the first gates
to one of the inputs of the other gate.
So, if a certain application demands
the use of two gates, we can use both.
This is a simplified way to explain
what can be done with an FPGA.
An FPGA has many logic blocks in sight,
and
when needed, these blocks can be connected
together to build complex circuits.
These connections, the inner structure
of the FPGA has to be configured
according to the application's
requirements before the execution.
So, when we deal with an FPGA,
we make changes on a hardware level
and FPGAs hardware design is meant for
certain applications.
You can see now that there
is no such flexibility for
FPGAs as there is for processors.
We need to change the hardware design for
an FPGA every time there
is a new application.
There is no flexibility.
The reasonable question
is why then use an FPGA?
Flexibility comes at the cost of
performance, and energy consumption.
Indeed, in most cases, the same
application implemented on an FPGA,
executes faster and consumes less energy
than if implemented on a processor.
There is one more thing which one needs
to consider when working with an FPGA.
An FPGA design is parallel in a sense
that there is no sequence of operations.
Things happen in parallel.
A good example is a four loop.
If the loop is executed on a processor, it
will be run one iteration after another.
However, if the loop is
implemented on FPGA,
a separate surrogate for
each iteration will be generated.
In a sense, iterations exist in parallel.
Now you can probably conclude
that a FPGA is meant for
computationally heavy applications.
Such as for example,
image processing or big data analytics.
It is also interesting that an embedded
processor can be implemented on an FPGA.
In this case,
a processor is the application itself.
There are several FPGA vendors
available in the market.
The living one is Xilinx,
which has a wide variety of devices
with different characteristics.
We will discuss the main ones as well
as the inner structure of an FPGA in
the following lectures, so
there are interesting things ahead.
Well, to sum up the video, I would
like to emphasize the main differences
between a processor and an FPGA.
Because these differences will impact the
choice when selecting a proper platform
to work with.
A processor has a sequential nature
at its core and provides flexibility.
Whereas, an FPGA is more application
oriented and provides hydro performance.
If the main goal is efficiency, then
an FPGA would probably be a good choice.
On the other hand, if we need
to build a generic platform, and
we have either no specific application or
many applications in mind, then
a processor would be a suitable solution.
And also it is worth mentioning
that sometimes the optimal solution
lies between two limits.
So a combination of a processor with
an FPGA may be a powerful tool.
Thank you for watching, and
see you in the next video.
[SOUND]