[MUSIC]
We've already used integrals to calculate
areas and
now, I want to use integrals to calculate
volumes.
I want to calculate the volume of some
complicated object.
If I can cut it up into pieces, where I
understand the volume and each
piece, then I can integrate to figure out
the volume of the whole thing, right?
You can take some complicated object and
slice it up into slabs.
You can take some complicated object slice
it up into disks.
Take some complicated object, slice it up
into these washer shaped regions, right?
We're going to have all kind of different
ways.
Of decomposing solid objects, in order to
calculate their volumes.
And this is really the first example of
something very general,
there are all kinds of problems in the
real world where
you can write down a, a Riemann sum that
you would
like to be able to, to calculate the, the
limit of, right?
A lot of real world problems are, are
modeled this way.
And if you, if you try to take the limit
of a Riemann sum,
what you're really trying to do is to
calculate the volume of an interval.
So, lots and lots of sort of, real world
problems reduce down to some sort of
integration problem.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]