[MUSIC]
Hello, it is good to see you back for
this lesson.
In previous videos we explored Kontiki and
Tanjores, their features and advantages.
Now we're going to address
another type of IOT embedded OS.
Right, which can be seen as an example
of a micro current of design.
First of all I will give you
an introduction to Riot and
then I will discuss its features and
advantages.
Riot is an open source
embedded operating system.
It is designed for networked and
memory constrained embedded systems.
Its primary focus is on low-power
wireless sensor network systems and
Internet of Things devices.
As a result of this,
it is made lightweight enough to satisfy
the requirements of embedded devices
having limited processing capacity,
small main memory and storage,
and powered by battery.
The kernel of Riot was first developed by
several European academic institutions
in 1999, and later by various companies,
individuals and universities.
Riot and
its applications are written in ANSI C.
Riot implements a microkernel of
architecture, inherited from Fire Kernal.
In addition to Fire Kernel's original
features, powerful C++ libraries such as,
the Wise Leaf algorithm framework and
tcpip network stack are added in to riot.
As primly mentioned, Riot is built for
networked and memory constrained systems.
Therefore it needs to save memory and
reduce the size of it's can.
In order to address this,
Riot is designed in a modular way.
It also tries to limit dependencies
between the modules as small as possible.
In addition, the configuration of
the system can be customized to meet
a particular specification,
thereby minimizing the size of the kernel.
For instance, a Riot kernel can require as
small as a few hundred bytes of RAM and
program storage.
Another benefit of modularity is
the effect of bugs is
limited in the module itself.
Similar to Kontiki a bug in a module
cannot mess up with the whole system.
In contrast to many other operating
systems, write a scheduler
works without periodic events and
it's consider a tickles scheduler.
One benefit of this is, to switch to idle
threat, when there are no pending tests.
In addition, the idle threat contains
a function to decide this looping duration
of a device, or system.
This decision is made, based on
the peripheral devices in use, this
gives the advantage that the system can
stay in sleep state as long as possible.
Subsequently, energy consumption
can be significantly minimized.
Only interrupts wake the system
up from the idle state.
Moreover, all kernel functions
are kept as small as possible
thus allowing the kernel to run even on a
small systems with very low clock speeds.
The scheduler is the sign to minimize
the occurrences of threats which
thereby reducing the overhead by switch
questions related to interrupts may
have popped out in your main software.
For instance, how do interrupts
awaken the system from a sleep state?
How this would get handled?
In order to give you answers for
such questions, I'm going to
explain interrupt handling in Riot.
Interrupt handling is an important
part of Riot because failure to handle
interrupts well has a serious impact
on the performance of the system.
It is known that most device drivers for
common real time and
wireless network are designed
to directly use interrupts.
However using interrupts
is not straightforward.
For example,
in a pre-emptively scheduled system,
interrupt is passed through kernel and
context switching must be carried out.
Before switching to the interrupt, the
context of the running task must be saved
as you can see,
it is complicated to work with.
In order to help programmers
achieve this easily,
Riot provides an API which is similar
to common sensor net programming model.
In addition, Riot is built
targeting the lowest possible
interrupt latencies so that real
time requirements can be fulfilled.
Similar to other embedded wireless
network operating systems, Riot supports
various types of hardware such as
16 bit MSP430 or 32 bit ARM server.
One of the benefits of Riot
is it's small footprint.
It only requires less than
five kilobytes of ROM and
two kilobytes of RAM to run a basic
wireless sensor network application.
Compare to Contiki, Riot is better
in terms of required minimum RAM and
ROM for a basic task.
Another advantage of Riot
related to portability
is in using advance
features of processors.
For instance,
ARM processors are powerful and
provide many complex features
like vector interrupt controller.
These features may not be suitable for
other embedded network OSs.
However, Riot utilizes,
by virtue of separation of CPU code
from the kernel implementation
Riot's kernel is built in the target
of achieving maximum reliability and
strong realtime characteristics.
Therefore, Riot supports multithreading
with zero-latency interrupt handlers and
minimum context-switching times.
In order to assist system developers
take advantage of really easily.
Riot provides a developer friendly API.
Another advantage of Riot is that
is allows developers to create
as many threads as possible.
In addition, distributed systems
can be easily implemented
using the kernel messaging API.
The maximum number of threads is only
limited by the available memory and
the size of the stack for threads,
while the computational and
memory overhead is minimum.
Similar to other embedded
network operating systems,
Riot supports different
network protocols for
resource constrains systems
Such as 6LoWPAN and RPL.
In addition, IPv4,
IPv6, UDP and
TCP are also fully supported.
Similar to Kontiki,
network stack in Riot is also modular.
This gives the flexibility to exchange
protocol layers at any hierarchy.
In addition,
an adaptation layer is provided
that offers an IEEE 802.15.4
complete interface.
There are many interesting things of Riot.
Unfortunately we cannot
discuss them all here.
In order to cover more features,
advantages of Riot and
learn to program for it in detail,
i suggest you to go through the
commentation in the suggested materials.
Before ending this section,
we're going to take a look at
the classic Helloworld example in Riot.
In this example, 'Hello World' will be
printed out to the terminal of the device.
In order to know the details
on how to write a program and
run applications in Riot,
please come back to our lecture.
Who have more detailed videos.
With this lesson, we concluded
the embedded operation systems model.
I hope you enjoyed watching.