[MUSIC]
The CERN accelerator complex
is a chain of machines,
which accelerate particles
to increasing energy.
Each machine increases the energy of
a particle beam before injecting it into
the next machine.
Most of the chain's accelerators are
equipped with their own experimental hall
in which the beams are used for
fixed target experiments at lower energy.
The source of protons is a simple
bottle of gaseous hydrogen.
An electric field ionizes
the hydrogen atoms to obtain protons.
The Linac 2,
the first link in the chain, accelerates
the protons up to an energy of 50 MeV.
The beam is then injected into
the PS injector synchrotron,
which is called the PS Booster.
It accelerates protons up to 1.4 GeV and
accumulates them.
They're then injected
into the Proton Synchrotron,
the PS, which carries
the beam up to 25 GeV.
The protons are then sent to
the Super Proton Synchrotron,
the SPS where they are in
turn accelerated to 450 GeV energy.
And finally, the protons
are sent to the two beam tubes of
the Large Hadron Collider, the LHC.
The beam travels clockwise
in the first tube and
counter clockwise in the second tube.
It takes about 4 minutes 20 seconds to
fill each of the two rings of the LHC
and 20 minutes for the protons to reach
their maximum energy of today 6.5 TeV.
Under normal operating conditions,
the beams circulate for
several hours in the tubes of the LHC.
They are focused by pairs
of quadropoles towards
the interaction point.
The two beams collide
inside four detectors.
ALICE, ATLAS, CMS and LHCb.
At the collision point,
the total energy in the center of
mass is 13 TeV today.
But the LHC does not only accelerate
protons, but also heavy ions.
The lead ions of the LHC are extracted
from a vaporized lead source and
passed through a Linac 3
before being collected and
accelerated into the ring
of low energy ions.
Then their path is the same as that for
protons. At the end of this path,
the ions reach their maximum energy.
[MUSIC]