Welcome to the module 4 of the course
Control of Mobile Robots.
So, in the last module we've learned
about linear systems and we saw where
they came from and at the end we even
managed to control them a little bit and
in fact we felt rather good about
ourselves.
because we could design a state feed back
controller for a point mass that
stabilized it, but at the same time we
were a little queasy and uneasy about
this whole thing because we had to have x
meaning the state to do our control
design but in reality, we actually don't
have x.
We have y, the output.
So what this module is devoted to is
trying to first of all, be systematic in
how we do the control design and,
secondly, how do we actually overcome
this seeming paradox of needing x but
only having y.
So what we're going to do in the first
lecture, is stabilize the point mass.
We're going to return to our old friend,
and in general, if I have a linear
system, x dot is Ax + Bu, y is Cx. The
dilemma, as I've already stated is that
we seem to need x for stability but all
we really have is y.
So here is the game play.
We're going to ignore the fact that we
don't have y.
Instead we're going to design our
controller as if we had the state itself
and then somehow we're going to hope that
we can figure out the state from the
Measurements, meaning from y, and this is
the game plan we're going to pursue
throughout this entire module.
And, the first step is, of course to
design u as if we had x.
So step one is to, do the control design
and we're going to use a method called,
pole placement.
And, pole placement is a rather powerful
idea.
So if I have my point mass system again,
x dot is Ax+Bu, where we have our old
friends the A and B matrices that we've
seen over and over again.
Well, state feedback means that, what we
are going to do is we're going to pick u
is -Kx.
Where K in this particular situation is a
1 by 2 matrix, so it has 2 components.
k1 and k2.
And those are, are gains.
And we've already seen in the previous
module, that k1 is a gain that looks at
precision.
And k2 is a gain that looks at velocity.
And by tweaking them, somehow, we can get
the system to be, behave well.
'Cuz we've already seen that.
So, the one question we need to ask
first, is, of course, is, how do we
actually pick these control gains?
Meaning, what should k be? Well.
Here is the whole idea behind pole
placement.
When we plug in U is minus KX we get a
closed loop system.
And what we're going to do, is we're
going to pick K such that the closed loop
system has the right eigenvalues.
And right meaning, we get to pick them.
And the risk is called pole placement,
its that eigen values of the system
matrices are sometimes referred to as
poles and what we're going to do is we're
going to make them be what we want them
to be, in particular we want them to have
negative real part because that is what
we need for asymptotic stability.
So but before we do that we actually need
to figure out how do we computer
eigenvalues? So in general, if I have a
matrix M, this doesn't have to be a 2 by
2, this is just some general M, then
every square matrix M has a so-called
characteristic equation associated with
it.
And it's given by this chi M of lambda,
and it's kind of a mouthful.
It's the determinant of lambda times the
identity matrix -M.
And then we set this determinant equal to
0.
And the lambdas that solve this are
Eigenvalues, well, let's see what this
means.
If I have a 2x2 system and equal to M1,
M2, M3 and M4 then lambda I, meaning
lambda times the identity minus M.
Well it's lambda times the identity minus
M, well, if you plug this in, you get the
following matrix.
Okay, now, let's take the determinant of
this matrix.
So the determinant, well, is this object
you get by taking this element times this
element.
And then you subtract away this element
times that element.
this is how you do it for 2 by 2
matrices.
in general it can become even more
complicated.
But in this case, I get this times that
which shows up as lambda - m1 * lambda -
m4.
And then I get -m2, or - - m2 * -m3,
which shows up like this.
So this is the, the determinant of this 2
by 2 M matrix. Okay.
We need to set this determinant equal to
zero, so aa, carrying out the
multiplications we have second order
equation that we have to solve for lambda
in order to be able to find Eigenvalues,
okay.
Lets try to that, we have this
equation.The way we solve second order
equations,
is while there are formulas for this it
is possible to do it.
In this case it turns out that lambda is
this rather annoying looking expression
here, but this is what the Eigenvalue,
the 2 Eigenvalue to this 2x2 matrix would
be.
But it is annoying.
I really don't want to do this.
So the question is there an easier way of
making the Eigenvalues be what we would
like them to be.
Turns out that the answer is, yes.
There is something called the fundamental
theorem of algebra.
And this fancy looking, or fancy sounding
theorem says that, if I have a
polynomial, the roots to that polynomial
are determined by the coefficients, which
means that you know what? I actually
don't have to solve this equation.
Here I have coefficients in front of
lambda then here I have the coefficients
that aren't in front of any lamda, those
coefficients alone are enough to
implicitly but completely determined
eigen values.
So what we're going to do is we're
actually not going to solve this.
We're just going to stop here and say,
fine, lets start massaging the
coefficients direct.
So if we go back to our point mass again.
I pick u as -kx.
Then I get x dot is (A - BK) x We've seen
this before.
this is the closed loop dynamics.
And in particular if I plug in what k is
I get A - BK being this two matrices
here.
And, if I compute that, I get 0, 1, -k1,
-k2.
And I, encourage all of you to perform
this multiplication at home, just to make
sure that you trust that this is indeed
Now let's compute the igon values or at
least the co-efficients in this thing
called the characteristic equation.
So, chi A minus BK lambda is the
determinent of this matrix or the
negative of that matrix plus Lambda times
the identity.
So, this is what I have here of course is
lambda I - (A - BK).
And, if you compute this determinant, you
get, lambda ^ 2 + lambda k2 + k1.
That's not so bad.
And the neat thing here is that again,
all we care about These coefficients.
The things that determine what the roots
are without us actually having to
complete the roots.
Now why does that help us? Well, what
we're going to do now is we're going to
pick our favorite eigenvalues in the
whole world.
We're going to pick the eigenvalues that
we would like the system to have, and if
we somehow magically manage to make the
closed loop system have these
eigenvalues, then the characteristic
equation would be lamda minus lamda 1
because the characteristic equation has
to be 0 has to be lamda 1 as a root.
And if I plug in lamda 1, I get 0 here.
Similarly if I plug in lamda 2 I get 0
here, and lamda and 0 here.
So what I have is a product of lamda
minus these desired favorite eigenvalues
in the whole world.
So let's do that.
so for the robot or the point mass, I'm
going to pick both eigenvalues at -1.
I need, I know that they need to have
negative real part, well, -1 is
particularly simple Because then I get
this phi of lambda which is this desired
characteristic equation, not the actual
characteristic equation but the desired
one.
It's just lambda + 1 * lambda + 1 or, if
I carry out this multiplication, I get
lambda ^ 2 + 2 lambda + 1.
Now, what we need to do is simply line up
these coefficients with the actual
coefficients that we have.
So if I do that, I see, this is the
characteristic equation.
This is what I would like it to look
like.
Well, here are the coefficients in front
of lambda.
And here are these coefficients that are
hanging out by themselves.
All we do now is simply line these up.
So k2 has to be = 2, k1 has to be = 1 and
wahlah, I've actually designed the k
matrix that I need.
So now all I do is I plug this in to my
original system which is x dot is Ax + Bu
but I've closed the loop right now with u
being -Kx and I have successfully
stabilized the system, by placing the
eigenvalues exactly where I would like
them to be.