So, we now have a general procedure for
designing controllers which is pole
placement.
And the whole idea there is, we pick our
k such that the desired eigenvalues line
up.
We also, in the last lecture, learned
when it works and when it doesn't and the
key characteristic there was
controlability or complete
controlability.
We can do pole placement when we have
complete controlability.
If we don't, we can't.
Simple as that.
And in fact, it's not just pole
placement.
If we don't have complete controlability,
we can't make the system do what we want
meaning, we have to buy a new one, bigger
b matrix.
There's nothing else we can do.
Today, in this lecture, I would like to
unleash these awesome powers that we have
on a complicated robotic system, namely a
Segway robot.
And in fact, this is a robot that's
balancing on these two wheels, and in
fact, here at Georgia Tech,
we have a Segway robot, known as the
golem crane in Professor Mike Stillman's
lab.
And basically, the way a Segway robot
works is that it's a unicycle, roughly a
unicycle, on top of which there is an
inverted pendulum.
And luckily for us, we know how to model
unicycles and inverted pendulas.
Now, I'm writing +...
there because there's a little bit more
going on, but basically we're going to be
moving while balancing this thing.
so, let's start with the base.
The base is a unicycle,
x1 and x2,
that's the x and y position of the base.
And it's v cosine psi, where psi is the
heading.
And psi dot is still omega.
We've seen this repeatedly.
So, this is the dynamics of the base,
almost.
And then, on top of that, we have this
inverted pendulum.
And as we've seen, we need phi, which is
the angle by which the pendulum is
deviating from upright position and we
also need the angular velocity to
describe what is going on here.
Now, the inputs to a Segway robot are
torques, wheel torques.
So, the left wheel torque and the right
wheel torque.
And torques translates into forces, or
torques and forces translate into
accelerations, but here in the unicycle,
these are, are old control inputs.
The velocities now, since we have inputs
that acts as torques, we need to actually
add v dot and omega dot into the
equation.
So, v and omega are going to be extra
states, that's where the +...
comes from because, what I have done is I
have added v and omega as states to my,
my model.
So, what I really have in terms of the
state of the system, well, it's the
position of the unicycle, the
translational velocity, its orientation,
the angular velocity, and then phi and
phi dot associated with the upright face.
And my inputs are these wheel torques,
left and right wheel torques.
And in fact, if I write down the dynamics
of this thing.
Well here, I just have the unicycle
dynamics.
That's all that I'm saying here, this is
unicycle dynamics.
And then, I have all these other
derivatives that I need to solve and
compute.
And if you sit down and do the math very
carefully or you look in a book or
something, you got this mess here.
Wooh, this looks kind of horrible.
Well, the first thing we do, of course,
when we have something like this is we
linearize it.
This looks absolutely miserable.
But if we linearize it, what we end up
with is a, an LTI system and, in fact,
it's x dot is Ax+Bu, and I should point
out that what I've done, is I've
linearized this around (x,u)=(0,0), which
means that I have zero torques and the
position of the robot is at zero.
It's looking at the x direction and the
pendulum is looking straight up.
So, I'm linearizing it around 0,0.
And if you do that, you get the following
A and B matrices.
Obviously, I'm not going to ask anyone to
[LAUGH] memorize this.
I'm just showing you.
This is where the A and B matrices came
from.
Now, before we even attempt pole
placement, let's make sure that we can
indeed do it.
So, the first thing we have to check now
for this system is controllability.
And this is too big, right? So, I'm going
to go to MatLab right away and write,
here's the controllability matrix of my A
and B, here's the rank, and out comes 6.
Does anyone remember what n was in this
case? Well, I do.
n was equal to 7, which means that the
rank of the controlability matrix was not
equal to 7.
So, this is not a completely controllable
system.
And the problem here is the unicycle.
We've already seen that when we linearize
the unicycle, the dynamics gets messed
up, we can't move in the y direction.
I don't know if you remember that but if
you say an x and y is the position of the
unicycle, then we had y dot equal to 0.
What that means is we have no way of
moving sideways basically.
So, the unicycle is what's making life
hard for us here, so what I'm going to do
is I'm just going to ignore the unicycle.
Say, that the position and orientation of
the base, I don't care about that, but
what I care about is, the velocities, how
quickly it's moving and how quickly it's
turning.
So, I'm going to shave off x, y, or x1,
y, x1, x2 and psi from the state space
and get a smaller system that has s
states, the velocity, translational
velocity, angular velocity and these phi
and phi dot associated with the pendulum.
If I do that, I get a 4 by 4 system with
the following A and B matrices, again,
the actual numbers aren't that, that
important.
Well, I go to MatLab, I write rank
controllability matrix, I get the answer
being 4.
In this case, n was equal to 4.
So, if I shave off the unicycle base from
my system, I get the completely
controllable system.
Now, I can start controlling it.
The last twist though before I do that
is, I want my system to actually move.
So, I'm not going to stabilize it to v
and omega equal to zero, because that's
not what I want.
Instead, I'm going to say, I would like
it to go to v desired and omega desired.
So, let's just subtract away v desired
and omega desired,
and then I have a 0 here because you want
to stabilize it to phi and phi dot being
zero,
meaning, the pendulum being upright.
I'm going to find a new state,
x tilde, which is my old state minus this
delta which is the thing I would like to
stabilize it to. So, this is my delta.
So, I have a new state.
Well, what's the dynamics of the new
state? Well, delta x tilde dot is x minus
delta dot, delta is constant so this is 0
so this is just x dot.
So, it's Ax+Bu.
Well, I can write, I can add a minus
delta and add in an A delta at the end
because then I have x tilde again here.
so, if I do that, I get a new system and
here is the lucky part for us.
A times delta turns out to be equal to
zero because of the structure of A so I
get this thing going away.
I have x tilde here so my new system
dynamics is the same as my old system
dynamics.
x tilde dot is Ax tilde plus Bu.
And now, I want to stabilize this system
down to the origin,
which means that the velocities are
actually going to end up being equal to
the desired velocities.
So, we have completely control of the
system.
We wish to stabilize it.
We do pole placement.
And again, like we talked about last
time,
it isn't entirely clear how to pick the
eigenvalues.
So, I played around with the eigenvalues
and this seemed to give a good response.
I didn't want oscillations, so there are
no imaginary parts, and I picked lambda 1
minus 19, lambda 2 minus 7.5, and so
forth.
This is the smallest eigenvalue, it's
going to tell me how quickly, in general,
the system responds.
So, with this, I'm going to pick u as -K
not x but x tilde, which is the, the new
system I'm interested in.
I get my close look dynamics like this.
And, in fact, the way I compute K is to
use the, the place command in MatLab.
So, I type in my P and K is place A, B,
and P.
So, this stabilizes the Segway robot.
So now, the last thing we have to do is
to actually do it.
And the reason why I'm okay with
neglecting the unicycle base and only
controlling v and omega is that the
curvature of the path that's being traced
by the Segway robot, actually is omega
over v.
So, what I'm really controlling now is
the curvature of the path rather than
where the actual robot is.
And what I can do in the simulation that
I'm about to show you is basically, with
buttons, make v bigger or v smaller or
omega bigger or omega smaller.
And in essence, what I'm doing when I'm
changing v and omega is I'm changing v
desired and omega desired.
So, that's the way I'm going to be giving
reference signals or commands to the, the
unicycle robot.
So, with that, let's move to the actual,
actually the simulation of an actual
Segway robot.
So now, we're ready to see our developed
Segway robot controller in action.
And I'm here with Greg Droge who is a
graduate student at Georgia Tech who will
be showing us a simulation of the, the
Segway robot, so, Greg, what do you have
to show us? Okay.
Here, we have a simulation of the Segway
robot.
On the left, we have a 3D implementation
of the graphics.
So, you can see that now, I'm able to
drive it around changing the velocities.
Just as, just as Dr.
Egerstedt mentioned with the keypad.
and you notice a few interesting things.
Right here in the top right corner you
see the plot of the translational
velocity.
The red line is the desired velocity and
the blue line is the, the actual
velocity.
And you see that it converts this very
quickly to the inputs that I give it.
And on the middle, you see the rotational
velocity and you see because of the
eigenvalues that we've chosen, that it
actually converges really slowly but it
still converges.
And on the bottom you see that they're,
the tilt angle will always keep the, the
robot stable.
So, I have a question.
Are you simulating this on the
linearization or on the full nonlinear
model?
So, the simulation is on the full
nonlinear model.
Aha, so I actually have a question.
So, linearizations are only valid
locally.
do you have any sense for when this
breaks? Meaning, can we make the robot
fall over, for instance? Yeah, so if you
give it a really big huge step input of
the translational velocity you'll see
that in the 3D simulation, it goes in a
full circle and it actually hit the
ground.
Do, do that again.
That was exciting.
Okay.
Aha, so there, we actually get a feeling
for how good or reasonable the
linearizations are.
And in this case, it's fairly reasonable,
you can drive it around, but if you give
it really large desired velocities, it
actually falls over.
Correct.
Alright.
Thank you very much,
Greg.
Yup.
You're welcome.