So with the last lecture, we are actually
declaring success in terms of designing
controllers.
The useful placement, which add
controllability, and off we go.
the big problem, though, is well, we
don't have x.
And we have to, when we do.
u=-Kx.
Well, x is there, but we don't have it.
So, what about y.
Ultimately, we don't have x.
We have y coming out of the system.
And somehow, this Y has to translate into
a u.
It's not enough to say x translates into
u because we actually don't have, y.
Well here is the, cool idea.
I'm going to put a little magic block
here.
And the output of that block, somehow
should become x meaning I would like to
be able to take y push it through a magic
block.
And get the state out.
Now I'm not going to get x exactly, in
fact I'm going to put a little hat on top
of it.
This is my estimate of a state.
Meaning I'm taking my sensor measurments,
y and based on those measurements I'm
going to estimate what x is.
And I'm going to call that x hat, in fact
the magic block.
The thing that allows to get x from y is
called an observer.
So in today's lecture I'm going to be
talking about these observers and how do
we actually be design them.
Well, it turns out the general idea
behind the observer design can be
summarized in the predictor-corrector.
Under the predictor corrector banner.
So, let's say that we have, a x is ax.
Forget about u for now, that doesn't
matter.
And y is cx.
Well, here is the idea.
The first thing we're going to do, is
we're going to make a copy of this
system.
And our estimator is going to be this
copy.
So I'm going to have x.
is =.
Sorry.
xhat.
is = to Ax hat, so my estimate is
going to evolve, according to the same
dynamics as my actual state.
And this is known as the predictor, which
allows me to predict what my estimate
should be doing.
But that's not enough, what I'm going to
do now is I'm going to add some kind of
notion of a wrong, or right the estimate
is to the model.
And one, one thing to note is the
actually output is Y, the output I would
have had if the state was, was exact is
c*x hat * exact.
So I'm going to compare y.
To c*x hat.
And, in fact, what I do, is, I add the
piece to my predictor.
So, x.
is ax or hat, + this difference.
y-cx hat.
which tells me how wrong I am.
And then I add some game matrix here, l.
And this.
Gives me a predictor and a corrector.
So, this part here is the predictor, and
this part here is the corrector.
And this kind of structure is known as a
Luenberger observer named after David
Luenberger, but the point is that, when
you have this predictor correct repair,
you have some way of hopefully figuring
out the state, or at least a good
estimate of the state, from the
measurements, y, that show up here.
So the only question now.
Well, one question is, does it work? The
other question is, what is this L? So the
first thing we should ask is, how do I
actually pick a reasonable L? Well the
first thing we'll do.
Is, let's define an estimation error, e,
as the actual state - my estimated state.
And I should point out that we don't know
e.
Beacuse we don't know x .but we can still
write down e as x-x hat.
Well, I would like E to go to 0, right.
'Cuz, if I can make e go to 0, the x hat
goes to x.
Which means that x hat is a good estimate
of x.
So what I would like to do is actually
stabilize e.
Make e asymptotically stable.
So, what we need to do first, is, write
down the dynamics for my error equation.
So e dot well that's x dot-x hat dot.
Well x dot is just Ax and x hat dot.
Well, we have this format the Ax hath+
L(y-Cxhath) and then we get the minus
signs in front of everything.
so this is my estimation.
Now y Is equal to c*x, right?
So what I actually have here is e dot
being A(x-xhat)-LC(x-xhat).
But x-xhat is e so e dot is (A-LC)e.
This is the dynamics of the estimation
error.
We don't know e but we know that this is
the dynamics.
So what we need to do now, of course.
Is pick L in such a way that the
eigenvalues to this matrix, A-LC, have
negative real parts.
Because if we've done that, we've
stabilized the estimation error.
And I wonder, I wonder how we should go
about doing that.
Actually, I don't wonder, we know how to
do it, pole-placement.
We know how to do control design this
looks just like control design but it's
actually observier design.
well, we wanted to import the values from
(A-LC) to be
the negative.
So, let's just pole place away.
Okay.
So here's an example.
x dot equal to this, y is equal to that.
Fine.
Now, I want my error dynamics to be
asymptotically stable, so if I write down
A-LC.
And I should point out that in this case
C is a 1x2, that means that L has to be a
2x1 because these things have to cancel
out.
And I get a 2x2 left so L is actually a
2x1 matrix in this case.
So, if I write down what A-LC is, it
becomes this semi-annoying matrix but at
least we know what this matrix is.
What do we do now? Well, we compute the
characteristic equation to A-LC.
And if we do that, we compute the
determinant of lambda i.
So this is the determinant of lambda i.
Minus A-LC.
Right, if we compute that, we get the
following expression.
Well, now we do what we always do in
these situations.
We pick our favorite eigenvalues.
And it seems like I am very, very fond of
lambda equal to negative 1.
If I do that, I get this as the desired.
Characteristic equation.
Well, what do we do now? Well, we line up
coefficients, of course.
These coefficients have to be the same,
and these coefficients have to be the
same.
And if you actually solve this, I'm not
going to go through the algebra.
I encourage you to do it on your own.
You get that L 1 = -2/3.
And L2 is a third.
And if fact, the way this would look my
observer gain is well, L1 was -2/3, there
is L1.
And L2 was the third which is there.
So my observer dynamics is x dot.
Well, x hat dot is Ax hat plus this is
L*Y-CL.
So this is my observer dynamics.
What I'm showing here in the plot in
blue, this is x1, the actual x1 and how
it's evolving and in red you see my
xhat1.
and you see that after a while, they end
up on top of each other very nicely.
Similarly, in the right figure, in blue,
you have x 2, and in red, you have x hat
2.
And as we can see, the state, the
estimated state, x hat, thus, indeed
converge 2.
The actual set.
So here is what's going on right now.
I have x as Ax, y is Cx out of this thing
I can suck y right? Because that's what
I'm seeing, these are the measurements.
What I'm doing now is I'm feeding this y
into my server That has a predictor part,
which is the dynamics, plus a corrector
part, which looks at the difference
between the actual output and what the
output would have been if x hat was my
state.
And then out of this comes x hat.
Which means that we have some way of
figuring out what the state of the system
is.
Now, obvious questions are.
Well, well.
There's only 1 question, actually.
Does this work? And the answer is, no.
It doesn't always work.
Just like pole placement doesn't always
work when you're doing control design.
For the same reason pole placement
doesn't always work when we do observer
design.
And, what we need is we need something
that's related to controllability.
So, controllability tells us.
Do we have enough control authority, are
actuater is good enough.
Well, for observer design, the concept is
known as observability, which means do i
have a rich enough y, meaning rich enough
sensor suite so that I'm able to figure
out what the system is doing.
Meaning estimate, estimate x from y.
And the topic of the next lecture is
exactly this observability.
When can we indeed figure out x from y.