So, in the last lecture, we saw that it
was possible to recover the state from
the outputs using this observer
structure.
And the key there was to build an
estimate, or a copy of the state, x hat.
And to let the dynamics be given by the
predictor part, which is x hat dot this
ax hat which is a copy of the original
dynamics.
Plus the corrector part, that basically
compares the outputs to what the outputs
would have been if x hat was indeed the
state, and that output would have been C
times X hat.
Now, what we have here, is this gain L.
And we saw that designing this L, was
just like designing A K, when you're
doing control design and, what we really
need to do then was just pull placement
on the aerodymamics, so if the error, we
had e dot now being equal to A minus LC
times E, and we just needed to stabilize
that system.
But just with to control the sign
observer the sign doesn't always work and
we saw that we needed some kind of notion
related to controlability that works for
obsever the sign and that notion is
observability So observability is really
the topic of today's lecture.
And just ask for controllability,
it's easiest to approach this with a
rather modest and simple example.
So we're going to deal with a discrete
time system where xk + 1 is Axk and the
output, yk is Cxk.
And we start somewhere, we have some X0,
and the question is, by collecting N
different outputs, can we recover the
initial condition? Meaning can we figure
out where we started from? Well, at time
0 the output is simply C times X0, right?
At time 1, the output is C times X1.
Well, X1 is A times X0, so the output at
time 1 is CAx0.
And so forth.
So at time, n - 1, the output is CA^n - 1
times X0.
So now I've gathered this little n
different measurements, or y's.
And the relationship that we have is
this.
It looks very similar to what we had in
the controllability case.
And in fact, this matrix here is going to
be the new main character in the
observability drama.
In fact, this is an important matrix that
we're going to call omega.
In fact omega will be called the,
observability matrix, as opposed to
gamma, which was the controllability
matrix.
Now, just as we had in the control
problem, we have a similar kind of setup,
where we want to be able to basically
invert omega to recover Xo from this
stack of outputs.
And just as in the controlability case,
this is possible when this omega, the
observability matrix has full rank.
Meaning that the number of linearly
independent rows or columns is the same,
is equal to little, little m.
And luckily, for us,
just as for controllability, this result
generalizes to the case that we're
actually interested in.
Which is, the continuous time x is ax, y
is Cx.
So, observability, in general.
Means that the system is completely
observable, which I'm going to call CO,
if it is possible to recover the initial
state from the output.
That's basically what it means.
I collect enough outputs, and from there
I'm able to tell you where the system
started.
And just like for controllability, we
have a matrix.
This case it's omega which is the
observability matrix and theorem number 1
mirrors exactly theorem number 1 in the
controllability case its as, so this is
controllability complete observability
theorem number 1.
It says the system is completely
observable if and only if the rank of
omega is equal to little n meaning this
observability matrix has full rank.
Now as before, the rank is simply the
number of linearly independent number of
rows or columns of the matrix only in
this case.
Now, we have the second theorem, it
follows directly in the same way as it
did for control ability.
So, if I have this as my observer
dynamics, and then I find the error
dynamics where e simply is the actual
state minus my state estimate.
Well, what I wanted to do of course, is
drive e to 0, that's what I would like.
Well, theorem number two tells me that
this is possible,
if and only if, using pole-placements to
arbitrary eigenvalues.
If and only if, the system is completely
observable.
So, we have an exact dual to
controlability when we're designing
observers.
And in fact, designing observers, or
estimating the state, is really the same
thing as doing control design.
It just happens that we're stabilizing
aerodynamics instead of stabilizing the
state.
So this is good news, right, because now
we can actually figure out what the state
is.
So we are very, very close now to being
able to design controllers as if we had
x,
which we don't, we have y, but we use y
to figure out an estimate on x.
So what we're going to do in the next
lecture is simply put what we've done on
the control design side, and on the
observant design side together, in order
to be able to actually control liner
systems where we don't have the state but
all we do have is the out