Now we have lots of really good building
blocks. We haven't yet put them together.
Cause we don't fully know how they fit
together, but we have lot's of cool
things.
We have controllability, that tells us
whether or not it's possible to control
the system, if we have access to the
state.
And the way we do that is using state
feedback.
We have this notion of observability,
which tells us whether or not it is
possible to, to figure out the state from
the output, and the way we do that is.
by building observers and we have this
tool that seems remarkably strong which
is pole-placement which basically allows
us to place the closed loop eigen values
where ever we want.
So make them equal to the desired eigen
values and the big question now is how do
we put everything together.
And the answer is known as the separation
principle.
And in a nut shell, the separation
principle, which by the way, is quite
wonderful tells us that we can actually
decouple observer design and control
design from each other meaning we can
actually control the system as if we have
X, even though we don't.
And then we can get their estimate from x
using an observer structure.
So this is the topic of today's lecture
and it really is the reason why we're
able to effectively control linear
systems.
So, here's the game plan.
Now, I have x dot is Ax + Bu.
Y is Cx.
So this is a standard linear time and
variance system.
Now I'm going to assume that this system
is both completely controllable and
completely observable.
If it's not then, to be completely frank,
we're toast.
What that means, we need to go and buy
new sensors, which is fancy speak for get
a new C matrix.
Or we need to buy more actuators which
means get a better B matrix.
So let's assume that we have complete
controllability and complete
observability.
Well, the 1st step in our game plan is
let's ignore the fact that we don't have
X.
So I'm going to design the state feedback
controller as if I had X, meaning I'm
going to pick U=-Kx, which means that I
get my closed loop, my closed loop
dynamics to be this.
Now, this is what I designed for and I
have my favorite pole placement tool to
do this.
Now, in reality, I don't have that.
reality is I have u is -Kx hat, where the
hat is my estimated state.
So that's what I actually have even
though that's not what I designed for.
Now step two, of course, is I'm going to
estimate x using, using an In order to
get this x hat and to make it be as
pleasant as it can.
The big thing that we should note now is
that previously we didn't have a U term
in the observer dynamics.
Now we do have a U term that we need to
take into account but it turns out that
it's very simple to do that.
I built my predicter and the predicter
part now.
Contains both Ax hat and a BU term,
because a predictor is just a copy of the
dynamics.
And then I have my corrector part which
is this error between the actual output
and what the ouput would have been if I
had x hat instead of x.
Well, this structure again gives me the
same aerodynamics here.
So what we do is I pick L so that my
error, my estimation error is stabilized.
And that's before the error is the actual
state minus my estimated state.
So this is my game plan.
Now, let's see if this game plan is any
good.
A fact.
It should be good right? because
otherwise I'm wasting everyones time with
these slides, but let's make sure that it
indeed is worth while.
What do we want, this system to do? We
want to drive x to zero, because we're
stabilizing it, and we want to drive e to
zero, because we want the estimate to be
good.
So, what I need to do, is analyze the
joint dynamics together.
So x dot, is ax+bu, but u is, if you
remember, u = -k, not x, but x-hat, which
is why I get my x dynamics to look like
this.
While me e dynamics, that's the matrenary
dynamics, is what it has always been.
Okay, let's simplify this a little bit.
So, I know that the error is X minus X
hat.
So I can replace this X hat with X minus
the error.
So then I get my dynamics after some
pushups to be A minus BKX.
Plus BK.
E.
So now I have something that involves X
and E and here it only invovles E.
So now I can actually write everything in
a joint way.
X dot E dot is this large matrix now
that's not an NxN but it's a 2Nx2N*X E.
And mow, our strategy, our joint strategy
works if and only if this new joint
system is an asymptotically stable
system.
Which means that we need to check the
eigenvalues of this new system matrix.
Now, here is where the separation
principle comes into play.
This is my dynamics.
Now, this matrix here is a rather special
matrix.
Because it's triangular.
It has a block there, it has a block
there and it has a block there.
And triangular matrices, or block
triangular matrices.
May they be upper or lower triangular.
They have a particularly nice structure.
So this is an upper triangle block-matrix
and the eigenvalues are given by the
diagonal blocks.
Which means that the eiganvalues to this
whole matrix are the eiganvalues to this
matrix and the eiganvalues to this
matrix.
Or another way of writing it is that the
characteristic equation is the
characteristic equation to the first
block here.
Times the characteristic equation to the
second block here.
All that this means is that the
eigenvalues are given by the values of
the diagonal blocks.
And here is the wonderful part.
If we haven't been stupid in how we did
the design, then this thing has been
stabalized, because we did cold placement
to make sure that the real part of our
diagonals is strictly negative.
This part we have made sure is also well
behaved because we have designed our
observer in such a way that real part of
the eigenvalue is completely negative.
Which means that we haven't messed
anything up.
Everything works.
What that means is.
Control design people, we can design our
controllers as if we had the state and
than we rely on our clever sensing people
to estimate the state for us.
And thanks to the separation principal
everything works.
Now the ones that we keep in mind is that
we still have this term here, and this
term that basically tells you something
about what happens to transients.
But after awhile.
This term doesn't really matter and
everything works, so now we are ready to
state the separation principle.
The separation principle tells us that we
can in fact design controllers as if we
have x.
And then, we can design the observers
independent of the control actions,
because all we're doing is, we're adding
a + Bu in the observer dynamic, so the
control actions are actually just
canceled out.
In other words, control and observer
designs can be completely separated.
So, if you put everything together, in a
final Glorious block diagram.
This is what the world looks like.
We have our system.
This is physics.
This is what a system does.
Now, we have modeled it using A B and C
matrices, but what comes out of this
thing is Y, meaning our measurements and
what we push into this system is U, our
control action.
Now, we're taking u, sorry, we're taking
y and feeding it into the observer.
So the observer now is, ax-hat + bu +
l(y-Cx-hat) and, the one thing to note,
is that we need both, y and u to Feed
into the observer.
Now, out of the observer comes x-hat,
meaning, our estimate of what the system
is actually doing.
And now, we use x-hat to feed back, to
get are, are u.
And the beautiful thing here is that,
these two blocks together, they
constitute the controller.
So these two blocks are what's being done
in software and this, is the physics of
the world.
So this the plant, there's nothing we can
do about that and the controller consists
now of two pieces.
One piece that, estimates the state and
another piece that computes the control
action/g.
So now we have everything we need to do
effective control design and what we'll
do in the next lecture, which is the
final lecture, lecture of this module is
that we'll actually deploy it.
And in fact, we're going to see it in
action on a humanoid robot where we're
doing simultaneous control and state
estimation.