So, last lecture was really satisfying
because there, we finally understood how
we can do control design using the state
and then at the same time, figure out
what the state is and everything works.
Thanks to this fantastic principle known,
known as the separation principle.
So, what it tells us is that we can
completely decouple a control and
observer design, and here, I have a
rather important little parentheses that
says, in theory.
Now, there is a great American thinker
that has figured out that this in theory
is actually kind of important.
This is Yogi Berra, the baseball player
who presumably said, in theory, theory
and practice are the same. In practice,
they are not.
Now, this is rather profound and it has
some implications on the fact that just
because the theory tells us something, we
need to be aware of certain things at
least.
So, the first thing we need to be aware
of is, the controller is really only
useful once the estimate, that the
estimated state is close to the actual
state,
meaning, that the controller doesn't
really do anything useful until the
observer has converged.
So, what we want to do is want to make
sure that the observer converges quickly.
What that means is that we want the
observer to be faster which in turn means
that this eigenvalues that we were
picking should be larger for the observer
than the controller.
Now, one thing we saw with large
eigenvalues though, is that we get large
gains.
So, in the control side, this is kind of
bad, because that means that we have
large actuation signals, which means that
we can saturate the actuators.
In the controller side, I'm sorry, the
observer side, that's no big deal because
the observer is entirely done in
software.
There is nothing that's going to
saturate, so we can actually make our
observer eigenvalues large without having
to run into issues like saturation.
So practically, what we need to do is
pick the eigenvalues typically in such a
way that the controller eigenvalues are
all, first of all, they all need to have
negative real part, of course.
And then, what we want to do is we want
to make the observer eigenvalues bigger
because that means that the observer is
faster than what the controller is.
So, here is a completely made up
eigenvalue selection.
But the important thing here is that the
slowest observer eigenvalue, which really
dictates how quickly the observer
converges, is significantly faster than
the slowest controller eigenvalue.
So, that's something that we typically
want when we're building our joint
observer control design structures.
Okay.
Having said that, let's actually use this
to control a humanoid robot.
And this is the Aldebaran Nao that we're
going to be working on, and in fact, what
we can control on this thing are joint
angles, meaning how the different angles
are, are moving.
And luckily for us, we actually have
detailed models of these joint angles.
In fact, for a given joint, the angular
acceleration is 1/J times Ki minus B
theta dot.
And these things, well, they are physical
things.
So, J is the moment of inertia, i is our
input, alright, so i is actually equal to
u, here in this case.
This is our input to the system.
This is the current replying at the
motor.
Well, K is a torque constant that
translates roughly currents into
accelerations and then there's always a
friction coefficient,
the viscous friction coefficient in these
motors.
Now, luckily for us when you buy a robot
like this, someone has already figured
out these physical parameters and there
are user manuals that describe what these
parameters are.
Now, we need to put this on state base
form. And the first thing we're going to
do, as always is say, well x1 is theta
and x2 is theta dot,
alright?
We're also going to say that what we can
match around this thing is the angle
itself.
So, y is going to be equal to theta.
Well, with this choice, we get a linear
time-invariance system that looks like
this.
x dot is 0 1 x 0-b/Jx and then we have
this b matrix which is 0K/J times u and y
is 1, 0 x is since we're pulling out the,
the, orientation.
Now, one nice thing about this system is
that it is completely controllable and
completely observable.
So, what we have indeed learned in this
class should be applicable.
Okay. So, let's do that.
The last thing we want to do though is we
actually don't want to hold or stabilize
the Nao into all the angles being zero.
We want to be able to move it around.
So, what we want to do is, we actually
would like to track a reference angle.
We would like the, the angle of joints to
be something.
So, I'm going to define a new variable e,
it stands for error.
It's not the estimation error, it's
another error, which is the current angle
minus the desired angle.
And then as the second variable tossing
in the angular velocity.
And I would like to drive e to zero
because if I have e=0, then I have theta
equal to theta desired, meaning, I'm
holding it at the angle I would like.
And I have theta dot equal to zero, which
means I'm actually holding it there.
I'm not moving through it only.
Okay, so this is what we would like to
do.
okay, then we need to write down the
dynamics for our new variable e.
Well, e dot, well, it's simply, Ax+Bu,
because e dot is really, [SOUND] well,
it's theta dot minus theta desired dot
theta double dot, right? But this thing
is 0 because the, the desired heading is
constant, so all we're left with is theta
dot, theta double dot, which is the same
as x dot,
right? This is the same as x dot so what
we do is we plug in the equation for x
dot and we get this.
Now, we don't want to express this in
terms of x.
We want to express it in terms of e.
And what we get if we plug in e is, we
get this expression instead.
Now luckily for us, a times this vector
is actually equal to zero.
And I encourage you to compute this so
that you trust me. But having done that,
what we get is that e dot is equal to
Ae+Bu meaning we have same system
dynamics as before but now, defined on
this error, where the error is the
current orientation or angle of the joint
minus the desired angle of the joint.
So, this is the dynamics we're caring
about.
Well, we have to do the same thing to the
output.
The output is Cx, well again, we replace
x with e plus this vector.
So, this is Ce+C times this vector, and
remember that C was actually 1,0.
So, if I take 1,0 times that, out comes
data desired.
So, my output is C times e plus theta
desired.
Now, this doesn't scare us one bit.
We just plug it into our standard
controller and observer design
methodology.
So, u is -K, not e because we don't know
e but e hat,
which is our estimate of e.
And e hat dot,
well,
it has the standard predictor part and it
has the corrector part.
And the corrector part is the current
output minus what the output would have
been.
And the only difference is I have to keep
track of this little extra theta desired.
But it's no big deal.
It acts exactly the same way.
So, this is now my control structure.
And instead of me talking about it, why
don't we move on to see an actual
humanoid robot executing this controlled
strategy.
So now, that we have designed a, an
observer based state feedback controller
for controlling the joint angles of this
humanoid robot, the Aldebaran Nao, we're
ready to do it for real.
And I'm here with Amy LaViers. She was a
graduate student at Georgia Tech.
And what she has done is made the Nao
move its arms and its head, and even its
upper body, in such a way that it is
executing a friendly wave towards,
probably you, who are watching this right
now.
And, what's happening is we're running
the same controller on all the different
joints with different desired angles to
get the effect out.
So, Amy, why don't we take the Nao for a
little spin there and see what it can do?
So, what's going on here is that we're
sequentially running multiple desired
angles and that's how we're getting this
effect.
In fact, why don't we watch this again
because I think this is quite, it's quite
charming to be honest.
So, here we go.
Observer-based state feedback controlling
action.
Oh, thank you very much,
Amy.
And thank you.