Hello, and welcome to Glue Lecture Four.
I'm Smriti Chopra, your instructor for the
Glue Lectures, and let's get into it.
So this lecture is titled Controllability
and Observability,
because this week, with Dr. Egerstedt, you
guys learned
about what is a system and then more
importantly, how do you see if it's
stable, unstable?
And if it's unstable, how do you
stabilize it through controls?
But before you can do that, you need to
see if the system is controllable.
And let's say you did stabilize it.
Now you want to see if it's observable,
because, you know, you
don't have state information, so you need
to somehow bring in output, etc.
And then we see how you put everything
together.
So in this lecture, we're just going to go
over this
one big example clearing all these
concepts for you guys.
Okay?
So let's start with system stability.
Let's say this is my robot, and just an
arm is all that we're going to consider,
which is your theta 1 and theta 2 to join
the angles of this arm, two angles.
And I'm going to see that my state is this
guy here, which are the angles and their
velocities.
And my A matrix is this.
This is how my state relates to its
derivatives, right?
This is given to us.
So this is what our system looks like,
this guy, by this equation here.
There you go.
So now what are we going to do?
We're going to check if the system is
stable.
Does it blow up, or as time goes to
infinity, or is going to be stable on its
own?
And the way to do that is by checking the
eigen values of A, right?
So in Matlab you can simply type eig A, or
you can sit and find out the
eigen values yourself.
Either way.
Here we just put it in Matlab, and we see
that all eigen values of A are 0.
And we know from our lectures that when
the eigen
values are all 0, that means your system
is unstable.
So we found out that for this system, this
particular x and A, our guy is unstable.
Okay, so that means we need to introduce
control, right?
But how do you introduce control?
We know this pretty equation here, x dot
equal to Ax plus Bu.
But what does it really mean?
What is B?
What is u; u of course, is our control
signal.
Well, we need to first find out what it is
that we can
control about the system, let's say
through
putting motors or through putting
actuators, etc.
So we're going to assume that we can
control
the acceleration of my first joint angle,
theta
1.
And if we do that, then we see that our B
matrix turns out to be this guy here.
Why?
Because now, when you put B here in this
equation of yours, you'll
see that the input u shows up next to
theta 1 double dot.
That means you can influence the
acceleration of
my theta 1 double of my theta 1, right?
That's where my input shows up.
So that's how you generate
your B matrix.
Now that we have this, great.
But can we, with this particular choice of
B, actually control this guy or not?
That is, do we see if it's controllable of
not?
And for this we have a very simple test,
which is you create this matrix.
This is the controllability matrix, right?
And then you simply check the rank of this
matrix.
So here we
going to make this matrix first.
And you guys should be comfortable with
finding matrix multiplications, etc.
Not for maybe such big systems, but for
let's say a
two by two matrix, you should be able to
do it.
If you want we can really fast go over one
example.
For example, this is your A, right: 0000,
1000, 0000,
0010.
And then you've got, I'm going to find AB.
So let's put B here, which is 0100.
And now, because my A is a 4 cross 4, and
my B is a 4 cross 1, my resulting matrix
is going to be a 4 cross 1, right?
And let's multiply quick: 0 times 01000.
So this guy, because there's a one that
lines up at the same place.
We're going to get a 1 here, which is here
too, right?
And then there are no 1s that line up, so
you get a 0, 0, and 0.
So you see how we got this guy here,
which correlates to this vector in the
controllability matrix.
So you should be able to do AB, A square
B, etc, quite easily, for at least 2 cross
2 matrices.
And now we're going to check the rank of
this guy,
and it turns out that the rank here is 2.
But we have this condition
that the rank needs to be full rank, or
the matrix
needs to have full rank in order for it to
be controllable.
That means it should have all linearly
independent vectors, right?
And what do you mean by full rank?
Basically, your rank should be equal to n,
Where
n is the number of states that you have.
Here n is 4, right?
So clearly, this guy has rank 2, not equal
to 4,
and that's why this guy is uncontrollable.
And in case you don't want to sit and,
you know, compute rank, etc, of all these
things, you can even do this in Matlab.
And this is the code for it.
You create your A matrix.
Create your B matrix.
Then the CTRB function will give you the
controllability matrix gamma.
And then you just do rank of this guy and
pops out 2,
which is not equal to 4, we know that, and
so it's uncontrollable.
Okay?
All right, perfect.
So now what do we do?
It's uncontrollable.
Should we just give up?
No.
We need to introduce more controls
somehow, right?
And then we saw earlier,
how do you introduce control?
It's by putting actuators, putting motors,
seeing what else you can control.
So here in this case, let's say now we can
control theta 1
double dot, and theta 2 double dot, the
acceleration of theta 2 as well.
And of course, then what will happen to
your B matrix?
This is how the B matrix will look, right?
And to double check again, put it here.
See if, in fact, u shows up for both theta
1 double dot, and theta 2 double dot, and
then we know that u is influencing these
accelerations, right?
Okay, so now we have this new guy, and
we have to check if this is controllable
or not.
And we do the same thing again.
We create the controllability matrix.
And we're going to do this in
Matlab, because we don't feel like
computing everything.
And this is the code again for it.
Again, very similar to what we did
earlier.
This time your controllability matrix is
going to
be much bigger, because you have two
vectors here in B.
So your AB is going to have dimension 4
plus 4 times
4 cross 2, which gives you 4 cross 2
instead of 4 cross 1.
So each guy here is going to be your, you
know, B, AB, A square B, A cube B.
So you see, now your matrix has expanded.
And anyway, now you find the rank of this
guy
in terms of this rank is 4, which is equal
to
the number of states we have, and so we
are
full rank, which is great, because that
means we are controllable.
Okay, so now that we are controllable, for
this particular system, what does it mean?
It means that I can use u to make my
original system,
which was x dot equal to Ax, unstable
original system, stable, right?
And how do we do that?
We use state feedback.
That is, we say, u is equal to negative
Kx.
And now we're going to try and design our
K so that we can force the eigen
values to make sure that this system is
stable, right?
Okay, let's go over this example, because
finding K for
this huge 4 cross 4 matrix, etc, is really
cumbersome.
We'll just use a simpler system.
Let's shave off one angle completely.
So let's just think of our state as theta
1.
And theta 1 double dot, theta 1 dot.
So we've just gotten rid of theta 2.
No problem.
So we have this new guy here, but again,
now we have to do this entire charade
again.
First we need to find out, is this guy
stable or not?
And I'm just going to give you the answer.
You should do it yourself, just to
convince yourself.
But yeah, this guy is unstable.
So I'm going to introduce control through
this plus Bu thing.
And again, I'm going to say I can control
the acceleration.
I'm going to get this as my B matrix.
And now, is this controllable?
Because that's the second question you
ask, right?
And I'm going to tell you it's
controllable.
You guys can find out on your own.
Just make the controllability matrix.
Do it.
It's good exercise.
And now I'm going to come back to, okay,
state feedback.
We're going to design state feedback, but
for the much simpler system, so
we can actually work it out ourselves
instead of putting it in Matlab.
Okay,
with that, so how do we do this?
We know that our system is controllable,
and
we have this guy, u equal to negative Kx.
So let's put u into this equation of our x
dot, and we get
this new guy here, right, x dot is equal
to this big guy here.
Okay.
So we just put the values inside.
A, this is A.
B, your K is this.
1 cross
2 matrix, k1 and k2, two gains, and what
you finally get
after solving this entire thing is this
new guy here, or simply A dash, right?
So you have this new A dash, where you've
put
in your control and everything, which is
this matrix here.
And we all know that if you are given a
system
x dot equal to Ax, or A dash x, or
whatever,
to see if it's stable or not, you check
the eigen values of A or A dash.
In this case, we have control over k1 and
k2, so we're actually going to force the
eigen values through our k1 and k2 to B to
make sure that the system is stable.
And if you remember, the eigen value's one
condition is that the, the
real part of the eigen value should be in
the left half plane, right?
So we're going to force, through our k1
and k2, the eigen values to be
in the left half plane of the world.
Okay, with that so how do you find the
eigen values?
So in the first slide we pretty much just
put it in Matlab and said eig A.
But really, how you do it is, you find
this guy here, the determinant of A dash
minus lambda I, which is really, if you
follow it, turns out to be this.
So basically what you're
doing is, you're saying A, and
then you have, so when you actually solve
the system, you're just going to get minus
lambda 1, 1 minus k1, minus k2, minus
lambda 2 as your final matrix.
And then you find the determinant of this
guy
and solve it, and you'll get this equation
right here.
Okay.
Another exercise that you guys should be
doing on your own.
And it's good stuff.
Okay.
So now that we have this characteristic
polynomial, what we're going to do is
we're going to pick our two favorite eigen
values on the left half plane.
And let's say we pick negative 1 and
negative 2.
So now what we're going to do is, this is
what we got.
And this is what we want, right, which is
just this guy here.
So we are just going to simply compare
these two guys,
and get our values for k2 and k1, just by
simple comparison of two polynomials.
Because what happens now is that, with
this particular choice of k2
and k1, my system, with this particular
choice is going to actually be stable.
Just one quick thing.
So yeah, when you put this k2 and k1 here,
in this guy, right,
in this matrix, now your A dash is
definitely going to have this eigen value.
This is what it really means.
And because we chose these eigen values to
be in the left
half plane, we know that this new system
is going to be stable.
Okay.
So yeah.
There you go.
We have state feedback on a simpler
system.
We chose our key, and now we know that
this guy is stable.
So,
woo-hoo.
But now, we come to another annoying
thing,
which is that we don't know our state.
We are very happy saying that, oh, you
should
be negative Kx, but we don't have this x.
What we instead have is x hat, an estimate
of our state.
We don't even have that, but this is what
we are using really.
And now we need to find this estimate of
our state.
And for that, again, now we have to
introduce this concept of output.
What can we see?
What are our senses?
What can we measure?
That's why the whole y matrix and the
whole thing comes in.
Why?
Because now we say, assume we can see this
guy here.
Theta 1.
So, accordingly, my C matrix is going to
be this, and my y is equal to Cx.
Again, why?
Because when
you put the C guy inside here, you'll see
that your
y becomes simply theta 1, and that's what
we can see, right?
So we choose what we can see, we choose
the senses we have,
and then we create C, and accordingly, get
this y equal to Cx thing.
But now we come to this other whole thing
of, is, is this observable?
Is this new system now observable?
The new system being these guys.
Is it observable?
Which means, that can I, in fact, estimate
my
state, x hat, based on this particular C
matrix.
And for that, you have a very
simple test, very similar to the
controllability matrix.
This guy is called the observability
matrix.
And because we have just two states here,
this is going to be a short little matrix.
And you find out what it is which, you
guys can.
And then you check the rank of this guy.
This rank is actually equal to 2.
Is it full rank or not?
Well it is, because our states, our number
of states are, sorry, 2, right?
Here.
So yes.
It is in fact full rank, which means that
this guy is observable.
Perfect.
That is great.
So yay.
But what does it really mean?
Again, just to reiterate, what it means
is that from lectures, you guys remember
that you can write
the dynamics of your estimate of your
state in this form.
Where L is just some gain matrix, very
similar to your K matrix for
controllability, right?
And by saying this, what it really means
is that if you were
to write down the error dynamics given
this guy for your state dynamics,
you get this matrix here, which looks very
similar to A minus
KB right?
For, if you guys remember from your
earlier controllability analysis.
So very nice.
Why?
Because now we can choose L the same way
that we chose
K, to make sure that the eigen values of
this guy here
force the error to become stable, or in
fact, what that
means is basically force that the error
does not blow up.
It, as time goes to infinity, the error
actually
diminishes to 0, and that's what really
observability means.
Can you in fact find an L that will make
sure that the error
goes to 0, which means that my estimate
will become equal to my state.
Okay,
perfect.
So for the quiz, it's important you guys
should be familiar at least with
what is really going on, what is the
dynamics of my estimate, error, etc.
Just be comfortable with understanding
what it is that's happening.
And now all together, execution, because
this is the most important part, right?
We have got these little blocks
everywhere, controllable, observable,
blah, blah, blah.
But we really don't know how to
put it all together.
And that's what we're going to do now.
So this is our system.
X dot equal to Ax plus Bu, y is equal to
Cx.
With this particular choice of x, A, B,
and C, which we've been solving all this
while.
Okay, and then we have found out that x
dot equal to
Ax on its own is unstable, and then by
introducing B and C,
the system is controllable and observable.
Great.
Controllable means I can find a K to make
sure that my system becomes stable.
Observable means I can find L to make sure
that I can in fact estimate my state,
right?
So let's put it all together.
So I wake up at this time t equal to t
nought where I'm at
some x equal to x nought that I don't
know, because I don't know my state.
But I'm
going to estimate my x had to be some x
hat nought.
Right?
Just something.
And I'm going to start my loop with DD
increments.
So I started d not, and I'm going to start
incrementing time with dd increments.
Okay, and I'm going to read the output.
Because I don't have my state information,
all I have is the
output, so I'm going to read what my
output is giving me.
Okay,
then using that, I'm going to compute my
control, u equal to negative Kx hat,
not using the output, using the estimate,
the initial estimate that we had.
Simply.
Okay and, remember that you've already
designed K and L.
Okay, so you compute your output, sorry,
compute your control,
and then you send this control signal to
your system, right?
And then you update x hat using your
dynamics, where x hat was this guy here.
And this is where you use your output,
what output you read.
Right?
Because for control you need x hat, so now
obviously you need to see
where is your new x hat, and that you're
going to update through this guy here.
And just remember, when you're updating
your dynamics,
all I have here is x hat dot.
How do I find out what my x hat should be
the next time instant, you know what,
you're going to use this Oiler's
approximation, which we
all studied together in the Glue Lecture
One, I think.
And of course you've
been going over it with Dr. Egerstedt.
Basically, your next step is your previous
step, plus dt times your dynamics.
Right?
So that's what we're going to do.
We're going to find out x hat dot, and
then we're going to just say our next
guy is our previous guy, which was this
estimate here, plus dt times x hat dot.
And that'll give us our new guy.
And now we're going to repeat.
So now when we come back, we can read the
output again, compute the new controls and
the control update
x hat, etc.
This is how we put all of this
stuff together, for execution, in your
code, etc, whatever.
Okay, and with that, check the forums,
good luck with Quiz Four.
All the best.