Hi and welcome to the second
segment of Spacecraft Kinetics.
Here, we're going to be looking at
torque free motion on rigid bodies.
We start out with a single rigid body and
study how this actually
will evolve over time.
How does the spin change?
And this is all coupled
to the gyroscopics.
We will study this with
several different methods.
One of them is called Portal.
It's a very cool graphical way actually
to study large scale motions and
why are certain spins stable and unstable.
We're also then going to be looking at
different specialized analytic answers
where we can consider things like
axisymmetric bodies that have special
answers or bodies that have.
Distinct inertias like this box here,
we go to skinny, intermediate, and
maximum edge.
You'll answer questions like why is this
spin more or less stable, while if you do
the other spin about the intermediate
axis, you'll find it flips very quickly.
So we're going to show those results.
In the end,
we're going to look at the dual spinner,
which another passive way
to stabilize an object.
So while certain spin orientations for
the single body are unstable,
with a double body system, we can
actually stabilize any of those axes.
And we go through the mathematics
of developing equations of motion,
looking at equilibria, and
then discussing stability again.