Quick questions.
What kind of shape do I have if my
interception curves look like this?
>> Symmetric.
>> Is it axisymmetric?
I know, you took it in 3200.
You've seen this one.
But why is it axisymmetric?
>> The energy ellipsoid is the same
width in one and two axis?
>> The interception
lines have constant H3.
If you go back and
look at the differential equations here,
H3 that means omega three is constant,
this will go to omega three dot
goes to zero if I2 is equal to I1.
And then you can have a constant H3,
right?
That's the intersection point
that you're going to have, and
we're spinning this way.
If you're here though, that means that my
omega three, my H3 coordinate is zero,
therefore omega three coordinate is zero.
If omega three is zero,
then this one is already zero to
begin with because of the inertias.
If omega three is zero these, omega threes
make both of those terms go to zero.
That's why you get points.
Those are now pure spin conditions
that you would have and
they don't wobble beyond that.
What kind of shape is this going to be?
So basically, it says whatever spin axis
I pick, it's just going to stay there.
>> Sphere.
>> A sphere, good.
With a sphere, you can take a sphere and
spin it about any axis and
it'll just keep spinning.
And that is a pure spin.
So, the sphere is an easy one.
No matter how bad you are,
you're spinning about a principal axis, or
it wouldn't be a sphere.
Is there another shape you could use?
The cube.
All you need is your principal inertias
have to be equal, and for a cube,
that's the case.
We don't have a spherical
mass distribution, but
we still get three equal.
That's why it's easy,
actually, to throw a cube.
A cube should be random, in that case.
So if you go to Vegas and throw the dice,
it should give you some random stuff.
Every throw should have
an equal probability,
unless you're playing with
a professional gambler, in which case,
they put a slight mass in there, right?
And bias it in one direction.
And all this kind of is no longer true,
because we no longer have equal inertias.
That's how gamblers today,
they're very smart with the math.
I'm sure you did it this way,
not just testing that.
>> [LAUGH]
>> But the cube is one of the things,
exactly.
Spheres people often think about it,
but the cubes,
cubes ask these kind of things as well.
If you want to spin them about any axis,
actually you can spin them,
as long as it's a perfect
mass distribution.
While we build cube sized spacecraft, the
internals aren't necessarily homogeneous,
so even with a cube outer shape,
you still have to look the internal.
Where's the battery?
Where's the antenna?
Right, that could shift and
give you three unique inertias.
But if you fill it up with lead and
launch it, that would happen.
Okay.