Torque free motion.
Momentum has to be constant.
The momentum magnitude has to be constant,
which is what I'm writing
here in the first equation.
And kinetic energy has to be constant.
So we're not considering actual
mechanical energy loss right now.
Like, before, like the Paul will plots,
let's assume T and
H are perfectly preserved.
You can write the momentum at energy
constraints in terms of your omegas.
H was I omega, so that for
the magnitude is the component squared.
That's easy, magnitude squared.
And kinetic energy was 1/2, so
the 2 comes to the left-hand side.
This one was just to make a transpose
I Omega, that I is a diagonal.
Again, makes it very easy.
This is the form that you would have.
Now these are two constraints.
And we have three variables.
And quickly this illustrates again,
that the omega curve that you're
going to get isn't going to be a plane or
a volume, the solution space.
It's going to be one dimensional curve
in three dimensional omega space, right?
That's what we're looking for.
We have three unknowns, omega one,
two and three and two constraints.
So I can always use these two constraints
and that's what I'm laying out here.
I say, okay well let me just pick to
write everything in terms over omega 1.
Why?
because it's the first thing one that
appears.
So I can use this and
solve for omega 2 squared and
that's what you have in this equation.
And I can solve this for
omega 3 squared which comes up here.
So you've got two equations and
two terms, omega one and
two that I'm solving for, so
just rule any algebra and you reduce it.
So, now because of these constrains if I
have an omega one and I know my momentum
and I know my energy added at
the beginning, I can quickly tell you what
the magnitude squared of omega two has and
the same thing for omega three, all right?
So it's just the way of
re-writing momentum and
energy constrains
exclusively in omega terms.
Now what makes omega 1 special?
Nothing really.
There's nothing special about omega 1.
You could've just as easily solved
everything in terms of omega 2 or
you could've used in two equations and
say, well,
I'm going to solve everything for
omega 1 and 2 in terms of omega 3, right?
You can solve this any which way you wish.
And substitute them again.
I will use all of them.
This was in the paper by Junkins,
Jacobson,
Blanton that you've got
a reference down here.
It's actually from 1973.
Most of you weren't even born.
But it's an eloquent result here and
you will see,
this has some analogy to
the axisymmetric cases.
But it gives you a more general
formulation that you don't often see.
So this page, all we've done is we've
taken momentum energy equations and
we've used it to express the omegas
in terms of momentum and energy and
one of the other omegas, that's it.
So let's go back to the original problem.
This is the one we're trying to solve.
We've got these differential equations.
There's no L's on the right-hand
side because there's no torque.
How do we solve this?
Before with axis symmetry,
one of them was 0.
So we could say omega 3 is fixed and
therefore we took a derivative of this,
substitute into the others, right?
And came up with nicely decoupled ones.
Now everything varies with time and
I can no longer do that trick directly.
But there's still similar steps.
We're going to start out with
the same kind of a step.
We have three fully coupled and
now non-linear differential equations,
whereas before I had two coupled
linear differential equations.
I'm still going to take a derivative just
because it worked so well for the axis and
metric let's try it here, right.
And you do this, and then with chain rule,
Omega is Omega 2's 3's Omega 1, everything
varies with time, and here you go, to make
a 1, 2, 3 double outs divided by inertia.
That's basically it.
So you're going okay,
great, where is this going?
So you took a derivative again.
Now similar as to with the axis
symmetric case, omega 1 dot for
the axis symmetric only depended on
omega 2 because omega 3 was constant.
Well, what we're going to do now
is we plug in the second and
third differential equation into here.
And rewrite this all and
you end up with this expression
here that you going to have.
So omega 1..,
is equal to omega 1 omega 2 squared.
And omega 1 omega 3 squared.
As you can see there's
still quite coupled.
There's still non-linear Just I went from
three non linear first order differential
equations to three non linear second
order differential equations.
Seems like we're going backwards,
we're not making much progress.
But here's the elegant thing now,
from the prior slide,
I have for example omega 2 squared
In terms of just a constant and
something times omega 1.
And the same thing for omega 3 squared.
So if you look at the second
order differential equations,
here is omega 1, omega 1.
I can write omega 2 squared in
terms of a constant and omega 1.
And the same thing for omega 3 squared.
So by using the momentum and
the kinetic energy constraints,
I can substitute those in and
instead of having time varying quantities,
I have everything in terms of constants of
energy and consular momentum magnitude.
And what you can do for one,
you can follow the same process here.
We use here the expressions where omega
1 and 3 are written in terms of omega 2.
And here we use the third set that writes
omega 1 and 2 in terms of omega 3, right.
There's three different ways we could
take two constraints and solve for
two to three variables.
If you do that and plug them in,
so that's the process,
those equations we found,
and you plug them in here.
And then you do the same thing for the
other two look what happens in the end.
This is omega 1,
just a bunch of constants.
Omega 1 times constant something
times omega 1 squared.
So you're going to get omega 1 term and
then something times omega 1 squared
will give you omega 1 cubed essentially.
So the final form for everyone of
these omegas, I can write it as a,
what's called a homogeneous
undamped Duffing equations.
Homogeneous just means
the right hand side is 0.
Undamped, there's no omega dot.
Just omega double dots and omegas.
And the Duffing equation, is this classic,
this would be a spring mass equation.
The Duffing equation is a spring mass with
a cubic Stiffness term added to it, so
like a cubic spring instead
of a linear spring.
It's a common modeling
thing to see as well.
So, all three of the omegas actually
have an equation of this form.
But you would have these As and
Bs which depend on omega 1, 2 and 3, and
you can see,
the inertias are computed differently, and
when you plug it in, energy and
momentum come in with different terms so
we have formulas for
the As and Bs have to be.
So this is actually very elegant
because we often see systems that are,
we end up with x double dot plus kx,
right?
If it's x double dot plus k equal to 0,
it should be trivial to talk
about linear stability, at least.
You've linearized the system for
small motions locally.
If k is positive, we know we'll have
a restoring force let me just draw
that out because we're about to mute that.
So if you, If I have M.
Forget M, we'll just do normalized.
That means x double dot = kx.
So if x is here, you can look
at what happens to x double dot.
If x is positive,
the x double dot is going to be negative.
And it's a linear relationship.
So if you're too far ahead, the force is
going to restore you back to the origin.
If you're too far behind,
and x is negative,
-k be the positive value that then
makes it positive, you can catch up.
This gives you the typical oscillator
equation that you'd have, but
it's a stable motion.
So that works.
But this result is typically due
to a linearization that you get.
Here have we linearized
anything when we derived this?
No, we just used full nonlinear
differential equations,
differentiated them,
substituted in energy momentum, and
you end up with three equations,
we've a first order term and a cubic term.
The cubic term 2, if you do structures,
you often see this cubic term.
But it's the result of an approximation.
Once you go beyond
the first order stiffness,
the next term people typically
include is the cubic term.
If the fractions get really big like
strain hardening on a spring or something.
You get this extra stiffness that
comes in, that's the cubic term.
But again,
in structures, that's an approximation
of a much more complex behavior.
It's like the next order
term that's included.
Here this is a perfectly
rigorous equation.
So in structures,
this is often found as an approximation.
Here there's no approximation.
Is it exact thing for
tumbling general inertia, motions.
So good, so we want to study this now.
A little bit more detail.
We have three equations.
When we only had these parts,
that was the axisymmetric case
it was easy, spring mass.
It was a sine and
a cosine response, right?
Now here it's going to get
a little more complicated.
Unfortunately I don't have analytic
answers as we have with the axisymmetric
codes but there are some arguments we can
talk about like global stability of these
motions and departures that you can write
it in this form is kind of a nice thing.
So yeah,
then I'll lead departure from Hooke's law.
That's the linear part,
this is an exact differential equation.
So we can do this.
So this is actually three equations.
Are these three equations decoupled?
>> [COUGH]
>> Sorry, what was your name?
>> Mark.
>> Mark, are they decoupled?
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
Are they independent?
>> Yes.
Well, not because of the constants.
>> You said it with such conviction
you almost had me convinced.
Why are they not independent?
Everybody agrees they're decoupled.
If you look at this each equation
has only omega 1s in there.
And the next term only has omega 2's and
the other one has only omega 3's there's
no omega 1 times omega
3's as we had originally.
So we definitely made them independent.
Once you have all the initial conditions
and these parameters you can solve three
independent differential equations
numerically and get the answer.
But independent is something
different that means,
lets say I have a spin
about omega 1 only and
the next simulation is a spin about omega
1 and tumble about B2 or something.
It is the same omega 1 but
it has a different B2.
What will be different in
these differential equations?
because you're right,
they aren't independent, Matt?
>> They are energy momentum terms?
>> Exactly.
The energy momentums are actually
what cross couples them, so
they're not independent.
I can't just go well,
if omega 1 is one radium per second,
I have a fixed answer that's not true.
Because the coefficients that go
here depend on momentum and energy.
And so it's a little bit more complicated
if you also tumbling about another access,
your energy state is different,
momentum states are different, and
that will give you different A's and B's.
So you have to solve it for
that particular case.
So there are three uncoupled equations but
not independent equations.
Is that make sense?
They're coupled through this coefficients
through energy and momentum, precisely.
So, the three uncoupled oscillators and
that's there.
If I write them out to As and Bs, this
is what they are, as you can see, T and
H has appeared.
The inertia's always the same,
it's the same with your body.
But as your math was saying,
if H is different and
T is different, I would have different
coefficients, and all of a sudden and
then we get a different response
with these omegas, right?
So that's where it does matter.
But it's very elegant so for the general
case you can always write this as
a harmonious,
homogenous on them to Duffling equation.
Now with these parameters we'll look
at this a little bit more carefully but
you can see, for
example, the cubic stiffness terms Bs,
there's differences of inertias again.
So we know right away
if it's axis symmetric,
some of these things will go away,
some insight you get.
But at the same time,
I'd say if it's a cube or
a sphere, all of these terms go away.
For a sphere, none of that matters.
Even in here there's always differences
of inertia so for sphere again, As and
Bs go away which we talked about.
A sphere you can tumble about any axis and
it'll just continue to tumble,
your mega 1, 2, 3s are all flat lines,
always, or for a cube the same response.
But for general bodies,
if I1 is your largest inertia.
You can see this is going to be
a positive term times a positive term,
this is going to be
a positive cubic stiffness.
Down here again, if I1 is the largest,
so this is going to be negative,
that's negative,
negative times negative is positive again.
Again we'll have a positive
stiffness whereas here
you'll have a negative stiffness.
So is positive stiffness good or
bad for a stability for a cubic one?
>> Good.
>> It's good.
It's pretty much analogous.
Instead of a liner response, now you
have something that's kind of cubic.
But you need the same kind of a sign,
right?
If you're positive, you want something
pulling you back to the origin.
The origin is the equilibrium
that we'll be studying here.
And if you're negative, you want
something positive to pull you back.
It's just got to be more aggressive for
big departures, but
way less aggressive for small departures.
So there's a difference
in the cubic terms.
That's why for a linearization, this is
the linear part it's going to dominate.
But if you go really big departures,
the cubic one is always going to win.
At some point,
x cubed is going to be bigger than x,
regardless of what these constant
coefficients are, these As and Bs.
So good.
So you can see just looking at
the signs of this we can get
some insight into what
must be happening and
we'll cover this a little bit more in
another slide as we go through it.