There's an integral, every one of those
equations we can actually integrate and
come up with these conserved quantities.
You can think I'm calling him K here,
this is not kinetic energy,
it's something different.
But it's like energy, so
it's an integral of motion basically.
So it leaves us a waypoint
to go to a set of slides.
So let's say we have our
classic mx double dot
= -kx.
Anybody know what the integral
of motion of this one is?
What's the preserved quantity
of this differential equation?
Spring mass system.
What's constant?
You did it in the homework with
two particles in the spring mass.
Part B, what did you have to
use to get that relationship?
Energy, right.
Basically.
We know out of this, this is nothing but
a spring mass system.
So we know that that kinetic energy and
the spring potential energy summed
up will give us a constant, right.
But we know that.
Can we mathematically prove it?
So I'm going to show you quickly
how to integrate these system.
And this is a simple linear system.
With this other term there, the cubic
stiffness has an x cubed instead of an x.
But even x cubed is trivial to integrate.
I expect you guys to know
how to integrate x cubed.
In the next homework you will
have other terms in there.
There was one homework where
you end up with a sine theta,
but even sine theta isn't that evil.
I know you guys know how to
integrate sine theta, hopefully.
So you can come up with these
integrals of motions, all right.
So let's see how we can do this.
And there's some little tricks.
You'd have to write them down to
remember all the little steps.
So I've got the second ordered
derivative of x equals to minus kx.
This works nicely.
Now I'm going to do a substitution where
I'm saying v is simply x dot, right?
It's commonly done,
like you do in second order system,
we put in first order forms and
integrate it.
That's typically what we do.
So this side can be
rewritten as dv/dt = -kx.
And you can can also say, well,
let me multiply this dt
Over to the other side.
So mass times differential velocities
equal to -kx times differential time.
This phone,
this side is easy to integrate.
That's just mdv.
The integral of that is just going to
a give you v plus the constant.
But the right hand side, x depends on
time and we don't have an answer for
it in this form yet.
Is not as easy, so once you get to
the stage breaking these dts and dvs up,
the trick is you want to
multiply both sides times v
which is of course dx/dt,
right that's what .x means.
So if I multiply both
sides over with this.
Here on the left hand side,
I'm going to have mvdv, that's easy.
So, right hand side -kx times v and
v is dx/dt.dt.
These dt's cancel and
you end up with nothing but
-kxdx, that's it.
Now we've got a set of equations we
can easily integrate and I'm not doing
in between two specific points in time I'm
just going to get the indefinite integral.
So, if you do the indefinite
integral of this,
the integral v with respect to v is
just going to be v squared over 2 right.
So you end up with mass velocity
squared over two which is nothing but
kinetic energy.
The right hand side,
the integral of x with respect to x is
just going to be -kx squared over 2.
And then out of this whole thing
you have to do plus a constant.
What's this constant physically
going to be in this problem?
If you look at it the constant mv
squared over 2 plus kx squared over 2,
what is that?
Total energy exactly that's it.
That's because it has a physical thing but
in a more abstract sense when you have
differential equations we
can often do this step but
you don't get something that's
actually in terms of energy it's just
an equation constant of whatever
these other things are right?
So here happens to be total energy but
if you go back to these differential
equations and do the same steps
bring this to the right hand side.
Instead of just having a minus A omega
I also Also have minus B omega cubed,
I did the integrals of those in the end
then I'll have an x to the 4th over 4 and
an x squared over 2 with
the right constants, and
an integration constant, right?
And that's what we found here,
so if you do that step,
and I encourage you to practice that
once because in the homework you have to
use it anyway for one of the solve
the homework for, you can get this.
So this is the integration constant,
you can see this is not mass over velocity
squared the units are wrong this
is actually velocity rates,
this is an acceleration squared,
this can't be energy but
it's something energy like in that
term and this is a preserve quantity.
If I get my resulting tumbling motion
out of your integration, and every
integration times that if you're computing
on mega .2 integrated and you have
your current omega and you go through this
math, you should always get the same k.
All right?
So this becomes the great integration
check for talk free motion as well.
And I think one of the homeworks, in the
next homeworks said has you numerically
stimulate this and validate that this
actually, you stimulate this numerically,
you compute this analytically
with the T's and the H's.
And this math should always
give you back that same value
that everything make sense.
That's a good numerical
check of what's going on.
So this k1, 2's and 3's are now
written out in terms of the energies,
these your integration constants for
the system.
So I'm giving you the complete
answer here at this stage.