We're looking at torque free motion.
And we did plots.
Let me jump to this one.
So what are the some key things
we did with these polar plots?
Nathaniel, can you talk me through here?
What does this stuff actually show us,
how do we get these kind of plots,
what are we doing?
>> We're showing the energy as the, and
the stability of the spinning, rigid body.
>> Okay.
>> So-
>> So what's this sphere?
Let's go back to basics,
you're jumping into details.
>> I don't remember the name of it.
>> Okay.
Was it Andrew?
>> No.
>> Sorry, next to Nathaniel, yes, Ick?
>> Nick.
>> That was off, completely.
>> The momentum sphere.
>> It's a momentum sphere, right?
So instead of using omega one's,
two's, and
three's as independent rate coordinates,
we use h one's, two's, and three's.
Which is nothing but omega i's times
the principal inertia, that's it, right?
But it's convenient because
the momentum magnitude being constant,
not the momentum vector.
We're using a sub result,
just a magnitude being constant.
It gives us a nice geometric answer,
it's a sphere, what causes these
intersections on this sphere?
So we're intersecting a sphere with what?
An ellipsoid,
an ellipsoid represents energy.
So your rotational kinetic energy,
using the same H1 2 coordinates,
we're able to rewrite and
it's a classic ellipsoidal shape.
So we've got this ellipsoid and
we have to intersect, so
here I'm showing you lots
of different energy levels.
Nathaniel was talking about stability.
If you hear stability,
the first thing you have to think
about is stability about what?
So in these plots we identified
some equilibrias, spin equilibrias.
So if you take an object and
you spin it about a certain axis,
it's just going to keep on spinning,
and that omega stays constant.
And all the omegas stay constants, right.
What were the equilibrias we identified
for a torque free rigid body?
Matt.
>> H1 and H3.
>> Well, if you have it only in
H1 intersection, that's true.
This was here, could you have a pure spin,
an equilibria here?
>> Pragmatically, yes.
>> Then is it an equilibria or not?
All right,
this is a common source of confusion.
That's why I'm glad we'll be going over
this again especially as we get into
control stuff.
Equilibrium just means, x dot is equal
to zero, and here, x is my omega right?
So all my omega rates are zero,
it's not mathematical, not mathematical.
That's an equilibrium of
the system all right?
Equilibrium has nothing
to do with stability.
Stability is a different argument but
sometimes,
people confuse equilibrium being as
stable as things turning a round.
So you've got the classical pendulum
this is one of the equilibrium.
And what's the other equilibrium
we have over planar pendulum?
Right, upside down.
Those are two equilibrius,
now its a must, that's it.
But if I look at now stability I
can talk about neighboring motions,
if you just off a little bit on this one.
Gravity will basically help stabilize and
it stays closed a little
bit that thing it settles.
If we turned it upside down, if we
have to use a little bit of departure,
are you going to stay close and
of course not.
We know it's can deviate away, right?
So, just keep those two
mathematical concepts separate,
equilibrium just means
your X star is equal to 0.
If you put it in this condition
it would remain there perfectly.
Stability now talks about well if I'm off
a little bit and that's kind of where
the real world starts because we never
have it perfectly, well do I stay close?
So of these you basically answered
the two spins that would be stable
if I have a slightly more than
my minimum energy condition,
I would be one of these wobbles, and
you can see you stay reasonably close.
Same thing here this is
the maximum energy condition,
I'm spinning about
the axis of least inertia.
And if I'm off a little bit you can
see wobble lines these intersection
lines are staying close.
This one though is unstable, that's
the one where you take your hammer and
you flip your tool, it always flips
180 very, very, very quickly, right?
So what happens, you go from this side and
you quickly go over here, all right?
Now, there is a very particular energy
case, this is the minimum energy,
maximum energy and
here is the intermediate access energy.
For minimum, maximum or
its general inertia
there's only one point one kind of
a spin you're spinning about b1 or b3.
If you have the intermediate energy level
you could be spinning here mathematically,
or you could also be on this inner section
line which is called the separatrix.
It's not just a single spin for
the intermediate energy level
that's the solution, it's actually
there's these different arcs.
Now if you're on the let's say,
you can see the arrows, they come in.
What can you say about how you will
approach this pure spin condition?
>> Tebow, like if you're exactly on it,
it'll take infinite to get there.
>> Right.
You never actually reach this point
in a fine right amount of time.
RIght, so you're only asymptotically
ever reach it on this energy
if you slightly off this one.
We saw that in the video last time
with the astronaut spinning that key.
Right, it kind of span.
It looked like it was reasonably stable,
a little bit of wabble but staying close.
The next thing you know,
it flipped over, wabbled here and
then it flipped back again,
and it just kept doing that.
That was one of the lines like here or
here.
So when it's close to the sphere spin
about the intermediate axis of inertia,
it tens to hand out there a long,
long time.
And then it flips over, but
you never remain there.
Whereas this one, you can hang out near
a pure spin about axis of maximum inertia.
And you will stay there forever, whereas
this one you will keep flipping back and
forth back and forth.
Now why don't we typically fly space craft
spinning about the axis of least inertia?
So that's kind of like having
a rocket body spinning this way.
Besides seeing what
happened to explorer one,
what's the mathematical reason we
don't like that stability up there?
Debo.
>> There's any kind of friction you're
going to go down in the energy level and
get to the separate.
>> This is all assuming
a perfectly mathematically rigid
body and any real body will have some
panels that will flex just a little bit,
inside there might be just
a little bit of give.
Every time you have a little bit of
friction you're losing mechanical energy,
and you could lose some,
these are all internal forces, all right.
With internal forces I can
actually change my energy state,
I can lose energy, but
can you bring your energy state to 0?
With enough flapping of the panels,
of fuel sloshing going on,
will your space craft ever come to rest?
Daniel, what do you think?
>> No.
>> Why not?
>> The minimum you can get to is just the.
The [INAUDIBLE] is only tangent
to the sphere from the inside.
>> Which one was that?
That was this one.
All right, you do [INAUDIBLE].
Right, your momentum internal forces and
fuel slosh,
as complicated as equations are.
Partial differential equations and surface
interactions and every stoke equations and
who knows what else.
It only internal forces and
we've shown up angular momentum
of a system cannot change unless
you apply external forces.
So, that's why when you're loosing energy,
you will asymptotically get to
this kind of the case which you
can never bring the craft to rest.
All right, so those are all quick
answer questions that we've had.
So good, these little pole hole plots,
they are quite common,
you see these sometimes
with different analysis.
We'll see after, it's going to do
a spin or similar configuration.
We're not spending too much time on one
but [INAUDIBLE] classic literature,
you'll often find these
kind of illustrations.
And I wanted to make sure
you're familiar with that.
Here the thing we did last
time was Torque-Free Motion.
These are the equations where we assume
to have a body of frame that's principal,
therefore the inertia tensor is diagonal,
right.
We get this nice form.
Now, if we have an axis symmetric body,
you can see from here what
happens on the right hand side.
You always have differences of inertia,
and if it's axis symmetric that basically
means two inertias have to be
equal about like this pen,
about orthogonal axis are equal.
Therefore one of the terms
is going to go to zero and
immediately we know that omega dot is
zero and that's going to be a constant.
Very, and
the trick how to solve this last time was,
we want to go from these equations.
We know Omega 3 is constant, and
to solve this they're now to couple
first order differential equation
Omega 1 that depends on Omega 2, and
Omega 2 that depends on Omega 1.
Anybody remember the trick
how we got to solve these two
coupled first order
differential equations?
Yeah?
>> One of the equations?
>> We differentiate them again,
which can seem counterintuitive.
We're trying to get rid of dots,
in fact we add dots first
because it makes it easier.
By differentiating them we
get basically omega 1 dot,
omega 3's a constant, you get omega 2 dot.
Now we get to plug in the coupled one that
depends on omega 1, and you end up with
a differential equation that's only
omega 1s, but we traded two coupled.
First order differential equations for
two uncoupled second order
differential equations right.
So that was a trade off but this one
is a classic spring mass system so
you can solve this very easily.
Anybody who has differential equations
should know how to solve this all right,
which is what we did.
So this is a classic answer if
you have an axisymmetric body And
when we do a numerical simulation,
just looking at the tumble rates,
you can see one of them flat lines.
That's expected, so
the spin about the axis of symmetry
is always going to be constant.
And the other two give you this
nice sinusoidal response, but
if you look at the attitude,
it's not easy to predict.