Now, let's talk about attitude.
With the axis symmetry I got
some really easy looking omegas.
One of the most flatline is
gets you the sine and cosines.
[SOUND].
That's how we get the amplitude and
the right phase.
But that's pretty straight forward, right?
So, but the resulting motion, just looking
at these yaw, pitch, rolls relative to
inertial frame, they were all over
the place, and very nasty to predict.
Lots of wiggles, bumps, and
stuff that was going on.
So, it wasn't very intuitive to
predict what happens to the natural
procession of a torque-free
attitude motion.
So this is a classic result
that people have done.
And anybody heard of
mutation procession before?
Good?
Was it Russell?
What does mutation mean?
>> It's where you're like
slowly going around and
circling around what you're [CROSSTALK]
>> So is this mutating or
is this processing?
Is it mutating now or processing?
Who thinks mutation procession
definitions are confusing?
>> Like slowly around the depth.
>> Good.
I hate them, quite frankly.
I'm always confused by those darn things.
Why?
In the end,
those mutation procession things,
as I'll show you, they're nothing but
older angle rates.
And, as often in the literature,
we're not consistent.
Some people talk about 3-1-3
Euler angle rates which means
certain motions mean something.
That's the notation part.
That's the procession part.
It's a 3-1-3 versus a 3-2-1.
The processions are often very similar
because they are both 3 first axis.
But the 3-2-1s and the 3-1-3s are the two
common things you will see people
use to describe torque free attitude
motions and look at the tumbles.
But they don't always tell you what they
are doing until you look at the math,
it takes a long time so
I'd rather they just tell me,
look I'm studying it using three
one three over under rates.
I know right away what you are talking
about verses mutation and damping.
But it is a common mutation, common
thing you hear so let's cover it and
I want to show you
a little bit what it does.
The other issue is so
we are going to use older angle rates.
to start to prescribe how much does
this wobbling disk process around and
what's happening there.
The other trick is, whereas my
earlier example acts as a metric,
I was plotting my yaw pitch roll
angles relative to the inertial frame.
With nutation precession,
those terms, we're never talking about
attitude motion relative to inertial.
We're talking about attitude motion
relative to your momentum vector.
That's the key difference.
So, if this thing is spinning this way,
you have a big momentum
vector sticking up.
Great!
Then you talk about precessing
about that momentum vector and
how much you're nutating and
wobbling Around the momentum.
If you're spinning this way,
then procession is really defined
around that momentum vector, right?
So it has nothing to do with
where your inertial system is,
it's torque-free motion.
Momentum vector is preserved.
So, if we do that, let's go through this.
I know some of you have seen this.
So, you have some momentum vector,
it's torque-free motion,
as seen by inertial observer,
this is a fixed quantity.
You give something some spin It's
going to have some fixed momentum.
And whatever else happens and
how it gyrates and wobbles,
that momentum has to be fixed.
So, we can now pick an inertial
frame that is lined up with n3.
Just historically they pick the third
one for some reason, to be = -H.
So now, I can talk about attitude
motion relative to this frame here.
And n one two are really arbitrary,
they don't really matter much
in the end you will find.
So I can write the momentum vector
as minus h times n three and
this is also an frame, right?
It's just lined, however you released it,
that momentum was this direction.
So n three goes in the opposite,
that's it.
So now we can write that and
we can say okay, good this makes my
h vector in this particular end frame,
all right this is a special end frame,
not a general end frame,
is zero zero something times a dcm.
This allows me to write my momentum
vector components in the body
frame in an easier way.
Generally this H if you have an arbitrary
inertial frame H would have an H1 two and
three in frame component.
Here we only have a third component, so
that means times the DCM you are not only
pulling out the parts of the third column.
That saves you lots of Algebra.
Why do we do that?
So here's the DCM and
using 3-2-1 Euler angles here so
I'll get 3-2-1 Euler angle rates out of
this stuff times that zero zero minus H.
You do this, you have the H times sine and
the minus minus cancel.
Here we have H with a minus and
a sine and a cosine of the third angle,
which is rolled and
the second angle which is pitch.
So phi is rolled, theta is pitch, and
the same thing for the third term.
And this is the momentum
vector in the body frame.
But then, you remember from kinetics,
H is also equal to i omega, right?
That's what we derived for
rotational motion.
And in principle coordinate frame.
This is simply i one, omega one, i two,
omega two, i three, omega three.
So this is an elegant way that we can use
the three dimensional and get momentum
vector to provide three constraints on how
does omega and the angles have to roll it.
And you can see out of the 3-2-1 Euler
angles pulling out this column here
because it was all about the third one,
theta one doesn't appear here.
There's no yaw angle in here.
Which kind of makes sense because there
will be the motion about the momentum
,vector that happens there.
So, if this is the spinning and
the processing rate you're going to have,
if we take the system and twist it for
80 degrees about the momentum vector,
it's completely asymmetric.
It gives you the same
kind of a wobbly motion.
So that's kind of what manifests
in the Mathew, does know we are.
There is H and these omegas.
Well, this is nice, so I don't have to
integrate differential kinematic equations
to come up with, at this attitude,
what is omega going to be?
It's kind of like the energy conservation,
the bouncing ball problem, right?
That we've used the complete
three dimensional h vector
here instead of just the magnitude
as we did with pole plots.
So that's good.
So now, we can divide by inertia and
you get this expression.
So, I can write analytically,
if this is the pitch and this is the roll,
these are the omegas you must have or
otherwise you're violating momentum.
So good, we have that.
Now the next step is we have our
differential kinematic equations for
my Euler angle rates and omega.
Now I just had an expression of omegas in
terms of these angles and you plug that
in so instead of having a differential
kinematic for theta, you know,
your state rates then you differentiate
omega to get the accelerations,
here we used angular momentum to
completely get rid of omega dots and
I get, I end up with torque free motion
that's three coupled non linear.
But first order of differential equations.
So I got, I used angular momentum
to get rid of some of those dots.
Didn't have double dots in the end, in
attitude angles, I only have single dots.
And this would be your procession,
this would be your mutation
if you used a 3-2-1.
And then, the third roll, we often just
call roll as the final roll motion.
But that's the wobbly plate problem, we've
all seen this plate on a table, right,
that wobbles It doesn't keep the same
plane, that plate kind of goes around and
precession and
does some weird stuff, right?
That's all going to be
predicted now by these motions.
If you look at this, positive, positive,
H magnitude is positive, sin squared,
cosine squared, all positive.
The precession rate, your yaw rate
essentially, is always negative.
And this comes out of the definition
that we've chosen and end frame which is
in the minus H direction otherwise
there will be a sign flip.
So is different this could be different
but this is more the classic one
whereas the pitching,
that's basically a mutation rate.
Does this, if this spinning,
is there an up and
down motion that happens because of this?
And you can see, for example,
if i3 is equal to i2.
This term actually vanishes and
you get rid of notation rates, as well.
So different shapes call
certain rate things to change.
Anyway, so this is the classic one for
general inertias, and
we cannot be positive.
If you have an axis symmetric case, so
I'm just assuming here B1
is my axis of symmetry.
So, I1 is unique and I2 and I3 are equal.
And you plug it into those equations.
They simply fly down to
a constant mutation rate and
a constant procession
rate that you would have.
This would tell you that
if the sphere is spinning,
that at about the momentum vector,
this object is spinning, but
it's also slowly processing around.
It has to do that to
conserve angular momentum.
And so, these are some classic results
where you can now actually make
predictions about the attitude motions,
and turns out all their angles are kind of
convenient for some of this stuff.
They're nicely to be worked out.
And this tells you what happens to
the motion, since data is constant,
your roll rate that you would have in
this situation also will stay constant.
So this is pretty classical.
We build a lot of spaceships that
are kind of, at least originally,
almost cylindrical, very axi-symmetric
just because they come out of rockets and
it's been released and have a wobble.
These equations are very common to kind of
analyze what happens post tip off,
how are things going to process,
what's going to go on.
So, it's a convenient form.
Now, there's some other stuff people.
I'm just going to highlight this.
We're not going to go through details.
There's no particular homeworks on this.
But if you have angular momentum vector,
here, this is my axis of symmetry, for
example, that I had.
I'm spinning about this axis,
and I'm slowly precessing around.
That's the momentum that I have.
So the current angular velocity vector
is not equal to just this spin,
because you're spinning about b1 and
some of the other axis.
And there's all these different angles,
but
you're basically revolving around this
while processing around the he vector.
So these two motions that I'm
doing is basically describe cones.
And there's different ways people
have written these equations, but
you can show mathematically
because this is equivalent to,
those are the right equations
this is a special case.
What they call a space cone and
a body cone, so
this is your momentum factor
that's fixed and our whole space.
The Omega Vector will
tend to evolve around it
depending on axis symmetry or not.
And then there's the body
axis that you have.
That one is going to
possess around as well.
And so, it's like,
you can mathematically describe it
as one cone rotating on another.
And this is a What I want
is the largest inertia.
So that means it's kind of like a frisbee,
a flat plate, spinning but
slightly wobbling.
That's kind of an oblate condition.
If you have a prolate condition,
which is more this pen, like a and
or rocket body, and
is spinning about the axis of symmetry and
wobbling, you end up also with
a body cone and a space cone.
But you can see you're kind of
wobbling on the outside of the,
the thing's on the outside.
Whereas here, it's kind of
wobbling around it as a whole.
So, if you study some classic papers on
torque-free motions, you might come across
some of these space cones, body cones and
what I hope you remember is wait a minute,
I remember this has to do
with these intersections.
And read up of on other angle rates and
how we can rewrite them as conic motions
essentially cones and
cones rolling this was all good and
popular way back before we had all
these wonderful computer tools.
These days use integrate and
[SOUND] out comes the answers.
But people done an amazing amount of
work in attitude as well to get analytic
answers and this is kind of one of
the stages where this stuff comes from.