[MUSIC]
You know even though I don't think that
many researchers think of preservation
as the first thing [LAUGH] when
they think of designing a study.
But if you think of, well that even for
yourself, if you think,
I want to be able to find and reuse
that data after a few years from now.
That's already a good goal to
[LAUGH] put into yourself.
And by doing the right things during
your research process would allow to,
not only while making it available for
yourself, but also for others.
>> The value of preservation
rises over time.
In real time, people feel like,
oh we don't really need to do preservation
because I only want to make it available.
I'm only interested in access.
If you're interested in long term access,
the investment in producing these well
formed packages pays off again and
again and again over time because you
can go back to the archival package and
re-present it in any kind of
technology that comes up.
>> Long-term access to stuff is
providing long-term access,
providing preservation.
That's communicating with the future.
[MUSIC]
That's essentially what it is.
It's being able to communicate
with people after we're gone.
And I think that the scholarly record,
that the scientific evidence base,
is an important
enough thing that the future
will want to know about it.
>> It's very important to be part of
the process where if people near want
information, records, data that they can
get it, and that we can be part of that.
We can do it well,
we can do it better than we could before,
we can incorporate technologies
into doing it better.
And making things more and
more accessible to whoever is interested.
And I think that part of that has to do
with, as we get into open access data,
it means that it's not necessarily a very
focused, constrained set of researchers.
It's anybody who wants to
know more about that thing.
And I really like the notion of open
access to anyone who's interested in it.
>> Well, archiving data is at
the core of sharing data effectively.
It places the data in a central
repository where researchers all over
the world can gain access to it.
It provides a legacy to that data as
software changes or technologies change.
Archives can preserve data and
make it accessible beyond
those changes in technology,
is really provides a much more robust
way of sharing data and recording and
documenting what it is we do as we
advance our scientific communities.
These.
So, archiving's absolutely essential.
It's a living,
breathing way to make the scientific
enterprise open to everyone who wants to
participate in the scientific enterprise.
>> If any of the items that are in digital
form will be needed in the future,
they have to start managing integrity.
You can not trust any desk drive,
you can not trust any vendor.
Eventually, this technology will
either fail or become obsolete.
So you need a way to migrate your
data from the prior type of storage
to the next cheaper type of storage
that's coming in the future.
>> I teach students in just my
epidemiology courses, cause I'll
have a session on data management and part
of that is were you going to archive data.
And I tell war stories from
national data collection in
Australia that was archived on five and
a quarter inch floppy disks.
Now, I'll leave it to you to explain
to the audience what a five and
a quarter inch floppy disk is
because I expect most people
who might watch this video would
have no idea what I'm talking about.
But it's a magnetic medium that you
would have to feed into a drive,
into an old desktop computer.
And it would have a whirring machine
that would read this disc and
you cannot find devices to
read those discs anymore.
And that the was the repository for
a national data collection of oral health.
And I've spoken to colleagues who have
magnetic tapes that had to be scraped
because they got oxidized.
And they would scrape the tapes and
I saw bits of metal coming off it,
some magnetic stuff coming of a tape
that hopefully it's oxidization,
not data, right, but
that is scraping tape.
So, the good people you
work with realize that in
certainly in 20 years now, and certainly
in 50 years to now, people will be doing
the equivalent of scraping data clouds
that we now regard as being permanent.
And it's fun to work with people
like that who have that vision,
because they are creating something for
they future, and
they realize the future is more
than just a thumb drive or a cloud.
[MUSIC]