[MUSIC]
Digital preservation is important
because it's not immediately obvious to
most people.
Researchers are busy with focus
on the research they're doing and
the important content of what they're
studying and it's up to people like me,
like data librarians, to remind them
to keep the data safe in the long term.
And also by doing that they're making it
available to themselves in the future.
Because, although it's very
known to you at this point,
you'll forget the details
about it in the future.
So you need to do the documentation and
everything to be able to share it and
also for your own self.
>> I think digital preservation
is very important.
I come from the scientific world,
and in the scientific world
researchers build on the results
that were published by others.
So, keeping these data is paramount
because if you don't take care of
the adequate digital preservation of
the data, there is no possibility for
later researchers to reuse these data and
to build on these results.
But it's not only important for academia.
Also outside of academia these
research data can be used.
So digital preservation should be
at the top of all of our lists.
>> Well digital preservation
is important because,
most of the output of research from
the academy is now digital and
there isn't an analog form of that,
in many cases.
So preserving that output serves
the same function as libraries and
archives have in the past.
If we don't preserve this digital
information it's really in danger
of being lost.
And that's a loss to the entire community.
And that creates a situation where
research cannot be validated, or
can be reproduced.
And that's a serious problem for
the entire academic endeavor.
>> Digital preservation as an extension
of preservation of anything else
is important because it allows us
to take resources which inspire and
inform to be transmitted
through time to those who,
in the future,
who'll want to better understand and
learn what has meaning to those
who have gone before them.
So preservation is important to do this,
both for our analog materials, but
also for our digital.
Which inherently, we cannot discern
without that proactive effort to preserve.
>> Digital preservation
is important because
it helps to unleash the value
in digital objects.
We create a lot of digital content
every day and some of it we save or
set aside for preservation purposes.
That value remains a potential,
like a latent value in these objects and
we release when we use the objects again.
In order to be able to use those objects,
we need to be able to
preserve them in between.
So preservation is a stage
in the value chain
that takes the value of
objects through time.
>> Digital preservation is important
because it allows us to capture
the knowledge needed to apply and recreate
the data sets that are being archived.
This in turn allows us to
manage reproducible research.
Where a second researcher can
reproduce the results of the original
researcher using the same data sets and
the same analysis mechanism.
So preservation is the mechanism by
which we capture the knowledge required
to do that.
>> It's important because our cultural
heritage is being saved in digital formats
now and it used to be that history was
saved by what didn't get thrown away.
And that's not a strategy that works
anymore because if we leave our digital
stuff just on the ground in the hopes
that it will manage to live for
100 years, it won't.
>> I think libraries which are drawn
into digital preservation for
whatever reason, I think,
into a great social service because
they are making the really available data,
information for scholastic research.
So this is another actually
helping the society to evolve and
also grow from the idea of
scholarly information which
otherwise would not have been available.
[MUSIC]