[MUSIC]
A major theme in calculus is change.
You've got one thing affecting something
else, you want to
know, how does changing this one thing
affect this other thing.
Often the relationship between these two
things is given by a function, right?
You've got some kind of function that has
inputs and outputs.
And you're wiggling that input point, and
you
want to know how the output value view
changes.
Very concretely.
You might ask for the ratio of change in
the output valve view to
change in the input point and that ratio,
that's the derivative.
Alright.
Derivatives measure how change in the
import affects the out port.
At least infinitesimally.
And studying derivatives is exactly what
we're going to do now.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]