[MUSIC]
As I mentioned before,
one of the obstacles to sharing data is a
lack of career incentives for researchers.
One method to reward researchers for
sharing their data is to ensure
they receive proper acknowledgement and
credit for their data through citation.
Data citation provides a standardized
method for secondary users to cite data.
Data citations can also be
used by data producers.
To cite their own data as
standalone research products.
For instance,
NSF has renamed publications to products
in its biographical sketch section of
its grant application where researchers
can now list datasets along with
publications and other research products.
Currently, work is being done
in the data curation field to
establish data citation principles and
standards.
For instance, the Joint Declaration
of Data Citation Principles,
which is a synthesis of work by
a number of prominent groups,
has established principles to guide the
development of human understandable and
machine actionable data citations.
The eight principles include importance,
credit and
attribution, evidence,
unique identification,
access, persistence,
specificity and verifiability,
and interoperability and flexibility.
Another group doing important work
in expanding the infrastructure and
culture for citing data is DataCite.
DataCite works with data repositories
incentives to assigned persistent
identifierssuch as digital object
identifiers, or DOIs, to data.
Through their work,
data sites support simple and
effective methods of data citation,
discovery, and access.
The DOI insures that data
can be discovered online,
regardless of where they are located.
So let's take a look at an actual data
citation generated by the data verse and
look at how the elements
of this citation map
to the joint declaration of
data citation principles.
The author and data publisher,
or distributer information,
maps to the principle of credit and
attribution, which stresses
the importance of contributors
receiving due credit for their data.
The version information maps to
the principle of specificity and
verifiability, which stresses the
importance of having enough information
to make sure the data retrieved and
used are the same as the data cited.
Finally, the DOI maps directly to
the principles of unique identification,
access and persistence.
The DOI provides a method for
identification that is machine
actionable as well as provides
stable access to the data resource
using a persistent identifier.
One thing researchers may want to consider
when choosing a data repository for
making their data available is whether the
repository supports the creation of unique
data citations that embody the joint
declaration of data citation principles.
Proper citation of datasets supports
the reproducibility of research,
ensures proper credit for researchers,
and enables the tracking of data reuse.
Although there are very real challenges
that may make it difficult, or
in some cases, impossible to share data,
there are significant benefits
to both researchers and
the broader research community.
By using these techniques and information
provided in this MOOC, you will be better
equipped to overcome these challenges and
reap the benefits of data sharing.
And don't forget, cite the data.
[MUSIC]