[MUSIC]
Hello.
It is good to see you back.
Welcome to the module
embedded operating systems.
In this module, we'll give an introduction
to the operating systems and
the Linux kernel.
A review of several kernel types,
I wield first popular Internet of
things embedded operating systems.
Let's begin with an example.
Every day we use computers and
smartphones for
daily activities, such as playing games,
working, or surfing the internet.
Each of these devices uses a particular
operating system, such as Mac,
iOS, Windows, or
some Linux based operating system.
The reason for this is that an operating
system is absolutely necessary
to provide users with
high quality service.
In complex devices such as smartphones,
it is simple to install and
run an OS, due to their powerful hardware,
such as large memory size,
high-frequency microcontroller,
and a large storage space.
However, have you ever wondered if
it's possible to run an OS in a tiny,
and resource-constrained, device?
The answer to this question is yes.
It is completely possible if we
use an embedded operating system.
During the next videos in this module,
we will provide a deeper
answer to this question.
However, the first question we should
answer is what is an operating system?
An operating system is a collection
of several pieces of software.
It works as an intermediate layer between
application software and the hardware.
The main function of an operating
system is to manage resources, and
to provide an environment for
executing applications.
In this course, we will focus on
embedded operating systems for
the Internet of Things, or IoT.
This is due to the large number
of embedded devices used for
IoT applications nowadays.
We can find them in very diverse fields,
such as entertainment, healthcare,
military, industrial automation,
and education.
According to an IHS report,
it is projected that the number of devices
in IoT applications will be
approximately 50 billion by 2020.
Therefore, it is important for
you to become acquainted with
IoT embedded operating systems.
To give you a clear view of
an operating system's functionality,
I will describe the most fundamental
tasks that an OS performs.
Memory management is a complex task
that enables efficient memory uses
by keeping track of the status
of each memory location.
In short, it checks how much memory
is used by a particular process and
how much is left.
In most cases,
the management system makes the decision
on when to allocate memory for a process.
One example of memory usage is when
calculating an effective address.
Which involves fetching from instruction,
and using an index object.
Another example of memory management is
mapping virtual memory to physical memory.
In which case, a virtual memory address
generated by the CPU is generated
into a physical memory address.
Processor management refers to the process
of deciding when a particular process
is granted access to the processor, and
for how long the process can use it.
In particular,
processor management keeps track of the
status of both processors and processes.
When the processor is available,
it is allocated to the process
with the highest priority.
Finally, the processor management will
deallocate processors when they are no
longer needed.
All devices in a system are managed
by an OS via their dot drivers.
This is known as input output control.
The device management system keeps
track of the status of all devices and
their drivers.
In particular, the system manages
queues and book and buffers.
For example,
in case of a suspended process,
this means the process is
not currently using the CPU.
The device manager instructs the buffer to
receive input data from the device, and
to stop sending it to
the suspended process.
When the suspended process
becomes active again,
which means that the CPU is
currently allocated to this process,
the device management system instructs the
buffer to send data to the active process.
Finally, the operating system
must handle the organization and
tracking of files and
directories safe in a computer disk.
This is called file management.
A file management system allows the user
to perform tasks such as creating files
and inventories, renaming, copying,
moving, and deleting files.
The operating system keeps track of
where the files are located in the hard
drive through the file system.
There are many other aspects
of an operating system,
such as system performance control,
job accounting,
error detection aids, and coordination
between other software and users.
Too much to cover here.
Let's move on to the Linux kernel, which
is a popular kernel used in many systems.
Let me give you a brief history to
the history of the Linux kernel.
The Linux kernel was created by a Finnish
student named Linus Torvalds in 1991.
The Linux kernel is the most vital part
of a Linux-based operating system.
Nowadays, the Linux kernel is very
popular, and it's used in many general
purpose operating systems, as well as
in IoT embedded operating systems.
The reason for
this is its code is open source, and
can easily be integrated with software and
libraries from third parties.
Many researchers and
programmers have contributed to develop
Linux kernels to offer high
quality service to the users.
The Linux kernel is extensive, and we
cannot cover it in detail in this video.
In order to provide a comprehensive
understanding of the Linux kernel,
we will analyze different types of
kernels altogether with their pros and
cons in the incoming video.
Thank you for watching.
[SOUND]