To start with, I was wondering if you
could give me an overview of your project.
And sort of the aims of the project,
just in a couple sentences.
>> Yeah, sure.
So the Comparative Agendas Project, or
CAP for short,
is actually a bit of a misnomer.
In reality,
the CAP is a network of more than
two dozen international projects on
the national and sub-national level.
All interested in measuring policy
attention through public and
governmental agendas.
>> Can you briefly describe
how you organize your data,
in relation to perhaps
file naming conventions,
versioning Documentation,
which obviously features quite heavily.
Metadata, etc.
>> In terms of the overall project, in
terms of bringing everything together and
actually making it comparative,
documentation plays a very important role.
These include the sort of master
code book that I talked about.
Sort of documents all the of
the inter-relations between the projects.
As in, if these are the things that
are included in health care in Mexico,
for instance.
What are the things that are included
in health care in Denmark,
in terms of that there are some things,
in terms of that's the broad policy area.
But there are some issue that might
only be covered in one country,
some issues that might only be
covered in another country.
Also includes the complete documentation
which I have already mentioned in
terms of the adnotated code books for
each individual langauge that allows
different language users not only
to trace the entire process but
they understand the data regardless
of what language they are approaching
things from and the sort of other
just broad documents talking about
the process of creating
the master code book itself.
And also, the process for
any new projects that might be interested
in joining the community as we're very
sort of open community interested in other
researchers that are looking to sort of
expand what we're doing and
whatever in a particular way.
Just as important as sort of
those documentation materials is
detailed metadata.
For so many data sets, so many different
languages, it's very important to keep
track of what each individual data
set measures in a particular way.
Oftentimes including more complete write
up than you would traditionally think of
with metadata.
Explaining, say, what is a law in the UK?
What is a law in the United States?
What is a law in another country?
>> And one final question, I guess it's in
relation to new researches coming onboard.
Do you have any advice in
relation to organizing?
Documenting or storing data that
will keep the new researcher on
track in relation tp managing that
content for their own purpose.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
So as a researcher who, so I deal with
quite a lot of different types of data
sets, quite a lot of different data sets.
In general with different data structures,
partially because
the data structures relate to different
tools, different methods that I might
use which means that while a data
set might all be based off laws.
There might be many different data
structures of laws that I will look at.
In relation to the particular
statistical method that I used.
In that sort of sense, both because
what you might want to do with data and
the fact that oftentimes with large data
sets, the type of large data sets that
a lot people are gathering now, you
might envision a particular use for it.
That particular use might be for example,
you want to look at law
production on a yearly level.
I cross many different countries,
and you decide to
potentially just make a yearly data set,
maybe throw away some sort of data,
because it just becomes excessive in terms
of when that individual law might have
been actually put on the books
in a particular way.
I would advise researchers away from
doing that, and advise them to keep.
The sort of raw data,
every bit of information that they did or
were able to gather whenever they're
building their data set, keep that,
store that and be able to access that.
You never know whenever you might
want to actually sort of change that
to a quarterly analysis or
a monthly analysis.
Or you might want to look at there's a
particular anomaly in some sort of way and
you need to investigate
that in more detail.
So, I find it's generally best when you're
working with data to work with the raw
dataset and to transform that dataset into
what you need for that particular project.
Oftentimes documenting some sort of way,
whether that'd be documenting by hand
using sort of the documentation for
the statistical software that
you're using to transform the data.
Such as R, MathLab or Stata or other sort
of software in whatever particular way.
Using their log files, using their new
files or other things to be able to
document everything that you did so they
can easily go back and change things, but
also so that you can easily debug any
sort of issues that you might have.
Especially in very large data sets you
might not notice that there was something
wrong with a calculation or
a transposition of the data.
>> Yeah.
>> Without changing into a wide data set
format or a long data set format if you're
working on panel data for instance.
So keep all that archived,
keeping all that tracked so
that you can fix things
whenever you see errors.
So, you can easily change your data set
to answer knew or different questions.
It's very good for you and it's very good
for the people who might be interested in
using your data for other purposes
that you haven't envisioned and
while we all sort of want the outputs from
our own data in whatever sort of way,
we want the research outputs and
we want other things.
We want the impact.
Getting people to use the data is a very
big part of that impact, very big part of
getting people to cite, to care about
the work that you're doing as well.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
Sean, many thanks.
>> Thank you.