[MUSIC].
We've already seen how the chain rule can
help us find the anti-derivatives.
Alright, that message is called u
substitution.
I'm going to do more messing around with
the chain rule and integration.
In particular, let's see what we can do
with the chain rule, and the end points
of integration.
Well here's an example to play around
with, if I take the integral from 0 to x,
of sine of t dt, well that's something.
But let's think about the derivative of
this with respect to x.
And by the fundamental theorem of
calculus this is sine of x.
The fundamental theorem of calculus is
the derivative of the accumulation
function is the integrand.
What if that upper endpoint were a
function of x?
What I'm asking is what if this endpoint
weren't x anymore?
But some function g of x right?
Then this wouldn't be sine of x anymore,
be something else.
So to analyze this let's define a
function f.
So that function will be given by this
rule.
f of x is the integral from 0 to x of
sine t dt.
Now what would it mean if we replace that
right hand endpoint instead of being x if
we replace that with g of x?
That would mean that I want to think
about f of g of x, right?
What's f of g of x?
So, that's the integral from 0 to g of x,
of sine t dt.
And specifically, right, what I want to
know, is what's the derivative with
respect x of f of g of x.
That's just the chain-rule.
So let me just write down the chain rule.
The derivative of f of g of x is the
derivative of f at g of x times the
derivative of g.
So what does it mean in this specific
case?
Remember in this case, f of x is the
integral from 0 to x of sine t dt.
So the derivative of f, by the
fundamental theorem is sin of x and that
means that the derivative of f of g of x,
well that's just sin the derivative of f
at g of x times the derivative of g.
Let's make it even more concrete.
Let's say that g is the squaring
function.
Let me write that down.
So if I'm making g the squaring function,
then the derivative of g is just 2x and
in that case the derivative of f of g of
x is sine of g which is x squared times
the derivative of g which is 2x.
So let's write down our final answer in
this specific case.
The final claim is that the derivative of
the integral from 0 to g of x which in
this case is x squared of sine t dt.
This is the derivative with respect to x
of f of g of x.
This is sin of x squared times 2x and
this statement, we can get by combining
the chain rule and the fundamental
theorem of calculus.