[MUSIC].
I've mostly been selling you on the idea
of u-substitution as a method for finding
antiderivatives, for evaluating
indefinite integrals.
Let's think about what u-substitution
says just for definite integrals.
So here's the setup.
I've got the integral x goes from a to b
of some function f, not the derivative of
f, just f g of x times g prime of x dx.
Now, how could I approach a problem like
this so I can make a substitution?
U equals g of x so that du is g prime of
x dx and, in that case, this integration
problem becomes the integral of f of u u
is g of x times this is du.
But now I've gotta change the bounds of
integration.
When is x is equal to a, u is g of a, and
when x is equal to b, u is g of b.
Assuming that those two integrals exist
to justify the equalty of those two
integrals.
It's just the chain rule and the
fundamental theorem of calculus.
And yet, this statement, the equality of
this integral and this integral, that's
just a statement about two definite
integrals.
I don't need to know the fundamental
theorem of calculus in order to make this
assertion.
This raises a fascinating question, u
substitution is making a claim about
definite integrals.
And yet the naive way to justify that
claim goes through the fundamental
theorem of calculus and the chain rule.
Is it possible to see why the statement
about u substitution for definite
integral should be true without resorting
back to anti-differentiation?
Well, to gain some insight into this,
here's a random graph that I made of some
function that's nearly constant.
But the function I'm calling f.
And this, area, in here is the interval
from 1 to 10 of f of udu.
And that's this area in here.
Now I want to imagine what happens when I
do the substitution.
What happens when I replace.
U with x squared plus 1, and that changes
du, right.
That's that formula that we saw a moment
ago.
If I'm integrating f of u du, I could
alternatively integrate f of g of x times
du g prime of xdx, and I can imagine that
in the graph, transforming from the u
coordinates to these x coordinates.
Well the u-coordinates are more stretched
out, right.
When x is 0, u is 1.
When x is 1, u is 2.
When is x is 2, u is 5.
And when x is 3, u is 10.
So if I redraw this picture in the,
x-coordinates, it's as if I've taken this
picture and squished it in, right, and
when I squish it in.
Then I'm going to get a picture more like
this.
And to calculate the area, there, I'd be
calculating this integral.
The integral from 0 to 3, this is x, of f
of what u is equal to in terms of x, du,
which is 2x dx.
And the whole gimmick here is just that
I'm trading the width in this picture for
the height in this picture.
And the factor that relates the width
here, the du's and the height here, well
that's exactly this factor here, right?
That's du but written in terms of dx.