It's also a good idea to
consider data transformations.
There are a number of reasons,
why you may wish to transform your data,
either during your project, or afterwards.
Unlike the earlier discussion about
migrating files from one format
to the other, data transformations
involve changing the actual data.
For example via anonymization.
For example in survey data collected
from questionnaires, multiple choice and
other kinds of responses are usually coded
as numbers instead of character strings.
This simple type of transformation has
the advantage of easing data entry
if you're typing in paper responses, and
it also avoids inconsistencies
such as typos in data values.
Qualitative data such as interview
transcripts, can be transformed into
quantitative data by applying textual
coding and categorization techniques.
Another reason for data transformation may
be to visualize the data more effectively.
A simple example is converting data where
there's a numerator and a denominator
from ratios to percentages, so you can
display it on a bar chart or pie graph.
A number of methods may be used
to transform confidential or
sensitive data, so
they can be shared with other researchers.
These include aggregation,
and anonymization.
You've now completed this module.
Take a look at the further reading, where
you'll find additional resources to learn
more about file formats, compression,
normalization, and data transformations.
You may wish to move on to the next module
and return to these references later.
We recommend that you move on to
the module about documentation and
data citation.