[SOUND].
Hello and welcome to week 3 of creative
programming for digital media and mobile
apps.
This week we're going to be looking at
audio visualization.
So that means algorithmic drawing in
comptuer graphics.
So ways of making abstract shapes.
More complex shapes with translations and
rotations and different kinds of
geometry.
And audio analysis.
So, what that really means is,
understanding what's being played back in
a sound and turning it into numbers which
are useful for changing the way that
something's drawn.
So, there's quite a big chunk of graphics
to do with translation, and rotation, and
transformations, and there's a nice chunk
of analysis.
If you're interested in audio, and you
have a background in audio, I think
there's a lot of good stuff for you
there.
but then I'll be doing a kind of putting
it together bit at the end.
Stuff I always do.
just literally showing you how we combine
analysis and combine graphics to make
something which you might find alongside
something like, I don't know, iTunes or
the Xbox audio player.
So, there's a market for visualizers but
there's a market for the techniques of
visualization.
It's not just about making something that
works with I tunes although there's a lot
of money to be made in that market.
It's also about how to how to analyze
audio and there's an increasing amount of
applications that really need to do that
including stuff like shazam which is a
really useful application.
So, we're going to start to be thinking
about all these things and how to put
them together.
[MUSIC]