[MUSIC].
Today we're going to talk a bit more
about moving things around in graphics.
So in the first week we talked about how
to draw stuff and there we could position
objects and then like rectangles, by
giving the pixel positions.And for
example the white command and the ellipse
command.
And, and that's fine, we can do that.
And last week we talked about doing
animation, but animation with image
sequences where we're playing lots of
different images all in the same
position.
Today I'm going to talk about more
powerful ways of moving objects around
beyond what you can do simply by putting
positions into the x y coordinates to say
say, a rectangle.
These techniques accord transforms, and
there are three of them.
The first transform is translate, which
is a basic movement.
Not too different from what you could do
by putting an X-Y position into, the
position of a rectangle, so.
And that is a command for translate and
you pass in an x and a y which is the
position you're moving whatever object
too and it's a separate command to
whatever command drawing you're doing
this.
So you can apply single translate to
multiple objects.
And group objects together and move them
around and I'll talk a little bit more in
detail about how you do that.
And the basic premise to translate an x
and a y which gives you the position for
which you'll translate.
So very similar to what we've done
before.
The second one is a scale that's getting
things bigger and smaller and that just
basically takes a number That is how much
of scaling apply.
If that number's one you're not scaling
it at all.
If it's less than one it's getting
smaller.
If it's more than one it's getting
bigger.
One quite useful thing about scale is you
can also give it two parameters which
means you can scale separately about the
x and the y.
So, you can make something wider While
making it sort of the same time, having
high x scale and a small y scale.
So the rotate command is used to spin
objects around.
And it takes an angle as its parameter.
So that's how much you want to spin it
by.
the normal way we talk about angles is in
degrees 0, 360 degrees.
But in computer programming we often work
with another way of dealing with angles
called radians.
Now the units we shall explain in a
minute and you have to pass in that value
and radiance through a take command.
If you don't want to get involved in
radians, there's a very simple command
radians, that takes an angle in degrees
and converts it to radians.
So I can just put radians 90 degrees, and
it will do it all for me.
But if you want to know what radians are,
this is it.
So radians work in terms of a circle.
And we can think of an angle as cutting
out a chunk of a circle.
So, like a, a, a slice of the pie.
now, if we make the circle of radius one.
So, each of these two straight edges is
linked one.
Then we can measure the angle by taking
the length of the arc, along the way just
to be certain, so that's how much of the
edge of the circle is being cut out by my
angle.
And that is a perfectly good measure of,
of, of angles, and that's what's called
radians.
A few things you need to know.
it's useful to know particular angles in
radians, if you ever use them.
The, 360 degrees is the entire
circumference of the circle, and if you
remember from school maths And the
circumference of a circle is two pi times
the radius.
Because the radius is 1, the arc length
of 360 degrees is two pi.
180 degrees is half that, pi.
And 90 degrees is pi divided by two.
So that, that's a useful way.
Thinking about, angles, you can use, put
values in terms of pi directly into the
rotate command.
But if you're not, if you don't want to
get involved in that, you can also the
radians command I just showed you to
convert that to degrees.
So what are transforms doing?
I said.
That transforms can apply to multiple
objects and they're independent of the
objects.
But how does a transform know to actually
move an object, if it's a separate
command from do, doing so, drawing a
rectangle or an ellipse.
Well what a transform does is in a way
not move just the object, but move the
entire coordinate system.
Sort of.
The, the screen.
What does that mean?
Well I taught, told you a couple weeks
ago about how we can represent any point
on screen by an x and a y.
How we do that is that we need to know
which direction is x and which direction
is y and that's normally horizontal and
vertical.
We can change that.
But also, we need a starting point, we
need to know where 0, X and 0 Y are and
normally, that is top left of the screen.
But what a translation does, is move
that, so that anything after the
translate.
The zero-zero point.
If I do Translate 20,100, I move my
zero-zero point to 20,100.
So, if I draw an ellipse at point say,
20,30, if I've done a transform on that,
Then that's 20, 30, relative to the new
zero, zero points.
So if I've transformed my 20 100s, it's
20, 30 relative to 20, 100.
Which is 20 plus 20, 40, 100 plus 30,
130, relative.
To the top left of the screen.
So I'm drawing, changing the way you draw
everything.
It changes the meaning of the numbers
you're putting into your rect command and
direct command .And what that means is
that if you draw both an ellipse and a
rectangle they're both affect the same
way.
So you can draw as many shapes as you
like.
You can draw really complicated drawings,
and then put a translate in front of it,
and they'll all move together.
Exactly the same thing with scale, but
this time, rather than changing the 0,0
point, you're changing how much one unit
of x or one unit of y means, so If you
scale up by two, each one unit you leave
in x counts for double.
So each time you move one in x, you're
moving two in the original screen used.
And finally the rotation, what that does
is it actually What takes the x and y
axis.
So, it changes the direction of x and the
direction of y.
So, they're pointing in different
directions.
So, if I've done this translation you're
seeing on, rotation you're seeing on the
screen then when I move across an x I'm
no longer moving Just horizontal and
moving diagonal down the screen.
So these transforms are very powerful
because they give you new ways of
deforming and changing shapes.
But also because they can apply
universally to multiple shapes.  [MUSIC].
[MUSIC]