[SOUND].
So transforms are great because.
And in fact everything if we do a
transloate it will move everything we
draw after but what if we do one
translate after another like this.
Well the most obvious thing that happens
is that we move and move again.
But what exactly is happening there.
When we call the translate command.
Everything after the call back command is
affected by the translate including any
other translates we do.
So, if we look at the second the second
translate that's a movement of any object
that have.
But that is also affected by the first
translate, the first translate and its,
and its mean to the first translate will
happen to the second translate and the
starting point is 0 by 0 point of the
second translate will be affected that of
the first translate.
So.
What happens is that you, the effect of
the fir, of the first translator is
applied to the second translator.
Which, kind of feels more naturally like
saying that well The second translate is
actually happening first.
Instead of happening to the object, and
then it's going to be translated by the,
by the [UNKNOWN] first translate.
We often think of translates, transforms
happening in the opposite order.
So what happens if we do a translate
followed by a rotate?
Well, the rotate spins around, that's
fine.
But if we've got a translate happening
before that rotates.
Then we're going to have a movement
applies to the 0, o point of our rotate.
So the 0-0 point of the rotate is
going to be moved.
in much the same way as we just saw with
the 2 translates.
They're applying one after the other.
And it's kind of like they're playing
backwards.
But what if we do it the other way
around?
Well, we put a translate and movement.
And then put a rotate applies to the zero
zero point of that translate.
What happens is that the zero zero of the
translate.
Is rotated relatively to the 0 0 point of
the screen.
So actually we're it's like, I'm taking
an object arms length and translate it
and then I spin it around.
So it's spinning from the starting point
of the translate.
Not through the center of the object.
So doing those two transforms in
different orders has a radically
different effect.
If I or for example this bottle of water,
if I apply the translate first rotate
second which basically means the other
way around.
I would take and I would translate Well,
I would take something and then I
translate.
I move out.
But if I do it the other way around, then
I translate first and then I rotate.
And I'm making, the rotate isn't just a
simply spinning around the center of the
object.
It's actually a big movement in space.
So the first thing to remember is that
you kind of think of them in the opposite
order if you have to think about
transforms it makes more sense to think
they're happening backwards but the other
thing to think about is is well, what if
I want to move 2 objects.
Well, if you want to move them together,
that's easy, we can translate.
But what if you got to move them
separately.
very often you'll have two objects, the
same two cars, two crates, whatever and
you just want, want to move one [UNKNOWN]
to move the other.
If I'm applying a translate.
Then, everything that happens after that
translation is going to be affected by
it.
So I translate the first object the
circle here then the square is also going
to get affect but if I want to move it
independeantly.
Well we use a command a called push
matrix and pop matrix
I won't go into the mathematical details,
but transforms are implemented using a
bit of maths called a matrix And when it
call upon the pushMatrix, we're basically
creating a new matrix that we're adding
all our new transforms to.
When we call popMatrix, any transforms
that we've added since we added push,
pushMatrix.
[INAUDIBLE] will get canceled, because
we're removing that matrix.
So push matrix and pop matrix are a way
of limiting the effect of transforms.
Any, in fact, transforms that happen
after push matrix will automatically be
removed, once you call pop matrix.
that [INAUDIBLE] gives you a nice way.
Of independently moving objects.
You pushmatrix, you do whatever
transforms you like, you draw the object
and then you pop matrix.
Then the next object, you do exactly the
same thing, pushmatrix, transform it,
draw it and then pop matrix.
[MUSIC]