The last thing I want to talk about today
is another powerful mathematical function
that we can use a lot enjoying, and, the,
these functions are, trigonometry which
he, probably studied in high school or
the equivalent.
and they are three functions that relate
to triangles.
relate angles and triangles.
So, if we look at the slide here, we've
got a right angled triangle.
We've got an angle A in that triangle,
and then we can label the sides.
The adjacent side, which means the side
that's next to the angle.
The opposite side, ones opposite it.
And the hypotenuse, which is the long the
long angle, the long side of the
triangle.
And this trigonometric functions are
defined in terms of these three sides.
The sine of an angle is the opposite side
to that angle divided by this hypotenuse,
the length of the opposite side divided
by the hypotenuse.
In the case of the tangent, it's also
defined the same way.
Now, we're not actually going to use
these to work with angles or triangles,
and I'm going to show you something
different.
I'm actually just interested in working
with sine as a function, because it's a
really instant function.
And it's really powerful for doing
graphics animation, and I'm going to show
you what it does.
So, if we're drawing the circle, you can
that the vertical line in the circle is
the opposite of the angle in the middle
of the circle as we rotate around.
So, we can see we're drawing a circle,
and I'm tracing out the path of the
actual sine function at the same time as
drawing the circle.
And you can see, is that when the angle
is.
When it starts again, it's near zero, the
sine function zero.
It gets increasingly more negative, then
increasingly more positive.
And then it goes back down to zero again,
and it starts the way around a circle.
So, it repeated itself exactly, going
negative, going positive again.
And what's powerful about is that it's
repetitive oscillating function.
So, it goes up and down, up and down, up
and down all the time.
It looks a little bit like a wave.
In fact, it's a very important mechanism
for modeling sound wave.
Sound waves act a lot like sou, sine
waves.
In fact, we can build up any sound wave
out of a whole load of si, of si, of sine
functions of different sizes and
frequencies.
So, what do we, what can we do with this?
Well, before we come to that, I'll talk a
little bit more about the function.
So, this is More detail about the sine,
sine function, this is how we would write
it out.
we're using the function sine, which is
the calculates the sine of an angle, but
we're putting some other numbers in.
Firstly t, we can think of this as time,
if you're working with animation with
sounds, the sine function is changing
over time.
Then we've got, we multiply the result by
A.
That's called the amplitude, that's how
high it gets and also how low it gets.
That's how big the sine wave is.
In audio, that is closely related to the
volume of audio.
If you take, if you're listening to
sound.
Then we have the frequency, that's how
many of the ups and downs you get in a
second, say, if you're dealing with time.
and that what I'm showing you in the
diagram here is that the distance from
one point to next identical point is one
divided by the frequency of wave.
And finally you got the phase, and that,
we can really just think of that wave's
as a starting point to the sine wave, say
how off, far off the zero point your
actual function is starting.
And you can combine together at different
sine waves at slightly different phases,
and you get an interesting effect.
Say, you're starting one at point, and
you're starting another one a little bit
later, and you combine them together, and
that'll [INAUDIBLE] an interesting visual
[INAUDIBLE] effect.
And there's a lot you can with sine
waves.
So, a sine wave can be used nicely in
graphics.
It has a nice shape.
it starts to look a bit like a water
wave.
You can [INAUDIBLE], you could model
water with sine waves.
And certainly, if you add a bunch of sine
waves together, you can get quite a nice
model of it, or even landscapes.
And importantly you can use in animation.
And that's really powerful because the
great thing about sine wave is that it
oscillates.
It goes up and down repeatedly.
And that's a really useful thing for
animating moving objects.
And we'll see make work, work a lot with
sine wave [INAUDIBLE].
The other great thing for sine wave is,
as I said, it's a fantastic tool for
modeling audio functions, and I think
Matthew will talk about that in a later
[MUSIC] [MUSIC]