[SOUND].
Hello.
In this lesson I'm going to teach you how
to access accelerometer data from your
mobile device.
most mobile devices have an accelerometer
in which essentially it allows you to
figure out what angle the device is being
held at.
And of course, we're going to use this
for creative purposes, to control sound
and visualization.
The accelerometer will give you three
values which relate to the various angles
from the phone, so it can be twisted like
this or like this, or like this.
So lets have a look at those.
So, here's some code which will, will
create an accelerometer and print out
some data from it.
So, let's run this on the phone, and see
what comes out.
First of all, I'm going to type it in, so
we need at the top, we create a global
variable.
And the type of the variable is
accelerometer.
And this is a built-in class for those of
you who've done a bit more programming.
Which comes with our audio and graphics
API.
Let's call, I'm going to call it XL.
So in set-up.
As usually we create teh variable XY
equals new acceleromter.
Okay so that's.
What we're going to do and now I can
quere that accel to now get some
information.
So lets just for example print out the X
value.
Okay so I has an X Y and Z value.
Well we put them all out actually and
we'll do X is Y is, and Z is.
Okay.
And I just need to edit this.
So that is getX, getY, and getZ.
So I've got 3 lines in my draw method
there.
So every time draw gets called it's going
to ask the accelerometer, what is your
current X position?
What's your current Y position?
What's your current Z position?
Okay, so let's run that on the device,
and we're going to just look at the
console to see the numbers that are
coming out.
Right, there are the numbers coming out
of the device.
That's telling me the current position of
the device.
Now if I pick it up.
And start moving it around.
You can see depending on which angle I'm
changing at different numbers are
produced.
And basically the range is from minus ten
through to ten.
So when you're at the most extreme angle
the numbers will go up to ten.
And, when you're at the opposite extreme
they'll get a minus ten.
So the values that come out from the
accelerator are in the range minus ten to
ten depending on the different angles
you're holding the phone at.
So how can we use this creatively?
Well, first of all let's just see if we
can use it to set the color of the
background.
So we're going to do this.
So we'll create some variables, which are
going to be our red, green and blue.
And we can set the red value using the
accelerometer data.
And then the green, and blue.
Right.
But remember, these values are in the
range minus 10 to 10.
And the range, the range that we need
for, colors is 0 to 255.
So well done if you've spotted that
already now what can I do here so to get
into the range 0 to 255 so I add 10.
Okay that puts it in the range 0 to 20.
And then, I can just.
Do an approximation here and just times
it by 10.
So it goes up to 0 to 200.
Okay.
That's near enough.
You can calculate that accurately by
dividing 10 by
255 by 10.
sorry, 255 by 20.
so we could do that.
We could do 255 by 20 to do it really
accurately.
[SOUND].
Okay.
So let's do that with the other ones as
well.
[SOUND].
Right.
And then, now this, remember that these
that come out are things like 0.15 or
-9.3 which are floating point numbers.
But I've declared my RGB's as integers.
So what I need to do is then cast it,
convert it to an integer before I can use
it.
Finally, I'm going to set my background
color using these values R, G, B.
Okay so, we've used the accelerometer
data to set up some red green and blue
value and then we're going to use that to
set up the background color so lets hit
play.
And see what happens to the background
color of the screen as we move the device
around.
[SOUND].
Okay.
So we pick up the device.
And as I move it around, you can see the
background color changes.
Now it, it seems to be changing kind of
slowly, so it kind of jumps from one
color to the next.
That's because the accelerometer data
updates quite slowly.
So remember, for example, the audio, what
we did with audio data, that updates very
fast.
so you know, that's very smooth and very
rapid, but it's, other types of data are
slower.
So, for example, the frame rate in
processing, which is the number of times
a second it cause a draw function is, is,
the default is 60.
Whereas the number of samples a second is
44,100 when you're dealing with audio.
So there's all these different rates of,
of data flow.
So what we're dealing with is a flow of
data from a sensor in the phone which is
coming in at certain rate.
that's not very high rate in this case.
Okay so that, that's dealing with
accelerometer data and sending it to the
background color.
In the next section, I'm going to talk
about how we can map that accelerometer
data to a playback control.
So there's a line here which if you're
quick you're going to.
Pause the video and quickly go and type
it in, see what it does.
So lets just lets just put the extra code
we need to be able to do this line here.
OK.
So back to here.
So now I need to create an audio player
and I want to control the speed with the
accelorometer.
So I can twist the phone around and it
will slow down and speed up the, the
playback of the audio.
So we do the usual thing, create the
maxim variable, create an Audio Player
variable, and then initialize it, maxim
equals new, maxim.
This should be familiar by now.
Oops.
And audio so player equals
maxim.loadFile, and the name of the file.
So, I'm going to use the, the beat we've
been using.
Okay, so thats the player.
So in the draw method, we just make sure
the player is playing.
In fact we can.
So we do player play.
If the player is already playing we would
just ignore that.
Just make sure its playing.
then, what we're going to do is say,
player, and set the speed.
Now, let's, let's do a calculation here.
We're going to do this as a float,
because remember speed so if we pass in a
speed of two, then it will playback the
audio twice as fast, so its going to skip
through all those samples twice as
quickly.
If we, if we set the speed to one it will
play back at the normal speed so it will
sound as it was originally recorded.
now, so, the kind of, an interesting
range for speed, as we've seen with the
DJVJ.
It might be zero through to two.
So we need to get that accelerometer
data, and scale it to the range, zero to
two.
Just an organizational note, that I've
just placed these variables from the
middle of the code up to the top of the
method.
Now, everyone has their own way of doing
things when it comes to programming.
There's many ways to, to program and to
organize your code.
For me, I quite like to put my variables
at the top of the method so that it's
really clear.
All of the variables I'm going to use in
that method.
its a, its a neater way to do it in my
mind.
So, so I've just placed those at the top
there.
Now, the speed.
Remember, I said an interesting range for
the speed was, say, zero to two.
So what we're going to do is take that
accelerometer data like, this, okay?
And we're going to scale it to the range,
zero to two.
So we're going to do add ten.
So that puts it in the range zero to 20
again.
And then we can just divide it by 10 and
that will put it in the range 0 to 2.
So then we use that set the speed.
So lets see how that goes.
I'm using X so that's me twisting the
phone like this.
So hopefully what this is going to do is
is if you like replace what we did last
week which is the having to touch the
screen to change the speed now we can
actually just move the phone to change
the speed.
So it becomes maybe a more embodied
experience.
More like a real instrument where you
move around and it changes the sound.
So lets lets run that.
[MUSIC] Okay so I pick the phone up and
you can hear the speed's already changing
now if I tip it that way, [SOUND] you can
see it's.
>> [MUSIC] It's now going really fast.
And I'll twist it back around.
I can take it to a stop.
So let's just try and play with that a
bit.
[SOUND] So, you can see it becomes a
really fun thing to do and, and once you,
if you got a few sounds going, you can
start really jerking the phone around and
getting quite creative with the way you
perform with that thing.
So it becomes like a rather than it
being, if you like.
An interface that you tap on becomes an
instrument that you can, you can really
try to perform with.
I would recommend that you try some
different sounds in there.
Try just record tones, try recording
anything really and sticking in there and
see if you can map different properties
of the sound to the tellurometer data
there.
[MUSIC]