[SOUND].
In the next section I am going to talk
about how to use audio in analysis to get
some information about the sound that's
currently playing.
Now, you can see in this code here, that
I've got a player and I'm telling the
player to do, to start analyzing by
calling the set analysis.
Set analyzing method and setting it to
true.
What that will do is that will cause the
player to, to begin, not just playing
back, but also listening to itself
playing and doing some analysis on there.
But the type of analysis we're going to
do, is, is called extracting in the,
spectrum.
So we're going to extract from the power
spectrum of the sound.
Now what does that mean?
Well, the basic idea is that when you
listen to a sound, there are different
components in that sound.
For example, if you listen to very heavy,
bass-y music like Reggae or something
like that.
There's a lot of really low frequency
sound in there, a lot of bass.
So maybe bass is a more familiar term
than low frequency, right?
So if we talk about base that's in the
low frequencies we can also talk about
treble which is what makes a sound bright
and treble the opposite end to bass in
the description of the sound.
So we talk about treble and midrange is
more, things, so speech happens a lot in,
in the mid-range and hmm, but it has lot
of trouble bits as well.
For example, if I go [SOUND] that's a lot
of, there is a lot of trouble in that.
Okay, so the idea is that with this
analysis we can actually get some
information about what, how much basis in
that, how much trouble is in there and so
on and also we know what is the average,
of, of the level of the sound.
And as I said the method we said to do
this is the fast Fourier transform, the
FFT.
And we can get the data out of that and
turn it into what we call a power
spectrum, which really is just telling us
how much power this is in those different
frequency bands.
So is there, how much bass is there, but
not just how much bass and how much
different bands of bass so low bass and
medium bass.
Okay.
And so what we're going to do first is
just take an average of all of those
difference frequencies.
And see if we can use that to, plot a
signal meter, which will show us what's
going on in the sound currently.
So you can see here, I'm pulling out this
float called Pow, which is the average
power in, in the spectrum.
So that's looking at all of those bands,
bass, treble, mid, and taking an average
of all that.
And then I'm going to set a color using
that, and following that I'm going to
draw a rectangle where the size is set by
the, by the power as well.
So let's just code that up and see what
it looks like.
So I'm going to have to first deactivate
a bit of this accelerometer code.
So I'm going to add another float up
here.
Float power okay.
Remember I have to say player.set
analyzing so apologies if you're used to
American English spelling, and you're
used to S's instead of zed zeds instead
of S's.
But for obvious reasons, we're using Ss.
okay now.
So that will tell it to start doing that
analysis.
So extracting that, that, that spectrum.
So that I can then ask for it later.
So, let's do that.
We'll leave this speed and in fact I'm
going to delete all of that code, okay.
So, lets pull out the power.
Power equal player get average power.
Okay, that's what I need to do to pull
out the average power.
The player calculates it all for me and
then I'm going to set a fill color using
that.
So I'm going to use the red now and the
power value actually has been set up so
it comes in the range zero to one.
Which makes it a little bit easier to
deal with in the accelorameter data we
looked at.
So its in the range zero to one so I
could just use it directly at that.
So that's the red component.
OK so its just going to set the red and
then I'm going to draw a rectangle with a
width which is set by the power.
So again, I just use it as a ratio if you
like.
Power times width.
So if it's full power, the bar should go
all the way across.
If it's, if it's, as it, as it gets
lower, it goes less and less across.
You'll see what that does in a minute.
The basic idea is that it will be like a
bouncing bar.
And height will be the complete height of
the screen.
Right.
So now let's run this on the device and
see what our new volume or power meter
looks like.
[MUSIC] [MUSIC].
Okay.
So, it's a bit difficult to see.
Because the red, maybe, is a little bit,
dim.
So what I'm going to do.
And also, I'm not filling in the
background color as I go.
Let's just fill in the background color.
because it wipes out, wipes the
background.
[MUSIC] So I made a few edits to the code
just to make it so that the background is
set at, is, is clear every time and the
power, it should be clearer now.
[MUSIC] Okay.
So that's, okay, that's a bit better.
[mmm] So there's quite a lot going on in
that sound.
So it's not necessarily very clear what,
what's going on from power there.
You can see when there are stronger,
bursts in sound.
You can see the power bouncing.
Let's just try it with a different sound.
So you can, you can see from that there
are the volume meter bounces.
The power meter bounces, but maybe we can
use a better sound to illustrate it.
So we actually have this sound we created
previously.
called ping, as I remember.
And so let's just run it with the ping
sound.
And it might be a bit clearer what's
going on.
[SOUND]
Perhaps that's a bit clearer.
You can see that hmm, the parameter is
bouncing every time the ping happens.
So we have covered how you can extract
some information about the spectrum, but
it's quite, it's quite low-resolution if
you like.
It's not telling us a lot of information
about what's going on.
We just looked at the average power which
was looking at all the frequency bands
and taking the average power, which is
basic, kind of like, you know, how loud
is it right now?
if you like, which allowed us to draw a
volume meter.
Now, if you want to get into more detail
You can actually access not just the
average power, but you can look at each,
individual band so you can tell how much
bass there is, how much mid range there
is, and how much treble there is.
So I've got some code on the next slide
which just shows you the basics of how to
do that.
But I'm going to do a more interesting
example in the editor.
So let's just look at that code first So
at the top of your code you can create a
float array called spec.
Now what's a float array?
Well remember that float is just a single
variable which can store a number, which
is something like 1.7 or you has a has a
decimal place if you like.
Its an accurate number think of it that
way and float away, you can see we've got
those square brackets can basically store
lots of floats.
Now, that makes sense because we don't,
we want to, we don't just want to store,
so the average power, we want to store
the power in every band.
So we need some place where we can store,
lots of numbers so that's why we've got
an array there.
Markers covered arrays in a previous
lesson and also you can look in his
additional programming lectures to find
out more.
Now in the code below so we asked the
player, we're assuming you've got a
player created and we ask it to do the
analysis and then In a draw method, we,
exp-, We, we ask for the power spectrum
from the player.
Which will give us the current snapshot
of whatever the power spectrum is.
And then, if we get something valid.
So we check if it's null.
So we check if we get something valid
back.
and then, if we do, we iterate that
spectrum using a four loop.
Again, four loops are covered in more
detail in.
Markers additional programming lectures.
So we've basically stepped through every
number in that spectrum and we set a fill
color using that and draw a rectangle
based on it.
Now as I said earlier that's a basic
example I want to do a more interesting
works example where what we're going to
do is plot that spectrum over time.
So you can kind of see a map of these
sounds you've been hearing over time.
So how we do that is like this.
So we've got an audio player and in draw
method, we can play as usual.
And that will, that won't effect it,
it'll only cause it to play if it's not
playing already.
So it's okay to just keep calling it And,
we going to try to extract the spectrum
so first of all we add the float spectrum
we'll expect so I can target slightly
more rapidly and here we going to say if.
So spec equals.
Player get power spectrum, like that.
And if spec is not input is no so we got
a valid got something plot, the we type
in a for loop.
So we set a variable i to not.
I has to be smaller than spec dot link so
and i plus plus so that's going to go
from zero up to whatever, how many
numbers there are in that spectrum we've
just been given.
Okay, and what I'm going to do is I'm
going plot the spectrum using differently
colored dots.
So if the If that, if the power band is,
is powerful, then it will do a brightly
colored dot.
So I'm going to do that using the stroke,
and I'm going to stroke color is 255,
which if, if it's just 255 it will give
us a white color, but 255 times the value
of the spectrum at I, so As it goes
through, it will start with the base at
the, the, the top end of the spectrum.
That is, the top end of the array.
And work through the array, and get to
the treble at the other end.
Okay?
And then I'm going to draw a point.
now, the x and y position, the point.
Well, the x position, I'm going to just,
I'm going to use a variable actually,
because what I want to do is, I want to,
each time I plot this, this spectrum, I'm
going to move along so that I can plot it
slightly further along the next time.
Which will allow me to, if you like, draw
a map of that spectrum over time.
So I'm going to create an integer called
xPos.
And set it to naught, in set up so it
starts at zero.
My x position is just going to be x
pause, and my y position will be just i.
So, as i increases it draws, it will draw
a line, it will draw these dots down the
screen where each dot has a different
color based on the power of that element.
So next time I'm going to draw, I want x
pause to go up by four.
So it moves along by four.
And since I'm moving along four.
So imagine I'm drawing these kind of
dotted lines down-screen.
I want to, I can also make my stroke
weight to four.
So that the dots are drawing, also, are
four pixels wide.
Okay?
So that should plot my, my sound over
time across the screen.
So let's just.
Let's run that on the device now.
[SOUND] [MUSIC] Okay, so you can see
it's, it's drawn, let's just stop that
and I'll explain it, so you can see what
it's drawn there is But looks like a kind
of, a bunch of white plotting gray scale
plot of some sort.
Now the top of that screen wherever the
bass frequencies and the lower down the
screen it gets the higher pitches so
that's how that works.
And you'll notice there are if you like
bands, looks like there was more going
on.
And those bits were signifying when there
was a bass drum playing, or a snare drum.
So that the, the, the break beat kind of
has a bass, snare, bass, snare sound.
And you can see that pattern in, in the
spectrum.
Now, what I want to do is just.
The problem is that x pause eventually
gets higher than the width of the screen.
So it starts plotting off of the edge of
the screen.
So you can't see it anymore.
So what I'll do just to make a final
change is if X pos is greater than width
in other words if I've moved off the edge
of the screen.
So go back to the other side of the
screen and wipe it ready to re draw the
new spectrum okay so set X so it will
move across the screen.
Drawing the spectrum and when you get to
the end we go back to the beginning.
So let's run that on a device now.
We should see when it gets to the edge of
the screen it, it returns to the other
side and starts plotting there again.
[SOUND]
So you can see the double base drum
there.
Dun, dun, dun, that sound.
[MUSIC] Right.
So that's the spectrum.
So you can see it's quite dense at the
top.
Quite dense.
That means there's plenty of bass going
on in it.
And there's, and it sort thins out
towards the top end.
So you can definitely see the bass drums
having a kind of denser sound [MUSIC] so
let's stop that.
Now, I encourage you try and load some
different sounds into there and record
yourself and load back into there and
just trying plotting some different
sounds and you see what's going on and
also the layer in the spectrum is perhaps
more interesting so, you might want to
plot the first.
So 50 things in that array and just plot
them across the whole screen so you can
really explore what's going on in that
spectrum so try some different sounds
explore the spectrum have fun and if you
can make something more interesting.
You can also add interactivity so that
they can slow down the sound speed up and
see how the spectrum changes so that's
what I would advise you to go and do.
And to, to explore this topic further.  [MUSIC]