[SOUND].
Okay, so we've had Marco explain to you
about rotation and translation and other
types of methods for changing the display
of certain types of graphics and
characteristics of graphics on the
screen.
And we've had Matt explaining to you,
explaining really how we analyze audio
among other things.
Now what we going to do is we're going to
try and combine those two things
together.
We're going to do a little bit of what we
call graphical synthesis to create
algorithmic graphics.
And we're going to do a little bit of
audio analysis and combine that to make
an audio visualizer.
Audio visualizers are really popular and
you find them all over the place
remarkably so in pretty much every media
player and every major console.
So for example in the xbox Jeff Minter's
audio visualizer is the main visualizer
when you see when you put a CD in.
although other visual artist like I think
it's flight 404, their visualizer used
for iTunes, so there is a whole range of
people who just make computer graphics,
abstract computer graphics.
And their work is a major part of
everybody's listening experience.
the audo analysis aspect of doing
audio-visualization is quite good to
understand and is quite nice to know how
to do some of those tricks.
I'm going to take you through basic
analysis and how we use it to change
graphic parameters.
And I'm also going to give you a really
quick introduction to beat detection.
so let's start at the beginning.
Building an audio visualiser.
So, the first thing we need to learn is
how to do algorithmic drawings.
There are so many different ways to doing
this and so many different methods and
different algorithms you can apply.
I'm going to teach you how to do some
really simple stuff that uses rotation
and translation, and we're going to start
with rotation.
Now, fundamentally the key to almost all
algorithmic drawing is a for loop.
And Marco will explain that to you if
you're not sure what for loops are you
should go back and check the programming
lectures that Marco supplied for you in
case you're a little rusty.
It's actually really, really easy to
understand the for loop and I'm sure
you'll be fine with it.
But all you really need to know is this
is a method for drawing lots and lots of
things in different ways on the screen.
Let me give you an example.
Here's a basic rotation sketch which we
can look at.
You can see this would run fine on an
iPad or an iPhone.
We've got a bunch of rectangles and
they're all spinning round.
You'll notice that when they spin round,
they seem to, line up at certain points.
Like just then.
Also you'll notice if you're looking,
that you get four, a group of four, then
a group of five, then a group of three,
and then it spins out into one long arm
and goes all the way around.
Now the reason this works is because
every individual shape I'm drawing is
spinning.
Based on its position in a system of a
certain number of object.
So if I want, If I had 20 objects and I
was spinning them all, and I was spinning
an object in the middle, I, I would be
spinning it 20 times slower than the
object on the object on the edge.
And when you do that, you get this
interesting symmetrical pattern.
This has been used by lots of artists
over the years and it's an interesting
way of getting feedback type effects that
are really symmetrical.
Let's have a quick look at how it works.
So it doesn't use any trigonometry
although we are going to look at some
basic trig real soon.
But what we do have is a so it doesn't
use any trigonometry, but what we do have
is a simple rotation.
And I'm going to show you how that works.
This is the sketch.
So ther's no sine, there's no cosine,
there's no tangents or stuff, and there's
no pi.
We'll be looking at pi a little bit
later.
Young blah etc.
But it has a similar effect, I'll just
used a variable called time.
This variable is initialized at zero at
the top of the sketch.
Let's have a quick look at what's going
on underneath here if we go back.
So we have time and time is this value
where we're incrementing bit by bit.
Every, every time that we ask the
computer to draw a frame that increments.
And then what we do is we say okay,
here's a for loop.
basically I want to do this 20 times
times, and it uses this variable i, which
is an integer, to do it 20 times.
We're going to rotate given the current
time so as time progresses and as time is
incremented by this value of 0.01, it's
going to change the rotation.
And then what we're going to do is we're
going to draw a rectangle based on its
position, i, it's position in the system,
whichever one it is.
And then we're also going to change the
signs based on their position.
and that's what we have here and that's
what gives us this spinning set of
squares.
So you can see here the normal sort
processing stuff size and frame rate, we
set the background to white.
We translated everything to the middle of
the screen so that zero and zero the 0x
and 0y is right in the center.
This is useful, and for all the sketches
I'm doing today, that why, that's how I'm
working.
I've turned the fill of and then here's
the bit we just looked at.
I'm incrementing time.
I've got 20 of these and then I'm just
spinning them around.
Each one is being spun around differently
based on what the time is.
And then I'm drawing it but the join
functions been parameterized with the
number i.
The number i represents the number in the
system, so remember what I said before.
So if I'm spinning the one in the center
around, I was spinning it 20 times slower
than the one on the edge.
So as I count each one out rectangle
here, rectangle here, rectangle here this
one spins like this and this one spins
like this.
So this one for every single rotation
this one does this one does 20 rotations,
the one on the other end.
Okay, so that's the basic idea.
Let's try something a bit more
complicated.
Let's do a for loop with rotation and a
bit of trigonometry.
It's a really, really simple algorithmic
process.
This one, I always use, I always used
this example when I'm explaining about
algorithmic drawing because it's a really
good algorithm to start with because it's
one of the earliest computer graphics
algorithms we're creating.
animations and it was used by John
Whitney, Sr to produce a range of really
famous abstract animated pieces.
He also used a similar technique for
generating what's called Lissajous
figures for doing the title sequence to
Vertigo.
Which I think there's just been a, in
fact the day we're recording this there's
a Google doodle which gives you an
indication of when we're recording this.
There's a Google doodle which celebrates
the work of Saul Bass and on that there's
quite a lot of stuff about John Whitney
because Saul Bass went with John Whitney
to do the vertigo type of sequence using
exactly this algorithm.
And it's one of the earliest pieces of
computer graphics that Whitney did on a
computer that he built himself, in fact.
So get this to work, we need to use some
trigonometry, and we need some elements.
We've got some variables and some
elements.
The elements is the number of objects
that we want to draw and the variables
are the way we want to draw them.
And we change these all inside the loop.
So we have a variable float spacing a
variable called rotation a variable
called radius and a variable called
magnify.
And the we have int the number of
elements.
So in the for loop we say.
As many elements as we've got, we keep
looping around until we've drawn them
all.
That's what it says int i equals 0, i
less than element i plus plus.
And then we're using pushMatrix and
popMatrix, which Marco will have
explained to you about already.
Now what we do is instead of rotating
given our time value, we rotate given
spacing, i and rotation.
So there are three numbers that we use to
calculate what the current rotation's
going to be.
So we have the spacing, which is the
distance between all the objects.
We have i, which is the number of the
object in the system.
And we have rotation, which is how much
rotation there currently is, how much
we're rotating into our system.
And then what we do is we're translating
it as well at the same time.
So that's the main difference.
Although we're parametrizing rotate
differently, we're still just rotating
it.
The key thing is here we're translating
at the same time.
Which means It doesn't just spin round,
it goes in and out.
And we are using sine to do this which is
a trigonometric function which squeezes
all the, all the shapes in and out.
Now, let's have a quick look.
Basically, we're drawing an ellipse every
time we do this.
I'm going to show you what that looks
like.
So this is the basic rotation with sine.
Now, as always with these examples,
they're accessible in week three, lesson
three of the coursera documents that you
should have.
and here we have it.
So this is this is the algorithm that I
was just talking about.
It's useful for all sorts of things.
And, it's neat so I'll pair, I'll
parametrize it with mouseX and mouseY so
you can see I'm just exploring with the
mouse at the moment.
you'll notice that while I'm just
traveling down the diagonal, we'll always
have it well it always gives us circles.
But if I move in the y dimension, it
rotates and if I move in the x dimension,
it translates.
And you see we get these interesting
symmetries.
Let's have a, a kind of closer look at
that.
I'm going to go back to here.
So how are we doing that?
Well, we're mapping the radius and the
rotation, given mouseX and mouseY,
exactly as I'm showing you on this slide.
So, we're going, okay.
Well, we'll take the mouseX as input.
And we presume that's from zero, which is
the leftmost side of the screen, to the
width of the screen.
And then we're mapping that to values
between 0 and 10.
And we're doing the same for the
rotation.
So, because of the way we've organized
these elements to be drawn, radius and
rotation are in the same range.
The other thing, the other variable which
we introduced in the last slide which
we're using to make this Whitney
algorithm, is, spacing.
Now spacing is how far apart, as I've
said, how far apart the different
elements are drawn.
And this is really about how far around a
circle it is.
So in this case, we're getting TWO_PI.
Now TWO_PI is basically how we measure
around a circle.
So we start here zero pi and we measure
around and we get to, TWO_PI.
Okay?
So Marco will have explained a little bit
about pi.
We're using pi divided by elements to
figure out how we get, say we have 1000
elements.
We're dividing TWO_PI by 1000.
And we're saying that's how far apart all
the, all the different elements are.
So it's a bit like saying, well, you
know, I've got a box which is one meter
long.
And I want to get ten sandwiches in it.
So I'm going to stick each one in at a
tenth of a meter, apart.
That's basically what we're doing.
Although they're not sandwiches.
There's no box.
It's just a circle and some graphics.
So radius and rotation, they're the two
variables which are how far around it's
going, and how far away from the center
it is, and spacing is how far apart we
are around the circle.
So quickly let's have a look at this.
So here they are.
We're in the draw loop.
We set the background to black.
We've mapped mouseX to ray x.
We've mapped mouseY to rotation.
We've created spacing which is TWO_PI
elements.
We translated the center of the screen
which is what we're doing for all these
sketches.
I've explained that to you before.
We turn fill off and then what we do is
we say for every element pick a color.
I'll be talking about a color in a
minute.
PushMatrix just like Marco said we needed
to.
Now rotate based on how far apart they're
supposed to be, which element and system
they are and what the rotation currently
is.
And then translate but when we
translating we're getting the sine of the
spacing which is how far apart they are.
The i which is the number which
particular element it is and the radius
which is how far from the center it is.
So we get the sine of that and then we
magnify it.
Now this is what creates that squeezing,
cause the, what sine produces is this
waveform like this.
And because we're running those values
into a sine wave and then magnifying them
out, then we're basically not just going
around the circle, we're going through
the circle as well.
As we are squeezing the radius to and
from the centerfold.
And that's how it works.
Then we draw our circles.
Now, you'll see, if I show you the
sketch, all the circles are the same
size.
I can do some interesting things quite
fast just by times-ing them by i.
Let's try again.
And you'll notice that immediately I've
got a very very different sketch with,
which looks a lot more interesting.
You see, I've got, I think they're far
too big so I should probably change the
size.
Let's just make them, I just, I'll say i
times 10 instead of 20, cause they're a
bit off the screen.
let's try that again.
Yeah, that's a bit more like it.
So you can see I've got a lot more
control, and you get this weird sort of
pseudo 3D effect.
And it's worrying as all the different
circles interact, exactly like they did
in the first sketch.
You get this kind of weird mesh.
Now, when I'm all the way over here, it
looks a bit messy.
But really when both the values are quite
near to zero, you get some quite nice
effects, nice 3D effects.
Also what we can do is we can change the
number of circles.
So if I change the number of elements to
something a bit ridiculous, like 1,000 is
a lot.
Let's try 256, just double them, I wonder
if it can handle that?
Yeah, there you go, well that's 256 and
you see that immediately.
It's starting to look a lot more
interesting, and all we've done is taken
a few of the variables and parameterized
them okay.
So we're going to use this, in a bit to
show you the final example.
But lets move on.
I want to talk a bit about hue and
rotation and then I'm going to talk about
how we organize, so we do color and then
I'm going to talk about how we organize
sound and beat detection.
So instead of using red, green, and blue
colors like we normally do I'm using hue
saturation and brightness, HSB.
Sometimes called HSV color where the V
stands for Value instead of brightness.
Sometimes called HSL, where it stands for
Luminance.
So basically, hue is the color tone.
Rather than having a mixture of red,
green and blue, we can say, well, I want
the color tone, whether it's red, blue or
yellow to be one number.
And that's normally expressed between
zero and 360 degrees.
And it's, it's as if it was going around
a circle.
saturation is the color depth which is
how strong the color is.
And brightness is self explanatory, it's
how bright it is.
So bright it is if so if saturation is
zero.
The color is, is either you know, is a
shade of gray.
And if brightness is zero, it's black.
And you can see by this triangle, how it
works.
Now so what we do here in processing, in
order to make this work is we change the
color mode to HSB.
And then we can control what we would
normally like the Fill command, or the
Stroke command to set the hue saturation
and brightness.
And in that example I was showing you,
you saw that the color was going through
a range of different colors from one
circle to the other.
Because in my Stroke command in my fit,
yeah, it was the Stroke command.
In that Stroke command I was setting it
based on the number of the elements in
the system.
So it went around the hue circle, you can
see the hue circle here, which is on the
top of this, on the bottom of this cone.
It went round and round and round that
cone, based on which number in the
graphical system we were drawing.
So, if we use that hue saturation and
brightness, and then we do some analysis,
we can create some interesting visuals.
I'm going to start with a really simple
visualizer, based on analyzing sound.
Exactly what Matt said.
We get, we analyze the audio by getting a
float value called power in this example.
And that's that's done by using the audio
method, get average power.
So, we go float power equals plat pow
Float power equals player.getAveragePower
and then we use the variable power to
change the animation.
I've got an example that I want to show
you.
Which is really, really simple.
what it does is, it's, uses HSV, as I've
already said, and it produces.
The form, it produces it, you load the
sound, you analyze the sound, and then we
just change the color.
You can see I'm changing the color here,
before it draws this circle.
And it looks like this.
And we should get some [MUSIC] and just
to prove that I'm actually analyzing it
if I change the speed you see that a hue
rotation changes speed too.
So, I'm clicking and dragging, [SOUND]
clicking and dragging to change the speed
and you gotta be a bit careful with this
cause if you stare at it to long it can
give you a funny feeling.
I guess I better move on.
So, if I show you a bit of that code,
it's really simple.
We have another for loop with a number of
elements which is exactly the same as
before.
I'm literally just drawing 20 circles,
and those 20 circles are spaced in the
screen from the outside in, just as if I
was laying sugar paper circles one on top
of the other.
And then, what I'm doing, is I'm using
the hue and I'm rotating the hue based on
the power, and also the also then the
number of the element that we're
currently in.
So, the outer circle is a different hue
to the inner circle.
Which is why it seems to cycle from the
outside to in.
That's basic color cycling.
Okay.
So, we're just to go through that again,
we're changing the color of the elements
depending on the power.
We get the float value power from the
getAveragePower method.
We also have another float called Go
which.
Go is basically how much energy we have.
So we keep adding the extra power and
I've got a multiplier plus 50 which you
can change.
Have a mess with that.
See how it effects how fast it moves.
So Go is a value which we use to keep
cycling through, through all the
different color values.
So, it's the, It's the additive power as
we keep going.
And it's kind of a number that keeps
getting bigger and bigger.
Now, I'm using Modulo here to make sure
that whatever that value is, it's
constrained to between 0 and 255.
And we go, basically we have a fill
command, i plus go, modulo 255.
And that's the hue, power times 512,
that's the saturation, and 255 is the
brightness, so it's always very bright.
And then we draw our ellipses, and the
size of the ellipse is dependent on which
circle we're actually drawing.
So the circle go from the outside in.
So that's the most simple kind of audio
visualiser.
Let's take another look at it because
it's good for the eyes [MUSIC].
Really simple and really effective.
Now let's say you want to do something
more complicated, we can control the
visualizer with sound through beat
detection.
Beat detection is something which is
useful when you're doing visualizers.
And I've got a simple example here.
Let me show you the example.
I'll tell you how it works.
As I've said before, all of these can be
found in the materials which you should
have week three.
So um, [MUSIC] we've got the same track
here and you'll notice we've got circle
in the middle, which is showing us the
average power.
And then there's a square appearing
whenever it, it detects a beat, and the
square is appearing in the top left hand
corner.
Let me show you how I did that.
So how did I do that?
Basically, what I'm doing is I'm getting
the average power, I'm running a beat
detector.
Let me talk you through how the beat
detector works.
So quickly, what we do is we need to have
two variables for beat detector.
In addition to power, we need to have
threshold, and we need to have wait.
So the threshold is what the power needs
to be for us to detect that there's been
a beat.
It's basically a level that we set and if
it goes over that level, we call it a
beat.
And then wait, tells us to wait a certain
amount of time before we go looking for
more beats.
Now, so we have a little method here, in
each statement.
Power, if the power is greater than the
threshold, and also weight is less than
zero so if we finished waiting and the
power is over the threshold then we can
do something to change the animation.
So in the case that I just showed you
we're just drawing a rectangle on the
screen but we could also do something
else.
We could get this value go or our other
value, we'll call it amplitude for
example and we can add the power to that
amplitude to create a running graph of
the current amplitude.
And then what we do is we add ten to the
wait value.
So we wait for another ten frames before
we detect another beat.
And then immediately we close that
bracket we do wait minus minus which
starts the countdown.
So every drawing frame we count down and
we're counting down until wait is less
than zero again and then we go okay we
can look for another beat.
And that's basically how it works.
Let me just show it working again so you
can see.
[MUSIC] And you can see that [MUSIC] you
should actually be able to see the
numbers flashing on as it detects a beat
here.
You've got the average here and the
square is being drawn when we get a beat.
[NOISE] So that's really simple.
Okay so this is the last example I'm
showing you, it's just a way of showing
you how we put all those things together.
it's not a fully In a worked example you
cold do a lot.
So for example, I'm, I'm not really using
the color cycling.
And also I've only done a little bit to
change the animation.
I just made it look slightly nice.
But I'm drawing lines instead of drawing
circles.
also I'm not changing the visualizer
through out.
You could have a number of different
drawing methods and change them based on.
How many beats are being detected or any
number of different ideas.
So let me just show you a bit what that
looks like and then you should take this
away as a starting point with all of the
other examples and try and build your
own.
So this is what it ends up looking like.
[MUSIC] You can see that we've got the
position of the lines changes based on
[MUSIC] the beat's being protected, but
they're also rotating based on the
energy, so they're really closely linked
to the music.
Also, because the lines are all being
rotated.
They're being rotated twice, once around
the origin and then again given a
separate value, and you'll see sometimes
we get nice symmetries, and sometimes we
get more noisy output.
[MUSIC] I'm also using a hue to rotate
all of the different colors, and so
that's it.
So in summary, what we've done is we're
created a simple visualizer, a really
basic one.
We could do a lot more by using alpha
blending, by doing more color cycling.
But essentially we are taking some
algorithmic approaches to drawing.
We are parameterizing them so that we can
control them in various ways.
We're analyzing the audio and we're
taking the output of the audio analysis
and plugging it into the sound, into the
graphics parameters.
So the sounds being plugged straight into
the graphics as if we were taking a Jack
plug out of a guitar and sticking it in.
In fact it's more complex than that
because we're doing spectral analysis and
we're doing weighted average spectral
analysis.
So this is a really good way a good
method of generating visual material and
generating interesting visual
applications [MUSIC]