[NOISE].
What did we do this week Mick?
What do we do?
We built some audio visualizers.
So yeah we did some [UNKNOWN] graphics
and we did some sound analysis.
So how did that go?
>> : Well I mean the sound analysis
basically you're just trying to get some
numbers out of some other numbers.
>> [LAUGH] :That's the most annoying
thing in the world.
Its quite a kind of dark art, isn't it?
It's a dark art and understanding what
those numbers mean is what it's all
about.
>> Yeah.
>> So I don't really emphasize that
some numbers tell you about the different
aspects of the sounds so is it bassy, is
it trebly and it's really important once
you've got an understanding of those
numbers to try and put those in to the
rest of your applications so that's where
Marco came in trying to explain.
The parameterization of graphics.
>> Actually yeah, there's a thing about
that Marco we used a really basic
visualization technique this week but
there's lot different types of approaches
you can take.
What's a good way for people to go and
find out better methods for drawing
stuff.
>> We'll got you know there's Pricing's
a really powerful tool set you'll
expanding your knowledge of Pricing/g, so
there's a lot to play with.
But I would say the best place to go for
ideas is the open processing website.
It's where people go to post their work
they've done in processing really created
people or doing exciting work and it's a
fantastic source of idea and you can get
the code there.
Some of it might be a little advanced for
you at the moment but you can also get a
lot ideas not only what people can do,
but how they did it.
Yeah and it's good as well because those
sorts of techniques they show you a lot
you can learn really fast by looking at
other peoples code and it's nice vital
community.
But speaking of communities, you should
check the forums out if you have any
questions and you know you should be at
the stage now where you should be able to
help each other.
And but ask students is there students in
more courses and if you've got anymore
questions you can always ask.
>> That's it for this week.
We'll see you next week where we're going
to be doing a game.
Aren't we?
>> Yes.
[CROSSTALK] That's right.
>> We are.
So, we'll see you for week four next
week.  [SOUND]