[MUSIC] If we care about extreme values,
it would really help to know how to find
them.
We can use a theorem, a theorem of
Fermat.
Here's Fermat's theorem.
Suppose f is a function and it's defined
on the interval between a and b.
c, is some point in this interval, this
backwards e, means that c is in this
interval.
Okay, so that's the set up.
Here's Fermat's Theorem.
If f(c) is an extreme value of the
function f, and the function is
differentiable at the point c, then the
derivitive vanishes at the point c.
It's actually easier to show something
slightly different.
So, instead of dealing with this, I'm
going to deal with a different statement.
Same setup as before, but now I'm going
to try to show that if f is
differentiable at point c and the
derivative is nonzero, then f(c) is not
an extreme value.
It's worth thinking a little bit about
the relationship between the original
statement where I'm starting off with the
claim that f(c) is an extreme value and
then concluding that the derivative
vanishes.
And here, I'm beginning, by assuming the
derivative doesn't vanish and then
concluding that f(c) is not an extreme
value.
This is the thing that I want to try to
prove now.
Why is that theorem true? I'm going to
get some intuitive idea as to why this is
true.
Why is it that if you differentiable a
point c with nonzero derivative there,
then f(c) isn't an extreme value? Well,
to get a sense of this, let's take a look
at this graph.
Here, I've drawn a graph of some random
function.
I've picked some point and f'(c) is not
zero.
Differentiable there, but the
derivative's nonzero.
It's negative.
Now, what does that mean? That means if I
wiggle the input a little bit, I actually
do affect the output.
If I increase the input a bit, the output
goes down.
If I decrease the input a bit, the output
goes up.
Consequently, that can't be an extreme
value.
That's not the biggest or the smallest
value when I plug in inputs near c, and
that's exactly what this statement is
saying.
If the derivative is not zero, that means
I do have some control over the output if
I change the input a little bit.
That means this output isn't an extreme
value because I can make the output
bigger or smaller with small pervations
to the input.
I'd like to have a more formal, a more
rigorous argument for this.
So, let's suppose that f is
differentiable at c, and the derivative
is equal to L, L some nonzero number.
Now, what that really means from the
definition of derivative is that the
limit of f(c+h)-f(c)/h as h approaches
zero is equal to L.
Now, what does this limit say?
Well, the limit's saying that if h is
near enough zero, I can make this
difference quotient as close as I like to
L.
In particular, I can guarantee that
f(c+h)-f(c)/h is between 1/2L and 3/2L.
Notice what just happened. So, I started
with infinitesimal information.
I'm just starting with a limit as h
approaches zero.
And I've promoted this infinitesimal
information to local information.
Now I know that this difference quotient
is between these two numbers as long as h
is close enough to zero.
Now, we can continue the proof.
So, I know that if h is close enough to
zero, this difference quotion is between
1/2L and 3/2L,
I'm going to multiply all this by h.
What do I find out then? Then, I find out
that if h is near enough zero,
multiplying all this by h, I find that
f(c+h)-f(c)/h*h is between 1/2hL and
3/2hL.
I get from here to here just by
multiplying by h.
Now, what can I do? Well, I can add f(c)
to all of this.
And I'll find out that if h is near
enough zero, then f(c+h) is between
1/2hL+f(c) and 3/2hL+f(c).
Okay.
So, this is what we've shown. We've shown
that if h is small enough, f(c+h) is
between these two numbers.
Now, why would you care? Well, think
about some possibilities.
What if L is positive?
If L is positive and h is some small but
positive number, this is telling me that
f(c+h), being between these two numbers,
f(c+h) is in particular bigger than f(c).
That means that f(c) can't be a local
maximum.
Same kind of game.
What if L is positive but I picked h to
be negative but real close to zero.
Then, f(c+h) being between these two
numbers, f(c+h) must actually be less
than f(c).
That means that f(c) can't be a local
minimum.
You play the same game when L is
negative.
Let's summarize what we've shown.
So, what we've shown is this.
We've shown that if a differentiable
function has nonzero derivative at the
point c, then f(c) is not an extreme
value.
And we can play this in reverse. That
means that if f(c) is a local extrema,
right? If f(c) is an extreme value, then
either the derivative doesn't exist to
prevent this first case from happening,
where f is differentiable at c, or the
derivatives equal to zero, which prevents
this second thing, f'(c) being nonzero.
So, this is another way to summarize what
we've done.
If f(c) is a local extremum, then one of
these two possibilities occurs.
Both of these possibilities do occur.
Here's the graph of the absolute value
function.
There's a local and a global minimum at
the point zero.
The derivative of this function isn't
defined at that point.
Here's another example.
Here's the graph of y=x^2.
This function also has a local and a
global minimum at the point zero.
Here, the derivative is defined but the
derivative is equal to zero at this
point.
We'll often want to talk about these two
cases together, the situation where the
derivative doesn't exist and the
situation where the derivative vanishes.
Let's give it a name to this phenomenon.
Here we go. If either the derivative at c
doesn't exist, meaning the function's not
differentiable at c, or the derivative is
equal to zero, then I'm going to call the
point c a critical point for the function
f.
This is a great definition because it
fits so well into Fermats theorem.
Here's another way to say Fermot's
Theorem.
Suppose f is a function as defined in
this interval and c is contained in
there, then if f(c) is an extreme value
of f,
well, we know that one of two
possibilities must occur.
At that point, either the function's not
differentiable, or the derivative's equal
to zero.
And that's exactly what we mean when I
say that c is a critical point of f.
So, giving a name to this phenomena gives
us a really nice way of stating Fermat's
Theorem.
The upshot is that if you want to find
extreme values for a function, you don't
have to look everywhere.
You only have to look at the critical
points where the derivative either
doesn't exist or the derivative vanishes.
and you should probably also worry about
the end points.
In other words, if you're trying to find
rain, you should just be looking for
clouds.
You just have to check the cloudy days to
see if it's raining.
In this same way, if you're looking for
extreme values, you only need to look for
the critical points because an extreme
value gives you a critical point.
So, this is a super concrete example.
Here's a function, y=x^3-x.
I've graphed this function.
I'm going to try to find these local
extrema, this local maximum and this
local minimum, using the machinery that
we've set up.
So, if I'm looking for local extrema, I
should be looking for critical points.
So, here's the function, f(x)=x^3-x.
I'm looking for for critical points in
this function.
Those are points whose derivative doesn't
exist, function is not differentiable, or
the derivative vanishes.
But this function is differentiable
everywhere.
Its derivative is 3x^2-1.
So, the only critical points are going to
be where the derivative is equal to zero,
right?
I'm looking for solutions to 3x^2-1=0.
I'll write one to both sides, 3x^2=1, so
I am trying to solve.
I'll divide both sides by 3,
x^2=1/3.
So, I am trying to solve.
Take the square root of both sides.
x is plus or minus the square root of a
third, which is about 0.577.
And that let's me find these critical
points,
right?
These are places where the derivative is
equal to zero.
The tangent line is horizontal and now I
know the x coordinate of these two red
points.
Here, are the x coordinates about 0.577,
and here the x coordinate is -0.577,
about.