[MUSIC] People have the idea that a local
minimum means the function decreases and
then increases.
Here's a local minimum on the graph of
this random function.
And the misconception is that they all
look like this.
That every time you got a local minimum
on one side, the function's decreasing,
and on the other side the function's
increasing.
Plenty of local minima do look exactly
like that. But, there's also plenty of
pathological examples.
For instance, consider this a somewhat
pathological example.
I'm going to define this function f as a
piecewise function.
If the input's nonzero, I'm going to do
this. 1+sin(1/x), which makes sense since
x isn't zero, time x^2.
And if the input is zero, the function's
output will also be zero.
In this case, there's a local minimum at
zero.
How do I know? Well, here's how I know.
Let's take a look at this function The
claim is that f(x) is never negative.
How do I know that? Well, what do I know
about sine? Sine of absolutely anything
at all, no matter what I take this sine
of, is between -1 and 1.
Now, if I add 1 to this, 1 plus sine of
absolutely anything at all,
is between zero and two.
Now, that's pretty good.
Now, think back to the definition of this
function.
Here, I've got 1 plus sine of something,
it doesn't matter what,
alright?
1 plus sine of anything,
this is between zero and two.
Now,
I'm multiplying it by x^2.
What do I know about x^2? Well, x^2 is
not negative.
It could be zero, it could be positive.
But no matter what x is, x^2 is not
negative.
Now, I'm multiplying 1+sin(1/x), this
number which is trapped between zero and
to, by x^2 which is never negative. And
that means f(x) is not negative as long
as x isn't equal to zero,
alright?
As long as x isn't equal to zero. I mean,
this first case and this is a
non-negative number times a non-negative
number, so the product is also
non-negative.
Now, the other possibility, of course, is
that I plug in zero for x.
But then, f(0) is just by definition
zero.
And that means in either case, no matter
that I plug in for x, f(x) is never a
negative.
Now if f(x) is never negative and f(0)=0,
then I know that this must be the
smallest possible output value for the
function.
The only numbers that are smaller than
zero are negative numbers, and the output
of this function is never negative. But
this isn't the usual sort of local
minimum where the function just decreases
and then increases.
Well, here's the graph for our funciton
f.
And, there is a local minimum at zero,
but if I start zooming in, no matter how
much I zoom in, there's no little region
on which the graph is just decreasing and
then increasing.
The graph is always wiggling.
The upshot here is that decreasing and
then increasing is one way to produce a
local minimum, but it's not the
definition of a local minimum.
And not every local minimum arises in
that exact way.
What a local minimum means is just that
no nearby output value is smaller than
that local minimum value.