Now, one of the things that we can do in
MongoDB is actually explain how a query
is executed.
Now, to do this in Python,
there's a completely different
command using the MongoDB shell.
But we're using our IPython notebook
here or our Jupyter notebook here.
We can perform the explain by running
a commands on the mflix database.
The explain command will be sent by
defining where we want to find, or
what the command on which collection
we want to find to perform.
In this case, the "find" on "movies".
And what's the filter that
we want to actually execute.
For example, "tomatoes.viewer.numReviews"
greater than 10.
It's a nice going to do.
And also, we can define the type of
verbosity of this explain command.
Once we run this,
we can see the execution of this query.
This different stages by which
the execution of the query needed to go
through.
If the stage is an index scan or
not, if it has it's FETCH stage,
and a bunch of other information
that is really, really important for
us to understand if the actual execution
is being optimum or close to that.
Now, I'm not going to go into too
much deep in terms of the weeds of
the query engine in all
the stages it performs.
But you should be aware of the fact that
every single query that is executed in
MongoDB and in other databases
will go through different stages.
For example, COLLSCAN basically stands for
a collection scan.
This is the worst performance you can get
because it will go into all different
documents of your collection and try to
match them against your query criteria.
But there's like FETCH, SORT, IXSCAN,
SHARD_MERGE, bunch of different
stages that make part of your query.
You will find some of them
on your explain output.
But getting back to the explain
itself of our query,
which is a filter on
"tomatoes.viewer.numReviews" greater
than 10, we can see here this
field called winningPlan.
It takes an inputStage
is a direction forward.
It has a couple of other
things which are interesting.
For example, the fact that it is passing
though an index scan into the stage.
Another important thing here to raise
up is the fact that it is using index.
And the index that's been used for
this query is this
tomatoes.viewer.numReviews -1.
So it's using a single index to
perform this particular query and
return results in a very,
very efficient manner.
But getting back to our list of indexes,
there's a particular index that I
want to raise your attention to.
This one here,
title_text_cast_text_directors_text.
Now, this means that this index here
is a fts, full-text search text.
Now, text search indexes
are slightly different from, for
example, single fill indexes like
tomatoes.viewer.numReviews, or
even compound indexes which are on
genres and tomatoes.viewer.numReviews.
The main difference is that, text indexes
do not just follow the exact match of
a value against the index structure.
They will take in consideration,
relevance.
How relevant is a key compared
to the different entries that
are present in that index?
In this particular example,
the title, cast, and
directors are all fields which are going
to be indexed based on their text.
That means that would be creating
an index for text search support.
So if we go down here to the notebook and
execute this particular query here where
our filters specifies that we're
looking for a title, Titanic.
We can see that we only
find the exact match
of the movies where the title is Titanic.
And if we would change something like
the title from capital case to lower
case on the title,
you might not find absolutely nothing.
Because there will not
be an exact match for
that particular title in our movies,
which is fine.
That's expected.
But we can also do another
different type of search.
We can specify that we are going
to be looking to a text search and
we're going to be searching for
the term titanic.
Once we execute that query,
we can see that we can find several
different movies, not just one.
And not all of them match titanic,
either case insensitive, but
also, for example,
the fact that we have Titan on it.
Now, why is that?
Text search will take in
consideration relevance.
And that means that we're going to be
looking to things like stemming of
the term, case insensitive,
diacritics and even stop words.
There's a bunch of different other options
that like we specified in our search terms
that would make this query results
smaller or larger depending on the type
of fidelity that we want based on the term
that we are providing for the search.
We're not going to go into
too much detail on that.
But this is a baseline functionality that
MongoDB supports based on a specific
set of text indexes that you
can specify on a collection.
The limitation here is that you can
only specify one text search index
per collection in MongoDB.
All right, cool.
l saw some of the different indexes that
MongoDB in this particular
movies collection has.
How can l create one my own if l want to?
Let's say, for example,
that we have this countries here filled,
that l would like to start searching on or
matching exactly,
or even sorting the results base on the
countries that the movie is related with.
Now, I could simply define a create index
method pathing on an array of two pools.
Those two pools will contain the field
key that I want, in this case, countries.
In what sort of order do I
want my index to be sorted?
If I would like to have a text field,
I could also specify that here or
even if it'd be to this field or
to the index.
That will be the type of index
that I'm going to be creating.
In this case, I'm going to create
a top level root level field,
single field index sorted ASCENDING.
Once I run the commands, it would tell me
back what's the name it was created with
following the nomenclature,
the fields, and the sorting order.
As a recap on this lesson's topics,
MongoDB has several
different types of indexes.
Now, indexes are used to optimize
our query performance and
the query access patterns that
we use in our application.
A collection may have several different
types of indexes on different fields.
Use them wisely,
because the more indexes we have,
the slower our writes will become.
If we are optimizing
our read capabilities,
we might be putting some
penalty in our write ability.
That's all I have for
you on indexes in movies lesson.