[SOUND] Hello this is week
six of Interactive Computer Graphics.
And the topic we'll discuss
here is Computer-aided Design.
So, computer-aided design is a process
of designing products using computers.
And today, almost all products
are designed using computers.
Starting from home electronics or
garments, or cars, and houses.
Everything is designed using a computer.
And physics,
plays an important role in here, and
physics simulation is already
heavily used in the design.
However, in most cases currently,
physics analysis is done after modeling.
So a user or designers design a model and
the modelers calibrate model.
And only after that, the model is
transported into the physical simulation
system, and then, so people will analyze
the property like collision, friction,
material property, gravity and so on.
And if there's a problem,
go back to the design.
So, but this is useful for
testing the validity afterwards, but
this is not very good for actively
use physics into the design process.
So what we try to do here, is to integrate
real-time physics into modeling.
So, so currently 3D model ignore physics.
Just specify x, y, z coordinates and
shapes, but
here in the system we introduce here.
Are all integrates, 3D of physical
assimilation into the modeling process, so
as user generates a model, of physical
assimilation automatically checks
validity and then provides feedbacks.
So that's the basic idea.
And then we will show a couple
of example systems here.
So, this is a list of topics
we're discussing this week.
So one is cantilever design for
architecture.
And design with music [INAUDIBLE]
noble musical instruments and
garment design, furniture design and
finally hobby glider design.
So the first one is cantilever design.
So this one is called responsive FEM,
Finite Element Method, for
aiding interactive geometric modeling.
So the program we want today,
discuss here is design of a,
physical with physical constraint.
Here, as an example is
a cantilever design.
Suppose you have a vertical wall here.
And they have a horizontal
steel bar attached to the wall.
So originally,
the steel bar is connected vertically com,
completely horizontally,
perpendicular to the wall.
But after construction,
if you release your hand,
support material,
gravity pulls the steel downwards.
So, this is of course exaggerated.
But in reality,
there's always a deformation.
So the goal is to find the shape that di,
ended in a completely flat horizontal
shape, after applying gravity.
So this is kind of
difficult inverse problem.
A traditional approach is to run
physical simulation after modeling.
So, use a space for the rest shape and
then physical simulation
predicts what happens.
Looking at the result, user go back to the
design phrase, and adjusts the shape and
they go to a simulation.
Now this kind of back and
forth interaction is not very efficient.
So what we propose is to run physical
simulation during modeling, specifically,
while the user is dragging one by one.
System should continuously
provides feedback.
This way, you can just know
when to release dragging.
So let me show you a demonstration.
So here is a demonstration.
So left side is original rest shape.
Then right side is after the gravity,
is applied.
And here, the simulation is continuous,
as a user.
So this is so natural, so smooth, it's
very hard to see, but hard to appreciate.
But, as a user drags a system continuously
physical simulation and continuously
presenting the deformed shape, after
physical simulation, it's very, very fast.
So as a user change, the position
system continuously updates lines many,
many simulations.
And the it shows a simulation result.
So it's so fast and
so smooth, so user actually looking at
this simulation result, while dragging.
So simulation result is satisfactory,
these are just stop dragging, and
you'll get the desired result.
So, that's the result, and
the other one that we use here is
a standard finite element simulation.
So finite element simulation is to divide
the domain, shape into small regions.
In this case triangle regions.
And then compute physical equations
on this matrix on these systems.
On the internally, this is a kind of many,
many it's internally
essentially it solves.
Huge linear equations, and
actually handling matrices.
And in order to accelerate this
computation in this kind of
direct manipulation editing,
what we use, what we use is here.
Reusing of intermediate
computation results.
So, traditionally it's too slow to hm,
run this kind of physi,
simulation from scratch each, each frame.
But in this example,
in this modeling task, you know,
you have the previous step for
simulation result.
And compared to the previous simulation
result, [INAUDIBLE] only a slight change,
you know?
Dragging single bar this,
the change is very small.
So you can reuse most of
the previous computation.
So that's a topic trick we use, we use.
Now, this is a little bit more details.
So, of course it's not possible
to explain everything,
because we skipped the exponential
finite element measure.
It's a little bit complicated.
But still, you can get the general idea.
So left hand side uses a coefficient
matrix a, reconditioned matrix x.
So, we do not describe
details about these other ma,
matrix structure we use in
the computation of this simulation.
And also, matrix has a value list and
their structure, and the body list,
and structure.
So these information
are heavily used in the system.
And construction,
of this information is time consuming.
So in the idle time, nothing happened, so
we can reuse old intermediate structure.
And in the during dragging, we divided
the dragging depending with the distance.
When the dragging operation is very small,
very small relocation,
then what's the system is do just
updates the mash-mish vertices.
And almost all information will be used.
As a user drags more and more, then,
simple vertex relocation doesn't work, so
system tries the update,
while it finds a topology.
But after a while, if the deformation
still rise, then simple relocation and
simple topology changes nothing there,
so system re,
reconstructs So this is what is happening,
behind the scene, in this example.
And internally,
if the relocation is very small.
Then only, system only,
recomputes a value list of its matrix A.
And if you change the topology,
you have to refresh all the coe,
coef, coefficient matrix A.
But you can reuse
the pre-condition matrix B.
But after the reconstruction
everything is re-computed.
So this is equivalent to [INAUDIBLE]
simulation from scratch.
But this happens very rarely.
So this is a very short section, but
summary is to introduce cantilever design
with concurrent physical simulation.
So you can change the shape while
watching a simulation result.
And internally, most important point
is that we apply multi-level reuse,
of intermediate computation result.
More specifically internal large matrixes,
matrices.
For efficient computation.
So original paper is available
as Responsive FEM for
Aiding Interactive Geometric Modeling.
We discussed many other
examples too there.
And finite element method is an est,
established method and
there are many textbooks.
One example is this one,
the finite element method.
It's basis on the fundamentals.
And structural optimization is often
discussed in computer graphics.
One example is this one.
A procedure modeling of structurally
sound masonry buildings.
So this one is the kind of
physics aware 3D modeling.
However, there is also just
automatic optimization, and
did not discuss interme not bring
the feedback to end user manipulation.
Thank you.