The last topic of this
week is a glider design.
So the work we here, we introduce here
is a teromis, an interactive design and
optimization of free form,
free flight model airplanes.
As you see, this is a very latest work.
So motivation the question we here
is how to design a paper airplane or
glider so you could fly the airplane,
and then we hope it flies well.
However, it is not very easy for
inexperienced people to design
a glider that flies well.
You know, there are many designs, but
this is the result of many,
many experimentation.
It's not easy to design
arbitrary shaped airplane.
So that's a problem we want to address.
And again, we ran concurrent simulation,
but not only ran simulation to
analyze it with as well,
we also provide automatic optimization.
So given current designs this model
automatic adjusts the shape so
that it flies well.
So, this is similar to
the previous system.
Behind the scene is more interesting.
Here, we use a data driven approach for
the simulation.
So accurate analytic simulation
of airflow is very difficult.
So here, we use many, many measured data.
So this is airplanes,
we actually fabricated, created,
flew together and measured.
We get this loads of data and
we infer many parameters.
And then we use it for
the physical analysis.
So that's the story.
So let me show you what we do.
Yeah, so this is a typical
example of not flying airplane.
So if you design arbitrary wing shape,
you know, it just drops, doesn't fly.
So our goal is to be able
to design arbitrary shape,
this kind of strange shape
airplane by yourself that flies.
And then this is one example we
created and it flies very well.
So, our approach is like this.
So first is offline precomputation.
So we took many,
many airplane trajectories and analyze it.
So we flew these gliders, and then check
the trajectory, flight trajectory.
And then we compare the simulation result,
and then adjust the parameters so
that simulation result fits
well with actual flight.
And this is the basis of
the physical analysis.
And given this data, now you generate,
you design your own airplane, and
the system now can predict
soft flight trajectory.
On the, in addition to showing or
predicting the flight trajectory the set
system runs automatic
optimization to make it flyable.
So the user can pause for
edit, edit and simulation [INAUDIBLE] and
then you get desired shape.
So this is our user interface.
So similarly, to the previous system
we use our edit to shape this kind of
two dimensional view.
So you're moving along the vertices, and
then system continuously
change the 3D shape.
In addition to that, here,
the bottom half is the simulation result.
So this predicts what happens.
In this case, the airplane goes upwards,
and the [INAUDIBLE] goes down.
And as user edits a shape, system
continuously runs physical simulation, and
tells whether the airplane flies well or
not.
The reason, why we have multiple
trajectories is that, you know,
the user's hand throw always changes.
Sometimes goes higher.
Sometimes goes lower.
So the system automatically predict,
consider multiple possibilities, and
then show general tendencies.
So that's a [INAUDIBLE].
And now let me describe
the optimization part.
So as you see,
there is a magic make it fly button.
So this is where you press this button,
system apprised automatic optimization,
and to make this airplane fly.
So here, in this design, it doesn't
fly well, it doesn't pass this line.
It goes too up or too down or
it doesn't fly well.
As soon as you press this button,
system optimizer, say it carefully,
it's kind of very subtle.
But I do not, nothing.
The video, shows the system
automatically adjust the wing position.
So, let's see.
The user press this button,
system adjust the wing position.
Yeah, here.
So, the front wing moved sideways,
so this is not by the user,
the system automatically adjusts
the shape so that it flies well.
So in this clip,
the user edits the front wing and
the system automatically adjusts the
position and orientation of the rear wing.
So as you see, user,
moves around the front wing and
then system automatically adjust,
the rear wing.
Please note that simulation results
[INAUDIBLE] drastically changes with
just small change in
the reorientation of the position.
Which is very difficult to do for
the user, or people to do it, but
the system can do it.
[SOUND] So again the important part is
this kind of interactive exploration.
You can test many different things and
the system continuously provide feedback.
After having the design,
you send the data to the laser cutter, and
then you get a shape.
And results.
So, here's our results.
So important thing is
it really flies well.
You know, it's kind of amazing for us too.
So this has a launcher and
they are starting from
As you see, yeah, it flies way back,
so it's very amazing.
Yeah, we have it here.
This dragon airplane, and this also flies.
You can also use other materials.
And this one.
Or this one.
Okay.
That's the video.
So, here's a summary of
the algorithm that we use.
So, standard fluid simulation
aerodynamics is too slow.
It's not, can be a real time.
So we use a traditional wing theory.
Wing theory is simplified
model of our airplane.
So it computes lift force occurring each
wing, and then after computing the lift
force and gravity and others, and then
you can predict the flight trajectory.
So that's the theory we use.
So wing theory looks like this.
So given given a, a wing,
shape, and then the force.
We compute, force up, close by the wing.
So it's the lift force, f,
and the drag force, fd, and
then rotation force in tau, tau.
And then it's a function of velocity and
area, you know.
It's faster and faster and then forces
gets bigger, and the area is bigger, and
the forces gets bigger.
And the question is these parameters.
You know, these are the constant.
Defines the behavior of the wing.
And it depends on the angle of attack and
also depends on the shape of the wing.
And these parameters are,
is what we want to know.
So to estimate this parameter, we take our
data driven parameterization approach.
So we fly many airplanes and
then measure the parameters and
then we try to fit the parameters.
So, you know, this Cd, Cl, Cm,
are all depending on the angle of attack.
And then we plot it in a measure,
we plot the measured data in the space and
then we get the best approximation.
And also we then,
we can estimate the force caused
by each wing element in this way.
And then we aggregate forces caused
by these small wing elements.
And then we computes approximate total
force caused by the total entire wing.
So to learn more the original paper is
published as Interactive Design and
Optimization of Free-Formed
Free-Flight Model Airplanes in 2014.
And flight simulation is also
discussed in graphics community.
One example is data-driven
controllable flapping flight.
So it simulates the flapping
flight of birds.
And data-driven simulation
is also a popular topic.
So you, it is opens a case too slow
to land, stand out a simulation.
So possible approach is to allow many,
many simulations beforehand of flying.
And then in a long time just assemble,
measure previous simulation
result to get a realistic result.
And one possible reading is
Data-driven simulation methods in
computer graphics is published as
a a Siggraph 12 course material.
So this is a summary of this week.
So we presented integration of
real time physics into modeling.
So user continuously aid it to save, and
then system continuously provides
feedback, running physical simulation.
On some systems, just provides
[INAUDIBLE] simulation results.
But, also some system provides continuous
guidance to design varied shapes.
So we introduce a fast,
simple cantilever design, and
also design, discuss musical
instruments with model analysis.
Also also garment design,
using linear approximation and
furniture design with active guidance
using joint force analysis, and
finally glider design using wing theory
with data driven parameter feeding.
So, that's the end of this video.
Thank you