[MUSIC]
We will calculate the motion of
electrons in a Penning trap like
the one shown in this small sketch.
For the moment we will neglect
the influence of the slight
inhomogeneity of the magnetic field
caused by the nickel ring, and
the electric field of the cap electodes.
If B points in the z direction it
follows from a vector potential equal to
(-By,0,0).
So the Hamiltonian of such a system
using minimal substitution
is 1/(2m) (p - eA)^2.
So with a bit of trivial mathematics,
we find 1/(2m)(p +
2m omega y p_x + m^2 omega^2 y^2).
If you write this in terms of
Cartesian components of the momentum,
we find that all the terms proportional
to p_x can be joined together and
the remaining term is p_z^2/(2m),
which corresponds to a uniform motion
in this z direction, which in reality,
will be limited by the cap electrodes.
The other two terms correspond to a
harmonic oscillation in the x-y plane.
The energy levels for
this oscillation are equal to
omega(n+1/2) with n a whole number, 0,
1, 2, and so on.
We now take into account
a spin of the electron.
The Hamiltonian acquires a term
µ_s B where µ_s is
the magnetic moment of the electron and
B is the magnetic field vector.
So this gives an additional splitting
by plus or minus g_e (eB)/(4m).
This last term is g/4 times the same
frequency which we had found earlier.
The energies corresponding
to these two spin directions
differ from E_n by plus or
minus g_e/4 times omega.
This results in a level spacing due to
spin of g_e/2 times omega compared
to one level spacing by the cyclotron
motion which is ∆E_n = omega.
The difference between
these two level spacings
directly measures (g_e - 2)/2.
[MUSIC]